通往契丹[1]之路

大家必须明白，继成吉思汗之后第二个统治者是窝阔台汗，第三个统治者是巴图汗，第四个是贵由汗，第五个是蒙哥汗，第六个就是忽必烈汗。忽必烈汗比以往任何一个可汗都更伟大、更有实力。事实上，将其他五个可汗的力量加在一起也没有忽必烈拥有的力量强大，我还可以稍微夸张一点：世界上所有的皇帝以及基督徒和撒拉森人[2]的国王加起来也不具备这样强大的实力，或者有能力取得像忽必烈汗这样多的成就。我将在这本书中清楚地向大家证明这点。

大家应该知道，所有具有成吉思汗血统的大贵族死后都要被埋葬在阿尔泰山[3]。即便他们驾崩的地方离阿尔泰山有一百天的路程，也必须埋葬于此。还有一个值得注意的事实是：在大汗的遗体被运送到阿尔泰山的途中（大概为四十天的路程），所有在路上偶然遇到大汗送葬队伍的人，都将被护送灵柩的护卫杀死，护卫会对他们说：“去阴间服侍你的主人吧！”因为护卫们确信被他们杀死的人一定会在阴间成为可汗的奴仆。同样，当可汗驾崩时，他们会杀死可汗最好的马，以便让可汗在阴间也能拥有那些马。事实上，在运送蒙哥汗遗体的途中，有不止两千人因为偶遇送葬的队伍而被护送的士兵杀死。

既然已经提到了鞑靼人[4]，我就向大家多介绍一些他们的情况。他们会在草原和温暖的地区过冬，因为这些地区适合放牧，可以为他们的牲口提供牧草。当夏天来临时，他们会迁往大山或峡谷中比较凉爽的地区，因为那儿有充足的水源和林地供他们放牧，在凉爽的地区放牧的另一个好处就是没有马蝇和其他虻虫一样的害虫来侵扰他们的牲口。通常他们在一个地方放牧两三个月后，就继续向山上迁徙，因为如果只在一个地方放牧，那么任何一个牧场都不足以养活如此多的牲口。

他们的屋子是圆形的，用木头建成，上面搭着毡布。这些用木棍支成的框架排列整齐、构造巧妙，并且十分轻巧，便于携带。迁移时，他们可以将这些材料放在他们的四轮车上一起带走。他们每次搭建房屋时，门总是朝向南面。他们还有一种极好的两轮车，这种车用黑色的毡布做顶，设计非常巧妙，就算车外一直下雨，车内的东西也不会被雨淋湿。通常由牛和骆驼拉车，车内载着鞑靼人的妻子、孩子以及他们所需要的各种器物。

我向大家保证，鞑靼妇女负责经营各种买卖，她们还要做好所有丈夫和家庭所需要的事情。而男人们除了狩猎、战争和放鹰捕猎以外，其他的活都不用干。鞑靼人以肉制品和乳制品为主食，靠狩猎和捕捉草原上随处可见的土拨鼠为生。他们也吃马肉和狗肉，也不介意喝马奶，事实上，任何肉类他们都不会拒绝。男人们绝不会接触其他男人的妻子，因为他们十分清楚这么做是错误的、可耻的。他们的妻子也十分忠于自己的丈夫，并且擅长操持家务，即使一个家庭中有十个甚至二十个妻子，她们也会和睦团结地生活在一起，更听不到她们互相谩骂，这点是十分值得称赞的。妻子们通常都全身心投入在各种各样的家务和对孩子的照顾中。对鞑靼男人来说，只要他们愿意，就可以娶很多妻子，即便是娶一百个，只要这个男人负担得起，也是可以的。娶妻时，丈夫需要给他妻子的母亲礼金，而妻子不用给丈夫任何东西。大家要明白，男人的第一个妻子被视为最优秀的，她拥有着比其他妻子更高的地位。由于鞑靼男人娶妻不受限制，所以他们的子女也比其他民族的男人要多得多。他们可以与自己的表妹或表姐结婚，并且当家庭中的父亲去世后，长子可以娶他父亲遗留的妻子，只有他的生母除外。当他们的兄弟去世后，他们也可以娶兄弟的妻子。每次娶妻，他们都会举行盛大的庆典。

接下来让我们看看鞑靼人的宗教信仰。他们信奉一个品格高尚、无比神圣的天神，每天都会向他焚香祈祷，只为祈求得到知识和健康。同时，他们还信奉一个叫纳蒂盖的神，他们认为他是一个俗世的神，掌管着他们的子孙、牲口和作物。他们非常尊重这个神，用毡布为神做了衣服，将他供奉在家中。他们还为这个神塑造了妻子和孩子，并将他的妻子摆放在他的左手边，将他的孩子摆放在他的前面。他们对这个神十分尊敬，每次吃饭前，他们都会用一块肥肉去涂抹神的嘴巴，然后再涂抹在他的妻子和孩子嘴边。他们还将肉汤洒在门外，让其他的神一同享用。做完这一切后，他们认为他们的神和神的家人已经享用得差不多了，然后才开始吃自己的食物。大家应该知道他们喝马奶，但是他们会将马奶加工成白色的酒，这种酒味道很好，他们把这种饮品叫作马奶酒。

鞑靼富人的服装极其奢华，由金丝银线或者名贵的皮毛，如黑貂皮、白貂皮或者狐狸皮等做成，他们的饰物同样精美和昂贵。他们的武器有弓、剑和棍棒，但最常用的是弓，他们个个都是杰出的射手。他们将水牛皮或者其他坚硬的兽皮做成的盔甲披挂在身上。

鞑靼人都是勇敢的战士，拥有过人的勇气和胆识。让我来解释一下他们有着怎样的超越其他民族的忍耐力，必要的时候，在没有其他干粮的情况下，他们经常可以只靠马奶和猎物来维持整整一个月的生活。同时，他们的马只需要吃草，这样也就不用为马准备大麦和稻草。鞑靼人对他们的长官绝对服从，在需要的时候，他们可以拿着武器在马背上度过整个夜晚，同时他们的马儿边吃草边前进。他们是世界上最能忍受艰难困苦，而又仅需要最少成本来维持生活的人，因此他们是最适合征服别国的战士。

他们的军队按照下面的方法进行编制。当一个鞑靼人的首领带着十万骑手的队伍去征战时，他会这样来组织他们：他作为最高统帅，下设万夫长、千夫长、百夫长、十夫长；万夫长听命于最高统帅，千夫长听命于万夫长，百夫长听命于千夫长，十夫长听命于百夫长，这样一来，统帅就只需要直接指挥不超过十个万夫长，同样，其他的长官也只需要直接面对十个下属，每个下属也只对自己的长官负责。当统帅需要派遣士兵去执行任务时，他会直接对他手下的万夫长下达命令，要求他派出一千个士兵，此时万夫长就会再下令给他手下的某个千夫长，让他带领手下一千士兵去完成任务。命令就这样传达下去，每个万夫长都会按要求完成统帅的命令，每一级长官都会迅速接到指令并执行。鞑靼人对于他们长官的服从，比其他任何民族都做得要好。他们把一支十万人的军队叫作图克，把一支一万人的军队叫作图孟安。同样，千人、百人、十人的军队也有相应的名称。

不管是在平原还是山地，当鞑靼人的军队被派出去执行某项任务时，他们都会提前两日派出由两百人组成的队伍进行侦查，军队的后方和侧面也部署队伍，即前后左右共有四支队伍来负责侦查，这样就可以使他们免遭敌人的偷袭。

当鞑靼人的军队长途远征时，他们不携带任何包裹，每人只带两个装奶的皮袋，一个煮肉的小锅，一顶能避雨的简单的帐篷。如果有必要，他们可以马不停蹄地行军十日，并且不需要预备任何粮食，也不用生火，只靠喝马血活命，每次骑兵都会切开马的一根血管，然后吮吸马血。他们还这样制作干燥乳制品：首先将奶煮开，并在适当的时候刮下浮在表面的乳脂，放在另一个容器里做成黄油，这样一来就可以保证奶水不会变干；然后他们会将这些乳制品放在太阳下晒干。在长途行军时，他们每人带十磅这样的乳制品，每天早上会拿出半磅来，将它们放在一个像葫芦一样的皮袋中，再加上适量的水。在骑行过程中，乳制品就会分解，融化在他们喝的水中，这就是他们的早餐。

当鞑靼人与敌人战斗时，他们有惯用的战术。他们从来不以示弱为耻，作战方法十分灵活，一会儿从这个方向打击敌人，一会儿又从其他方向攻打敌人。他们的战马训练有素，可以像狗一样快速改变行动方向。被敌人追击时，他们也可以像和敌人正面作战时那样有效率。在他们快速逃跑时，同样可以转过身来用弓箭射伤敌人的马和骑手。这样，当敌人自认为已经打垮鞑靼人的军队时，他们会发现自己军队中的马和战士大都已经被鞑靼人杀死。而鞑靼人一旦确定已杀死足够多的追兵和战马时，他们就会掉头攻击敌人，从而完全取得战斗胜利。他们已经运用这种战术赢得了无数的胜利，打败了无数民族和国家。

以上我告诉大家的都是纯正的鞑靼人的做法和传统。但是现在他们已经退化了，那些生活在契丹的鞑靼人已经适应了佛教徒的风俗礼仪，放弃了他们的信仰；而生活在黎凡特[5]的鞑靼人已经被撒拉森人同化了。

接下来我要告诉大家鞑靼人主持正义的方式。对于小额盗窃罪不至死的罪犯，根据犯罪的轻重程度，盗窃者会受到一定数目的杖责，如七下、十七下、二十七下、三十七下、四十七下或一百零七下，许多人死于这种鞭打。而当盗窃犯偷了一匹马或者其他应处以死刑的物品时，就会被劈成两段。当然，如果他可以承担所偷东西价值九倍的赔偿，就可以免遭惩罚。

鞑靼人的大贵族和其他人都会拥有很多牲畜，包括战马、母马、骆驼、公牛、母牛和其他牲畜，主人都会在这些牲畜身上烙上自己的标记，然后将它们放至平原和山坡上吃草，而不需要任何牧人看管。如果这些牲畜混在一起，他们也可以通过牲口身上的标记分辨出它们的主人是谁，然后物归原主。他们的绵羊和公羊是托给牧人看管的。鞑靼人所有的牲口都体型健硕、高大肥壮。

鞑靼人还有一个和其他民族不一样的习俗：当一个鞑靼男人有一个已经死去的儿子（有可能在四岁时就死亡），而另一个男人有一个已经死去的女儿时，他们可以给死去的男孩、女孩安排一段婚姻，并会起草婚约。然后他们烧掉这份婚约，并坚信烧掉婚约时燃起的烟雾会在另一个世界里找到他们的孩子，孩子们会从风中得到他们已经结为夫妇的消息。他们还会举行盛大的婚宴，到处分发食物，宣告他们的孩子已经在另一个世界里结成夫妇。此外，他们还要将一些奴隶、马、衣服、钱币和家居用品画在纸上，然后烧给他们死去的儿女，他们认为，这些东西都将在另一个世界里成为他们儿女的财产。当做完这些事情以后，他们就认为彼此已经结成亲家，和儿女在世时结成的亲家一样。

到现在为止，我向大家描述了鞑靼人最质朴的风俗习惯。我还没讲的是鞑靼人的伟大领袖大汗建立的光辉业绩和他的王朝，这些我将在书中根据时间和地点慢慢告诉大家，这的确是值得好好来描述的奇妙事情。在这里，让我们顺着刚才的线索，重新回到那辽阔的平原，讲述鞑靼人所留下的历史。

旅行者离开喀喇昆仑和前面所说的埋葬鞑靼人可汗的阿尔泰山，继续北行，将横穿过一个叫作巴尔古平原的地方，这大概要走上四十天。这里的居民被称为墨斯克力蒲特人，这是一个野蛮的种族，靠兽类维持生活，主要是他们用来乘骑的驯鹿。他们的风俗习惯和鞑靼人很相似，也同样臣服于大汗。他们不生产农作物，也没有酒。在夏季，有许多鸟兽供他们猎食，但是在冬季，由于极其严寒，鸟兽都不能在此生存。在夏天鸟类换毛的季节，这些鸟尤其喜欢聚集在湖、池塘、沼泽等有水源的地方，当它们换下所有羽毛时是不能飞行的，所以此时捕猎者可以捕捉到很多鸟。同样，这个族群也靠捕鱼为生。

在经过四十天的跋涉后，旅行者就可以到达海边。游隼会在这里的山中筑巢。大家要知道，这儿既无人烟，也无鸟兽，只有一种叫作巴格拉克的鸟供猎鹰捕食。这种鸟的体型和鹧鸪相似，有着和鹦鹉一样的爪子，燕子一样的尾巴，还有着超强的飞行能力。当大汗想要得到雏鹰时，就会派人来这里寻找。海洋中的岛屿生长着这些矛隼。我肯定这个地区非常靠北，以至于北极星都朝向了南面。在这个地方，栖息着大量矛隼，因此大汗想要多少就能捉到多少。大家不要以为一些基督教国家的人给鞑靼人的矛隼最后被送给了大汗，实际上，他们将这些矛隼送给了地中海沿岸诸国的可汗，或者像阿鲁浑[6]大汗这样的人。

……

离开这些省市，继续向前走三天，我们就会到达一个叫作张加诺[7]的城市，那儿有一座很大的大汗行宫。由于这里河湖密布，并有许多天鹅栖息于此，因此大汗十分喜欢在此居住。这儿还有肥沃的平原，栖息着许多鹤、野鸡、鹧鸪和其他野生禽类。大汗是一个热衷于运动并且十分喜欢放鹰行猎的人，所以这个地方对大汗就更有吸引力了。这里的鹤有五种：第一种有着像乌鸦一样纯黑的羽毛，体型十分庞大；第二种羽毛是纯白的，翅膀十分优美，上面点缀着圆圆的斑点，就像孔雀一样，只是斑点是亮亮的金色，它们还有着红黑相间的头和黑白相间的长长的脖子；第三种和我们最常见的鹤一样；第四种鹤体型很小，耳边上有着长长的羽毛，红黑相间，十分美丽；最后一种羽毛大都是灰色的，只是头部为红黑两色，体型较大。

这个城市的附近有一个山谷，大汗在这里饲养了不计其数的鹧鸪。为了喂养它们，大汗下令每年夏天都定期在山坡上种植粟子和这些鸟类喜欢的其他谷物，并且不容许任何人收获这些作物，以保证这些鸟类有足够的食物。大汗还派看守照看这些鸟，保护它们不被其他人或动物捕捉；冬天，看护者还会撒布粟子喂鸟。由于这些鸟习惯了被饲养，当饲养者把谷物撒在地上后，只要吹哨子，它们就会从四面八方向他飞来。大汗还下令修建许多小屋，供这些鸟类夜间栖息。这样一来，每次大汗游历到此地，都会有许多鸟禽供大汗玩乐。由于这里冬季严寒，大汗不会在此过冬，而此时正是鸟禽漂亮丰满的季节，于是，大汗就会用骆驼将这些鸟禽带去他所在的地方。

当旅行者离开这个城市，继续向东北走上三天后，就会到达上都[8]，它是忽必烈统治时建造的都城。在这里，忽必烈用大理石和其他美丽的石头建成了一座巨大的宫殿，殿堂和房间都是镀金的，装饰得富丽堂皇。宫殿的一面延伸到城市的中心，另一面紧靠城墙，在城墙的背面，也就是宫殿的反方向，延伸出另一面城墙，围出了一片近十六英里的公园，公园被清泉和溪流环绕，使这片美丽的草地得到了充分的灌溉。除了宫殿，再没有其他的路可以到达这个公园。在这里，大汗饲养了各种动物，如雄鹿、雄獐等，用来给他的猎鹰捕猎。在这里，光矛隼就有两百多只，大汗每周都会视察这些鹰笼里的猎鹰，也经常会带上一只豹子，骑着马，当觉得时机已到，就把豹子放出去，让它去捉雄鹿或者雄獐，然后把它捕到的猎物拿去喂鹰，这就是他的休闲和运动。

在这个封闭的公园中间，有一个风景优美的小树林，大汗在这儿也修建了一个大行宫，这个行宫完全由竹子建成，但是宫殿内部都是镀金的，并且用精美的鸟兽图案作为装饰。行宫由镀金的柱子支撑，每个柱子上都画有一条龙，龙尾朝下，龙身向上盘绕在柱子上，龙足支撑着宫殿顶部。顶部也是由竹子编成，被涂上了漆，因此能够防水。我来解释一下这座行宫是如何建成的。大家要知道，这些竹子的周长大概有三个手长，高度大概十到十五步那么高，它们被从中间劈开，这样就有了两个用来做屋顶的竹板，这些竹板又厚又长，不仅可以用来做屋顶，还可以用来建造行宫的任何部位。就这样，整个行宫都是由这些竹子建造的。为了防风，每个竹条都用钉子固定。这种行宫由两百多根坚韧的细绳拴住，由于它被设计得如此巧妙，所以可以随时分拆，在大汗需要的时候搭建。

每年的六、七、八月，大汗都会停留在上都，一方面为了避暑，另一方面也为了休养娱乐。在这三个月中，大汗都住在由竹子搭建的行宫里，其他时候，这座行宫就会被拆除，需要时再搭建起来。

每年八月二十八日，大汗就会离开这个城市，离开这所行宫，我会告诉大家，大汗为什么每年都会选择这个特定的日子离开。事实上大汗有一群纯白的无杂色的马，马群的规模十分大，仅母马就不下一万只。没有皇族血统的人没有权利喝这些白色的母马所产的奶，只有一个例外，就是一个叫霍里阿德的家族。因为他们在过去的战争中立下了汗马功劳，所以成吉思汗授予他们家族特权，允许他们饮用这种马奶。当这种白马在吃草时，任何人都不敢去打扰它们，即使是一个大贵族要经过这条路，也绝不会从马群中间穿过，而是等到马群吃完后或者绕过马群再继续前进。一些占星家和信奉神灵的人们告诉大汗每年的八月二十八日，他都必须用这种白马的奶酿成的酒来进行祭奠，将这种酒洒在天空中，洒在大地上，以祭奉他们崇拜的神灵。他们认为大汗必须通过这样的祭奉，来保卫他所有的财产、臣民、鸟兽、作物等。

出于以上原因，大汗每年都会在这个时候离开上都，前往别的地方。在我们跟随他离开之前，让我再向大家讲述一件奇怪的事情。当大汗所在的行宫下雨或者乌云密布时，占星家和巫师们会施展他们的技能和巫术来驱散行宫上方的乌云和大雨，这样即使行宫周围的天气十分恶劣，行宫上方的天气也很好。这些法师被叫作特贝斯[9]和克施密特，这是信奉神灵的民族。他们比普通人知道更多魔法和巫术。他们所做的事情似乎是魔鬼的行为，但让别人认为他们所做的一切都是圣洁的，都是上帝的旨意。他们肮脏污秽，不注重自己的容貌，也不在意别人对他们的看法，他们经常不洗脸，不梳头，总是生活在肮脏之中。我还要告诉大家这些人的一个独特风俗，当一个人被处以死刑后，这些人会将尸体取走，煮熟尸体，然后吃掉，但是正常死亡的人他们是不会吃的。

这些巫师也被叫作巴克斯[10]。还有一件不可思议的事情。一次，大汗坐在高高的大殿上用膳，他位置高于大殿地面约八腕尺[11]，而杯子放在大殿的地板上，盛满了酒、奶和其他美味的饮品，这些巴克斯运用他们的巫术和技巧，让这些盛满各种饮品的杯子在没有任何人接触的情况下，自动从大殿的地面升起，并移动到大汗面前。这些行为是在一万多人的注视下完成的，我向大家保证我所说的都千真万确，没有半点谎言。并且那些精通巫术的人证实，这是行得通的。

还有一件关于巴克斯的事情，每当祭祀神明的日子来临时，他们都会向大汗禀报：“陛下，祭祀我们神明的日子就要临近了，”然后他们随便报出几个神灵的名字，然后接着说，“您知道，如果这些神明不享受到祭典，他们就会让我们的天气变糟，损害我们的财产、牲口和谷物。因此我们恳求陛下赐予我们足够的黑头羊、香料和燃料，多多益善，让我们来举行庄严的祭祀，以求得神明的保佑。”他们将这些奏报给大汗手下的官员，再由这些官员向大汗请奏，等到大汗准奏，这些巴克斯就能得到他们要求的祭品了。然后他们就开始载歌载舞进行祭祀仪式。他们会使用大量香料；会将肉煮熟后摆放在神明面前，并将肉汤洒在地上，通知神明来享用。这就是巴克斯在祭祀典礼上向他们的神明表达尊敬的方式。

大家要知道，就和我们的圣人一样，所有的神明都有他们自己特定的节日。他们拥有极多的僧侣和寺院，寺中住着两千多名僧侣，像一个小城市一样，由于身份特殊，僧侣穿的通常要比其他人好。他们的头发和胡子也都要被剃掉。这些僧侣们为他们信奉的神明举行我们所未见过的盛大的祭祀，念经祈福。

此外，这些巴克斯还享有特权，其中之一就是他们可以根据需要娶妻，并生育很多后代。

除了巴克斯以外，还有一类叫作笙新的教徒。他们教规极其严格，生活也十分简朴，除了糠，不吃任何食物。他们将小麦制成的谷物放进热水里，使谷粒和谷壳分离，然后将谷壳磨成面粉，做成他们所吃的糠。他们也从来不在食物中加入任何作料。他们也信奉很多神明，他们中的很多人都拜火为神。其他教派的教徒都视这些禁欲者为异教徒，因为笙新教徒崇拜神明的方式与其他教徒很不相同。在两个教派之间，还有一个很大的不同之处：那些遵守严格教规的教徒是不允许娶妻的。他们同样会剃光头发和胡子，通常穿着麻布做成的黑色或蓝色的长袍，即使长袍是用丝绸做的，也仍然会是黑色或蓝色。他们睡在柳条编成的草席上，过着比世界上大多数人都简朴的生活。

由于他们崇拜的神明都是女性，他们都继承着女性的姓氏。

关于这些我们就讲到这里，接下来的故事更有趣，下面我将向大家讲述所有鞑靼人的主人的主人—最高贵的大汗—忽必烈汗的伟大功绩。

忽必烈汗

下面我就将为大家讲述忽必烈汗的伟大功绩。“可汗”用我们的语言来说就是“伟大的众王之王”的意思，而忽必烈汗完全无愧于这个称号。大家要知道，不管是从隶属于他的国家，还是从他控制的疆土，甚至是他拥有的财富方面来说，从古至今，没有任何国王能超越忽必烈汗，他可以说是世界上拥有最大权力的人。在这本书中我将给大家一个真实清晰的描述，让大家相信忽必烈汗的确是世界上最伟大的国王。

首先，大家要知道，忽必烈汗是成吉思汗的直系后代，是所有鞑靼人公认的首领。他是继成吉思汗后，鞑靼人的第六位大汗，于公元1256年继位[12]并开始他的统治。尽管他的亲属和兄弟从中阻挠，忽必烈汗还是凭借自己的勇气与智慧赢得了王位。从他继位到现在（公元1298年）已经有四十二年的时间了，他也有八十五岁了。成为可汗以前，忽必烈经常参加军事征战，在战争中他证明了自己不仅是一个英勇的战士，同时也是一个伟大的统帅。但在继承王位后，除了在1286年的那次亲自出征外，就没有再亲自参加过战斗，我将向大家描述那次出征的情况。

忽必烈有个叫那彦的叔叔。他很年轻，拥有许多领土，统治着很多城市，并且有一支由四十万骑兵组成的军队。那彦和他的祖先一样，都臣服于大汗，但是由于他只有三十多岁，年轻气盛，手下又有很多士兵，所以决定不再听命于大汗，而是去夺取大汗的皇位。那彦派出使者去勾结另一个实力强大的首领海都，海都是忽必烈的侄子，由于反对过忽必烈，忽必烈一直对他怀恨在心。那彦建议海都从一侧攻击大汗的军队，而他自己则从另一侧发起攻击，两侧夹击，打败大汗。海都欣然接受了那彦的建议，并且向那彦保证，一定会在指定的日期调集好十万大军来对抗大汗。这样，那彦和海都这两位亲王就作好了准备，召集好人马，准备对大汗宣战。

当大汗得到这个消息时，并没有手忙脚乱，而是英明果断地召集自己的军队，并且宣称，叛乱不平，他就不会再当大汗。他用了二十二天的时间秘密完成了战斗的准备工作，除了他的智囊团之外没有任何人知道。他集合了二十六万骑兵和十万步兵，这些士兵都是从离他较近的地区调集而来的。虽然大汗还有许多军队，但是离他较远，来不及调集。如果大汗调集了他全部的军队，那么他军队的数量将是不可估计的。此时的三十六万大军，大都由大汗的养鹰者和他的卫队组成。

如果大汗要召集在契丹各省所有的军队，需要三十到四十天的时间，海都和那彦就一定会得到消息，这样一来，他们就会调集军队，抢占要害关口。而大汗打算以速度取胜，先单独攻打那彦，破坏他的准备活动，这样比攻击他和海都的联军要容易得多。

大家要知道在契丹和蛮子各省及大汗统治的其他地区，有很多人对大汗不满、不忠于大汗，只要他们有机会，他们就会起来反抗大汗。因此，在每个规模较大的城市和人口较多的省份，大汗都要派兵驻守。这些驻军驻守在离城市四到五英里的乡村里，这些开放的乡村不允许有城墙，并且允许人们自由进出。这些驻军和他们的首领都是两年一换。有了这些控制措施，大汗的臣民才得以安分守己，不敢制造任何骚动和叛乱。这些军队除了依靠大汗每年从全国收入中拨出的军费生活外，还会把他们的牛群送到城镇卖掉，换钱以维持军需。这种军队有很多驻点，相隔距离各不相同，有的相距三四十天的路程，有的相隔六十天的路程。

大汗仅仅召集了上述军队中的一小部分后，他就去询问占星家，想知道他是否能打败敌人，取得战斗的胜利。占星师向他保证，他可以轻松打败敌人。这样，大汗就派出了军队，日夜兼程，经过二十天的行军到达了那彦驻军的大草原，那彦在这儿聚集了四十多万骑兵。由于大汗派人一路看守行军的道路，任何经过的人都会被拦截，因此当大汗的军队在一个清晨到达这个大草原时，那彦的军队对此一无所知。事实上，当大汗的军队到达时，那彦正和他最心爱的妻子躺在军营里。

第二天黎明，大汗的军队突然出现在平原的一个小山坡上，而那彦的军队还十分自由散漫，丝毫没有意识到大汗的军队正在临近。事实上，他们认为自己非常安全，既没有派遣哨兵驻守他们的兵营，也没有士兵在大营的前后方巡逻。大汗站在一个木制的塔上，周围有许多弓弩手，木塔由四头大象驮着，每头大象都穿着用结实的皮革做成的盔甲，盔甲上又覆盖上一层用金子和丝做成的织品。木塔顶上高高飘扬着象征日月的皇旗，这样双方都能清楚看到。大汗的军队由三十个骑兵大队组成，每队都有一万个弓箭手。他们分为三组，分别从前方和两侧包围那彦的军队。每队骑兵的前面都有五百名拿着短矛和刀剑的步兵。每当骑兵撤退时，他们就会跳上马背，和他们一起撤退；当撤退被敌军阻挠时，他们就下马，挥矛杀死敌人的马。这就是双方军队靠近时，大汗设计的战斗阵型。

当那彦和他的军队发现大汗时，他们立即组织起来，匆忙拿起武器，整编军队，排列好阵型。

鞑靼人有这样的习俗，当双方军队面对敌人，排列好作战队形后，并不急于展开战斗，而是开始奏乐唱歌，直到鼓声擂响时才开始战斗。而在鼓声擂响前，所有鞑靼人都跟着乐器合唱，继而可以听到很多乐器混合的声音和士兵刺耳的歌声。

当双方军队都准备就绪后，大汗的军队首先敲响战鼓，双方骑兵立刻短兵相接，展开激战。他们的武器有弓、剑、木棍和长矛。步兵也手持横弓和其他武器参与战斗。而这只是这场残酷血腥战争的开始，不久，战场中就箭如雨下，尸横遍地，声盖雷鸣。大家要知道那彦是一个受过洗礼的基督徒，在这场战争中，他用十字架作为自己军队的旗帜。

这是一场前所未有的残酷的战斗。在我们的历史上，从未有过这么多骑兵投入一场战斗中。双方死伤不计其数。战斗从拂晓打到中午，很长时间里双方都相持不下。由于那彦是一位慷慨的首领，他的追随者对他都十分忠诚，宁可战死沙场也不愿背叛自己的主人。可是，最后的胜利属于忽必烈。当那彦和他的手下觉得军队支持不了太久时，他们企图逃跑，但是最终还是被擒拿，他的官员和军队也都向大汗投降了。

大汗得知那彦被囚后，下令处死他。那彦被紧紧裹在一条毯子里，然后被系在马后，在地上拖拽至死。选择这种方法处死那彦，是因为这样一来皇室的血就不会洒溅到大地上，暴露在太阳和空气之中。

在大汗取得战争的胜利后，那彦的残余势力也都誓死效忠于大汗，他们大都是女真、卡利、巴斯克尔、西亭基四省的居民。

大汗的士兵来自很多民族，比如撒拉森人、犹太人和佛教徒，他们都不信仰上帝，战争胜利后他们就嘲笑那彦军旗上的十字架。他们嘲讽基督徒：“瞧瞧你们上帝的十字架是怎么保护基督徒那彦的！”这些话传到大汗耳朵里后，大汗当面斥责那些嘲笑者，然后他召集了很多基督徒，安抚他们：“你们的上帝没有保护那彦，是因为上帝只站在善良和正义的一边。那彦是背叛君主的叛徒，是非正义的，而你们的上帝不会保佑对抗正义的人。”基督徒们回应道：“吾主圣明，陛下所言极是。上帝是不会像那彦一样犯下滔天大错的，那彦实在罪有应得。”这就是大汗和基督徒关于那彦的十字旗的对话。

战争胜利后，大汗凯旋，回到了他的首都汗八里[13]，那里被喜悦和快乐的气氛包围着。

当另一个造反的亲王——海都听说那彦战败并被处死的消息后，心慌意乱，生怕自己会有同样的下场，立刻取消了叛乱的计划。

大汗回到汗八里时正值十一月，大汗将在这儿一直住到第二年的二三月，也就是我们的复活节时期。大汗得知复活节是我们最重要的节日之一，就将所有的基督徒都召集来，并要他们将四大福音书献给他。在举行了盛大的仪式，反复香熏四大福音书后，大汗虔诚地亲吻了这部书，并且要求他的亲王和首领们也亲吻此书。他在基督徒的重大节日，如复活节、圣诞节时，总会这么做。而在撒拉森人、犹太人和佛教徒的重大节日时，他也会做相似的事情。当被问及原因时，大汗总是说：“有四位被人崇拜和被世界尊敬的先知：基督徒信仰上帝耶稣，撒拉森人崇拜真主穆罕默德，犹太人信奉摩西，而佛教徒信奉释迦牟尼大佛。我尊重他们所信奉的神，并向他们中最伟大的神祈求帮助。”但是从大汗自己的表现来看，他认为基督徒是最好的，因为基督徒所做的一切都是仁慈和圣洁的。他不允许基督徒手持十字架，因为这让他想到伟大的耶稣所遭受的苦难。

大家也许会问，既然大汗认为基督教是最好的宗教，那他自己为什么不去信仰基督教呢？这也许可以从大汗对波罗兄弟[14]所说的话中找到答案。当大汗将他们作为使者派去教皇那儿时，他们不时地向大汗提到这个问题，大汗回答说：“你们是站在谁的立场上想让我成为基督徒呢？你们知道这个国家的基督徒都是如此的无知，既没有任何成就，也没有任何权力。而佛教徒却可以做任何他们想做的事情：当我坐在大殿上时，他们可以在没有任何人接触的情况下，把各种酒和饮品从大殿中间送到我的面前。他们可以驱逐坏的天气并且拥有许多神奇的功能能力。当他们向佛祖祈求帮助时，佛祖还会给予他们指引。但是，如果我信仰基督教，成为一个基督徒，那么我的亲王和其他不信仰耶稣的人就会对我说：‘是什么促使您接受洗礼，信仰基督教的呢？’这些佛教徒就会说他们所做的各种事情，并说他们的佛祖是最圣洁高尚的。这样一来我就无法回答了，而这些在艺术上和科学上都有如此多成就的佛教徒就可以轻易谋害我。如果你们见到教皇，请求他派来一些有学识的基督徒，当这些基督徒面对那些佛教徒时，可以当面斥责他们的巫术，并且告诉那些佛教徒，他们所做的基督徒一样可以做到，只是因为那些都是邪恶的行为，所以不会去做，然后向佛教徒展示你们基督徒的法力。这时我就会废除他们的宗教，接受洗礼，我所有的亲王、贵族以及他们的部下也都会和我一样接受洗礼。这样一来，这里的基督徒将会比你们国家的基督徒还要多。”果真如上所说，教皇派出有能力的教徒来向大汗传教，大汗一定会成为一个基督徒，因为这才是大汗真正想信仰的宗教。

大家已经从这次战役中知道了大汗是如何打仗的，在其他战役中，大汗通常是将他的儿子或亲王们派上战场，但是这次，他却亲自指挥，可以看出他对亲王叛乱的重视和愤怒。让我们先把这个话题放下，再来详述大汗的丰功伟绩。

我已经向大家讲述了大汗的血脉和年龄。现在我们来讲讲大汗是如何奖罚在战斗中表现勇敢或胆怯的官兵的。对于前者，大汗将他们中的百夫长提升到千夫长，将千夫长提升到万夫长，还根据他们的级别，慷慨赏赐给他们银质的象征权力的奖牌。百夫长会得到一个银牌；千夫长得到一个镀金的奖牌；而万夫长则得到一个刻有狮子头的金牌。百夫长、千夫长的奖牌每个重一百二十萨吉；万夫长的奖牌重二百二十萨吉。每个奖牌后都刻有这样的文字：“借伟大的神赐予的力量，以及他对我们皇帝的无限慈悲，保佑我们的大汗，逆命者斩。”所有拥有这些奖牌的人也被授予各种权力，由官员记载下来。

对于十万军队的首领，大汗赐予他们重三百萨吉的金质奖牌，奖牌后也刻着上面所提到的文字。在奖牌下端，刻着一只位于日月之上的狮子。同时十万军队的首领还能享受到极大的特权，当他骑马出门时，头顶可以撑伞，以象征他高贵的地位；当他就坐时，他必须坐在银质的椅子上。对另外一些地位高贵的人，大汗同样赐予刻有白隼的奖牌，这些奖牌通常赐予亲王们，他们可以动用所有的力量，当他们想要发送快信或是派送使者时，他们甚至可以使用大汗的马匹，这实际上也就意味着，他们可以使用任何人的马匹。

下面我们来看看忽必烈汗的外表。他中等身材，不高不矮，四肢匀称，面色红润，有着乌黑俊亮的眼睛和端正高挺的鼻子。

大汗有四个合法的妻子，这四个妻子中任何一人所生的长子在可汗驾崩后都有权继承皇位。她们都是皇后，并且各有一座宫殿。她们每人都有不下三百名的美丽侍女，还有许多宦官和其他男女侍从，这样一来，每位皇后都有近万人服侍。当大汗想要和她们中的一位共寝时，他就会召皇后进宫，或者是亲自前往皇后的宫殿。

除了四位皇后，大汗还有许多妃子。大汗领土中有个省，在那儿居住的鞑靼人被叫作翁古特，这个省也同样叫作翁古特。翁古特的居民都十分美丽，皮肤光滑。根据大汗的旨意，大概每隔两年，大汗都会派人去翁古特，按照他的要求为他挑选美丽的未婚女子。有时候会挑选四五百人，人数的多少都由大汗决定。选拔是这样进行的：当使者到达时，他们集中翁古特的所有未婚少女，然后派人前去考察。在仔细检查她们的头发、容貌、眉毛、口齿、嘴唇和其他部位，并观察身体是否协调、匀称后，挑选的使者会根据她们的美丽程度给她们打分，从十六分、十七分、十八分到二十几分不等。若大汗要求他们将得到二十分或者二十一分的女子带到宫中，她们的数量达到时，这些使者的使命也就完成了。当她们被带到宫中后，大汗会派另外一组评价者继续来考察她们，然后选出三十到四十个得分最高的女子，带到他的寝宫侍奉。大汗派亲王的妻子们夜间在这些女子的房间里仔细观察她们，以确保她们的处女之身不被任何人玷污和侵犯，确认她们睡觉时没有鼾声，并且呼吸轻柔，身体没有任何异味。通过的少女被分为六组，每组在可汗的寝宫和床上侍奉三天三夜，满足大汗所有的要求。而大汗可以随意支配她们。三天三夜之后，就由另一组少女来侍奉大汗，这样一直轮换一年。当其中一组少女在大汗的寝宫内侍奉大汗时，其他的几组少女就在寝宫外面守候。如果大汗需要任何东西，比如食物或酒，这些在寝宫里面侍奉的少女就会传话给外面的人，而屋外的少女就会马上去准备。这样一来，侍奉大汗的责任就全由这些少女担当。对于剩下的得分较低的少女，她们仍然会留在皇宫中，被分派去做针线、剪裁等其他体面的工作。当一些贵族要娶妻时，大汗就将她们赐予这些贵族，并给她们配上丰厚的嫁妆。这样，大汗就将她们都体面地嫁给了贵族。

大家可能会问：“翁古特的男人们不会认为大汗这样抢走他们的女儿是不公平的吗？”大部分人当然不会这么认为。他们将这视为大汗对他们的偏爱和恩宠。那些有着漂亮女儿的人会很高兴大汗会屈尊接受他们的女儿。他们这样说道：“如果我的女儿命好，大汗会赐予她一个高贵的丈夫，这将会比我能给她的好得多。”如果他们的女儿表现得不好，没有得到很好的归宿，她们的父亲会说：“这是因为她的命不好才会这样。”

大家要知道，大汗的四个妻子一共为大汗生下了二十二个儿子。长子叫作真金，是为了纪念成吉思汗而取的名字。他被指定为皇位继承人，但是他不幸去世了，留下一个儿子叫作铁穆耳，由于铁穆耳是皇太孙，所以他将继承皇位。就像他在多次战斗中表现出来的一样，铁穆耳是个智勇双全的人。

除了大汗妻子所生的儿子以外，大汗的妃子还为他生下了二十五个儿子，他们都是勇敢的战士，伟大的亲王。

大汗妻子所生的儿子中，有七个都当上了广大省区和王国的国王。他们都将王国统治得很好，审慎而又英勇。而这都是有原因的，因为他们的父亲忽必烈汗在各个方面都是最英明能干的，是鞑靼人历史上最优秀的统治者和品德最高尚的人。

大家要知道每年十二月、一月和二月这三个月，大汗都住在契丹国的首都—汗八里。大汗在这座城里有座雄伟的宫殿，我将向大家描述这座宫殿。

这座宫殿完全被正方形的城墙围绕，每面城墙长一英里，这样所有的城墙就共有四英里长。城墙很厚，并且有十步长那么高，被刷成白色，上面有城垛。在城墙的每个角上都有一个美丽壮观的城堡，是大汗储藏军备的地方。在每面城墙的中间也都有和四个角上一样的城堡，这样整个城墙上就共有八座这样的城堡，均作为军械库使用。每个城堡里都存放着一种特定的兵器，因此，当一个城堡里储存着马鞍、马缰、马镫和其他马具时，另一个城堡里就放着弓、弓弦、箭袋、箭和其他射箭所需要的物品，而第三个城堡就保存着胸甲、甲胄和其他坚硬的皮制盔甲。其他城堡储存的东西依次类推。

南面的城墙上有五道门，最大的一道门在中间，只供大汗进出；大门的两边各有两道小门，供其他人进出。南面城墙的两个角上也各有一道更大的门，也供其他人进出。

外墙的里面还有一层城墙，比外墙要宽一些。它和外墙一样有八个用于储存军备的城堡，朝南开的五道门和外墙的五道门相对应，两侧也各有一道门。

这个城墙里面就是我将向大家描述的大汗的宫殿。这座宫殿比我所见过的任何宫殿都要宏大。宫殿只有一层，但是地基高出地面有十掌高；周围被一圈和地基一样高并且大概两步宽的大理石包围。这样就在宫殿外形成了一个平台，方便士兵巡逻和视察宫殿外面的情况。平台的外侧是由圆柱装饰成的精美的走廊，人们可以在此交谈。宫殿的每面都有一个大理石做的楼梯，从地面通向大理石城墙的平台，供进入宫殿的人们使用。

宫殿非常高，大殿和房间的墙上都覆盖着由金银装饰成的龙、凤、骑兵、各种鸟兽和战争场景的图案。天花板也同样被装饰了，因此整个大殿显得富丽堂皇。大殿十分宽敞，可容纳六千人同时进餐。同时宫殿还有不计其数的房间。整个建筑能立刻给人极好的感觉，布局精良，世界上再无人敢认为自己有能力建造出这样的建筑，也没有人能对这个建筑提出任何设计上的改进。屋顶外部被红黄蓝绿各种颜色装饰着，并像水晶一样闪耀着五颜六色的光芒，在很远的地方就能看到。屋顶也十分坚固，久经岁月洗礼。

皇宫的后面还有一些宫殿，也有许多房间和走廊，是大汗存放私人财产的地方。这儿存放着大汗的金银珠宝，同样也是大汗的皇后和妃子居住的地方，这些宫殿里所有的布置安排都是为了大汗的舒适和方便，外人是不允许进入的。

两层城墙的中间是宽敞的公园用地，种着笔直的树木。这儿的草都长得极其茂盛，由于所有小路的铺建都整整高于地面两腕尺，这样一来草地上就没有污泥和积水，雨水涓涓地流过草坪，流向两侧，滋润着土壤，滋养着小草，让它们繁茂生长。在这些公园里饲养着各种各样美丽的动物，如白鹿、麝鹿、雄獐、雄鹿、松鼠等。总之，在两墙中间的这片公园里，除了供人行走的小路外，满是这些可爱的生物。

在这片土地的西北角，有个大而深的凹坑，设计得十分巧妙，从凹坑中挖走的土都被用来建造小山，一条小溪的水流入凹坑中形成了一个池塘，池塘里的水可供动物们饮用。同时，小溪里的水还顺着小山旁的水渠流出，注满了另一个相似的凹坑，这个凹坑位于大汗的宫殿和他儿子真金的宫殿中间，凹坑里的土同样被挖出来修建成小山。大汗在池塘里养了很多种类的鱼，当他想吃鱼时，就可以从池塘中选择。池塘更远处是小溪的出口，在小溪的出口和入口都装着铜铁制成的栅栏，可以防止鱼儿逃走。池塘中还有天鹅和其他水禽。小溪上有一座桥，从一座宫殿通向另一座宫殿。

皇宫北面大约一箭尺的距离，大汗大兴土木，建造了一座一百步高的山，山脚周长有一英里。这座山上栽满了茂密的常青树，大汗只要听说哪儿有独特的树木，不管树有多大，他都会派人将树连着根和周围的土壤一起挖出，然后用大象把它运到这座山上来。这样他就把整个国家最好的树木都集中到了这儿。同时，他在山上铺上了天青石（一种绿色的石头），使得树和石头都是绿色的，整座山除了绿色没有其他的颜色，由此得名为青山。在山顶上，大汗还建造了一座精美的宫殿，整座宫殿也同样是绿色的，和青山绿树相映衬，形成了一幅赏心悦目的图画。大汗建造这座宫殿既是为了美观，也是为了在此休闲娱乐。

在大汗皇宫的边上，还修建了一座和皇宫一样的宫殿，这是太子的宫殿。由于太子是要继承皇位的，所以他的宫殿和皇宫的风格、规模、大小都一样。皇位的继承人铁穆耳——真金的儿子，居住在这里。由于他被选作忽必烈汗的继承人，所以他和大汗享用着同等规模的礼仪。虽然皇帝的公文和大印已经归他所有，但是只要忽必烈汗还健在，他就不能随心所欲地使用他的权力。

我已经描述完了这些宫殿，下面我将向大家介绍它们所在的城市大都，及其建立的原因和方法。

汗八里位于契丹的一条大河旁边，是一座古老壮观的城市，这个名字在我们的语言中就是“帝都”的意思。大汗通过占星师们的预测，认为这座城市将会发生反叛，对抗皇权。因此大汗在河的对岸又修建了一座新城，并给这座新城取名为大都。他命令旧城中的居民都搬到新城，只留下那些他认为没有任何反叛迹象的人，因为新都中没有足够多的房子容纳旧都所有的居民。

新都呈正方形，周长有二十四英里。它被土筑的城墙围绕，有二十步高。城墙底部宽十步，从底部向顶部逐渐变窄，到了顶部大概就只有三步宽了。城墙上有城垛并被涂成白色。城墙一共有十二道门，每道门旁边都有一座漂亮宏伟的建筑物守卫，算上每个角上的建筑物，城墙的四面每面都有三道门和五个守卫的建筑物。每座建筑物里都有很大的大厅，用来贮藏守城士兵的武器。

城里的街道又宽又直，从城墙的顶部一眼看去，就能看到整条道路一直延伸到对面的城门。城里到处都是官邸、客栈和平民居住的房屋。主要街道的两旁有着各式各样的货摊和商店。城中所有建筑用地都按照规定被划成四方形，每块地都有充足的空间来修建带有后院和花园的宽敞住宅。这些地皮被分给每户的户主，这样一块地属于一位户主，另一块地属于另一位户主，所有土地都这样分配。每块地和街区都被一条条马路包围，这样整个城市就被一块块方形的土地编排得像一个棋盘，如此巧妙精致，以至于无法用语言描述。

城里、城外都有着不计其数的居民和房屋，事实上城郊外的居民要比城里的居民还多。每个城门外都有一片城郊，一片连一片，长度大概有三四英里。城郊离城内一英里的地方，有很多为各地商人提供住所的客栈。每个国家的人都被指定住在一种客栈，比如一种客栈专门供伦巴第人居住，另一种指定给德意志人，还有一种供法兰西人使用。来这儿做生意的商人很多，一方面因为可汗提供了住所，另一方面是可汗为大家提供了一个有利可图的市场。除了可汗的宫殿外，城郊也有着和城里一样华丽的房屋和住宅。

大家要知道，人们去世后都不能被埋葬在城里。如果佛教徒归天，他的遗体将会被带到城郊外的一个地方火葬；其他人去世后也一样，他们的遗体会被带到城郊外的地方埋葬。同样地，任何暴力行动都会被带到城外执行。

城内的妓女都是非法的，而城郊则有近两万名妓女。她们有一个总管，下面又有管百人、千人的官员。每当有大使为了大汗的利益来时，大汗对他们都十分慷慨，会吩咐妓女总管，让他每天晚上给大使和他的随从们各派一名妓女。这些妓女每天都换，并且她们不收取任何费用，只把这当作向大汗纳的税。从这些妓女的人数大家就能大概推断出每日往返于他们业务的商人和访客的数量了。

被运往汗八里的珍贵奢华的物品比被送往其他城市的都多，宝物主要是从印度运来的，有宝石、珍珠和其他罕有的宝物。它们都是契丹和其他各省最珍贵，最昂贵的珍宝。这些宝物被大汗自己、贵族、贵妇、众多的客栈主人和其他居民以及被大汗盛情接待的访客所买走。这就是这些进口货物和国内生产的货物在城里的交易在总量上和价值上都能超过其他城市的原因。每天都有不下千担的丝被运到城里，城中还有各种用金银线制成的织物。不仅如此，汗八里旁，远近还有两百多个其他的城市，那儿的商人也会来到城里进行买卖交易。所以，城中有这么多来来往往的人也就不足为奇了。

城市的中央有一座高大钟楼，上面有一口大钟，每天晚上钟声敲响三次后，人们就不能在城中闲逛了。除了一些紧急情况，比如孕妇分娩和有人生病以外，任何人都不敢随意走动。那些有急事要出行的人也必须点着灯笼。每晚都有三十或四十人一组的士兵在城中巡逻，查找那些在三声钟响后还在外面的人。如果发现有人在街上，他就会立刻被逮捕，关进监狱。第二天，会有长官了解他外出的原因，如果他被认为有罪，就会根据情节的轻重处以杖责，而这些杖刑有时候是会致命的。采取这种处罚方式，可以避免受刑人流血，因为根据他们专于星象的巴克斯的说法，让人流血是罪恶的行为。

每一个城门有不下千人守卫，大家不要以为这是对城内居民的不信任。事实上，这一部分出于对大汗的尊重，另一方面也是为了防止有人叛乱。由于占星家们的预言，大汗对契丹旧城中的居民一直心存怀疑。

下面让我向大家描述一次城中契丹人的叛乱。这是一次有计划的行动。大汗曾经任命过十二个人，给予他们处置土地和任命官吏的大权，其中有一个撒拉森人，叫作艾哈迈德。他的精力和才能都很出众，比其他十一个人权力更大，并且深得大汗的信任，可以为所欲为。从他死了之后的事情可以看出，他是用邪恶的巫术蛊惑了皇帝，以至于让大汗对他言听计从，得以肆意妄行。他曾经掌管了一切任命官吏和惩治罪犯的权力。每次他想铲除不喜欢的人，不管是公正还是不公正，他都会向大汗禀报：“某人应该被处死，因为他做了一些事情触犯了您的王权。”而大汗则会说：“按你说的去做吧。”于是艾哈迈德就会处死此人。其他人看到大汗对他如此信任，给他如此大的权力，即使自己有再大的本事，也都不敢冒犯他。如果有被他诬告的人想为自己辩护，他也没有机会反驳或者澄清案情，因为他无法给出证据—所有的人都害怕得罪艾哈迈德。这样，艾哈迈德处死了许多无辜的人。

此外，他看上的美丽女子，若是未婚的，就会被强娶过来，若是已婚，他也会想方设法要她顺从。当他得知哪家的女儿容貌美丽时，他就会派手下的地痞流氓去找到她的父亲，然后说：“你有什么想法？不如把你的女儿给了艾哈迈德，我们可以帮你回禀一声，赏你一个三年的官做。”这样父亲就只有将他的女儿送给艾哈迈德。然后艾哈迈德就会向大汗禀报：“有某个职位空缺，或者将要于某时空缺，有谁正适合这份工作。”而大汗总会说：“按照你的意思办吧。”于是艾哈迈德就会把这个人安置做官。这样一来，部分由于父亲们的野心，部分由于他们的恐惧，这些漂亮的女子要不就被艾哈迈德娶走，要不就成了他的情人。艾哈迈德还有二十五个儿子，因为他而身居高官，他们中的有些人借着父亲的名义，像他们父亲一样强抢民女，还犯下了很多其他罪行。艾哈迈德还大肆收敛财物，因为每个想得到职位和官职的人都会向他进贡丰厚的财物。

艾哈迈德拥有和统治者一样的权力长达二十二年。在他统治下的契丹人，发现他不停地做着不正当和令人厌恶的事情，想尽办法蹂躏妇女，终于忍无可忍。他们决心刺杀艾哈迈德，并反对政府的统治。有一个叫张易的契丹人，是一个千夫长，他的母亲、女儿、妻子都曾经被艾哈迈德凌辱过。被强烈的仇恨所驱使，张易和一个叫王著的万夫长联合起来密谋反叛。他们打算在大汗结束在汗八里三个月的逗留前往上都后再采取行动，大汗通常在大都也要停留三个月，这时皇太子真金照例也会离开汗八里。而艾哈迈德就会留下来守城，只有在出现紧急情况时，才会派人传话给在上都的大汗。这两个密谋者决定将他们的计划告诉国家中契丹人的领导者，等到大家一致同意后，就告诉其他城中的朋友。他们的计划是在指定的一天采取行动，以烽火为信号，所有谋反者收到信号后，就立刻行动，杀死所有有胡须的人，然后通过烽火台将信号传递给其他城中的人，大家就会采取同样的行动。他们杀死所有有胡须的人，因为契丹人不留胡须，而鞑靼人、撒拉森人和基督徒则留有胡须。大家必须知道所有的契丹人都憎恨大汗的统治，因为大汗所任命的统治者都是鞑靼人或者撒拉森人，他们对待契丹人就像对待奴隶一样，让契丹人无法忍受。再加上大汗征服契丹是靠武力，而不是通过合法的方式。所以，大汗也没有得到契丹人的信任和尊重，并且他把统治的权力都交给鞑靼人、撒拉森人和基督徒，这些人依附皇族，忠于大汗，并视契丹人为异族。

当王著和张易在约定的一天夜间潜入皇宫后，王著就坐在王座上，在他面前点起许多灯火，然后派人去告诉艾哈迈德，太子真金在夜里突然返京，要他立刻前来觐见。当艾哈迈德听到这个消息后，虽然十分疑惑，但还是立刻前往。在他去面见太子的路上，他遇见一个叫科甲台的鞑靼人，他手下有一万二千士兵，负责城内日常的巡逻，他问艾哈迈德：“这么晚了，您还要去哪儿啊？”艾哈迈德回答道：“去面见太子真金，他刚到。”科甲台说：“怎么可能？难道他行动如此隐蔽，以至于我都没有听到任何消息？”于是他带着他手下的一小队人跟着艾哈迈德一同进宫。而此时谋反者对自己说道：“只要我们杀死艾哈迈德，就再没有什么好惧怕的了。”这时艾哈迈德进入了皇宫，看见宫中灯壁辉煌，误以为王著是真金，跪在了他的面前，一旁的张易立刻用手中的剑砍下了他的脑袋。

当在宫殿外守候的科甲台看到这种情况后，大叫一声：“叛乱！”然后用箭射向坐在王座上的王著，杀死了他。然后他吩咐手下抓住了张易，并立刻向全城宣告，城中任何人都不得出门，只要被发现，就地处死。契丹人见鞑靼人已经发现了他们的密谋，并且他们的首领一个被杀、一个被抓，就放弃了叛乱，都留在屋里，也就没有向其他城中准备反叛的人发出叛乱信号。科甲台立刻派人向大汗详细汇报所发生的事情，大汗即刻吩咐进行彻底调查，并且根据情节轻重惩罚叛乱者。第二天清晨，科甲台就审问所有契丹人，处死了许多同谋者，当发现城中的其他人也有叛乱意图时，也采取了同样的搜捕行动。

大汗回到汗八里后，想知道这次叛乱的原因，随后他得知了艾哈迈德父子的恶劣行径。大汗发现艾哈迈德和他的七个儿子娶了不计其数的妻妾，更不用说那些被强暴的妇女。于是大汗下令没收艾哈迈德搜刮的财物，并把它们从旧城运往新城，成为大汗的财产。这些财物之多令人难以想象。他还下令将艾哈迈德的尸体从坟墓中挖出来，扔到大街上让野狗撕咬，那些和艾哈迈德一样犯下滔天罪行的儿子们都被处以剥皮的刑罚。大汗还注意到了撒拉森人邪恶的教义，他们认为只要不是针对与他们同宗教的人，一切恶行，包括杀人都被看作合法的行为。出于此因，罪大恶极的艾哈迈德和他的儿子们根本没有意识到自己犯下的罪行，大汗对此深恶痛绝。他召集所有的撒拉森人到他面前，禁止他们按照自己的法律去行事。大汗还特别命令他们采取鞑靼人的婚姻制度；在猎杀动物时，不能像以前那样割断动物的喉咙，而是要剥开肚子。当这一切发生时，马可·波罗正好待在那儿。

至于那一万两千保卫大汗的士兵，他们被叫作卡西坦，也就是“大汗的骑士与臣子”。大汗拥有这支军队不是因为惧怕任何人，而是把这作为皇权的标志。这一万二千人被分为三组，每组三千人。每组士兵都要在大汗的宫殿驻守三天三夜，然后再轮换下一组驻守，整年就如此轮换。白天时，剩下的九千士兵不能离开皇宫，除非是受到大汗的指派或者是有很重要的私事，比如有很严重的事情发生，如父亲、兄弟、其他亲近的亲属即将去世，或者如果不立刻回去就会遭到巨大损失时，在经长官同意后，他才可以离开皇宫。而在晚上，这九千人是可以回家的。

大汗设宴的座次要这样安排：大汗坐北朝南，高高在上，皇后坐在他的左侧。右侧低一些的地方，按年龄大小坐着皇子、皇孙和其他皇室成员，太子真金的座位要高于其他皇子，并且他们的头和大汗的脚刚好在同一高度，而在他们旁边更低一些的地方是其他贵族的座位。妇女们也按同样的方式安排座次，皇媳、皇孙媳和其他亲王的妻子坐在大汗的左侧低一些的地方，贵族夫人和武官夫人的座位则被安排在她们左侧更低的地方。所有人都按照大汗的安排，坐在自己的位置上。这样的安排使得大汗可以看到大殿中所有的人。但是大家不要以为所有的人都有座位，大部分武官和贵族都要坐在地毯上就餐。而在大殿外参加宴会的人有四万之多，他们中有许多带着贵重礼物前来参拜的使者，有带来新鲜玩意的外国人，还有一些想加官进爵的人们。这些就是参加大汗恩赐的宴会，或者庆祝婚礼的人们和场景。

在大汗御案所在的大殿中央，摆放着一件方形器具，每边长约十步，十分精美大气。四面雕刻着栩栩如生的动物形象，并且都是镀金的，中间是空心的，放着盛满美酒的金质带把瓶装器皿。在每个角上各有一个小瓶，分别盛着马奶、骆驼奶等其他饮品。御案旁边摆放着盛放大汗饮品的各种容器。每个容器都用纯金制成，里面的美酒和珍贵的饮品倒进纯金的大酒壶中，足够八到十个人饮用。其中每两人中间都会放置一个酒壶，每人都有一个带把的金杯，用来盛放酒壶中的酒。对于妇女也是同样安排。这些酒壶和器皿都十分珍贵。大汗有如此之多的金银器皿，没有亲眼见到的人是无法想象的。在一旁服侍大汗进餐和饮酒的人都是大汗指定的男爵。他们用金丝制成的面纱遮住自己的嘴和鼻子，这样他们的气息和体液就不会污染大汗的食物和饮品。

还有一些男爵被派去照看那些新来的不了解大殿里规矩的客人，告诉他们应该坐在什么位置上。这些男爵一直在大殿中走动，询问客人们有什么需要，如果有谁需要酒、奶，或者其他东西，他们就立刻让侍者送来。大殿所有入口处都有两个身材魁梧、手持长棍的侍卫站在两边，因为进入大殿的人不允许踩到大殿的门槛，而只能跨过去。如果有人不小心踩到了门槛，两旁的侍卫就会拿走他的衣服，然后让他拿赎金来取；如果不拿衣服，他们就会给他一顿毒打。新来的宾客不知道这些规矩，那些指定的男爵就会被派去提醒他们注意。这样做是因为他们认为踩到门槛是不祥之兆。在大家离开大殿的时候，由于客人喝醉了酒，不那么注意，这时就没有这些规矩了。

大殿里有各种各样的乐器，当大汗要饮酒时，他们就开始演奏，拿着酒杯的侍从将酒奉上后，就后退三步，然后跪下，这时所有的男爵和宾客也都跪下，表现出对大汗的谦卑，直到大汗喝完酒。每次大汗要喝酒时，都会有这样的礼仪。至于食物，我不用多说，大家一定能够想象食物的充足。还要告诉大家，男爵和武官是不能在宴会上就餐的，但是可以带来他们的妻子同其他的妇人一起就餐。当所有人都就餐完毕后，桌子就被撤掉，魔术、杂技和其他项目的表演者就会进入大殿，带来丰富多彩的节目。他们在大汗面前竭尽全力表演，得到宾客们的阵阵掌声。当表演结束后，宾客们就离开大殿回住所了。

大家要知道，鞑靼人将自己的生日当作节日来庆祝。大汗的生日是农历九月二十八日。每年大汗都要在这一天举办除新年之外的最盛大的庆祝活动。在这一天，大汗会披上金袍，另外，还有一万二千名男爵和武官也会披上大汗赐予的长袍，这些长袍与大汗的金袍颜色款式相同—都是用金线银线织成，并且腰间有金质的束带，只是不如大汗的贵重。这些长袍，就像他们经常佩戴的宝石和珍珠一样珍贵，大概价值一万金币—这可不是小数目。而大汗每年要赐给这一万两千名男爵和武官十三次长袍，这样一来他们就能穿得和他一样，显得富丽华贵。大家可以看出这不是轻而易举就能做到的事情，也再无其他皇帝能够承担这样的花销了。

在这个盛大的节日里，所有的鞑靼人和大汗统治下的省份和地区的贵族地主，都要向大汗献上与他们身份相符的珍贵礼物。此外还有很多向大汗讨要官位的人也会向大汗奉上贵重礼物，然后大汗就让掌管此事的十二名总管按照申请人的功绩进行奖赏。在这一天，所有的佛教徒、基督教徒、撒拉森人和其他种族的臣民都要唱赞美诗，点长明灯，焚香祈祷，虔诚地恳求他们所信奉的神明，让他们保佑大汗长命百岁，幸福安康。这一天就在祝福祈祷、愉快欢庆中度过。在描述完这个节日后，就让我向大家介绍另一个重大的节日—庆祝新年的白色节。

他们的新年开始于每年二月，根据习俗，大汗和他的臣民，无论男女，都穿上白色的衣服，因为他们认为白色的装束代表着吉利祥和，在新年里穿上它就能保佑他们在整年中富贵幸福。在新年这一天，大汗统治下的所有首领，和各个省份和地区的贵族地主都要向大汗献上真金白银、珍珠宝石和大量高档白衣，祝福大汗在全年中锦衣玉食、幸福快乐。贵族、官员和平民百姓在这一天也互赠礼物，并且相互祝贺道：“万事如意，心想事成。”这样一来，他们就能在新的一年里诸事顺利了。

在这一天里，大汗还会收到十万匹价值连城的白色骏马，大汗的五千头大象也会披上画有鸟兽的衣服，每头大象的背上都驮有两个大箱子，里面装满了精美贵重的器皿和白色的长袍。大象后面跟着不计其数的骆驼，也穿着衣服，驮着节日所需的物品。它们排成纵列，从大汗面前走过，极其壮观。

在节日的早晨，宴席摆好之前，所有的国王、公爵、伯爵、子爵、男爵、武官、占星家、医师、养鹰人和其他官员都要来到大殿拜见大汗。不能进入大殿的人，就在大殿外大汗可以看见的地方叩拜。让我向大家介绍一下他们位置的安排。在最前面的是皇子、皇孙和其他皇室成员；后面是大王、公爵和其他官员，按照官位大小，有秩序地排列。当他们各就各位后，一位高官就站起来，用洪亮的声音说道：“致敬叩首。”话音未落，所有的人都下跪叩首，像祝福上帝一样高声祝福大汗。然后高官说道：“保佑大汗永远幸福快乐！”众人便齐声应道：“天佑吾皇！”高官又道：“保佑大汗国富民强，国泰民安！”众人再次应道：“天佑吾皇！”这样的礼仪要重复四次。然后他们就走向装饰得极其华丽的祭坛，上面摆放着刻有历任大汗名字的红色牌位，前面摆有制作精美华丽的香炉。官员们毕恭毕敬地向着牌位焚香叩首。随后他们就退回到自己的位置上，当所有人礼毕后，他们就呈上前面所提到的各种珍贵礼物。等大汗过目后，宴会就正式开始，皇亲国戚、文武百官就按照上文中所提到的次序依次入座。宴会完毕后是各种表演。表演结束后，赴宴的人们就回各自住所了。

大汗指定了十三个节日，每个农历月份中都有一个。每个节日都有一万两千名被叫作卡西坦的男爵参加。他们是最忠于大汗并且离大汗最近的人。大汗赏赐他们每人十三件不同颜色的长袍，每件都有珍珠宝石镶嵌，价值连城。大汗还赏赐他们每人一条美丽贵重的金腰带和一双用银线镶边的皮质靴子，也是同样的精美珍贵。他们的服装是如此华丽庄重，以至于每个人都像是国王一样。大汗自己也有十三套颜色类似的长袍，装饰得更加奢华名贵。并且，大汗与他的男爵们总是穿一样颜色的长袍。

这些长袍共有十五万六千件，它们的价值难以估计，更不用说那些昂贵的腰带与靴子了。大汗准备这些只是为了增加节日气氛。

让我再用一个值得大家注意的事实总结一下。有一头大狮子被带到大汗面前，狮子是没被锁住的，当它见到大汗时，立刻趴在大汗面前，表现出深深的敬意，似乎它知道大汗的地位一样，这的确是一件让人惊叹的事情。

下面，让我们来谈谈大汗的狩猎活动。

大家应该知道大汗停留在汗八里的三个月（十二月、一月、二月）中，都会下令进行狩猎和捕鹰活动，距离汗八里六十天路程以内地区的所有人都要参与。各地的长官必须将较大的猎物，比如野猪、雄鹿、雄獐、熊或者其他类似的大型猎物进贡给大汗。所以每个长官都聚集其统治地区中所有的猎人，派他们去野兽出没的地方，轮流射杀猎物。他们有时候会放出猎犬咬死猎物，但是大多数时候是用箭射死它们。然后他们挖去猎物的内脏，放在两轮推车上运送给大汗。这些猎物，都能够在三十天之内被送给大汗，总数很多。那些离大汗三十天到六十天路程的地区，由于距离太远，不适合向大汗运送猎物，但是他们要向大汗运送适当装饰过和硝过的兽皮，这样大汗就可以用它们来制作军需品。

大家要知道，大汗还饲养了许多善于捕猎的豹子和山猫。大汗还拥有一些大狮子，比埃及的狮子还要大一些，这些狮子的皮毛十分光亮，身上还有黑色、橙色、白色的条纹。它们被训练捕捉野猪、公牛、熊、野驴、雄鹿和雄獐等其他猎物。这些狮子猎食这些高贵动物的场景是十分壮观的。当狮子被带出来捕捉猎物时，它们被关在笼子里，笼子放在车上，每只狮子旁边都有一只小狗做伴。由于它们见到猎物后会十分凶残和冲动，人们无法控制，所以这些狮子都要被关在笼子里。它们都要被放在下风的位置，因为一旦那些猎物嗅到狮子的气味，就会立刻逃窜得不见踪影。大汗还训练了许多鹰，用来捕捉狼、狐狸和棕色的鹿。那些被用来猎狼的鹰，体型巨大，强壮有力，再大的狼也逃不出这些鹰的鹰爪。

下面我将向大家介绍一下大汗拥有的众多优秀猎犬。大家要知道在大汗的男爵中，有两兄弟叫作伯颜和明安，他们又被叫作钦纽奇，意思是“大型猎犬的饲养者”。他们两人分别有一万名随从，一万人穿着红色制服，另一万人穿着蓝色制服。无论什么时候陪伴大汗出猎，他们都穿着这样的制服。不管是有两千人还是一万人，他们每人都领着至少一只大型猎犬，有时候也会带着两只或者更多，这样，猎犬的总数是极多的。当大汗打猎时，这两兄弟中的一人带着他的一万手下和五千猎犬，跟在大汗的一侧，而另一个兄弟则带着他的手下和猎犬，跟在另一侧。两队的配合十分默契，队伍有一天的路程那么长。这样，只要被他们发现的野生动物都能被猎杀。这样一场猎人和猎犬的狩猎活动是多么壮观啊！大家可以想象，大汗和他的男爵们带着猎鹰在猎场上行猎，猎犬跟在两边，捕捉熊、雄鹿和其他野兽，的确是一幕壮观的场景。从十月初一直到次年的三月底，这两兄弟每天都要负责向大汗和他的随从提供数以千计的猎物，包括各种鸟兽，鹌鹑还不计在内，同时还要尽全力为大汗提供鱼类，提供足够三人食用的鱼被视为猎杀了一头野兽。

当大汗在这儿度过十二月、一月、二月这三个月后，在三月份，大汗会继续向南前进，到达一个离海仅有两天路程的地方。陪同他的有一万名养鹰者，五千只矛隼、游隼和猎隼，此外还有大量的苍鹰沿河捕猎。大家要知道，大汗并不把所有的随从集中在一个地方，而是将他们分成不同的小队，每队一两百人或者更多，将他们分派到不同的地方。他们各自进行捕猎，大部分猎物都被进贡给大汗。大汗手下的一万人被分为两人一组，他们被叫作塔斯克尔，意思是“看守人”。这些人两人一组，被分配到各个地方，这样就能观察到一片广阔的领域。他们每人都有一个哨子和一块头巾，用这些来控制猎鹰。当大汗命令猎鹰去行猎时，这些养鹰者没有必要紧跟在猎鹰后面，因为这些看守人会仔细关注猎鹰的去向，当有人需要帮助时，其他人立刻就会给予援助。

所有大汗和男爵的猎鹰爪子上都系有银牌，上面刻着它们主人和看守人的名字，便于看管。这样一来，当猎鹰被收回时，就能辨认出它的主人，然后物归原主。如果辨认不出主人，就将它送到叫巴尔盖奇的男爵那儿，巴尔盖奇是专门负责失物招领的官员。任何人如果发现不能辨认出主人的马、剑或者猎鹰等，都会送到这个男爵那儿，由他来保管。如果发现物件的人没有及时地将别人的遗失物交给巴尔盖奇，他就会被看作贼。而遗失东西的人到官员那儿登记后，只要官员收到他们的遗失物，就会立刻归还给他们。这些官员有专门办公的地方，通常在大营的最高处，顶上还插着高高飘扬的旗帜，这样那些遗失东西的人很容易就能找得到，所遗失的东西也能被找到并归还给他们。

当大汗继续向海边前进时，旅途中会出现许多精彩的狩猎活动，世界上没有任何运动能和这种狩猎活动相媲美。大汗一般都会坐在一个精致的小木亭里，木亭由四头大象驮着，亭子内部用金子装饰，外部则用狮子皮装饰。大汗身边总有十二只最好的矛隼供他娱乐，还有一些男爵在他身边侍奉陪伴。当骑着马的男爵向大汗报道“陛下，有鹤经过”时，大汗就下令将木亭的顶部打开，这样他就能看到鹤群，然后他就吩咐他的随从将那些矛隼带来，大汗会从中选取几只，放飞它们。这样，大汗躺在亭中就能看到这些矛隼捕食鹤群的全过程，这给大汗带来了极大的娱乐和享受。同时，男爵和骑士们也骑着马，陪伴在大汗周围。世界上再也没有人能够享受到这样的运动和娱乐。

当大汗前行至一个叫作卡察摩都的地方时，就会在这儿安营扎寨，他的儿子、男爵和妃子等不下一万人都会在此停留，场面十分壮观。让我来向大家形容一下大汗所在的帐篷：帐篷中设有大汗会见大臣的宫室，十分宽敞，能够容纳一千名骑兵。帐篷的入口朝南开，还有供男爵和其他大臣休息的厅堂。和宫室相连的是另外一个朝西的帐篷，是大汗私下与大臣会面的地方。在一个大厅堂的后面有一个漂亮的大房间，大汗在这儿就寝。除此之外，还有很多的房间和帐篷，只是不和这个大帐篷相连。让我来告诉大家这两个厅堂和房间的构造。每个厅堂都由精心雕刻过的腊梅木做支撑，厅堂外部都铺着一层十分美丽的狮子皮，有黑、白、橙三色并呈条纹状，能够防风挡雨。里侧还有一层白貂和黑貂的皮毛，是两种最昂贵的皮毛。最上乘的黑貂皮做成外衣，价值两千金币，制成一件普通的衣服也要一千金币。鞑靼人将黑貂皮称为“毛皮之王”。黑貂的体型和貂鼠差不多。这两个厅堂就是用这些貂皮连接起来，极有艺术感地拼凑成一幅壮观场景。大汗的房间与两个厅堂相连，外面同样是狮子皮，内部是黑貂和白貂的皮毛，手艺精巧，设计独特。固定两个厅堂和大汗房间的绳子都是丝做的。这三个帐篷如此精细贵重，其他小国国王是承受不起的。

在这三个帐篷周围还搭有其他帐篷，也十分精美，供大汗的妃子居住。还有大量的帐篷用来放置矛隼、猎鹰和其他鸟兽。在这里宿营的人数几乎超出了想象，大家可以想象一下大汗就像居住在他富庶的城市里一样，因为各种人都聚集在这儿，大汗的家眷、医师、占星家、养鹰人和其他不计其数的官员，一切都像在他的都城里一样井然有序。

大汗在此处停留直到春季，不久之后便是我们的复活节。在他停留期间，大汗也从不停止在湖边或者河边行猎，并且猎取了大量的鹤、天鹅和其他鸟类。大汗的随从也被派到周围其他地方，为大汗捕猎大量的野兽和鸟类。在此期间，大汗享受着世界上最好的休闲运动，没有亲眼见到的人，是难以相信的。到目前为止，大汗的伟大，他的状态，他的享乐都超出了我的描述。

让我再告诉大家一个事实。在大汗居住的地方方圆二十天路程的地区，不管是商人、工匠，还是农民都不允许饲养任何猎鹰、捕食猎物的鸟类和其他追逐猎物的猎犬。但是在大汗统治的其他地区，居民是可以随意用猎鹰和猎犬捕捉猎物的。大家还要知道，每年的三月到十月，在大汗统治的领域中，任何亲王、男爵和其他人都不允许猎杀野兔、雄鹿、羚羊或者其他野兽，这样这些动物就能够更好地繁衍生息。任何违反规定的人都会受到严厉的惩罚，因为这是由大汗亲自制定的规矩。人们都严格遵守大汗的命令，即使野兔、雄鹿和其他兽类出现在一个人面前，他也不会捕捉或者伤害它们。

当狩猎季节结束，复活节快来临时，大汗和他的随从们就出发，按原路返回汗八里，一路上也和来时一样行猎，享受着运动娱乐。

大汗在汗八里铸造他的货币，铸造过程是如此的系统，大家甚至可能认为大汗掌握了炼金术。下面让我在这里向大家描述一下。

大汗是按如下程序铸造货币的：将树皮从桑树（叶子可以用来养蚕）上剥下来，剥出树干和树皮之间的内皮，然后将它捣碎弄平，用浆糊粘成薄片，就像棉花制成的纸一样，不过是黑色的。随后，将它裁成大小不一的长方形，最小的薄片价值半个图洛，稍大一些的价值一个图洛，再大一些的价值一个威尼斯银币，还有的价值两个、五个和十个银币，或者一个、三个、十个金币。所有的薄片都要加印大汗的图章。整个制造过程都十分正式严肃，就像在铸造真金白银一样。每张货币上都有专门的官员签名，加印图章。当这些程序都完成后，由大汗指定的一个总管就将大汗的印章蘸上朱砂，盖到每张纸币上，这样印章的图案就保留在了纸币上。这时候纸币才成为真正的货币，任何人伪造钱币都会受到极其严厉的惩罚。

大汗制造了大量的这种货币，可以买到世界上所有的奇珍异宝。所有在大汗统治领域内的交易都要使用这种货币，没有人敢冒生命危险拒绝使用。并且，大汗统治下的臣民也都欣然接受了这种纸币，因为不管是货物、珍珠、宝石还是金银，都可以用同样的货币来支付。他们可以用这些纸币买到任何东西。

每年都有几次，许多商人带上珍珠、宝石、金银和其他贵重物品，比如金银线织成的衣物，进贡给大汗。大汗就会召集挑选各种货物的专家，让他们检查商人们带来的货物，并且给出合适的价钱。这些专家们仔细检查货物后，就付给商人上面所提到的纸币。而商人们会欣然接受纸币，因为他们以后可以用这些纸币在大汗统治的疆域内买到各种货物。全年中，这些被送来的不同货物价值四十万金币，都是用纸币支付的。

大汗每年都会几次下令臣民们将他们所拥有的宝石、珍珠、金银送到铸币厂，数量之多是难以估计的，然后大汗会付给他们纸币。通过这种方法，大汗就拥有了他统治领土内所有的金银珠宝。

当这些纸币流通太久，被撕坏或者磨损时，可以将它们送回铸币厂，扣除百分之三的价格后换成新的纸币。如果有谁需要购买金银来制造金银器，比如盘子、腰带或者其他装饰品，他可以拿这些纸币向铸币厂的官员购买金银。同样，大汗的军队也是用这种纸币来发放军饷的。

我已经向大家提到过大汗拥有比任何人都多的财富。我可以进一步地说，世界上所有其他统治者拥有的财富加起来也比不上大汗一人所拥有的财富。

大家已经知道大汗任命过十二位权力极大的男爵，负责审查所有的军事决定，包括军队的行动、高级军官的更换、兵力的配置，以及根据战争情况派送军队的数量等。同时，他们还负责区分强壮勇敢的战士与胆怯懦弱的士兵，提升那些勇敢的士兵，对无能胆小的士兵则给予降职处分。如果一个千夫长在行动中没有良好表现，男爵们认定他不配留在现在的职位，就会将他降职为百夫长；相反，如果千夫长的行为证明他是可信而优秀的，就会被认为适合更高级的职位，男爵们会任命他为万夫长。不过，官员的升降都是要经过大汗同意的，他们会向大汗禀报：“某人不配在某个职位上。”大汗命令道：“那让他降级吧！”这样，官员就会被降职。当他们认为某人的功绩值得使他升职时，他们就向大汗禀报：“某人是千夫长，但是完全有能力成为一个万夫长。”如果得到大汗的认可，大汗就会授予他适合的奖牌，然后立刻给予他物质奖励，以激励其他的官员。这十二名男爵组成的议会被叫作枢密院—也就是“军事委员会”，是除了大汗以外的最高权力机构。

除此之外，大汗还任命了另外十二个男爵负责处理三十四个省份的事务。他们都住在汗八里的一座宫殿内，这座宫殿有许多厅室，每个省份都有一个主要官员和其他办事员，他们都居住在宫殿内。这些官员和办事员掌管他们负责省份的所有事务，直接服从于十二名男爵。这十二名男爵被赋予任命各个省份官员的权力，当他们认为某人有能力并且适合某个职位时，他们就向大汗禀报，当大汗认可他们的任命后，就授予此人奖牌。他们还负责监督各省的税收和经费的使用以及除军事活动外的一切事务。这个议会被叫作中书省，他们办公的地方叫作中书院。

枢密院和中书省都是最高国家机关，除了大汗外，没人拥有比他们更高的权力。但是枢密院，也可以叫作军事委员会，被认为拥有更高的等级和尊严。

在这里，我还不打算向大家介绍那些不计其数的省份，在后面我再向大家介绍。现在让我们了解一下大汗用于寄送信件的邮递系统。

以汗八里为中心，有许多条路通向各个省份，这些路都以各个省的名字命名。整个系统的设计十分精巧。当大汗派出信使时，他每走二十五英里就会发现一个驿站。每个驿站都有宽敞明亮的房间供他们休息。这些房间里有着舒适的床铺，上面铺有厚厚的丝质床单，供高级别的使者使用。即使一个国王来到这儿，也会觉得居住得十分舒适。在这里，按照大汗的要求，饲养了不下四百匹马，随时准备着供大汗的信使骑乘。大家要知道，每条通往各个省份的大路上，每隔二十五英里或者三十英里都有一个这样的驿站，每个驿站也都有三四百匹马供信使骑乘，这在大汗所统治的所有省份和王国都是一样的。

在一些偏僻的乡村，没有多少房屋和居民，大汗仍然建造了驿站，和大路上的驿站有着相同的居住环境，配备了相同的马匹和其他物品。只是各个驿站间的距离要稍远一些，大概相隔三十五英里，在有些地方还超过了四十英里。

通过这样的安排，大汗的信使在全国送递信件时都能有住处和充足的马匹。毫无疑问，这使大汗享有高于任何人的特权和最丰富的资源。大家要知道，有超过二十万的马匹被饲养在这些驿站，供信使使用。单是驿站的数目就超过了一万座，并且每个驿站都配备精良。整个系统是如此的惊人和昂贵，任何言语都难以描述。

如果有人问，他们怎么能有如此多的人力来完成这项工作，他们靠什么生活，我的回答是这样的：所有的佛教徒和撒拉森人一样，每人都有六个、八个或者十个妻子，只要他们能够供养，便可以随便娶妻。这样他们也就有了许多孩子，有很多男人都有三十多个儿子，可以跟随他一起从军。这是由于他们有众多妻子的缘故。而我们实行一夫一妻制，如果妻子不能生育，丈夫也要和她共同生活，也就不能拥有孩子，因此我们的人口要远远少于他们。而且他们的食物也不会短缺，因为他们的主要食物是米、粟等，尤其是鞑靼人、契丹人和蛮子，而这些作物在他们国家产量十分丰富。他们不吃面包，而是将米、粟和牛奶或者肉煮熟后食用。小麦在他们国家的产量不是很高，他们通常将收获的小麦做成面条或者面饼食用。在他们的国家，没有闲置土地，家禽繁殖也十分迅速。当他们服兵役时，每人都有六匹、八匹或者更多的马匹供他自己使用。这样也就不难理解为什么这个国家有如此多人口和如此多谋生手段。

现在让我向大家描述另外一件和驿站密切相关的事情。在各个驿站之间，每隔三英里就有一个站点，每个站点大概有四十户徒步为大汗送信的信使。他们系着长长的腰带，身上挂着铃铛，这样当他们送信时，离着很远的距离就能听到他们的声音。他们总是快速跑步送信，但是从来不超过三英里，在三英里外的另一个站点的信使听到铃声后，就会准备好收信，当第一个送信人到达时，新的信使就接过他要送达的物品和书记员给他的小条，然后就开始跑步送信。当他跑完三英里后，又有另一个信使接替，如此反复。通过这些徒步的信使，大汗在一天一夜就能收到原本需要十天才能收到的消息。因为这些徒步信使可以不到一天一夜走完十天的路程，或者用两天两夜的时间走完二十天的路程。在果实成熟的季节，通过这种方法，白天在汗八里采摘的水果，在第二天晚上就能送到大汗所在的城市—上都，而两个城市原本需要十天的路程。

在每隔三英里的站点都有一个书记员，负责记录每个信使到达和离开的时间和日期，每个站点都要执行这样的记录。同时，每月还有官吏来巡查，检查每一个站点，这是为了找出粗心大意的信使并惩罚他们。大汗对这些信使和站点的工作人员免除赋税，并且向他们提供充足的粮食来维持生活。

对于上文中提到的那些驿站中供皇家信使使用的马匹，我将向大家详细描述大汗是如何安排的。首先，大汗会询问：“离某个驿站最近的城市是哪座？”然后问：“它能为信使提供多少马匹？”接下来通过专门的官员进行调查，查出驿站周围的居民以及附近的城镇和村庄能够提供多少马匹，然后根据实际情况，让居民提供相应数目的马匹。所有的城市都一样，考虑到两个驿站之间有时候会穿过另一个城市，那么这个城市也要提供相应的马匹。他们提供马匹的费用可以从他们的赋税中扣除，因此，如果一个人需要交纳的税费总共价值一匹半马，那么他就要向邻近的驿站提供相应的马匹。但是大家要知道，不是任何时候驿站都有四百匹马。实际上，他们将二百匹马留在驿站一个月，供信使使用，另外两百匹则在草原上喂养。在月末的时候，再将喂养的两百匹马与留在驿站的马匹交换，这样就可以不断地轮流使用。

信使送信时，如果遇到必须经过的河流或者湖泊，邻近的城市就要准备三到四条渡船，随时供信使使用；如果遇到需要很多天才能穿越的沙漠，而且沙漠中没有其他常住居民，那么沙漠边缘的城市就要向大汗的特使提供充足的马匹和食物，以满足特使及其随从的需要。但是对这样的城市，大汗会给予特殊的补助。对于距离主路较远的驿站，那儿的马匹一部分由大汗自己提供，一部分由附近的城镇、村庄提供。

当遇到大汗急需的消息，比如发生叛乱或者其他引起大汗深思的事情时，信使可以每天行驶两百英里，有时候甚至是两百五十英里。让我来告诉大家这是如何做到的：当信使收到急需传递的信件时，就会持有一个刻有矛隼的牌子，作为传送急件的信号。如果有两个信使，他们出发时就骑上两匹强壮的马，系紧他们的腰带，用布包住头，以最快的速度前进，直到下一个驿站。当他们接近驿站时，他们会用牛角吹出声响，这种声音在很远的地方也能听到，这样，驿站就能为他们备好马匹。当他们到达时，就会换乘两匹已经套好马具、状态极佳的马，然后立刻出发，马不停蹄地赶往下一个驿站，再换马前进。这样，信使就能在一天内跑完两百五十英里，将消息送到大汗手中。事实上，如果是极其紧要的消息，他们每天可以奔驰三百英里。在这种情况下，他们晚上也不休息，如果没有月光，就由各个驿站的人持灯跑步，为他们照明。在夜间骑马的速度不如白天快，因为他们会受到跑步照明者速度的影响。能够如此劳累送信的使者，都会得到丰厚的奖励。

现在，让我向大家讲述一下大汗对臣民的恩赐。大汗总是希望能给予他的臣民直接的帮助，使他们能正常生活劳作，积累财富。每年他都要派出使者和巡查员，去全国各地了解臣民们是否因为天气原因、蝗灾或其他虫灾而导致收成不足。当他发现有些地区的百姓收成不足时，不但免去当年的赋税，还会赐予他们国库中的粮食，供他们播种和食用，这是一项重要的恩惠制度。大汗通常在夏天的时候给予百姓这种恩惠，而在冬天，灾难通常发生在牲畜身上。当大汗了解到某一地区居民的牲畜由于瘟疫而死亡时，他就将从其他省份通过什一税收上来的牲畜分给受灾的百姓，为了更进一步地帮助这些百姓，大汗还会免除他们当年的赋税。

当百姓的羊群、牛群或者其他畜群被雷电击中时，不管这些牲畜是属于一个人还是更多人，也不管畜群的数目有多大，大汗都会免去他们三年的赋税。同样地，当一艘装满货物的商船被雷电击中时，大汗也不会向那些货物征税，因为大汗认为，雷击是不祥之兆。他说：“老天爷一定是厌恶此人，才会用雷电袭击他。”所以，他并不希望那些惹老天爷愤怒的货品成为他的财物。

大汗还给予他的百姓另一项恩赐：在各条供信使送信或商人通商的大路上，大汗都令人在道路的两边种植树木，每两步的距离就种植一棵。这些树木长得十分茂盛，在很远的地方就能看到，这使得旅行者很容易就能辨认出路的方向，而不至于迷路。大家会发现，即使在荒无人烟的地方，道路两旁也会种植树木，这给旅行者和商人带来了极大便利。全国各地都如此。当道路穿过沙漠或者石山而无法种植树木时，大汗就下令用石头或者柱子作为路标，指明道路。还有专门的官员负责检查这些规定是否顺利执行。大汗种植树木的另一个原因，是因为算命者和占星家告诉他，种植树木可以延年益寿。

大家要知道，契丹省的居民大都饮用一种酒，我将向大家描述。他们用米和香料制成酒，因而比其他的酒类都要可口。酒水清澈香醇，通常加热后饮用，比其他酒品更容易醉人。

在契丹省的各个地方，都有一种黑色的石头，它们埋藏在山体中，可以像圆木一样燃烧。它们的火焰比木头更好，可以整夜不灭。要想点燃这种石头，需要先点燃它们中的一小部分，然后其他的才会被点着，就像木炭一样，一旦点着，就会散发出很高的热度。这种可以燃烧的石头遍布契丹全省。他们同样还拥有充足的可供燃烧的木柴，但是由于人口众多，有如此多的澡堂和浴室，水要不断地加热，木柴也就供不应求了。因为每个人每周都要至少洗三次澡，即使在冬季，每周也要洗一次。一些官员或富人在自己的家中就设有浴室供他们沐浴。因此，根本没有足够的木柴来满足如此大量的需求，而这些石头数量多，又便宜，很大程度上减少了木柴的使用。

让我们回到谷物的供应上。当大汗发现某年获得大丰收，并且粮食的价格很便宜时，就下令购买许多粮食，并储藏在一个大粮仓内，在这里，粮食被精心保管，即使放上三四年也不会腐烂。这样，大汗就储藏了大量各种粮食—小麦、大麦、粟、大米等。当作物收成不好，发生饥荒时，大汗就动用这些储备，仅以四分之一的价格卖出这些储备的粮食。大汗会发放足够多的粮食，这样就能满足所有人的需要。在大汗统治的地区都实行这样的政策，因而臣民的需求都能得到满足。

下面让我向大家讲述大汗是如何给予汗八里的贫困百姓慷慨施舍的。当大汗得知一些正直的家庭和一些有声望的人，由于遭遇不幸或者由于生病无法劳作，因而变得穷困，无法维持生计时，他就会给予这些家庭（通常由六到十个人或者更多人组成）可供他们使用一年的必需品。这些贫民在指定的日期就可以去专门掌管大汗花费的官员那儿，每人都要提供一个证明书，上面记载着上一年他获得的救济总数，这样今年也可以照前一年度那样发放救济。发放的物品中还包括衣物，其来源是大汗征收什一税获得的毛皮、丝、麻等材料。大汗将这些材料在指定的地点织成布匹并且贮存在那儿。由于所有的工匠每周都要为大汗工作一天，大汗就令他们将这些布匹做成衣服，供贫穷的家庭冬夏使用。大汗还为他的军队提供衣物，每个城市都要纺织羊毛布，作为向大汗上缴的什一税的一部分。

大家要知道，根据鞑靼人的习俗，在成为佛教徒之前，他们是从来不向他人施舍的。事实上，当有穷人向他们行乞时，他们会赶走这些人，并诅咒道：“让老天爷惩罚你吧，如果老天爷像爱护我一样的爱护你，就会保佑你生活无忧！”但是自从佛教徒中的圣人，尤其是巴克斯向大汗讲到乐善好施是一件功德无量的事情，他们的佛祖会因此而高兴之后，大汗才开始提供上文中提到的救济。向朝廷乞求食物的百姓都不会空手而归，每人都会得到一部分粮食。每天都有官员在指定的地点分发两万到三万碗米、粟。由于大汗对待贫苦百姓是如此的宽宏大量，慷慨救济，因此所有的百姓都对他十分尊敬，把他当作神明一样看待。

在汗八里还居住着许多基督徒、撒拉森人、契丹人和大概五千名占星家和算命者。大汗同样向他们提供衣物和食物，就像提供给那些穷人一样。这样他们就可以正常地在城里研究法术。他们有一种年鉴，上面记载了整年中每时每刻行星通过星群的运动。每年这些占星家、基督徒、撒拉森人和契丹人都要根据他们自己的记载，检查年鉴中每年每月天体运行的轨道和行星的位置。因为他们研究发现，每年每月在一些条件下，行星和星群运行的轨迹和所处的位置，与某些自然现象的发生有着一定联系。比如，某月会有雷雨天气，某月会有地震，某月又会有闪电和暴雨，还有一些月份会爆发瘟疫、战争和冲突等。根据逐月的发现，他们就会根据规律宣称将要发生什么事情，但是他们又说到老天爷可以随意改动他们所预言的事情。因此，他们将可能发生的事情逐月写在一个小册子上，以每册一个银币的价格卖给那些想知道全年中会发生什么事情的人。那些能够给出最准确预言的人被认为是最成功的法术大师，受到极大尊重。

当有人需要从事某项重要的商业活动，或者要去某处经商，或从事其他事业，或者想知道某项计划的结果时，他就会去询问占星家，告诉他们自己的生辰八字。根据习俗，每个人都从小被告知自己的生辰八字，父母会仔细地将孩子的生辰八字记在一个本子里，所以每个人都可以说出自己的生辰八字。他们认为十二年为一个周期，每年都有一个符号：第一年的符号为狮子，第二年是牛年，第三年是龙年，第四年是狗年，以此类推，直到十二年。所以，当有人被问及他是何时出生时，他就会回答：“狮年的某月某时某刻。”当十二年的周期完成后，他们就以同样的顺序开始一个新的十二年。所以当一个人向占星家或者算命者询问他们的冒险会有什么样的结果时，首先要说出他的生辰八字，算命者就可以确定他属于哪个星座和行星，然后预测他这次远行或者冒险的结果是好还是坏。同样地，如果询问者是一个商人，他就会被告知，他的行星正处于上升的通道，这会对他的冒险产生不利的影响，他需要等待一个更好的时机；如果他的星座刚好直接面向他准备离开的城门，则不利于他的出行，这样他就需要换一个城门离开，或者等到星座离开现在的位置；或者在某时某地，他会遇到强盗，在另外一些时候他会遭遇狂风暴雨，其他一些时候他的马匹会有一条腿骨折，在这儿他的一些非法交易会给他带来损失，在那儿又能给他带来一些利润等。这样算命者就会根据星象来预测他的整个旅程的运气变化，是顺利还是损失惨重。

我已经告诉大家，契丹百姓都是佛教徒，每人家里的墙壁上都会挂有一个图像，代表高高在上的天神，或者至少有一个写着神明名字的牌位。每天他们都要面对神明焚香叩拜，双手合十，叩头三次，祈求天神保佑他们长命百岁、智慧健康。除此之外，别无所求。在地上，他们还有一个叫作纳蒂盖的地神。他们给纳蒂盖配有妻子儿女，并以同样的方式对他焚香礼拜、合掌叩首。他们向他祈求风调雨顺、五谷丰登、儿孙满堂。

由于投入了很多时间去学习知识，因此他们在言行举止和许多方面的学识都超过了其他民族。他们谈吐高雅，讲究礼貌，总是相互问候，面目和善，举止高贵，吃饭时也十分讲究卫生。但是他们并不注重他们的灵魂，只关心他们现在的身体和自己的快乐。关于灵魂，他们相信灵魂不灭，认为当一个人死去后他的灵魂会进入另外一个身体，根据此人生前的善恶来决定投胎的好坏。也就是说：如果一个人生前是等级低下的人，但是他行为高尚，那么他死后第一次就会投胎于一位体面的妇人，然后成为一个体面的人；第二次就会投胎于一个贵妇，成为一个贵族。这样就会一次次越来越好，直到与神合为一体。但是，如果一个出身高贵的人，行为举止却十分恶劣，死后他就会投胎为一个农夫的儿子，然后再成为一只狗，越降越低。

他们对父母十分尊敬，如果有哪个孩子作出让父母生气的事情或者忽视了父母的需求，那么国家就有一个部门专门来惩罚这些忘恩负义的不孝子孙。

各种罪犯被抓住后都被关进监狱。如果没有被判处死刑，大汗规定，普通罪犯都要坐三年大牢，然后才被释放，但是在他们的脸颊上会烙有印记，以便于分辨。

赌博和行骗在这个国家曾经十分普遍，因此大汗下令禁止赌博和行骗。为了改变他们这种习惯，大汗说道：“我已经用武力征服了你们，你们所有的财产都属于我，所以，如果你们赌博，就是在用我的财产赌博。”但是，大汗并没有用这个理由从百姓那儿巧取豪夺。

我不会忘记向大家描述大汗的臣民和贵族觐见大汗时的举止。首先，不管是谁，在离大汗半英里的地方，就会表现出对大汗的尊敬，他们行为恭谦温顺，从不大声喧哗，也从不大声交谈。每位男爵或者贵族都会随身带有一个设计精巧的小容器，供他们吐痰时使用。而在大汗的大殿中，没有人敢随地吐痰。同样地，他们还随身携带一双白色皮革制成的鞋子，当他们来到朝廷，即将受到大汗的接见时，就会换上这双白鞋，把原来穿的鞋子交给随从，这样就不会弄脏那些用金线织成的美丽多彩的丝质地毯。

从北京到孟加拉

现在让我们离开汗八里，进入中国，让大家了解到她的富庶与伟大。

大家要知道，大汗曾经任命马可·波罗作为使者出使西部，距离汗八里有整整四个月的路程。下面我们就要向大家介绍他来回旅途中的所见所闻。

……

旅行者要用五天的时间骑马穿越平原山谷，经过无数村庄部落才能离开成都府。这儿的居民以农业为生。这个地区有许多狮子、熊和其他野兽，也有一些制造业，可以生产出一些薄绢和其他织物。这个地区是成都府的一部分，但是在经过五天的路程后，旅行者就进入了另一个地区—西藏[15]。

由于这个地区在蒙哥汗发起的征战中受到了极大的破坏，西藏十分荒凉。有许多城镇、村庄和部落都成了废墟。

这个地区盛产一种又粗又高的竹子，能长到三掌粗、十五步高，每两个竹节间也有整整三掌的距离。经过这儿的商人和旅行者在晚上用这些竹子当燃料，因为这些竹子十分易燃，并且在燃烧时会发出乒乒乓乓的声响，那些狮子、熊和其他野兽就会因为害怕不敢靠近火堆。这样，火堆就能保护旅行者的牲口，以免它们被在这个地区频繁出没的野兽所伤害。让我向大家讲述一件值得一提的事情—这些竹子是如何发出清脆惊人的爆裂声以及产生的效果。大家要知道，这些竹子还是绿色的时候就被折断扔到火里，作为木柴使用。当它们在这种情况下被扔到火里时，它们开始弯曲爆裂，并发出嘭嘭的声响，在夜间隔着十英里也能听到。不熟悉这种声响的人会被这种声音惊呆，因为这种声音十分恐怖。从未听到过这种声音的马匹也会被吓到，它们会挣脱缰绳和所有束缚，拔腿就跑。很多旅行者都有这样的经历，如果马匹从未听到过这种声音，他们会用布蒙住马的眼睛并用铁锁锁住马蹄。这样当它们听到竹子的爆裂声试图逃跑时，就不会成功。通过这种方法，旅行者的安全在夜晚得到保证。旅行者和他的牲畜都不会被附近的狮子、豹子和其他危险的野兽伤害。

在这个荒凉并充满危险野兽的地区，即使行走二十天也不会有旅店、食物。每隔三四天，这些旅行者可能会找到一些有人居住的地方，补充一些食物。二十天后，他们才会到达一个地区，那儿有许多村庄和部落以及少许城镇，都坐落在陡峭的悬崖边上。我将向大家讲述那儿盛行的一种婚姻习俗。这里的男人都不愿意娶处女为妻。他们认为只有很了解男人的女人才值得娶为妻子。他们还认为处女是被神明所厌恶的，因为如果神明很喜欢这个女子，就会派男人去满足她，与她发生关系。他们就是这样看待妇女的。当别的地区的男人经过这个地区，要在此处搭帐篷过夜时，附近村庄和部落的妇女就会带着女儿过来，大概会有二十到四十人，然后祈求这些旅客与她们的女儿一同睡觉。那些漂亮的女子会被选中，而剩下的人就只能闷闷而归了。在旅行者停留期间，他们都可以和这些女子在一起，并且可以让她们做任何他想做的事情，不过他们不可以将这些女子带到别的地方。当这些旅行者满足了自己的需求准备离开时，按照习俗，他们要将一些小饰物或者纪念品送给陪伴他们的女子，当女子要结婚时，她可以拿出这些纪念品，对别人说她曾经有一个情人。每个女子都要将这些饰品戴在脖子上，显示自己有过许多情人，和很多男人睡过。拥有纪念品最多的女子，表明她有最多的情人，和她睡过的男人最多，也就被认为最有价值，最值得被娶为妻子，用他们的话说就是最受老天的宠爱。当他们通过这种方法将女子娶为妻子后，任何人再接触他人的妻子就会被视为极大的冒犯，他们严禁这种行为。这就是他们的婚姻制度。很明显，这个地区对十六至二十四岁的男青年来说，是个很好的地方。

这里的本地人都是佛教徒，并且都是十足的坏人。他们不认为抢劫和虐待是一种罪恶，并且他们是世界上最大的强盗土匪。他们靠打猎和种植水果生活。这个地区盛产一种能够生产麝香的动物[16]，他们把它叫作谷得利。它们数量极多，以至于在这里到处都能闻到麝香。这种液囊像一个肿瘤一样长在野兽的肚脐上，里面充满了血液，而这些血液就是麝香。每个月液囊中都会充满了血液，当无法承受血液的重量时，液囊就会破裂。由于这种动物很多，当液囊破裂时，麝香就被洒到很多地方，因此整个地区都弥漫着麝香的香气。卑鄙的当地人为了得到麝香，用狗猎取了许多这种动物。

当地居民并不使用任何钱币，也不使用大汗的纸币，他们把盐当作货币使用。他们的衣衫十分匮乏，通常用动物皮革、帆布、粗麻布制成。他们使用自己的语言，并且把自己叫作“西藏人”。

西藏地域十分辽阔，与蛮子省和其他许多省份接壤。当地的居民都是佛教徒，并且都是臭名昭著的强盗土匪。整个省份被划分为八个王国，拥有许多的城市和小镇。很多地区都是湖河和山区。在湖河中还发现了大量金沙。这里盛产肉桂。珊瑚的价格很高，妇女们用它来制作项链，并且用它来装饰偶像。这个省份还盛产驼毛布、金银线布、粗棉布和其他我们国家从未见到过的布料。这个地区有许多优秀的巫师和占星家，可以随心所欲地呼风唤雨。他们通过魔鬼般的行为表现出强大的巫术和伟大的奇迹，都是前所未见，闻所未闻的。在此书中还是不要提及，以免人们太过诧异。他们的习俗是招人厌恶的。他们饲养了许多藏獒，体型和驴差不多大，很善于捕捉猎物，包括体积巨大并且十分凶残的野牛。除了优秀的猎鹰和猎隼外，他们还有各种猎犬。这些猎鹰和猎隼飞行技术十分出色，并且十分适合行猎。在离开西藏之前，让我向大家再说明一下，除了在书的开头提到过的一个省份受阿鲁浑的儿子统治外，和书中所提到的其他王国、省份、地区一样，西藏是属于大汗统治的。大家要明白，除了上面提到的那个省份，书中所提到的所有地区都属于大汗的统治范围。

我们将向大家介绍下一个省份—建都省[17]。建都省位于国土的西部。这个省中只有一个王国，百姓都为佛教徒，并且受大汗的统治。建都省内有许多城镇，最主要的城市也叫建都，位于省份的入口处。这儿还有一个大湖[18]，湖中盛产珍珠，这些珍珠颜色洁白，但都不是圆形的，就像四、五、六个或者更多的球连在一起。大汗禁止随意采集珍珠，因为如果所有被发现的珍珠都被采集出来，数量会很多，那么珍珠就会贬值，失去它的价值。所以大汗下令从湖中采集的珍珠只供他自己使用，其他人未经允许采集珍珠会被处以死刑。这里还有一座山，山上盛产一种叫作绿松石的石头，这也是十分珍贵的宝石，并且储量很多，同样，不经过大汗的允许也不能随意开采。

这里的妇女盛行一种风气，我将向大家描述。当一个陌生人或者别的男人和一个家庭中的妻子、女儿、姐妹或者其他女子发生关系时，他们的男人丝毫不会感到愤怒。反而将男人与她们睡觉看作一种恩惠。他们认为这么做是为了抚慰他们的神明和偶像，这样神明就能保佑他们在凡世间生活富足。出于这个原因，他们总是像下文中提到的那样慷慨地交出自己的妻子：当这个地区的主人发现有陌生的男子到他家里来住宿，或者仅仅是来到家里并未打算住宿时，他们就会立刻离家出走，并且告诉妻子要满足陌生人的所有要求。在陌生人离开之前，主人都会留在自己的田地或者葡萄园里。而陌生人通常会在家里停留三天，当他在这个家里时，他就会挂出自己的帽子或者其他标记，来表示自己仍然留在这个家中。而这些能够容忍妻子对自己不忠的丈夫看见这样的标记，就不会回家。这种风俗盛行于全省。虽然大汗下令禁止，但是他们仍然保留了这种风俗，因为每家每户都这么做，也就没有谁会去责备别人。在乡村和峭壁边部落的路旁，那些有着美丽妻子的人会把自己的妻子献给路过的商人享用。这些商人会送给妇女们一匹好布或者其他一些不值钱的小东西，当他们得到满足后，就会骑马离开，而这时，那些丈夫和妻子就会在他后面嘲笑：“嗨，你就这样走了！看看你拿走了我们的什么东西，看看你得到了什么好处，看看你给我们留下了什么！看看你忘记了什么！”然后他们就会拿出商人送给他们的布匹炫耀，“我们可是从你那儿得到了这个，而你却什么也没得到，你真是个大傻瓜！”

下面让我向大家介绍一下他们的货币。他们使用金条，并且用萨吉表示重量，金条的价值就取决于它的重量。但是他们没有印有图章的硬币。对于小面额的交易，他们采取以下方法：制盐的锅中有许多盐水，煮上一小时后，它们就会结晶在一个模型里，形成一个像两便士的面包一样的块状，底部是平的，上面是凸起的。当块状形成后，就被放于火边加热了的石头上，让它们变得干燥坚硬。这些盐块上会加盖大汗的印章，用于流通的盐币只有大汗任命的官员才能制造。八十个这样的盐块就价值一个萨吉的金币。但是在偏远的地区，根据该地区距离城市的远近，商人们用六十、五十，甚至四十个盐块就能换到一萨吉的金币。这些地区的居民不能处理他们手中的金币或者麝香，只能等着购买者来收购，由于他们在湖河中就能找到金沙，所以，他们将金币便宜卖出。商人们走遍西藏所有的高地山区，在这些地方，盐块也是流通货币，他们赚取了巨大的利润，因为对高原上的居民来说，盐块不仅是货币，还是生活的必需品。但是在城市里，盐块只作为货币使用，人们则食用未成块的盐。

这儿也有许多分泌麝香的动物，猎人通过捕捉它们得到了大量的麝香。盛产珍珠的那个湖中，同样盛产各种鱼，同时，狮子、山猫、熊、雄鹿、雄獐以及各种鸟类都十分常见。这儿没有葡萄酒，他们喝的酒都是由小麦、大米加上一些香料酿成的，十分可口。这里还盛产丁香，丁香树较小，树叶和桂树的叶子很像，不过要稍长、稍窄，花是白色的，和丁香石竹的花一样。这儿还盛产生姜和肉桂，更不用提那些从未传到我们国家的品种了。

当旅行者离开建都后，他要花上十天的时间穿过这个省份，沿途都能看到城镇、农村，还有许多鸟兽出没。这些地方居民的风俗习惯和我刚刚所描述的相同。走了十天后，旅行者就能到达一条大河旁边，叫作不鲁思河[19]，是建都省的天然疆界。此地区仍然盛产肉桂，河中也富含有大量金沙，河水流向大海。

在不鲁思河的另一边是另一个省份，叫作哈剌章省[20]。这个省份的面积很大，至少包含了七个王国。该省位于西部，居民是佛教徒，都服从于大汗的统治。这里的君王是大汗的儿子也先帖木儿。他是一个十分伟大、富有、极有权势的君王，并且正直明智，很好地统治着这个省份。

离开不鲁思河，旅行者需要向西行走五日，穿过一个王国，这个王国有许多城镇，并且养育出许多优秀的马匹，这里的居民依靠畜牧和耕种维持生活。他们有自己的语言，十分难懂。经过五天的路程以后，旅行者能到达这个王国的首都押赤[21]。这是一个十分雄伟壮丽的城市，城中有许多商人和工匠，这儿的居民有好几种：有伊斯兰教徒、佛教徒，还有一些基督教聂斯托利派的信徒。小麦和米在这里的产量都十分丰富，但是他们不吃面包，因为他们认为面包是不健康的食物。当地居民主要吃大米，还用大米加上香料酿成美酒，酒水十分清澈爽口。他们将白色的玛瑙贝作为货币，他们曾经用这种贝壳制作狗项圈。八十个玛瑙贝价值一萨吉的银币，相当于两个威尼斯银币；八萨吉的银币则价值一个金币。他们同样烧制盐水，制成的盐块可供全国居民食用。这个地区的君主从这些盐中得到了许多税收。这里的男人们不介意别的男人触摸自己的妻子，只要她自己同意即可。

在离开这个王国之前，我还要向大家讲述一件事情。这个地区有一个方圆一百英里的大湖，盛产各种优质鱼类，体型也很大。当地居民食用生肉，包括家禽、羊肉、牛肉和水牛肉。更穷一点的居民会拿走从动物身上取下的肝脏，将它切成小块，放入蒜和酱油，然后吃掉，他们也这样处理其他肉类。贵族们也吃生肉，只是他们会将肉剁碎，加入大蒜、酱油和香料，然后就像我们吃煮熟的肉一样将它们吃掉。

离开押赤继续向西走十日，旅行者就能到达哈剌章省的另一王国，这个国家的首都就叫作哈剌章。这里的居民同样是佛教徒，并且臣服于大汗。这个王国的君主是大汗的儿子忽哥赤[22]。这个地区的大河中也含有金沙，并且有些湖中和山里有天然金块。由于金矿十分丰富，所以这个地区只用六个银币就能换取一萨吉金币。他们也用玛瑙贝当作货币，但是这些贝壳不是本地产的，而是从印度传来的。

这个地区还生活着大型的蛇和鳄鱼。它们的长相十分难看，其中有一些身长近十步，身体像一个粗壮的柱子，腰身长达十掌。靠近头部的地方有两只粗短的腿，没有脚，但是有三个爪子，两短一长，和猎鹰、狮子的爪子很像。它们有着巨大的脑袋，眼睛向外突出，比面包还大。它们张大了嘴，一口就能吞下一个人，牙齿也十分锋利。总的来说，如此凶残巨大的怪兽，不管是人还是动物见到了都会害怕。它们中也有体型稍小的，长八步、六步或者五步。

让我告诉大家如何捕捉这些鳄鱼。由于白天天气炎热，鳄鱼会躲在地下，到了晚上，它们就会出洞捕食它们能够得到的一切猎物。它们还会到小溪和河中饮水。由于身体特别庞大笨重，当它们夜间出来觅食或者饮水经过沙地时，就会留下深深的痕迹，就像树桩在地上拖过一样。专门捕捉它们的猎人就会在它们经常出没的地方设置陷阱。他们将粗壮的木桩插入泥土中，将木桩的顶端装上大概有一掌长的铁矛，并且让铁矛向鳄鱼爬来的方向倾斜，然后将这些用沙子覆盖，使鳄鱼无法察觉。这种陷阱很多，当鳄鱼沿着痕迹去饮水时，就会掉进陷阱，而铁矛会刺穿它的胸腔，撕裂它的肚皮，使它们立刻毙命。猎人能够通过鸟的叫声得知鳄鱼被杀死，然后他才敢处理猎物。否则，他是不敢靠近鳄鱼的。

当猎人通过这种方法捉住鳄鱼后，他们从鳄鱼的腹中取出胆汁，这种胆汁是十分名贵的药材，可以卖出很高的价钱。如果某人被疯狗咬了，只要喝下半便士重的胆汁就能立刻被治愈；正在分娩的孕妇，无法忍受疼痛，只要喝下一些胆汁就能立刻顺利分娩；如果有人长出各种脓包，只要涂上胆汁，一两天就能痊愈。出于这些作用，鳄鱼的胆汁在这些地区的价格十分昂贵。

还有一些关于这些鳄鱼的事情：它们还会爬进狮子、熊和其他野兽搭的洞穴，捕食幼兽。

这个地区的马匹都十分强壮，它们在很小的时候就被出口到印度。大家要知道，根据当地的习惯，这儿的马都会被去掉两到三节尾骨，这样马尾巴就不会打到骑马的人，奔跑的时候也不会刷刷地挥动尾巴，因为当地的居民认为挥动马尾巴是很难看的。这里居民骑马的方式和法兰西人一样，都使用长长的马镫，这是相对于鞑靼人和其他民族骑马射箭时使用的短马镫而言的，短马镫可以使他们在射箭时站立起来，便于射箭。

他们用水牛皮做成盔甲穿在身上，使用长矛和盾，同样也用弩，并且所有的箭头都蘸有毒药。当地居民，无论男女，尤其那些心怀鬼胎的人，都随身携带毒药。如果有人在犯下罪行被捕后，很可能遭受折磨，为了免于忍受鞭打之苦，他们就选择服毒自杀。但是，统治者发现了他们的诡计后，就随时备有狗屎，当他们吞下毒药后，统治者就立刻将狗屎塞到他的口中，让他们将毒药呕吐出来。这就是他们对这种行为的补救办法，这种办法十分有效。在被大汗征服前，他们还有一种习惯：当有上流社会的绅士或者“善良的化身”到这个地区的某户居民家里住宿时，他们就会用毒药或者其他手段在夜晚杀死他。他们这样做并不是为了谋财，而是他们希望死者的善良、智慧和灵魂会留在他们的家中。这样，在大汗征服他们前，很多人都由于这个原因死去。由于大汗严厉禁止这种做法，出于对大汗的害怕，在最近的三十五年中，他们已经改掉了这个恶习。

[1]契丹（Cathay）：我国古代民族，是东胡的一支，在今辽河上游西拉木伦河一带，过着游牧生活。十世纪初耶律阿保机统一各族，建立契丹国。——译者注

[2]撒拉森人（Saracens）：在早期的罗马帝国时代，撒拉森只用以指称西奈半岛上的阿拉伯游牧民族。后来的东罗马帝国则将这个名字套用在所有阿拉伯民族上。伊斯兰教兴起于西亚，特别在十一世纪末期的十字军东征后，以基督教信仰为主的欧洲人，普遍用“撒拉森”来称呼所有位于亚洲与北非的穆斯林。在西方的历史文献中，撒拉森最常用来笼统地泛称伊斯兰的阿拉伯帝国。——译者注

[3]阿尔泰山（Altai）：亚洲宏伟山系之一，北西—南东走向，斜跨中国、哈萨克斯坦、俄罗斯、蒙古国境，绵延两千余千米。——译者注

[4]鞑靼人（Tartar）：操突厥语的民族之一，十三世纪初，这些蒙古突厥游牧民族的不同群体成为蒙古征服者成吉思汗部队的一部分，其后蒙古人与突厥人混杂在一起，因而入侵俄罗斯和匈牙利的蒙古军队，就被欧洲人统称为鞑靼人。——译者注

[5]黎凡特（Levant）：指中东托罗斯山脉以南、地中海东岸、阿拉伯沙漠以北和美索不达米亚以东的一大片地区。——译者注

[6]阿鲁浑（Arghun，约1258—1291）：第四代蒙古族伊儿汗。——译者注

[7]张加诺（Chagan-nor）：今白城子。——译者注

[8]上都（Shang-tu）：位于今内蒙古自治区锡林郭勒盟正蓝旗境内，多伦县西北闪电河畔。——译者注

[9]特贝斯（Tibetans）：即西藏人，藏族信仰大乘佛教。大乘佛教吸收了藏族土著信仰本教的某些仪式和内容，形成具有藏族色彩的“藏传佛教”。藏族对活佛高僧尊为上人，藏语称为喇嘛，故藏传佛教又被称为喇嘛教。——译者注

[10]巴克斯（Bakhshi）：一种特殊的宗教人群，像多米尼加人或者济修士。——译者注

[11]一腕尺约十八英寸。——译者注

[12]史料记载蒙哥汗在1259年去世后，次年其弟阿里不哥在哈拉和林被选作蒙古帝国大汗，而忽必烈则在中原开平自立为大汗。大蒙古国第四任大汗蒙哥去世后，大蒙古国一分为五个国家，不复存在。这五个国家分别是拔都的金帐汗国、忽必烈的大元国（中国元朝）、西亚的伊尔汗国、南亚的察合台汗国，以及中亚的窝阔台汗国。——译者注

[13]汗八里（Khan-balik）：元代都城大都（北京）的别称。——译者注

[14]指马可·波罗的父亲和叔叔，尼科洛·波罗及马费奥·波罗。——译者注

[15]这里所说的西藏主要包括现在的四川省、云南省以及现在西藏的东部地区。

[16]根据描述，此动物应为雄麝。麝香为雄麝的肚脐和生殖器之间的腺囊的分泌物，干燥后呈颗粒状或块状，有特殊的香气，有苦味，可以制成香料，也可以入药。——译者注

[17]位于云南省丽江市附近。——译者注

[18]指滇池。——译者注

[19]指金沙江。——译者注

[20]指云南大理。——译者注

[21]指云南昆明。——译者注

[22]指忽必烈汗第五子：云南王。——译者注

The Road to Cathay

You must know that after Chinghiz Khan the next ruler was Kuyuk Khan, the third Batu Khan, the fourth Altou Khan, the fifth Mongu Khan and the sixth Kubilai Khan, who is greater and more powerful than any of the others. For all the other five put together would not have such power as belongs to Kubilai. And here is a greater claim still, which I can confidently assert: that all the emperors of the world and all the kings of Christians and of Saracens combined would not possess such power or be able to accomplish so much as this same Kubilai, the Great Khan. And this I will clearly demonstrate to you in this book.

You should know that all the great lords who are of the lineage of Chinghiz Khan are conveyed for burial to a great mountain called Altai. When one of them dies, even if it be at a distance of a hundred days' journey from this mountain, he must be brought here for burial. And here is a remarkable fact: when the body of a Great Khan is being carried to this mountain—be it forty days' journey or more or less—all those who are encountered along the route by which the body is being conveyed are put to the sword by the attendants who are escorting it. ‘Go!’ they cry, ‘and serve your lord in the next world.’ For they truly believe that all those whom they put to death must go and serve the Khan in the next world. And they do the same thing with horses: when the Khan dies, they kill all his best horses, so that he may have them in the next world. It is a fact that, when Mongu Khan died, more than 20,000 men were put to death, having encountered his body on the way to burial.

Since we have begun to speak of the Tartars, I have much to tell you about them. They spend the winter in steppes and warm regions where there is good grazing and pasturage for their beasts. In summer they live in cool regions, among mountains and valleys, where they find water and woodland as well as pasturage. A further advantage is that in cooler regions there are no horse-flies or gad-flies or similar pests to annoy them and their beasts. They spend two or three months climbing steadily and grazing as they go, because if they confined their grazing to one spot there would not be grass enough for the multitude of their flocks.

They have circular houses made of wood and covered with felt, which they carry about with them on four-wheeled wagons wherever they go. For the framework of rods is so neatly and skilfully constructed that it is light to carry. And every time they unfold their house and set it up, the door is always facing south. They also have excellent two-wheeled carts covered with black felt, of such good design that if it rained all the time the rain would never wet anything in the cart. These are drawn by oxen and camels. And in these carts they carry their wives and children and all they need in the way of utensils.

And I assure you that the womenfolk buy and sell and do all that is needful for their husbands and households. For the men do not bother themselves about anything but hunting and warfare and falconry. They live on meat and milk and game and on Pharaoh's rats, which are abundant everywhere in the steppes. They have no objection to eating the flesh of horses and dogs and drinking mares' milk. In fact they eat flesh of any sort. Not for anything in the world would one of them touch another's wife; they are too well assured that such a deed is wrongful and disgraceful. The wives are true and loyal to their husbands and very good at their household tasks. Even if there are as many as ten or twenty of them in one household, they live together in a concord and unity beyond praise, so that you would never hear a harsh word spoken. They all devote themselves to their various tasks and the care of the children, who are held among them in common. Their mode of marriage is such that any man may take as many wives as he pleases, even up to a hundred, if he is able to support them. The husband gives a dowry to his wife's mother; the wife gives nothing to the husband. You must understand that the first wife is reckoned the best and enjoys the highest status. Because they have so many wives, they have more children than other men. They may marry their cousins; and, when a father dies, the eldest son marries his father's wives, excluding his own mother. He may also marry his brother's wife, if the brother dies. When they take a wife, they hold a great wedding celebration.

I will now tell you of their religion. They say that there is a High God, exalted and heavenly, to whom they offer daily prayer with thurible and incense, but only for a sound understanding and good health. They also have a god of their own whom they call Natigai. They say that he is an earthly god and watches over their children, their beasts, and their crops. They pay him great reverence and honour; for each man has one in his house. They make this god of felt and cloth and keep him in their house; and they also make the god's wife and children. They set his wife at his left hand and his children in front. And they treat them with great reverence. When they are about to have a meal, they take a lump of fat and smear the god's mouth with it, and the mouths of his wife and children. Then they take some broth and pour it outside the door of the house. When they have done this, they say that their god and his household have had their share. After this they eat and drink. You should know that they drink mare's milk; but they subject it to a process that makes it like white wine and very good to drink, and they call it koumiss.

As to their costume, the rich wear cloth of gold and silk and rich furs—sable and ermine and miniver and fox. And all their trappings are very fine and very costly. Their weapons are bows and swords and clubs; but they rely mainly on their bows, for they are excellent archers. On their backs they wear an armour of buffalo hide or some other leather which is very tough.

They are stout fighters, excelling in courage and hardihood. Let me explain how it is that they can endure more than any other men. Often enough, if need be, they will go or stay for a whole month without provisions, drinking only the milk of a mare and eating wild game of their own taking. Their horses, meanwhile, support themselves by grazing, so that there is no need to carry barley or straw. They are very obedient to their masters. In case of need they will stay all night on horseback under arms, while their mount goes on steadily cropping the grass. They are of all men in the world the best able to endure exertion and hardship and the least costly to maintain and therefore the best adapted for conquering territory and over-throwing kingdoms.

Now the plan on which their armies are marshalled is this. When a lord of the Tartars goes out to war with a following of 100,000 horsemen, he has them organized as follows. He has one captain in command of every ten, one of every hundred, one of every thousand and one of every ten-thousand, so that he never needs to consult with more than ten men. In the same way each commander of ten-thousand or a thousand or a hundred consults only with his ten immediate subordinates, and each man is answerable to his own chief. When the supreme commander wishes to send someone on some operation, he orders the commander of ten-thousand to give him a thousand men; the latter orders the captain of a thousand to contribute his share. So the order is passed down, each commander being required to furnish his quota towards the thousand. At each stage it is promptly received and executed. For they are all obedient to the word of command more than any other people in the world. You should know that the unit of 100,000 is called a tuk, that of 10,000 a tomaun, and there are corresponding terms for the thousands, the hundreds, and the tens.

When an army sets out on some operation, whether it be in the plains or in the mountains, 200 men are sent two days' ride in advance as scouts, and as many to the rear and on the flanks; that is four scouting parties in all. And this they do so that the army cannot be attacked without warning.

When they are going on a long expedition, they carry no baggage with them. They each carry two leather flasks to hold the milk they drink and a small pot for cooking meat. They also carry a small tent to shelter them from the rain. In case of need, they will ride a good ten days' journey without provisions and without making a fire, living only on the blood of their horses; for every rider pierces a vein of his horse and drinks the blood. They also have their dried milk, which is solid like paste; and this is how they dry it. First they bring the milk to the boil. At the appropriate moment they skim off the cream that floats on the surface and put it in another vessel to be made into butter, because so long as it remained the milk could not be dried. Then they stand the milk in the sun and leave it to dry. When they are going on an expedition, they take about ten pounds of this milk; and every morning they take out about half a pound of it and put it in a small leather flask, shaped like a gourd, with as much water as they please. Then, while they ride, the milk in the flask dissolves into a fluid, which they drink. And this is their breakfast.

When they join battle with their enemies, these are the tactics by which they prevail. They are never ashamed to have recourse to flight. They manoeuvre freely, shooting at the enemy, now from this quarter, now from that. They have trained their horses so well that they wheel this way or that as quickly as a dog would do. When they are pursued and take to flight, they fight as well and as effectively as when they are face to face with the enemy. When they are fleeing at top speed, they twist round with their bows and let fly their arrows to such good purpose that they kill the horses of the enemy and the riders too. When the enemy thinks he has routed and crushed them, then he is lost; for he finds his horses killed and not a few of his men. As soon as the Tartars decide that they have killed enough of the pursuing horses and horsemen, they wheel round and attack and acquit themselves so well and so courageously that they gain a complete victory. By these tactics they have already won many battles and conquered many nations.

All that I have told you concerns the usages and customs of the genuine Tartars. But nowadays their stock has degenerated. Those who live in Cathay have adopted the manners and customs of the idolaters and abandoned their own faith, while those who live in the Levant have adopted the manners of the Saracens.

Let me tell you next of the Tartar fashion of maintaining justice. For a petty theft, not amounting to a capital offence, the culprit receives seven strokes of the rod, or seventeen or twenty-seven or thirty-seven or forty-seven, ascending thus by tens to 107 in proportion to the magnitude of his crime. And many die of this flogging. If the offender has stolen a horse or otherwise incurred the death penalty, he is chopped in two by the sword. If, however, he can afford to pay, and is prepared to pay nine times the value of what he has stolen, he escapes other punishment.

All the great lords, and other owners of flocks and herds, including horses, mares, camels, oxen, cows, and other large beasts, have them branded with their own mark. Then they turn them loose to graze on the plains and hillsides with no herdsman to guard them. If the herds intermingle, each beast is duly returned to the owner whose mark it bears. Their sheep and rams are entrusted to the care of shepherds. All their beasts are of great size and fat and exceedingly fine.

Here is another strange custom which I had forgot-ten to describe. You may take it for a fact that, when there are two men of whom one has had a male child who has died at the age of four, or what you will, and the other has had a female child who has also died, they arrange a marriage between them. They give the dead girl to the dead boy as a wife and draw up a deed of matrimony. Then they burn this deed, and declare that the smoke that rises into the air goes to their children in the other world and that they get wind of it and regard themselves as husband and wife. They hold a great wedding feast and scatter some of the food here and there and declare that that too goes to their children in the other world. And here is something else that they do. They draw pictures on paper of men in the guise of slaves, and of horses, clothes, coins, and furniture and then burn them; and they declare that all these become the possessions of their children in the next world. When they have done this, they consider themselves to be kinsfolk and uphold their kinship just as firmly as if the children were alive.

Now I have given you an unvarnished account of the usages and customs of the Tartars. Not that I have told you of the lofty state of the Great Khan, the Great Lord of all the Tartars, or of his high imperial court. I will tell you all about them in this book in due time and place. For they are truly wonderful things to set down in writing. Meanwhile, let us resume the thread of our discourse in the great plain where we were when we began to talk about the doings of the Tartars.

If the traveller leaves Karakorum and Altai, where, as I have told you, the Tartars bury their dead, and journeys towards the north, he traverses a country called the plain of Bargu, which extends for forty days' journey. The inhabitants, who are called Mekrit, are a savage race. Their livelihood depends on beasts, mostly reindeer, which they even use for riding. They resemble the Tartars in their customs and are subject to the Great Khan. They have neither corn nor wine. In summer they have plenty of game for hunting, both beasts and birds; but in winter neither beast nor bird lives there because of the great cold. The birds especially congregate during the moulting season in summer round the numerous lakes, meres, and marshes; and when they have shed all their old plumage, so that they cannot fly, the hunters take as many as they want. They also live on fish.

At the end of forty days, the traveller reaches the Ocean. Here there are mountains where peregrine falcons build their nests. You must understand that there are neither men nor women here, nor beasts nor birds, except a species of bird called bargherlac on which the falcons prey. They are of the size of partridges and have feet like parrots and tails like swallows. They are strong fliers. When the Great Khan wants eyasses of the peregrine falcon, he sends for them all the way to this district. The islands in this ocean breed gerfalcons. I assure you that this region is so far north that the Pole Star is left behind towards the south. The gerfalcons of which I have spoken are so abundant here that the Great Khan has as many of them as he wants. So you must not suppose that those who export them from Christendom to the Tartars send them to the Great Khan; they actually export them to the Khan of the Levant, to Arghun or whoever it may be.

[...]

If we leave this province and city and go on our way for three days, we shall find a city called Chagan-nor where there is a large palace belonging to the Great Khan. He enjoys staying in this palace because there are lakes and rivers here in plenty, well stocked with swans. There are also fine plains, teeming with cranes, pheasants and partridges, and many other sorts of wild fowl; and that is a further attraction for the Great Khan, who is a keen sportsman and takes great delight in hawking for birds with falcons and gerfalcons. There are five sorts of crane, which I will describe to you. One is entirely black, like a raven, and very large. The second is pure white. Its wings are beautiful, with all the plumage studded with round eyes like those of a peacock but of the colour of burnished gold. It has a scarlet and black head and a black and white neck and is larger than any of the others. The third species is like the cranes we know. The fourth is small, with long plumes by its ears, scarlet and black in colour and very beautiful. The fifth is a very large bird, quite grey with shapely head coloured scarlet and black.

Beyond this city lies a valley in which the Great Khan keeps flocks of cators, which we call ‘great partridges', in such quantities that they are a sight to behold. In order to feed them, he regularly has crops sown on the slopes in summer, consisting of millet and panic and other favourite foods of such fowl, and allows no one to reap them, so that they may eat their fill. And many guards are set to watch these birds, to prevent anyone from taking them. And in winter their keepers scatter millet for them; and they are so used to this feeding that, if a man flings some of the grain on the ground, he has only to whistle and, wherever they may be, they flock to him. And the Great Khan has had many huts built, in which they spend the night. So, when he visits this country, he has a plentiful supply of these fowl, as many as he wants. And in winter, when they are nice and plump, since he does not stay there himself at this season because of the intense cold, he has camel-loads of them brought to him, wherever he may be.

When the traveller leaves this city and journeys north-north-east for three days, he comes to a city called Shang-tu, which was built by the Great Khan now reigning, whose name is Kubilai. In this city Kubilai Khan built a huge palace of marble and other ornamental stones. Its halls and chambers are all gilded, and the whole building is marvellously embellished and richly adorned. At one end it extends into the middle of the city; at the other it abuts on the city wall. At this end another wall, running out from the city wall in the direction opposite to the palace, encloses and encircles fully sixteen miles of park-land well watered with springs and streams and diversified with lawns. Into this park there is no entry except by way of the palace. Here the Great Khan keeps game animals of all sorts, such as hart, stag, and roebuck, to provide food for the gerfalcons and other falcons which he has here in mew. The gerfalcons alone amount to more than 200. Once a week he comes in person to inspect them in the mew. Often, too, he enters the park with a leopard on the crupper of his horse; when he feels inclined, he lets it go and thus catches a hart or stag or roebuck to give to the gerfalcons that he keeps in mew. And this he does for recreation and sport.

In the midst of this enclosed park, where there is a beautiful grove, the Great Khan has built another large palace, constructed entirely of canes, but with the interior all gilt and decorated with beasts and birds of very skilful workmanship. It is reared on gilt and varnished pillars, on each of which stands a dragon, entwining the pillar with his tail and supporting the roof on his outstretched limbs. The roof is also made of canes, so well varnished that it is quite waterproof. Let me explain how it is constructed. You must know that these canes are more than three palms in girth and from ten to fifteen paces long. They are sliced down through the middle from one knot to the next, thus making two shingles. These shingles are thick and long enough not only for roofing but for every sort of construction. The palace, then, is built entirely of such canes. As a protection against the wind each shingle is fastened with nails. And the Great Khan has had it so designed that it can be moved whenever he fancies; for it is held in place by more than 200 cords of silk.

The Great Khan stays at Shang-tu for three months in the year, June, July, and August, to escape from the heat and for the sake of the recreation it affords. During these three months he keeps the palace of canes erected; for the rest of the year it is dismantled. And he has had it so constructed that he can erect or dismantle it at pleasure.

When it comes to the 28th day of August, the Great Khan takes his leave of this city and of this palace. Every year he leaves on this precise day; and I will tell you why. The fact is that he has a stud of snow-white stallions and snow-white mares, without a speck of any other colour. Their numbers are such that the mares alone amount to more than 10,000. The milk of these mares may not be drunk by anyone who is not of the imperial lineage, that is to say of the lineage of the Great Khan. To this rule there is one exception; the milk may be drunk by a race of men called Horiat, by virtue of a special privilege granted to them by Chinghiz Khan because of a victory that they won with him in the old days. When these white steeds are grazing, such reverence is shown to them that if a great lord were going that way he could not pass through their midst, but would either wait till they had passed or go on until he had passed them. The astrologers and idolaters have told the Great Khan that he must make a libation of the milk of these mares every year on the 28th August, flinging it into the air and on the earth, so that the spirits may have their share to drink. They must have this, it is said, in order that they may guard all his possessions, men and women, beasts, birds, crops, and everything besides.

For this purpose the Great Khan leaves this palace and goes elsewhere. But, before we follow him, let me tell you of a strange thing which I had forgotten. You must know that, when the Great Khan was staying in his palace and the weather was rainy or cloudy, he had wise astrologers and enchanters who by their skill and their enchantments would dispel all the clouds and the bad weather from above the palace so that, while bad weather continued all around, the weather above the palace was fine. The wise men who do this are called Tibetans and Kashmiris; these are two races of men who practise idolatry. They know more of diabolic arts and enchantments than any other men. They do what they do by the arts of the Devil; but they make others believe that they do it by great holiness and by the work of God. For this reason they go about filthy and begrimed, with no regard for their own decency or for the persons who behold them; they keep the dirt on their faces, never wash or comb, but always remain in a state of squalor. These men have a peculiar custom, of which I will tell you. When a man is condemned to die and is put to death by the authorities, they take the body and cook and eat it. But, if anyone dies a natural death, they would never think of eating him.

Here is another remarkable fact about these enchanters, or Bakhshi[1] as they are called. I assure you that, when the Great Khan is seated in his high hall at his table, which is raised more than eight cubits above the floor, and the cups are on the floor of the hall, a good, ten paces distant from the table, and are full of wine and milk and other pleasant drinks, these Bakhshi contrive by their enchantment and their art that the full cups rise up of their own accord from the floor on which they have been standing and come to the Great Khan without anyone touching them. And this they do in the sight of 10,000 men. What I have told you is the plain truth without a word of falsehood. And those who are skilled in necromancy will confirm that it is perfectly feasible.

Here is a further fact about these Bakhshi. When the feast-days of their idols come round, they go to the Great Khan and say: ‘Sire, the feast of such-and-such of our idols is approaching.’ And they mention the name of some idol, whichever they may choose, and then continue: ‘You are aware, Sire, that it is the practice of this idol to cause bad weather and damage to our property and to cattle and crops unless it receives oblations and holocausts. We accordingly beseech you, Sire, that we may be given so many black-faced sheep, so much incense, so much aloes wood, so much of this and so much of that, so that we may offer great worship and sacrifice to our idols in order that they may save us, our bodies, cattle, and crops.’ This they say to the barons who surround the Great Khan and to those who hold authority under him. And these repeat their words to the Great Khan, so that the Bakhshi have everything they ask for in order to celebrate the feast of their idol. Thereupon they proceed to perform their rites with much chanting and festivity. For they regale their idols with fragrant incense from these sweet spices; and they cook the meat and set it before them and sprinkle some of the gravy here and there, declaring that the idols are taking as much of it as they want. That is how they do honour to their idols on their feast-days.

You may take it for a fact that all the idols have their own feasts on the days assigned to them, just as our saints have. They have huge monasteries and abbeys, of such a size that I assure you that some resemble small cities inhabited by more than 2,000 monks according to their usage, who are better dressed than other men. They wear their heads and chins clean-shaven. They make the most magnificent feasts for their idols with the most magnificent hymns and illuminations that were ever seen.

A further point about these Bakhshi is that among their other privileges they are entitled according to their order to take wives. And so they do, and rear children in plenty.

Besides these there is another order of devotees who are called Sien-seng. They are men of extreme abstinence according to their own observances, and lead a life of great austerity which I will describe to you. The plain truth is that all their lives long they eat nothing but bran, that is to say the husk left over from wheat flour. For they take wheaten grain and put it in hot water and leave it there a little while till all the kernel or marrow is separated from the husk; then they eat the bran that has been washed in this way, without anything to give it a flavour. They fast many times in the year, besides eating absolutely nothing but this bran of which I have told you. They have huge idols, and many of them, and sometimes they worship fire. The other devotees declare that those who live this life of abstinence are heretics, as it were Patarins, because they do not worship their idols in the same manner as the rest. There is one great difference between the two orders of devotees; those who observe the stricter rule would not take a wife for anything in the world. They also have their heads and chins shaven. They wear black and blue robes of sackcloth; if they should happen to wear silk, it is still of the same colours. They sleep on mats of wicker-work. Altogether they lead the most austere lives of any men in the world.

Their idols are all female, that is to say they all bear the names of women.

So much, then, for that. I will now tell you the truly amazing facts about the greatest lord of the Lords of all the Tartars, the right noble Great Khan whose name is Kubilai.

注释

[1]A special religious order, like the Dominican or Franciscan Friars.

Kubilai Khan

I have come to the point in our book at which I will tell you of the great achievements of the Great Khan now reigning. The title Khan means in our language ‘Great Lord of Lords’. And certainly he has every right to this title; for everyone should know that this Great Khan is the mightiest man, whether in respect of subjects or of territory or of treasure, who is in the world today or who ever has been, from Adam our first parent down to the present moment. And I will make it quite clear to you in our book that this is the plain truth, so that everyone will be convinced that he is indeed the greatest lord the world has ever known. Here, then, is my proof.

First, you should know that he is undoubtedly descended in the direct imperial line from Chinghiz Khan; for only one of that lineage may be Lord of all the Tartars. He is sixth in succession of the Great Khans of all the Tartars, having received the lordship and begun his reign in the year of Christ's nativity 1246. He won the lordship by his own valour and prowess and good sense; his kinsfolk and brothers tried to debar him from it, but by his great prowess he won it. And you must know that it was properly his by right. From the beginning of his reign down to the present year 1298 is a period of fortytwo years. His age today may well be as much as eightyfive years. Before he became Khan, he used to go out regularly on military expeditions and he showed himself a valiant soldier and a good commander. But thereafter he went out only once; that was in 1286, and I will tell you how it came about.

The fact is that a certain man named Nayan, who was Kubilai's uncle, found himself while still a youth the lord and ruler of many lands and provinces, so that he could easily raise a force of 400,000 horsemen. Like his ancestors before him, he was subject to the Great Khan. But, seeing that he was a young man of thirty with so many men at his command, he resolved that he would be subject no longer but to the best of his ability would despoil his overlord of the suzerainty. This Nayan, then, sent envoys to Kaidu, who was a great and powerful lord and nephew to the Great Khan, but had rebelled against him and was his bitter enemy. He proposed that Kaidu should attack the Great Khan from one quarter while he himself advanced against him from the opposite one, so as to despoil him of land and lordship. Kaidu welcomed the proposal and promised to have his forces fully arrayed by the date fixed and to march against the Great Khan. And this he was well able to do; for he could put 100,000 horsemen in the field. What need of more words? These two barons, Nayan and Kaidu, made their preparations and mustered a great array of horse and foot to attack the Great Khan.

When the Great Khan got word of this plot, he was not unduly perturbed; but like a wise man of approved valour he began to marshal his own forces, declaring that he would never wear his crown or hold his land if he did not bring these two false traitors to an evil end. He completed his preparations in twenty-two days, so secretly that no one knew anything about them except those of his own Council. He had assembled 260,000 cavalry and 100,000 infantry. The reason why he confined himself to this number was that these were drawn from the troops in his own immediate neighbourhood. His other armies, which were twelve in all and totalled an immense number of men, were so far away on campaigns of conquest in many parts that he could not have got them together at the right time and place. If he had assembled all his forces, he would have had as many horsemen as he could possibly desire and their numbers would have been past all reckoning or belief. The 360,000 men whom he actually levied were his falconers and other members of his personal bodyguard.

If he had summoned the armies which he keeps continually on guard over the provinces of Cathay, this would inevitably have consumed thirty or forty days. Moreover, the levy would have become common knowledge and Kaidu and Nayan would have joined forces and occupied strong and advantageous positions. But Kubilai intended by means of speed, the companion of victory, to forestall Nayan's preparations and catch him alone, because he could more easily defeat him alone than in conjunction with his ally.

This is a convenient place to record a few facts about the armies of the Great Khan. You should know that in all the provinces of Cathay and Manzi and in all the rest of his dominions there are many disaffected and disloyal subjects who, if they had the chance, would rebel against their lord. Accordingly, in every province where there are big cities and a large population he is obliged to maintain armies. These are stationed in the open country four or five miles from the cities, which are not allowed to have gates or walls so as to bar the ingress of anyone who chooses to enter. These armies the Great Khan changes every two years, and so likewise the captains who command them. And with this bridle to restrain them the people stay quiet, and cannot cause any disturbance or insurrection. Besides the pay which the Great Khan gives them regularly from the revenues of the provinces, these armies live on the immense herds of cattle that are assigned to them and on the milk which they send into the towns to sell in return for necessary provisions. They are stationed at various points, thirty, forty, or sixty days' journey apart.

When the Great Khan had mustered the mere handful of men of which I have spoken, he consulted his astrologers to learn whether he would defeat his enemies and bring his affairs to a happy issue. They assured him that he would deal with his enemies as he pleased. Thereupon he set out with all his forces and went on until after twenty days they came to a great plain where Nayan lay with all his forces, who were not less than 400,000 horsemen. They arrived early in the morning and caught the enemy completely unawares; the Great Khan had had all the roads so carefully watched that no one could come or go without being intercepted, and had thus ensured that the enemy had no suspicion of their approach. Indeed, when they arrived Nayan was in his tent, dallying in bed with his wife, to whom he was greatly attached.

What more shall I say? When the day of battle dawned, the Great Khan suddenly appeared on a mound that rose from the plain where Nayan's forces were bivouacked. They were quite at their ease, like men who had not the faintest suspicion that anyone was approaching with hostile intent. Indeed they felt so secure that they had posted no sentries round their camp and sent out no patrols to van or rear. And suddenly there was the Great Khan on the hill I have mentioned. He stood on the top of a wooden tower, full of crossbowmen and archers, which was carried by four elephants wearing stout leather armour draped with cloths of silk and gold. Above his head flew his banner with the emblem of the sun and moon, so high that it could be clearly seen on every side. His troops were marshalled in thirty squadrons of 10,000 mounted archers each, grouped in three divisions; and those on the left and right he flung out so that they encircled Nayan's camp in a moment. In front of every squadron of horse were 400 foot-soldiers with short pikes and swords. They were so trained that, whenever the cavalry purposed a retreat, they would jump on the horses' cruppers and flee with them; then, when the retreat was halted, they would dismount and slaughter the enemies' horses with their pikes. Such, then, was the formation in which the Great Khan's forces were drawn up round Nayan's camp in readiness for the battle.

When Nayan and his men saw the troops of the Great Khan surrounding their camp, they were utterly taken aback. They rushed to arms, arrayed themselves in haste, and formed their ranks in due order.

When both parties were lined up in battle array, so that nothing remained but to come to blows, then might be heard a tumult of many instruments, the shrilling of fifes and sound of men singing at the pitch of their voices. For the usage of the Tartars is such that when they are confronting the foe and marshalled for the fray they do not join battle till the drums begin to beat—that is the drums of the commander. While they wait for the beat of the drums, all the Tartar host sound their instruments and join in song. That is why the noise of instruments and of singing was so loud on both sides alike.

When all the troops were in readiness on both sides, then the drums of the Great Khan began to beat. After that there was no more delay; but the two armies fell upon each other with bow and sword and club, and a few with lances. The foot-soldiers had cross-bows also and other weapons in plenty. What more shall I say? This was the start of a bitter and bloody battle. Now you might see arrows flying like pelting rain, for the whole air was full of them. Now you might see horsemen and horses tumbling dead upon the ground. So loud was the shouting and the clash of armies that you could not have heard the thunder of heaven. You must know that Nayan was a baptized Christian and in this battle he had the cross of Christ on his standard.

What need to make a long story of it? Enough that this was the most hazardous fight and the most fiercely contested that ever was seen. Never in our time were so many men engaged on one battlefield, especially so many horsemen. So many died on either side that it was a marvel to behold. The battle raged from daybreak till noon, and for a long time its issue hung in the balance; Nayan's followers were so devoted to him, for he was an open-handed master, that they were ready to die rather than turn their backs. But in the end the victory fell to the Great Khan. When Nayan and his men saw that they could hold out no longer, they took to flight. But this availed them nothing; for Nayan was taken prisoner, and all his barons and his men surrendered to the Great Khan.

When the Great Khan learnt that Nayan was a prisoner, he commanded that he should be put to death. And this was how it was done. He was wrapped up tightly in a carpet and then dragged about so violently, this way and that, that he died. Their object in choosing this mode of death was so that the blood of the imperial lineage might not be spilt upon the earth, and that sun and air might not witness it.

After this victory all Nayan's men and barons did homage to the Great Khan and swore fealty to him. They were men of four different provinces named Chorcha, Kauli, Barskol, and Sikintinju.

After the Great Khan had won this victory, the various races of men who were there — Saracens, idolaters, and Jews, and many others who do not believe in God — made mock of the cross which Nayan had borne on his banner. They jeered at the Christians who were there: ‘See how the cross of your God has helped Nayan, who was a Christian!’ So unrestrained was their mockery and their jeering that it came to the ears of the Great Khan. Thereupon he rebuked those who mocked at the cross in his presence. Then he summoned many Christians who were there and began to comfort them. ‘If the cross of your God has not helped Nayan,’ he said, ‘it was for a very good reason. Because it is good, it ought not to lend its aid except in a good and righteous cause. Nayan was a traitor who broke faith with his liege lord. Hence the fate that has befallen him was a vindication of the right. And the cross of your God did well in not helping against the right.’ The Christians answered: ‘Most mighty lord, what you say is quite true. The cross would not lend itself to wrong-doing and disloyalty like that of Nayan, who was a traitor to his liege lord. He has received what he well deserved.’ Such were the words that passed between the Great Khan and the Christians about the cross that Nayan had borne on his standard.

After this victory over Nayan, the Great Khan returned to his capital of Khan-balik. And there he stayed, amid great rejoicing and merry-making.

As for that other rebellious baron, the prince whose name was Kaidu, when he heard of Nayan's defeat and death he was greatly perturbed and abandoned his campaign, for fear lest he might meet the same fate.

It was in the month of November that Kubilai returned to Khan-balik. And there he stayed till February and March, the season of our Easter. Learning that this was one of our principal feasts, he sent for all the Christians and desired them to bring him the book containing the four Gospels. After treating the book to repeated applications of incense with great ceremony, he kissed it devoutly and desired all his barons and lords there present to do the same. This usage he regularly observes on the principal feasts of the Christians, such as Easter and Christmas. And he does likewise on the principal feasts of the Saracens, Jews, and idolaters. Being asked why he did so, he replied: ‘There are four prophets who are worshipped and to whom all the world does reverence. The Christians say that their God was Jesus Christ, the Saracens Mahomet, the Jews Moses, and the idolaters Sakyamuni Burkhan, who was the first to be represented as God in the form of an idol. And I do honour and reverence to all four, so that I may be sure of doing it to him who is greatest in heaven and truest; and to him I pray for aid.’ But on the Great Khan's own showing he regards as truest and best the faith of the Christians, because he declares that it commands nothing that is not full of all goodness and holiness. He will not on any account allow the Christians to carry the cross before them, and this because on it suffered and died such a great man as Christ.

Someone may well ask why, since he regards the Christian faith as the best, he does not embrace it and become a Christian. The reason may be gathered from what he said to Messer Niccolò and Messer Maffeo when he sent them as emissaries to the Pope. They used from time to time to raise this matter with him; but he would reply: ‘On what grounds do you desire me to become a Christian? You see that the Christians who live in these parts are so ignorant that they accomplish nothing and are powerless. And you see that these idolaters do whatever they will; and when I sit at table the cups in the middle of the hall come to me full of wine or other beverages without anyone touching them, and I drink from them. They banish bad weather in any direction they choose and perform many marvels. And, as you know, their idols speak and give them such predictions as they ask. But, if I am converted to the faith of Christ and become a Christian, then my barons and others who do not embrace the faith of Christ will say to me: “What has induced you to undergo baptism and adopt the faith of Christ? What virtues or what miracles have you seen to his credit?” For these idolaters declare that what they do they do by their holiness and by virtue of their idols. Then I should not know what to answer, which would be a grave error in their eyes. And these idolaters, who by their arts and sciences achieve such great results, could easily compass my death. But do you go to your Pope and ask him on my behalf to send me a hundred men learned in your religion, who in the face of these idolaters will have the knowledge to condemn their performances and tell them that they too can do such things but will not, because they are done by diabolic art and evil spirits, and will show their mastery by making the idolaters powerless to perform these marvels in their presence. On the day when we see this, I too will condemn them and their religion. Then I will be baptized, and all my barons and magnates will do likewise, and their subjects in turn will undergo baptism. So there will be more Christians here than there are in your part of the world.’ And if, as was said at the beginning, men had really been sent by the Pope with the ability to preach our faith to the Great Khan, then assuredly he would have become a Christian. For it is known for a fact that he was most desirous to be converted.

You have heard how on this one campaign Kubilai led his army out to battle. On all his other enterprises or campaigns he used to send his sons or barons; but on this occasion he would have no one in command but himself, so serious and so culpable did he consider the rebellion of this baron. Let us now leave this subject and return to a recital of the great achievements of the Great Khan.

We have told you of his lineage and his age. We shall now relate how he dealt with those barons who acquitted themselves well in the battle and how with those who showed themselves cowards and poltroons. Of the former, he promoted those who were commanders of 100 men to the command of 1,000, and commanders of 1,000 to the command of 10,000; and he gave them lavish gifts of silver plate and tablets of authority, each according to his rank. For a commander of 100 has a tablet of silver; a commander of 1,000 a tablet of gold, or rather of silver gilt; and a commander of 10,000 a tablet of gold with a lion's head. The tablets of command over 100 or 1,000 weigh 120 saggi apiece, those with a lion's head weigh 220. On all these tablets is written a command in these words: ‘By the might of the Great God and the great grace he has given to our Emperor, blessed be the name of the Khan, and death and destruction to all who do not obey him.’ Let me add that all who have these tablets also have warrants setting forth in writing all the powers vested in them by their office.

As for the commander of 100,000, or the generalissimo of a great army, he has a tablet of gold weighing 300 saggi, with an inscription such as I have mentioned; and at the foot of the tablet is portrayed the lion, and above it is an image of the sun and moon. In addition he has warrants of high command and great authority. And whenever he goes riding he must carry an umbrella over his head in token of his exalted rank; and when he sits he must sit on a silver chair. To these dignitaries the Great Khan also gives a tablet with the sign of the gerfalcon; these tablets are given to the very great barons so that they may exercise full powers equivalent to his own. When one of them wishes to send a courier or other emissary, he is authorized to requisition a king's horses if he wishes; and when I say a king's horses, this naturally implies the horses of any other man.

Let me tell you next of the personal appearance of the Great Lord of Lords whose name is Kubilai Khan. He is a man of good stature, neither short nor tall but of moderate height. His limbs are well fleshed out and modelled in due proportion. His complexion is fair and ruddy like a rose, the eyes black and handsome, the nose shapely and set squarely in place.

He has four consorts who are all accounted his lawful wives; and his eldest son by any of these four has a rightful claim to be emperor on the death of the present Khan. They are called empresses, each by her own name. Each of these ladies holds her own court. None of them has less than 300 ladies in waiting, all of great beauty and charm. They have many eunuchs and many other men and women in attendance, so that each one of these ladies has in her court 10,000 persons. When he wishes to lie with one of his four wives, he invites her to his chamber; or sometimes he goes to his wife's chamber.

He also has many concubines, about whom I will tell you. There is a province inhabited by Tartars who are called Kungurat, which is also the name of their city. They are a very good-looking race with fair complexions. Every two years or so, according to his pleasure, the Great Khan sends emissaries to this province to select for him out of the most beautiful maidens, according to the standard of beauty which he lays down for them, some four or five hundred, more or less as he may decide. This is how the selection is made. When the emissaries arrive, they summon to their presence all the maidens of the province. And there valuers are deputed for the task. After inspecting and surveying every girl feature by feature, her hair, her face, her eyebrows, her mouth, her lips, and every other feature, to see whether they are well-formed and in harmony with her person, the valuers award to some a score of sixteen marks, to others seventeen, eighteen, or twenty, or more or less according to the degree of their beauty. And, if the Great Khan has ordered them to bring him all who score twenty marks, or perhaps twenty-one, according to the number ordered, these are duly brought. When they have come to his presence, he has them assessed a second time by other valuers, and then the thirty or forty with the highest score are selected for his chamber. These are first allotted, one by one, to the barons' wives, who are instructed to observe them carefully at night in their chambers, to make sure that they are virgins and not blemished or defective in any member, that they sleep sweetly without snoring, and that their breath is sweet and they give out no unpleasant odour. Then those who are approved are divided into groups of six, who serve the Khan for three days and three nights at a time in his chamber and his bed, ministering to all his needs. And he uses them according to his pleasure. After three days and nights, in come the next six damsels. And so they continue in rotation throughout the year. While some of the group are in attendance in their lord's chamber, the others are waiting in an antechamber hard by. If he is in need of anything from outside, such as food or drink, the damsels inside the chamber pass word to those outside, who immediately get it ready. In this way the Khan is served by no one except these damsels. As for the other damsels, who are rated at a lower score, they remain with the Khan's other women in the palace, where they are instructed in needle-work, glove-making, and other elegant accomplishments. When some nobleman is looking for a wife, the Great Khan gives him one of these damsels with a great dowry. And in this way he marries them all off honourably.

You may be inclined to ask: ‘Do not the men of this province regard it as a grievance that the Great Khan robs them of their daughters?’ Most certainly not. They esteem it a great favour and distinction; and those who have beautiful daughters are delighted that he should deign to accept them. They reason thus: ‘If my daughter is born under a good planet and happy auspices, the Khan will be better able to satisfy her than I; he will marry her to a noble husband, which is more than my means would permit of.’ And if she does not behave well or it does not turn out well for her, then the father says: ‘This has happened to her because her planet was not propitious.’

You should know further that by his four wives the Great Khan has twenty-two male children. The eldest was called Chinghiz, for love of the good Chinghiz Khan. He was to have succeeded his father as Great Khan and lord of the whole empire. But it happened that he died, leaving a son named Temur; this Temur is now destined to be Great Khan and lord, because he is the son of the eldest son of the Great Khan. I can assure you that this Temur is a man of wisdom and prowess, as he has already proved many times on the field of battle.

By his mistresses the Great Khan has a further twenty-five sons, all good men and brave soldiers. And each of them is a great baron.

Of his sons by his four wives, seven are kings of great provinces and kingdoms. They all exercise their authority well, lacking neither prudence nor prowess. And for this there is good reason, for I give you my word that their father the Great Khan is the wisest man and the ablest in all respects, the best ruler of subjects and of empire and the man of the highest character of all that have ever been in the whole history of the Tartars.

You must know that for three months in the year, December, January, and February, the Great Khan lives in the capital city of Cathay, whose name is Khanbalik. In this city he has his great palace, which I will now describe to you.

The palace is completely surrounded by a square wall, each side being a mile in length so that the whole circuit is four miles. It is a very thick wall and fully ten paces in height. It is all whitewashed and battlemented. At each corner of this wall stands a large palace of great beauty and splendour, in which the Great Khan keeps his military stores. In the middle of each side is another palace resembling the comer palaces, so that round the whole circuit of the walls there are eight palaces, all serving as arsenals. Each is reserved for a particular type of munition. Thus, one contains saddles, bridles, stirrups, and other items of a horse's harness. In another are bows, bow-strings, quivers, arrows, and other requisites of archery. In a third are cuirasses, corselets, and other armour of boiled leather. And so with the rest.

In the southern front of this wall there are five gates. There is one great gate in the middle, which is never opened except when the Great Khan is leaving or entering. Next to this, one on either side, are two small gates, by which everyone else enters. There are also two more large gates, one near each corner, which are likewise used by other people.

Within this outer wall is another wall, somewhat greater in length than in breadth. In this also there are eight palaces, just like the others, and used in the same way to house military stores. It also has five gates in its southern front, corresponding to those in the outer wall. In each of the other sides it has one gate only; and so has the outer wall.

Within this wall is the Great Khan's palace, which I will now describe to you. It is the largest that was ever seen. It has no upper floor, but the basement on which it stands is raised ten palms above the level of the surrounding earth; and all round it there runs a marble wall level with the basement, two paces in thickness. The foundation of the palace lies within this wall, so that as much of the wall as projects beyond it forms a sort of terrace, on which men can walk right round and inspect the outside of the palace. At the outer edge of this wall is a fine gallery with columns, where men can meet and talk. At each face of the palace is a great marble staircase, ascending from ground level to the top of this marble wall, which affords an entry into the palace.

The palace itself has a very high roof. Inside, the walls of the halls and chambers are all covered with gold and silver and decorated with pictures of dragons and birds and horsemen and various breeds of beasts and scenes of battle. The ceiling is similarly adorned, so that there is nothing to be seen anywhere but gold and pictures. The hall is so vast and so wide that a meal might well be served there for more than 6,000 men. The number of chambers is quite bewildering. The whole building is at once so immense and so well constructed that no man in the world, granted that he had the power to effect it, could imagine any improvement in design or execution. The roof is all ablaze with scarlet and green and blue and yellow and all the colours that are, so brilliantly varnished that it glitters like crystal and the sparkle of it can be seen from far away. And this roof is so strong and so stoutly built as to last for many a long year.

In the rear part of the palace are extensive apartments, both chambers and halls, in which are kept the private possessions of the Khan. Here is stored his treasure: gold, and silver, precious stones and pearls, and his gold and silver vessels. And here too are his ladies and his concubines. In these apartments everything is arranged for his comfort and convenience, and outsiders are not admitted.

Between the inner and the outer walls, of which I have told you, are stretches of park-land with stately trees. The grass grows here in abundance, because all the paths are paved and built up fully two cubits above the level of the ground, so that no mud forms on them and no rain-water collects in puddles, but the moisture trickles over the lawns, enriching the soil and promoting a lush growth of herbage. In these parks there is a great variety of game, such as white harts, musk-deer, roebuck, stags, squirrels, and many other beautiful animals. All the area within the walls is full of these graceful creatures, except the paths that people walk on.

In the north-western corner of the grounds is a pit of great size and depth, very neatly made, from which the earth was removed to build the mound of which I shall speak. The pit is filled with water by a fair-sized stream so as to form a sort of pond where the animals come to drink. The stream flows out through an aqueduct near the mound and fills another similar pit between the Great Khan's palace and that of Chinghiz his son, from which the earth was dug for the same purpose. These pits or ponds contain a great variety of fish. For the Great Khan has had them stocked with many different species, so that, whenever he feels in-clined, he may have his pick. At the farther end of the pond there is an outlet for the stream, through which it flows away. It is so contrived that at the entrance and the outlet there are gratings of iron and copper to stop the fish from escaping. There are also swans and other water-fowl. It is possible to pass from one palace to the other by way of a bridge over this stream.

On the northern side of the palace, at the distance of a bow-shot but still within the walls, the Great Khan has had made an earthwork, that is to say a mound fully 100 paces in height and over a mile in circumference. This mound is covered with a dense growth of trees, all evergreens that never shed their leaves. And I assure you that whenever the Great Khan hears tell of a particularly fine tree he has it pulled up, roots and all and with a quantity of earth, and transported to this mound by elephants. No matter how big the tree may be, he is not deterred from transplanting it. In this way he has assembled here the finest trees in the world. In addition, he has had the mound covered with lapis lazuli, which is intensely green, so that trees and rock alike are as green as green can be and there is no other colour to be seen. For this reason it is called the Green Mound. On top of this mound, in the middle of the summit, he has a large and handsome palace, and this too is entirely green. And I give you my word that mound and trees and palace form a vision of such beauty that it gladdens the hearts of all beholders. It was for the sake of this entrancing view that the Great Khan had them constructed, as well as for the refreshment and recreation they might afford him.

Let me tell you also that beside this palace the Great Khan has had another one built, just like his own and no whit inferior. This is built to be occupied by his son when he shall succeed him as ruler. That is why it is built in the same style and on the same scale as the Great Khan's own, which I have described above, and with walls of equal size. This is the residence of Temur the son of Chinghiz, of whom I have already spoken, who is destined to be Khan; and he observes the same ceremony and usages as the Great Khan, because he has been chosen to rule after the Great Khan's death. The bull and seal of empire are his already, though so long as the Great Khan is alive he does not enjoy them so absolutely.

Now that I have told you about these palaces, I will go on to tell you of the great town of Taidu in which they are situated, and why and how it came to be built.

On the banks of a great river in the province of Cathay there stood an ancient city of great size and splendour which was named Khan-balik, that is to say in our language ‘the Lord's City’. Now the Great Khan discovered through his astrologers that this city would rebel and put up a stubborn resistance against the Empire. For this reason he had this new city built next to the old one, with only the river between. And he removed the inhabitants of the old city and settled them in the new one, which is called Taidu, leaving only those whom he did not suspect of any rebellious designs; for the new city was not big enough to house all those who lived in the old.

Taidu is built in the form of a square with all its sides of equal length and a total circumference of twenty-four miles. It is enclosed by earthern ramparts, twenty paces high and ten paces thick at the base; the sides slope inwards from base to summit, so that at the top the width is only about three paces. They are all battlemented and white-washed. They have twelve gates, each surmounted by a fine, large palace. So on each of the four sides there are three gates and five palaces, because there is an additional palace at each corner. In these palaces there are immense halls, which house the weapons of the city guards.

I assure you that the streets are so broad and straight that from the top of the wall above one gate you can see along the whole length of the road to the gate opposite. The city is full of fine mansions, inns, and dwelling-houses. All the way down the sides of every main street there are booths and shops of every sort. All the building sites throughout the city are square and measured by the rule; and on every site stand large and spacious mansions with ample courtyards and gardens. These sites are allotted to heads of households, so that one belongs to such-and-such a person, representing such-and-such a family, the next to a representative of another family, and so all the way along. Every site or block is surrounded by good public roads; and in this way the whole interior of the city is laid out in squares like a chess-board with such masterly precision that no description can do justice to it.

In this city there is such a multitude of houses and of people, both within the walls and without, that no one could count their number. Actually there are more people outside the walls in the suburbs than in the city itself. There is a suburb outside every gate, such that each one touches the neighbouring suburbs on either side. They extend in length for three or four miles. And in every suburb or ward, at about a mile's distance from the city, there are many fine hostels which provide lodging for merchants coming from different parts: a particular hostel is assigned to every nation, as we might say one for the Lombards, another for the Germans, another for the French. Merchants and others come here on business in great numbers, both because it is the Khan's residence and because it affords a profitable market. And the suburbs have as fine houses and mansions as the city, except of course for the Khan's palace.

You must know that no one who dies is buried in the city. If an idolater dies there, his body is taken to the place of cremation, which lies outside all the suburbs. And so with the others also; when they die they are taken right outside the suburbs for burial. Similarly, no act of violence is performed inside the city, but only outside the suburbs.

Let me tell you also that no sinful woman dares live within the city, unless it be in secret — no woman of the world, that is, who prostitutes her body for money. But they all live in the suburbs, and there are so many of them that no one could believe it. For I assure you that there are fully 20,000 of them, all serving the needs of men for money. They have a captain general, and there are chiefs of hundreds and of thousands responsible to the captain. This is because, whenever ambassadors come to the Great Khan on his business and are maintained at his expense, which is done on a lavish scale, the captain is called upon to provide one of these women every night for the ambassador and one for each of his attendants. They are changed every night and receive no payment; for this is the tax they pay to the Great Khan. From the number of these prostitutes you may infer the number of traders and other visitors who are daily coming and going here about their business.

You may take it for a fact that more precious and costly wares are imported into Khan-balik than into any other city in the world. Let me give you particulars. All the treasures that come from India — precious stones, pearls, and other rarities — are brought here. So too are the choicest and costliest products of Cathay itself and every other province. This is on account of the Great Khan himself, who lives here, and of the lords and ladies and the enormous multitude of hotel-keepers and other residents and of visitors who attend the courts held here by the Khan. That is why the volume and value of the imports and of the internal trade exceed those of any other city in the world. It is a fact that every day more than 1,000 cart-loads of silk enter the city; for much cloth of gold and silk is woven here. Furthermore, Khan-balik is surrounded by more than 200 other cities, near and far, from which traders come to it to sell and to buy. So it is not surprising that it is the centre of such a traffic as I have described.

In the centre of the city stands a huge palace in which is a great bell; in the evening this peals three times as a signal that no one may go about the town. Once this bell has sounded the due number of peals, no one ventures abroad in the city except in case of childbirth or illness; and those who are called out by such emergencies are obliged to carry lights. Every night there are guards riding about the city in troops of thirty or forty, to discover whether anyone is going about at an abnormal hour, that is after the third peal of the bell. If anyone is found, he is promptly arrested and clapped into prison. Next morning he is examined by the officials appointed for the purpose, and if he is found guilty of any offence, he is punished according to its gravity with a proportionate number of strokes of a rod, which sometimes cause death. They employ this mode of punishment in order to avoid bloodshed, because their Bakhshi, that is, the adepts in astrology, declare that it is wrong to shed human blood.

It is ordered that every gateway must be guarded by 1,000 men. You must not suppose that this guard is maintained out of mistrust of the inhabitants. It is there, in fact, partly as a mark of respect to the Great Khan who lives in the city, partly as a check upon evil-doers — although, because of the prophecy of his astrologers, the Khan does harbour certain suspicions of the people of Cathay.

Let me now tell you how on one occasion the Cathayans in the city actually did plan to revolt. It is an established practice, as will be explained below, that twelve men are appointed with full powers of disposal over territories and public offices at their own discretion. Among these was a Saracen called Ahmad, a man of great energy and ability, who surpassed all the rest in his authority and influence over the Great Khan. The Emperor was so fond of him that he gave him a completely free hand. It seems, as was learnt after his death, that this Ahmad used to bewitch the Emperor by his black arts to such purpose that he won a ready hearing and acceptance for everything he said; and so he was free to do whatever he chose. He used to make all appointments to office and punish all delinquents. Whenever he wished to cause the death of anyone whom he hated, whether justly or unjustly, he would go to the Emperor and say to him: ‘So-and-so deserves to die, because he has offended your Majesty in such-and-such a way.’ Then the Emperor would say: ‘Do as you think best.’ And Ahmad would thereupon put him to death. Therefore, seeing the complete liberty he enjoyed and the absolute faith reposed in him by the Emperor, men did not venture to thwart him in anything. There was no one so great or of such authority as not to fear him. If anyone was accused by him to the Emperor of a capital offence and wished to plead his cause, he had no chance to rebut the charge or state his own case, because he could count on no support—everyone was too much afraid of going against Ahmad. In this way, he caused the death of many innocent people.

Furthermore, there was not a pretty woman who took his fancy but he would have his will with her, taking her as a wife if she was not already married or otherwise enforcing her submission. Whenever he learnt that someone had a good-looking daughter, he would send his ruffians to the girl's father, and they would say: ‘What is your ambition? Well then, how about this daughter of yours? Give her to the Bailo (for Ahmad was called by the title of Bailo or Lord-Lieutenant) and we will see that he gives you such-and-such a post or office for three years.’ So the man would give him his daughter. Then Ahmad would say to the Khan: ‘Such-and-such a post is vacant, or will fall vacant on such-and-such a date. So-and-so is the right man for the job.’ To which the Khan would answer: ‘Do as you think best.’ And Ahmad would promptly instal him. By this means, playing partly on men's ambition for office, partly on their fears, Ahmad got possession of all the best-looking women as his wives and his concubines. He also had sons, some twenty-five of them, whom he installed in the highest offices. Some of them, under cover of their father's name, used to practise adultery in their father's fashion and commit many other crimes and abominations. Ahmad had also accumulated an immense fortune, because everyone who aspired to any post or office used to send him a handsome present.

Ahmad exercised this authority as governor for twenty-two years. At length the people of the country, that is the Cathayans, seeing that there was no end to the iniquities and abominations that he perpetrated beyond all measure at the expense of their womenfolk as well as their own persons, reached the point where they could endure it no longer. They made up their minds to assassinate him and revolt against the government of the city. Among their number was a Cathayan named Ch'ien-hu, a commander of 1,000, whose mother, daughter, and wife had all been ravished by Ahmad. Ch'ien-hu, moved by fierce indignation, plotted the destruction of the governor with another Cathayan named Wan-hu, a commander of 10,000.[1] They planned to do the deed when the Great Khan had completed his three months' sojourn at Khan-balik and had left for the city of Shang-tu, where he would likewise spend three months, and his son Chinghiz had also set out for his accustomed residences. At such times Ahmad was left to keep guard over the city: when the need arose, he would send word to the Great Khan at Shang-tu and the Khan would send back word of his wishes. The two plotters decided to impart their plot to the leading Cathayans of the country, and by common consent they made it known in many other cities to their own friends. The scheme was to take effect on the appointed day in the following manner. At the sight of a signal fire, all the conspirators were immediately to put to death any man wearing a beard and to pass on the signal to other cities by means of beacons that they should do the same. The reason for killing the bearded men was that the Cathayans are naturally beardless, whereas the Tartars, Saracens, and Christians wear beards. You must understand that all the Cathayans hated the government of the Great Khan, because he set over them Tartar rulers, mostly Saracens, and they could not endure it, since it made them feel that they were no more than slaves. Moreover the Great Khan had no legal title to rule the province of Cathay, having acquired it by force. So, putting no trust in the people, he committed the government of the country to Tartars, Saracens, and Christians who were attached to his household and personally loyal to him and not natives of Cathay.

Then Wan-hu and Ch'ien-hu, on the appointed date, entered the palace by night. And Wan-hu seated himself on the throne and had many lights lit in front of him. And he sent a courier to Ahmad, who lived in the old city, announcing that Chinghiz, the Khan's son, had just arrived that very night and summoned the Bailo to wait upon him without delay. When Ahmad heard this, he went immediately, greatly puzzled and not a little alarmed. On his way in through the city gate he met a Tartar named Kogatai, who was in command of the 12,000 men who kept constant watch and ward over the city. ‘Where are you going at this late hour?’ asked Kogatai. ‘To Chinghiz, who has just arrived.’ ‘How is it possible,’ asked Kogatai, ‘that he can have arrived so secretly that I have heard nothing of it?’ And he followed him with a detachment of his guard. Now the conspirators had said among themselves: ‘If only we can kill Ahmad, we have nothing to fear from anything else.’ The moment Ahmad entered the palace and saw it such a blaze of lights, he knelt before Wan-hu, mistaking him for Chinghiz; and Ch'ien-hu, who was there armed with a sword, cut off his head.

When Kogatai, who had stopped at the entrance to the palace, saw this, he shouted ‘Treason!’ And there and then he aimed an arrow at Wan-hu, who was seated on the throne, and shot him dead. Then, calling on his followers, he seized Ch'ien-hu. And he issued a proclamation throughout the city that anyone found out of doors would be killed on the spot. The Cathayans, seeing that the Tartars had discovered their plot and that they were left without a head, one of their leaders being killed and the other captured, stayed quietly in their homes and hence could give no sign to the other cities to carry out their plan of rebellion. Kogatai promptly sent couriers to the Great Khan with a full account of everything that had happened, and received in reply an order to conduct a thorough investigation and punish the guilty according to their deserts. When morning came, Kogatai examined all the Cathayans, and put to death many whom he found to be ring-leaders in the conspiracy. And the same thing was done in the other cities, when it came out that they were involved in the crime.

When the Great Khan had returned to Khan-balik, he wanted to know the cause of this occurrence. He then learnt the truth about the abominable outrages committed, as already related, by the execrable Ahmad and his sons. He found out that Ahmad himself and seven of his sons—for they were not all wicked—had taken innumerable ladies to be their wives, not to speak of those whom they had possessed by force. Then he caused all the treasure that Ahmad had amassed in the Old City to be brought into the New City; and put it with his own treasure; and it was found to be beyond all reckoning. He ordered Ahmad's body to be taken from the grave and flung in the street to be torn to pieces by dogs. And those of his sons who had followed the example of his evil deeds he caused to be flayed alive. And when he called to mind the accursed doctrine of the Saracens, by which every sin is accounted a lawful act even to the killing of any man who is not of their creed, so that because of it the execrable Ahmad and his sons were not conscious of committing any sin, he utterly contemned it and held it in abomination. He summoned the Saracens to his presence and expressly forbade them to do many things which their law commanded. In particular he commanded them to take their wives according to the law of the Tartars and not to cut the throats of animals, as they used to do, in order to eat their flesh, but to slit their bellies. And at the time when all this happened, Messer Marco was in this place.

As for the Great Khan's guard of 12,000 men, you must know that they are called Keshikten, which is as much as to say ‘knights and liegemen of the lord’. He employs them not out of fear of any man but in token of his sovereignty. These 12,000 horsemen have four captains, one over every 3,000. Each 3,000 in turn reside in the Khan's palace for three days and three nights and eat and drink there, and at the end of that time another 3,000 take their place, and so they continue throughout the year. By day indeed the other 9,000 do not leave the palace, unless it happens that one of them goes off on the Khan's affairs or on some urgent private business and then only if it is legitimate and he has his captain's leave. If he is faced with something really serious, such as the impending death of a father or brother or other near relative, or the threat of some heavy loss which would not permit of his immediate return, then he must get leave from the Khan. But at night the 9,000 are free to go home.

When the Great Khan is holding court, the seating at banquets is arranged as follows. He himself sits at a much higher table than the rest at the northern end of the hall, so that he faces south. His principal wife sits next to him on the left. On the right, at a somewhat lower level, sit his sons in order of age, Chinghiz the eldest being placed rather higher than the rest, and his grandsons and his kinsmen of the imperial lineage. They are so placed that their heads are on a level with the Great Khan's feet. Next to them are seated the other noblemen at other tables lower down again. And the ladies are seated on the same plan. All the wives of the Khan's sons and grandsons and kinsmen are seated on his left at a lower level, and next to them the wives of his nobles and knights lower down still. And they all know their appointed place in the lord's plan. The tables are so arranged that the Great Khan can see everything, and there are a great many of them. But you must not imagine that all the guests sit at table; for most of the knights and nobles in the hall take their meal seated on carpets for want of tables. Outside the hall the guests at the banquet number more than 40,000. For they include many visitors with costly gifts, men who come from strange countries bringing strange things, and some who have held high office and aspire to further advancement. Such are the guests who attend on such occasions, when the Great Khan is holding court or celebrating a wedding.

In the midst of the hall where the Great Khan has his table is a very fine piece of furniture of great size and splendour in the form of a square chest, each side being three paces in length, elaborately carved with figures of animals finely wrought in gold. The inside is hollow and contains a huge golden vessel in the form of a pitcher with the capacity of a butt, which is filled with wine. In each comer of the chest is a vessel with the capacity of a firkin, one filled with mares' milk, one with camels' milk, and the others with other beverages. On the chest stand all the Khan's vessels in which drink is served to him. From it the wine or other precious beverage is drawn off to fill huge stoups of gold, each containing enough to satisfy eight or ten men. One of these is set between every two men seated at the table. Each of the two has a gold cup with a handle, which he fills from the stoup. And for every pair of ladies one stoup and two cups are provided in the same way. You must understand that these stoups and the rest are of great value. I can assure you that the Great Khan has such a store of vessels of gold and silver that no one who did not see it with his own eyes could well believe it. And the waiters who serve his food and drink are certain of his barons. They have their mouths and noses swathed in fine napkins of silk and gold, so that the food and drink are not contaminated by their breath or effluence.

Certain barons are also appointed to look after newcomers unfamiliar with court etiquette and show them to their allotted and appropriate seats. These barons are continually passing to and fro through the hall, asking the guests if they lack anything. And if there are any who want wine or milk or anything else, they have it promptly brought to them by the waiters. At all the entrances of the hall, or wherever else the Great Khan may be, stand two men of gigantic stature, one on either side, with staves in their hands. This is because it is not permissible for anyone to touch the threshold of the door, but all who enter must step over it. If anyone should happen to touch it by accident, the guardians take his clothes from him and he must pay a fine to redeem them. Or if they do not take his clothes, they administer the appointed number of blows. But if they are newcomers who do not know of the rule, certain barons are assigned to introduce them and warn them of the rule. This is done because touching the threshold is looked upon as a bad omen. In leaving the hall, since some of the guests are overcome with drinking so that they could not possibly exercise due care, no such rule is enjoined.

There are many instruments in the hall, of every sort, and when the Great Khan is about to drink they all strike up. As soon as the cup-bearer has handed him the cup, he retires three paces and kneels down; and all the barons and all the people present go down on their knees and make a show of great humility. Then the Great Khan drinks. And every time he drinks the same performance is repeated. Of the food I say nothing, because everyone will readily believe that there is no lack of it. Let me add that there is no baron or knight at the banquet but brings his wife to dine with the other ladies. When they have fed and the tables are removed, a great troupe of jugglers and acrobats and other entertainers comes into the hall and performs remarkable feats of various kinds. And they all afford great amusement and entertainment in the Khan's presence, and the guests show their enjoyment by peals of laughter. When all is over, the guests take their leave and return each to his own lodging or house.

You must know that all the Tartars celebrate their birthdays as festivals. The Great Khan was born on the twenty-eighth day of the lunar cycle in the month of September. And on this day he holds the greatest feast of the year, excepting only the new year festival of which I will tell you later. On his birthday he dons a magnificent robe of beaten gold. And fully 12,000 barons and knights robe themselves with him in a similar colour and style — not so costly as his, but still of the same colour and style, in cloth of silk and gold, and all with gold belts. These robes are given to them by the Great Khan. And I assure you that the value of some of these robes, reckoning the precious stones and pearls with which they are often adorned, amounts to 10,000 golden bezants. Of such there are not a few. And you must know that the Great Khan gives rich robes to these 12,000 barons and knights thirteen times a year, so that they are all dressed in robes like his own and of great value. You can see for yourselves that this is no light matter, and that there is no other prince in the world besides himself who could bear such an expense.

On this royal birthday all the Tartars in the world, all the provinces and regions where men hold land and lordship under the Great Khan, give him costly presents proportionate to the giver and in accordance with prescribed order. And rich gifts are also brought to him by many others, petitioners for high office — which is awarded to applicants according to merit by twelve barons appointed for the purpose. And on this day all the idolaters and all the Christians and all the Saracens and all the races of men offer solemn prayers to their idols and their gods, with singing of hymns and lighting of lamps and burning of incense, that they may save their lord and give him long life and joy and health. So this day is passed in merry-making and birthday festivities. Now that I have fully described them, let us turn to another great feast which is celebrated at the new year and is called the White Feast.

The new year begins with them in February, and this is how it is observed by the Great Khan and all his subjects. According to custom they all array themselves in white, both male and female, so far as their means allow. And this they do because they regard white costume as auspicious and benign, and they don it at the new year so that throughout the year they may enjoy prosperity and happiness. On this day all the rulers, and all the provinces and regions and realms where men hold land or lordship under his sway, bring him costly gifts of gold and silver and pearls and precious stones and abundance of fine white cloth, so that throughout the year their lord may have no lack of treasure and may live in joy and gladness. Let me tell you also that the barons and knights and all the people make gifts to one another of white things. And they greet one another gaily and cheerfully saying, very much as we do: ‘May this year be a lucky one for you and bring you success in all you undertake.’ And this they do so that throughout the year all may go well with them and all their enterprises prosper.

I can also assure you for a fact that on this day the Great Khan receives gifts of more than 100,000 white horses, of great beauty and price. And on this day also there is a procession of his elephants, fully 4,000 in number, all draped in fine cloths embroidered with beasts and birds. Each one bears on its back two strong-boxes of great beauty and price filled with the Khan's plate and with costly apparel for this white-robed court. With them come innumerable camels also draped with cloths and laden with provisions for the feast. They all defile in front of the Great Khan and it is the most splendid sight that ever was seen.

On the morning of this feast, before the tables are set up, all the kings and all the dukes, marquises and counts, barons, knights, astrologers, physicians, falconers, and many other officials and rulers of men and lands and armies appear before the Khan in the great hall. And those who do not achieve this assemble outside the palace in a spot where the Khan can readily inspect them. Let me tell you in what order they are stationed. In front are his sons and grandsons and those of his imperial lineage. Next come the kings, then the dukes and then all the other ranks, one behind another, in due order. And when they are all seated, each in his proper station, up stands a great dignitary and proclaims in a loud voice: ‘Bow down and worship!’ No sooner has he said this than they bow down, then and there, and touch the ground with their foreheads, and address a prayer to the lord and worship him as if he were a god. Then the dignitary proclaims: ‘God save our lord and long preserve him in gladness and joy!’ And one and all reply: ‘God do so!’ Once again the dignitary proclaims: ‘God increase and multiply his empire from good to better and keep all his subjects in untroubled peace and good will and in all his lands grant universal prosperity!’ And one and all reply: ‘God do so!’ In this manner they worship him four times. Then they go to an altar, adorned with great splendour, on which is a scarlet tablet bearing the name of the Great Khan, and also a splendidly wrought censer. They cense this tablet and the altar with great reverence. Then they return, each to his place. When they have all done this, then the precious gifts of which I have spoken are presented. After this, when the Great Khan has viewed all the gifts, the tables are laid and the guests take their places in due order as I have already related — the Khan alone at his high table with his first wife, and the others each in his degree, and their ladies on the empress's side of the hall, just as I have described it to you before. When they have fed, the performers come in and entertain the court as before. Finally they return, everyone to his own lodging or home.

Next let me tell you that the Great Khan has ordained thirteen feasts, one for each of the thirteen lunar months, which are attended by the 12,000 barons called Keshikten, that is to say the henchmen most closely attached to the Khan. To each of these he has given thirteen robes, every one of a different colour. They are splendidly adorned with pearls and gems and other ornaments and are of immense value. He has also given to each of the 12,000 a gold belt of great beauty and price, and shoes of fine leather (called canaut or borgal) cunningly embroidered with silver thread, which are likewise beautiful and costly. All their attire is so gorgeous and so stately that when they are fully robed any one of them might pass for a king. One of these robes is appointed to be worn at each of the thirteen feasts. The Great Khan himself has thirteen similar robes — similar, that is, in colour, but more splendid and costly and more richly adorned; and he always dresses in the same colour as his barons.

The cost of these robes, to the number of 146,000 in all, amounts to a quantity of treasure that is almost past computation, to say nothing of the belts and shoes, which also cost a goodly sum. And all this the Khan does for the embellishment or enhancement of his feasts.

Let me conclude with one more fact, a very remarkable one well worthy of mention in our book. You must know that a great lion is led into the Great Khan's presence; and as soon as it sees him it flings itself down prostrate before him with every appearance of deep humility and seems to acknowledge him as lord. There it stays without a chain, and is indeed a thing to marvel at.

We will turn next to the Great Khan's hunting parties.

You may take it for a fact that during the three months which the Great Khan spends in the city of Khan-balik, that is, December, January, and February, he has ordered that within a distance of sixty days' journey from where he is staying everybody must devote himself to hunting and hawking. The order goes out to every governor of men or lands to send all such large beasts as wild boars, harts, stags, roebucks, bears, and the like, or at any rate the greater part of them. So every governor gathers round him all the huntsmen of the district, and together they go wherever these beasts are to be found, beating their coverts in turn and killing some of them with their hounds but most with their arrows. That is how they hunt them. And those beasts that they wish to send to the Great Khan they first disembowel and then load on carts and so dispatch. This applies to all those within thirty days' journey, and their combined bag is enormous. Those distant from thirty to sixty days do not send the flesh — the journey is too long for that — but send the hides duly dressed and tanned, so that the Khan may use them in the manufacture of necessary equipment for his armies.

You must know also that the Great Khan has a plentiful supply of leopards skilled in hunting game and of lynxes trained in the chase and past masters of their craft. He has a number of lions of immense size, bigger than those of Egypt; they have very handsome, richly coloured fur, with longitudinal stripes of black, orange, and white. They are trained to hunt wild boars and bulls, bears, wild asses, stags, roebuck, and other game. A grand sight it is to see the stately creatures that fall a prey to these lions. When the lions are led out to the chase, they are carried on carts in cages, each with a little dog for company. They are caged because otherwise they would be too ferocious and too eager in their pursuit of game, so that there would be no holding them. They must always be led upwind; for if their prey caught wind of the smell they would not wait, but would be off in a flash. He has also a great many eagles trained to take wolves and foxes and fallow-deer and roe-deer, and these too bring in game in plenty. Those that are trained to take wolves are of immense size and power, for there is never a wolf so big that he escapes capture by one of these eagles.

Now that you have heard what I have to tell on this subject, I will tell you of the numbers and excellence of the Great Khan's hounds. You must know that among his barons there are two brothers in blood who are named Bayan and Mingan. They bear the title kuyukchi, that is to say, keepers of the mastiffs. Each of them has 10,000 subordinates, who all wear livery of one colour; and the other 10,000 all wear another colour. The two colours are scarlet and blue. Whenever they accompany the Great Khan in the chase, they wear these liveries. Among either 10,000 there are 2,000 of whom each one leads a mastiff, or maybe two or more, so that the total number is immense. When the Great Khan goes hunting, one of the two brothers with his 10,000 men and fully 4,000 hounds goes with him on one side and the other with his 10,000 and his hounds goes on the other. The two bands keep pace with each other exactly, so that the whole line extends in length over a day's journey. And not a wild beast do they find but falls a prey. What a sight it is to see the hunt and the performance of the hounds and the hunters! For you must picture that, while the Great Khan rides out hawking with his barons across the open country, then packs of these hounds are to be seen advancing on either side, hunting bears and stags and other beasts, so that it is truly a fine sight to see. These two brothers are bound by covenant to provide the Great Khan's court every day, beginning in October and continuing to the end of March, with a thousand head of game, including both beasts and birds, except quails, and also fish to the best of their ability, reckoning as the equivalent of one head as much fish as would make a square meal for three persons.

When the Khan has spent the three months of December, January, and February in the city of which I have spoken, he sets off in March and travels southward to within two days' journey of the Ocean. He is accompanied by fully 10,000 falconers and takes with him fully 4,000 gerfalcons and peregrine falcons and sakers in great abundance, besides a quantity of goshawks for hawking along the riversides. You must not imagine that he keeps all this company with him in one place. In fact he distributes them here and there, in groups of a hundred or two hundred or more. Then they engage in fowling, and most of the fowl they take are brought to the Great Khan. And I would have you know that when he goes hawking with his gerfalcons and other hawks, he has fully 10,000 men in parties of two who are called toscaor, which signifies in our language ‘watchmen’. These men are posted here and there in couples, so as to occupy a wide enough area. Each has a call and a hood, so that they can call in the hawks and hold them. And when the Khan orders the hawks to be cast, there is no need for the casters to go after them, because the men of whom I have spoken, dispersed here and there, keep such careful watch that wherever a hawk may go they are always on the spot and if one is in need of help they are prompt to render it.

All the Great Khan's hawks and those of the other barons have a little tablet of silver attached to their feet on which is written the name of the owner and also that of the keeper. By this means the bird is recognized as soon as it is taken, and is returned to the owner. If the finder does not know whose it is, he takes it to a baron who is called bularguchi, which is as much as to say ‘keeper of lost property’. For, I would have you know that, if anyone finds a horse or a sword or a hawk or anything else and cannot discover the owner, it is immediately brought to this baron, and he takes charge of it. If the finder does not hand it over forthwith, he is reckoned a thief. And the losers apply to this baron, and if he has received their property he promptly returns it. He always has his official residence, with its flag flying, at the highest point in the whole camp, so as to be readily seen by those who have lost anything. By this means nothing can be lost without being found and returned.

When the Great Khan goes on the journey of which I have told you towards the Ocean, the expedition is marked by many fine displays of huntsmanship and falconry. Indeed, there is no sport in the world to compare with it. He always rides on the back of four elephants, in a very handsome shelter of wood, covered inside with cloth of beaten gold and outside with lionskins. Here he always keeps twelve gerfalcons of the best he possesses and is attended by several barons to entertain him and keep him company. When he is travelling in this shelter on the elephants, and other barons who are riding in his train call out, ‘Sire, there are cranes passing,’ and he orders the roof of the shelter to be thrown open and so sees the cranes, he bids his attendants fetch such gerfalcons as he may choose and lets them fly. And often, the gerfalcons take the cranes in full view while the Great Khan remains all the while on his couch. And this affords him great sport and recreation. Meanwhile the other barons and knights ride all round him. And you may rest assured that there never was, and I do not believe there ever will be, any man who can enjoy such sport and recreation in this world as he does, or has such facilities for doing so.

When he has travelled so far that he arrives at a place called Cachar Modun, then he finds his pavilions ready pitched there and those of his sons and his barons and his mistresses to the number of more than 10,000; and very fine they are, and very costly. Let me tell you how his pavilion is made. First, the tent in which he holds his court is big enough to accommodate fully a thousand knights. This tent has its entrance towards the south and serves as a hall for the barons and other retainers. Adjoining this is another tent which faces west and is occupied by the Khan himself. It is to this tent that he summons anyone with whom he wishes to converse. At the back of the great hall is a large and handsome chamber in which he sleeps. There are also other chambers and other tents; but they do not adjoin the great tent. Let me tell you how these two halls and the chamber are constructed. Each hall has columns of spicewood very skilfully carved. On the outside they are all covered with lion-skins of great beauty, striped with black and white and orange. They are so well designed that neither wind nor rain can harm them or do any mischief. Inside they are all of ermine and sable, which are the two finest and richest and costliest furs there are. The truth is that a superfine sable fur big enough for a man's cloak is worth up to 2,000 golden bezants, while an ordinary one is worth 1,000. The Tartars call it ‘the king of furs'. The sable is about the size of a marten. With these two sorts of skin the two great halls are lined, pieced together with such artistry that it is a truly amazing spectacle. And the chamber where the Khan sleeps, which adjoins the two halls, is also of lion-skins without and ermine and sable with-in, magnificent in workmanship and design. The cords that hold up the halls and chambers are all of silk. So precious indeed and so costly are these three tents that no petty king could afford them.

Round these three tents are pitched all the other tents, also well designed and appointed. The Khan's mistresses too have splendid pavilions. And for the gerfalcons and falcons and other birds and beasts there are tents in vast numbers. What need of more words? You may take it for a fact that the number of people in this camp almost passes belief. You might well fancy that the Khan was here in residence in his finest city. For it is thronged with multitudes from all parts. His whole household staff is here with him, besides physicians and astrologers and falconers and other officials in great numbers, and everything is as well ordered as in his capital.

In this place he stays till spring, which in these parts falls about our Easter Day. Throughout his stay he never ceases to go hawking by lake or stream, and he makes an ample catch of cranes and swans and other birds. And his followers who are dispersed about the neighbourhood send in lavish contributions of game and fowl. All this time he enjoys the finest sport and recreation in the world, so that no one in the world who has not seen it could ever believe it; so far do his magnificence and his state and his pleasures surpass my description.

Let me tell you one thing more. No merchant or artisan or peasant dare keep any falcon or bird of prey or any hound for the chase within twenty days' journey of the Great Khan's residence; but in every other province and region of his dominions they are free to hunt and do as they please with hawks and hounds. And you must understand, furthermore, that throughout his empire no king or baron or any other person dares to take or hunt hare or hart, buck or stag, or any other such beast between the months of March and October, so that they may increase and multiply. And anyone who contravenes this rule is made to repent it bitterly, because it is the Khan's own enactment. And I assure you that his commandment is so strictly obeyed that hares and bucks and the other beasts I have mentioned often come right up to a man, and he does not touch them or do them any harm.

After spending his time here in this fashion till about Easter Day, the Great Khan sets out with all his retainers and returns direct to the city of Khan-balik by the same route by which he came, hunting and hawking all the way and enjoying good sport.

It is in this city of Khan-balik that the Great Khan has his mint; and it is so organized that you might well say that he has mastered the art of alchemy. I will demonstrate this to you here and now.

You must know that he has money made for him by the following process, out of the bark of trees — to be precise, from mulberry trees (the same whose leaves furnish food for silkworms). The fine bast between the bark and the wood of the tree is stripped off. Then it is crumbled and pounded and flattened out with the aid of glue into sheets like sheets of cotton paper, which are all black. When made, they are cut up into rectangles of various sizes, longer than they are broad. The smallest is worth half a small tornesel; the next an entire such tornesel; the next half a silver groat; the next an entire silver groat, equal in value to a silver groat of Venice; and there are others equivalent to two, five, and ten groats and one, three, and as many as ten gold bezants. And all these papers are sealed with the seal of the Great Khan. The procedure of issue is as formal and as authoritative as if they were made of pure gold or silver. On each piece of money several specially appointed officials write their names, each setting his own stamp. When it is completed in due form, the chief of the officials deputed by the Khan dips in cinnabar the seal or bull assigned to him and stamps it on the top of the piece of money so that the shape of the seal in vermilion remains impressed upon it. And then the money is authentic. And if anyone were to forge it, he would suffer the extreme penalty.

Of this money the Khan has such a quantity made that with it he could buy all the treasure in the world. With this currency he orders all payments to be made throughout every province and kingdom and region of his empire. And no one dares refuse it on pain of losing his life. And I assure you that all the peoples and populations who are subject to his rule are perfectly willing to accept these papers in payment, since wherever they go they pay in the same currency, whether for goods or for pearls or precious stones or gold or silver. With these pieces of paper they can buy anything and pay for anything. And I can tell you that the papers that reckon as ten bezants do not weigh one.

Several times a year parties of traders arrive with pearls and precious stones and gold and silver and other valuables, such as cloth of gold and silk, and surrender them all to the Great Khan. The Khan then summons twelve experts, who are chosen for the task and have special knowledge of it, and bids them examine the wares that the traders have brought and pay for them what they judge to be their true value. The twelve experts duly examine the wares and pay the value in the paper currency of which I have spoken. The traders accept it willingly, because they can spend it afterwards on the various goods they buy throughout the Great Khan's dominions. And I give you my word that the wares brought in at different times during the year mount up to a value of fully 400,000 bezants, and they are all paid for in this paper currency.

Let me tell you further that several times a year a fiat goes forth through the towns that all those who have gems and pearls and gold and silver must bring them to the Great Khan's mint. This they do, and in such abundance that it is past all reckoning; and they are all paid in paper money. By this means the Great Khan acquires all the gold and silver and pearls and precious stones of all his territories.

Here is another fact well worth relating. When these papers have been so long in circulation that they are growing torn and frayed, they are brought to the mint and changed for new and fresh ones at a discount of 3 per cent. And here again is an admirable practice that well deserves mention in our book: if a man wants to buy gold or silver to make his service of plate or his belts or other finery, he goes to the Khan's mint with some of these papers and gives them in payment for the gold and silver which he buys from the mintmaster. And all the Khan's armies are paid with this sort of money.

I have now told you how it comes about that the Great Khan must have, as indeed he has, more treasure than anyone else in the world. I may go further and affirm that all the world's great potentates put together have not such riches as belong to the Great Khan alone.

Let me tell you next of the magnates who exercise authority from Khan-balik.

You must know that the Great Khan, as already mentioned, has appointed twelve great and powerful barons to supervise all decisions concerning the movement of the armies, changes in the high command, and dispatch of troops to one theatre or another in greater or less force, as need may require, according to the importance of the war. In addition it rests with them to sort out the staunch and fearless fighters from the faint-hearted, promoting the former and degrading those who prove incompetent or cowardly. And if anyone is captain of a thousand and has disgraced himself in any action, these barons decide that he has shown himself unworthy of his office and debase him to the rank of captain of a hundred. But if he has conducted himself creditably and with distinction, so that they judge him fit for a higher command, they advance him to a captaincy of ten thousand. In every case, however, they act with the knowledge of the Great Khan. When they propose to degrade anyone, they say to the Khan, ‘So-and-so is unworthy of such-and-such an office,’ to which he replies, ‘Let him be degraded to a lower rank’; and so it is done. If they have it in mind to promote anyone in acknowledgement of his merits, they say, ‘Such-and-such a captain of a thousand is fit and worthy to be captain of ten thousand’; then the Khan confirms the appointment and gives him the appropriate tablet, as previously described, and immediately orders him to be given presents of great value, so as to encourage the others to make the most of their abilities. This council of twelve barons is called Thai, that is to say ‘Supreme Court’, because there is no higher authority except the Great Khan himself.

Besides these there are twelve other barons to whom the Khan has committed authority over all the affairs of the thirty-four provinces. And this is how they are organized. Let me tell you first that they live in a palace in the town of Khan-balik, a palace of great size and beauty with many halls and residential quarters. For every province there is a judge and a staff of clerks, who all live in this palace, each in his own private residence. And the judge and his staff administer all the affairs of the province to which they are assigned, subject to the will and authority of the twelve barons. It rests with these barons to choose the governors of all the provinces. And when they have chosen men whom they consider competent and suitable, they recommend them to the Great Khan, who confirms their appointment and confers the appropriate tablet. They also supervise the collection of taxes and revenues together with their administration and expenditure and all else that concerns the imperial government throughout these provinces, except purely military matters. This Council goes by the name of Shieng, and the palace in which it is housed is also called Shieng.

Both the Thai and the Shieng are supreme courts, having no authority above them except the Great Khan himself, and enjoying the power to confer great benefits on whom they will. The Thai, however, that is to say the military court, is esteemed more highly and carries greater dignity than any other office.

I do not propose to enumerate the provinces at this stage, as I shall be giving a full account of them later in the book. Let us turn now to the system of post-horses by which the Great Khan sends his dispatches.

You must know that the city of Khan-balik is a centre from which many roads radiate to many provinces, one to each, and every road bears the name of the province to which it runs. The whole system is admirably contrived. When one of the Great Khan's messengers sets out along any of these roads, he has only to go twenty-five miles and there he finds a posting station, which in their language is called yamb and in our language may be rendered ‘horse post’. At every post the messengers find a spacious and palatial hostelry for their lodging. These hostelries have splendid beds with rich coverlets of silk and all that befits an emissary of high rank. If a king came here, he would be well lodged. Here the messengers find no less than 400 horses, stationed here by the Great Khan's orders and always kept in readiness for his messengers when they are sent on any mission. And you must understand that posts such as these, at distances of twenty-five or thirty miles, are to be found along all the main highways leading to the provinces of which I have spoken. And at each of these posts the messengers find three or four hundred horses in readiness awaiting their command, and palatial lodgings such as I have described. And this holds good throughout all the provinces and kingdoms of the Great Khan's empire.

When the messengers are travelling through out-of-the-way country, where there are no homesteads or habitations, they find that the Great Khan has had posts established even in these wilds, with the same palatial accommodation and the same supply of horses and accoutrements. But here the stages are longer; for the posts are thirty-five miles apart and in some cases over forty miles.

By this means the Great Khan's messengers travel throughout his dominions and have lodgings and horses fully accoutred for every stage. And this is surely the highest privilege and the greatest resource ever enjoyed by any man on earth, king or emperor or what you will. For you may be well assured that more than 200,000 horses are stabled at these posts for the special use of these messengers. Moreover, the posts themselves number more than 10,000, all furnished on the same lavish scale. The whole organization is so stupendous and so costly that it baffles speech and writing.

If anyone is puzzled to understand how there can be enough people to execute such tasks, and what is the source of their livelihood, my answer is this. All the idolaters, and likewise the Saracens, take six, eight, or ten wives apiece, as many as they can afford to keep, and beget innumerable children. Hence there will be many men with more than thirty sons of their own, who all follow them under arms. This follows from the plurality of wives. With us, on the other hand, a man has only one wife, and if she should prove barren he will end his days with her and beget no children. Hence our population is less than theirs. As to the means of life, they have no shortage, because they mostly use rice, panic, or millet, especially the Tartars and the people of Cathay and Manzi, and these three cereals in their countries yield an increase of a hundredfold on each sowing. These peoples do not use bread, but simply boil these three sorts of grain with milk or flesh and then eat them. Wheat in their country does not yield such an increase; but such of it as they harvest they eat only in the form of noodles or other pasty foods. Among them no land is left idle that might be cultivated. Their beasts increase and multiply without end. When they are on military service, there is not one of them who does not lead with him six, eight, or more horses for his own use. So it is not difficult to understand why the population in these parts is so enormous and the means of life so plentiful.

Now let me tell you another thing which I forgot to mention—one that is very germane to the matter in hand. The fact is that between one post and the next, at distances of three miles apart, there are stations which may contain as many as forty buildings occupied by unmounted couriers, who also play a part in the Great Khan's postal service. I will tell you how. They wear large belts, set all round with bells, so that when they run they are audible at a great distance. They always run at full speed and never for more than three miles. And at the next station three miles away, where the noise they make gives due notice of their approach, another courier is waiting in readiness. As soon as the first man arrives, the new one takes what he is carrying and also a little note given to him by the clerk, and starts to run. After he has run for three miles, the performance is repeated. And I can assure you that by means of this service of unmounted couriers, the Great Khan receives news over a ten days' journey in a day and a night. For it takes these runners no more than a day and a night to cover a ten days' journey, or two days and two nights for a twenty days' journey. So in ten days they can transmit news over a journey of a hundred days. And in the fruit season it often happens that by this means fruit gathered in the morning in the city of Khan-balik is delivered on the evening of the next day to the Great Khan in the city of Shang-tu, ten days' journey away.

At each of these three-mile stations there is appointed a clerk who notes the day and hour of the arrival of every courier and the departure of his successor; and this practice is in force at every station. And there are also inspectors charged with the duty of going round every month and examining all these stations, in order to detect any couriers who have been remiss and punish them. From these couriers, and from the staff at the stations, the Great Khan exacts no tax, and he makes generous provision for their maintenance.

As for the horses of which I have spoken, which are kept in such numbers at the posts to carry the imperial messengers, I will tell you exactly how the Great Khan has established them. First he inquires, ‘Which is the nearest city to such-and-such a post?’; then, ‘How many horses can it maintain for the messengers?’ Then the civic authorities investigate by means of experts how many horses can be maintained in the neighbouring post by the city and how many by the local towns and villages, and they apportion them according to the resources available. The cities act in concert, taking into consideration that between one post and the next there is sometimes another city, which makes its contribution with the rest. They provide for the horses out of the taxes due to the Great Khan: thus, if a man is assessed for taxation at a sum that would maintain a horse and a half, he is ordered to make corresponding provision at the neighbouring post. But you must understand that the cities do not maintain 400 horses continuously at each post. Actually they keep 200 for a month, to sustain the burdens of the post, while the other 200 are fattening. At the end of the month the fattened horses are transferred to the post while the others take their turn at grass. So they alternate perpetually.

If it happens at any point that there is some river or lake over which the couriers and mounted messengers must pass, the neighbouring cities keep three or four ferry-boats continually in readiness for this purpose. And if there is a desert to cross of many days' journey in extent, in which no permanent habitation can be established, the city next to the desert is obliged to furnish horses to the Khan's envoys to see them across, together with provisions for their escort. But to such cities the Khan affords special aid. And in out-of-the-way posts the horses are maintained partly by the Khan himself, partly by the nearest cities, towns, and villages.

When the need arises for the Great Khan to receive immediate tidings by mounted messenger, as of the rebellion of a subject country or of one of his barons or any matter that may concern him deeply, I assure you that the messengers ride 200 miles in a day, sometimes even 240. Let me explain how it is done. When a messenger wishes to travel at this speed and cover so many miles in a day, he carries a tablet with the sign of the gerfalcon as a token that he wishes to ride post haste. If there are two of them, they set out from the place where they are on two good horses, strongly built and swift runners. They tighten their belts and swathe their heads and off they go with all the speed they can muster, till they reach the next post-house twenty-five miles away. As they draw near they sound a sort of horn which is audible at a great distance, so that horses may be got ready for them. On arrival they find two fresh horses, ready harnessed, fully rested, and in good running form. They mount there and then, without a moment's breathing-space, and are no sooner mounted than off they go again, taking the last ounce out of their horses and not pausing till they reach the next post, where they find two more horses harnessed as before. Then up and off again. And so it goes on till evening. That is how these messengers manage to cover 240 miles a day with news for the Great Khan. Indeed, in extreme urgency, they can achieve 300 miles. In such cases they ride all night long; and if there is no moon the men of the post run in front of them with torches as far as the next post. But they cannot ride as fast by night as by day, because they are delayed by the slower pace of the runners. Messengers who can endure the fatigue of such a ride as this are very highly prized.

Now let me tell you something of the bounties that the Great Khan confers upon his subjects. For all his thoughts are directed towards helping the people who are subject to him, so that they may live and labour and increase their wealth. You may take it for a fact that he sends emissaries and inspectors throughout all his dominions and kingdoms and provinces to learn whether any of his people have suffered a failure of their crops either through weather or through locusts or other pests. And if he finds that any have lost their harvest, he exempts them for that year from their tribute and even gives them some of his own grain to sow and to eat—a magnificent act of royal bounty. This he does in the summer. And in winter he does likewise in the matter of cattle. If he finds any man whose cattle have been killed by an outbreak of plague, he gives him some of his own, derived from the tithes of other provinces, and to help him further he relieves him of tribute for the year.

Again, if it should happen that lightning strikes any flock of sheep or herd of other beasts, whether the herd belongs to one person or more and no matter how big it may be, the Great Khan will not take tithe of it for three years. And similarly if it chances to strike a ship laden with merchandise, he will not have any due or share of the cargo, because he accounts it an ill omen when lightning strikes any man's possessions. He reasons: ‘God must have been angry with this man, since He launched a thunderbolt at him.’ Therefore he does not wish that such possessions, struck by the wrath of God, should find their way into his treasury.

Here is another benefit that he confers.

Along the main highways frequented by his messengers and by merchants and other folk, he has ordered trees to be planted on both sides, two paces distant from one another. They are so large that they can be seen from a long way off. And he has done this so that any wayfarer may recognize the roads and not lose his way. For you will find these wayside trees in the heart of the wilderness; and a great boon they are to travellers and traders. They extend throughout every province and every kingdom. Where the roads traverse sandy deserts or rocky mountain ranges, so that it is not possible to plant trees, he has other landmarks set up in the form of cairns or pillars to indicate the track. He has certain officials whose duty it is to ensure that these are always kept in order. Besides the reasons already mentioned, he is all the more willing to have these trees planted because his soothsayers and astrologers declare that he who causes trees to be planted lives long.

You must know that most of the inhabitants of the province of Cathay drink a wine such as I will describe to you. They make a drink of rice and an assortment of excellent spices, prepared in such a way that it is better to drink than any other wine. It is beautifully clear and it intoxicates more speedily than any other wine, because it is very heating.

Let me tell you next of stones that bum like logs. It is a fact that throughout the province of Cathay there is a sort of black stone, which is dug out of veins in the hillsides and burns like logs. These stones keep a fire going better than wood. I assure you that, if you put them on the fire in the evening and see that they are well alight, they will continue to burn all night, so that you will find them still glowing in the morning. They do not give off flames, except a little when they are first kindled, just as charcoal does, and once they have caught fire they give out great heat. And you must know that these stones are burnt throughout the province of Cathay. It is true that they also have plenty of firewood. But the population is so enormous and there are so many bath-houses and baths continually being heated, that the wood could not possibly suffice, since there is no one who does not go to a bath-house at least three times a week and take a bath, and in winter every day, if he can manage it. And every man of rank or means has his own bathroom in his house, where he takes a bath. So it is clear that there could never be enough wood to maintain such a conflagration. So these stones, being very plentiful and very cheap, effect a great saving of wood.

To return to the provision of grain, you may take it for a fact that the Great Khan, when he sees that the harvests are plentiful and corn is cheap, accumulates vast quantities of it and stores it in huge granaries, where it is so carefully preserved that it remains unspoilt for three or four years. So he builds up a stock of every sort of grain — wheat, barley, millet, rice, panic, and others — in great abundance. Then, when it happens that some crops fail and there is a dearth of grain, he draws on these stocks. If the price is running at a bezant for a measure of wheat, for instance, he supplies four measures for the same sum. And he releases enough for all, so that everyone has plenty of corn to meet his needs. In this way he sees to it that none of his subjects need ever go short. And this he does throughout all parts of his empire.

Let me now tell you how the Great Khan bestows charity on the poor people of Khan-balik. When he learns that some family of honest and respectable people have been impoverished by some misfortune or disabled from working by illness, so that they have no means of earning their daily bread, he sees to it that such families (which may consist of six to ten persons or more) are given enough to cover their expenses for the whole year. These families, at the time appointed, go to the officials whose task it is to superintend the Great Khan's expenditure and who live in a palatial building assigned to their office. And each one produces a certificate of the sum paid to him for his subsistence the year before, and provision is made for them at the same rate this year. This provision includes clothing inasmuch as the Great Khan receives a tithe of all the wool, silk, and hemp used for cloth-making. He has these materials woven into cloth in a specially appointed building in which they are stored. Since all the crafts are under obligation to devote one day a week to working on his behalf, he has this cloth made up into garments, which he gives to the poor families in accordance with their needs for winter and for summer wear. He also provides clothing for his armies by having woollen cloth woven in every city as a contribution towards the payment of its tithe.

You must understand that the Tartars according to their ancient customs, before they became familiar with the doctrines of the idolaters, never used to give any alms. Indeed, when a poor man came to them, they would drive him off with maledictions, saying: ‘Go with God's curse upon you! If he had loved you as he loves me, he would have blessed you with prosperity!’ But since the sages of the idolaters, in particular the Bakhshi of whom I have spoken above, preached to the Great Khan that it was a good work to provide for the poor and that their idols would be greatly pleased by it, he was induced to make such provision as I have described. No one who cares to go to his court in quest of bread is ever turned away empty-handed. Everyone receives a portion. And not a day passes but twenty or thirty thousand bowls of rice, millet, and panic are doled out and given away by the officials appointed. And this goes on all the year round. For this amazing and stupendous munificence which the Great Khan exercises towards the poor, all the people hold him in such esteem that they revere him as a god.

There are also in the city of Khan-balik, including Christians, Saracens, and Cathayans, about 4,000 astrologers and soothsayers, for whom the Great Khan makes yearly provision of food and clothing as he does for the poor. These regularly practice their art in the city. They have a sort of almanack in which are written the movements of the planets through the constellations, hour by hour and minute by minute, throughout the year. Every year these astrologers, Christian, Saracen, and Cathayan, each sect on its own account, examine in this almanack the course and disposition of the whole year and of each particular moon. For they search out and discover what sort of conditions each moon of the year will produce in accordance with the natural course and disposition of the planets and constellations and their special influences: in such-and-such a month there will be thunderstorms, in another earthquakes, in another lightning and heavy rain, in yet another deadly outbreaks of pestilence and wars and civil dissensions. And so month by month in accordance with their findings. And they will declare that so it should happen in harmony with the natural and orderly sequence of things, but God may send more or less. So they will make many little booklets in which they will set down everything that is due to happen in the course of the year, moon by moon. These booklets are called tacuim and are sold at a groat apiece to anyone who cares to buy, so that he may know what will happen throughout the year. And those who prove to be the most accurate in their predictions will be reckoned the most accomplished masters of their art and will gain the greatest honour.

If anyone proposes to embark on some important enterprise or to travel somewhere on a trading venture or on other business, or has in mind some other project whose outcome he would like to know, he will consult the astrologers, telling them the year, month, hour, and minute of his nativity. This he is able to do, because in accordance with their custom everyone is taught from birth what he must say about his nativity, and parents are careful to note the particulars in a book. They divide the years into cycles of twelve, each with its own sign: the first bears the sign of the lion, the second of the ox, the third of the dragon, the fourth of the dog, and so on up to twelve. So, when a man is asked when he was born, he answers ‘in a year of the lion, on such-and-such a day or night, hour, and minute of such-and-such a moon’, according as the time and the year-sign may have been. When they have completed the cycle of twelve years, they begin again at the first sign and repeat the series, always in the same order. So, when anyone asks an astrologer or soothsayer how his proposed venture will turn out and tells him the hour and minute of his nativity and the sign of the year, then the soothsayer, having ascertained under which constellation and which planet he was born, will predict in due sequence all that is to happen to him on his travels and what fortune, good or bad, will attend his undertaking. Likewise, the inquirer may be warned, if he is a merchant, that the planet then in the ascendant will be hostile to his venture, so that he should await the ascendancy of one more favourable; or that the constellation directly facing the gate by which he is planning to leave the city will be adverse to the one under which he was born, so that he should leave by another gate or wait till the constellation has moved past; or that in such a place and on such a date he will encounter robbers, in another he will be assailed by rain and storm, in another his horse will break a leg, here his trafficking will involve him in loss, there it will bring in a profit. So the soothsayer will foretell the vicissitudes of his journey, propitious or disastrous, according to the sequence of favourable or unfavourable constellations.

As I have already said, the people of Cathay are all idolaters. Every man has in his house an image hanging on his chamber wall which represents the High God of Heaven, or at least a tablet on which the name of God is written. And every day they cense this with a thurible and worship it with uplifted hands, gnashing their teeth three times and praying that the god will give them a long and happy life, good health, and a sound understanding. From him they ask nothing else. But down below on the ground they have another image representing Natigai, the god of earthly things, who guides the course of all that is born on earth. They make him with a wife and children and worship him in the same way, with incense and gnashing of teeth and uplifted hands; and to him they pray for good weather and harvests and children and the like.

They surpass other nations in the excellence of their manners and their knowledge of many subjects, since they devote much time to their study and to the acquisition of knowledge. They speak in an agreeable and orderly manner, greet one another courteously with bright and cheerful faces, are dignified in their demeanour, cleanly at table, and so forth. But they have no regard for the welfare of their souls, caring only for the nurture of their bodies and for their own happiness. Concerning the soul, they believe indeed that it is immortal, but in this fashion. They hold that as soon as a man is dead he enters into another body; and according as he has conducted himself well or ill in life, he passes from good to better or from bad to worse. That is to say, if he is a man of humble rank and has behaved well and virtuously in life, he will be reborn after death from a gentlewoman and will be a gentleman, and thereafter from the womb of a noblewoman and will become a nobleman; and so he follows an ever upward path culminating in assumption into the Deity. But, if he is a man of good birth and has behaved badly, he will be reborn as the son of a peasant; from a peasant's life he will pass to a dog's and so continually downwards.

They treat their father and mother with profound respect. If it should happen that a child does anything to displease his parents or fails to remember them in their need, there is a department of state whose sole function it is to impose severe penalties on those who are found guilty of such ingratitude.

Perpetrators of various crimes who are caught and put in prison, if they have not been set free at the time appointed by the Great Khan for the release of prisoners, which recurs every three years, are then let out; but they are branded on the jaw, so that they may be recognized.

The present Khan prohibited all the gambling and cheating that used to be more prevalent among them than anywhere else in the world. To cure them of the habit he would say: ‘I have acquired you by force of arms and all that you possess is mine. So, if you gamble, you are gambling with my property.’ He did not, however, make this a pretext to take anything from them.

I will not omit to tell you about the behaviour of the Khan's people and noblemen when they come into his presence. First, all those who are within half a mile from the Great Khan, wherever he may be, show their reverence for his majesty by conducting themselves deferentially, peaceably, and quietly so that no hub-bub or uproar may be heard, nor the voice of anyone shouting or talking loudly. Next, every baron or nobleman continually carries with him a little vessel of pleasing design into which he spits so long as he is in the hall, so that no one may make so bold as to spit on the floor; and when he has spat he covers it up and keeps it. Likewise they have handsome slippers of white leather, which they carry about with them. When they have come to court, if they are about to enter the hall at the Lord's invitation, they put on these white slippers and hand their others to the attendants, so as not to dirty the beautiful and elaborate carpets of silk, wrought in gold and other colours.

注释

[1]The titles Ch'ien-hu and Wan-hu mean respectively commander of 1,000 and of 10,000.

From Peking to Bengal

Let us now leave the city of Khan-balik and travel into Cathay, so that you may learn something of its grandeurs and its treasures.

You must understand that Messer Marco himself was sent by the Great Khan as an emissary towards the west, on a journey of fully four months from Khan-balik. So we will tell you what he saw on the way, going and coming.

[...]

On leaving Ch'êng-tu-fu the traveller rides for five days through plain and valley, passing villages and hamlets in plenty. The people here live on the yield of the earth. The country is infested with lions, bears, and other wild beasts. There is some local industry, in the weaving of fine sendal and other fabrics. This country is part of Ch'êng-tu-fu province. But at the end of the five days the route enters another province whose name is Tibet.[1]

The province of Tibet is terribly devastated, for it was ravaged in a campaign by Mongu Khan. There are many towns and villages and hamlets lying ruined and desolate.

This country produces canes of immense size and girth; indeed I can assure you that they grow to about three palms in circumference and a good fifteen paces in length, the distance from one knot to the next amounting to fully three palms. Merchants and other travellers who are passing through this country at night use these canes as fuel because, when they are alight, they make such a popping and banging that lions and bears and other beasts of prey are scared away in terror and dare not on any account come near the fire. So fires of this sort are made by travellers to protect their own animals from the savage predators with which the country is infested. Let me tell you — or it is well worth telling — how it happens that the crackling of these canes is so loud and terrifying and what effect it produces. You must understand that the canes are taken when quite green and thrown on a fire made of a substantial pile of logs. When they have lain for some time on a fire of this size, they begin to warp and to burst, and then they make such a bang that it can be heard at nights fully ten miles away. Anyone who is not accustomed to the noise is startled out of his wits by it; it is such a terrifying sound to hear. I assure you that horses that have never heard it before are so scared when they hear it that they snap their halters and all the cords that tether them and take to their heels. Many travellers have experienced this. So, when they have horses that are known never to have heard this noise, they bandage their eyes and shackle all the feet with iron fetlocks. Then, when they hear the crackling of the canes, however hard they try to bolt, they cannot do it. And by this means travellers keep safe at nights; both they and their beasts, from the lions and ounces and other dangerous beasts that abound in these parts.

This desolate country, infested by dangerous wild beasts, extends for twenty days' journey, without shelter or food except perhaps every third or fourth day, when the traveller may find some habitation where he can renew his stock of provisions. Then he reaches a region with villages and hamlets in plenty and a few towns perched on precipitous crags. Here there prevails a marriage custom of which I will tell you. It is such that no man would ever on any account take a virgin to wife. For they say that a woman is worthless unless she has had knowledge of many men. They argue that she must have displeased the gods, because if she enjoyed the favour of their idols then men would desire her and consort with her. So they deal with their womenfolk in this way. When it happens that men from a foreign land are passing through this country and have pitched their tents and made a camp, the matrons from neighbouring villages and hamlets bring their daughters to these camps, to the number of twenty or forty, and beg the travellers to take them and lie with them. So these choose the girls who please them best, and the others return home disconsolate. So long as they remain, the visitors are free to take their pleasure with the women and use them as they will, but they are not allowed to carry them off anywhere else. When the men have worked their will and are ready to be gone, then it is the custom for every man to give to the woman with whom he has lain some trinket or token so that she can show, when she comes to marry, that she has had a lover. In this way custom requires every girl to wear more than a score of such tokens hung round her neck to show that she has had lovers in plenty and plenty of men have lain with her. And she who has most tokens and can show that she has had most lovers and that most men have lain with her is the most highly esteemed and the most acceptable as a wife; for they say that she is the most favoured by the gods. And when they have taken a wife in this way they prize her highly; and they account it a grave offence for any man to touch another's wife, and they all strictly abstain from such an act. So much, then, for this marriage custom, which fully merits a description. Obviously the country is a fine one to visit for a lad from sixteen to twenty-four.

The natives are idolaters and out-and-out bad. They deem it no sin to rob and maltreat and are the greatest rogues and the greatest robbers in the world. They live by the chase and by their herds and the fruits of the earth. The country abounds with animals that produce musk, which in their language are called gudderi. They are so plentiful that you can smell musk everywhere. I have already explained that a sac in the form of a tumour and filled with blood grows next to the beast's navel, and this blood is musk. But I must add that once in every moon the sac becomes overcharged with blood and discharges its contents. So it happens, since these animals are very plentiful here, that they discharge their musk in many places, so that the whole country is pervaded with the scent. The rascally natives have many excellent dogs, who catch great numbers of these animals; so they have no lack of musk.

The natives have no coinage and do not use the Khan's paper currency; but for money they use salt. They are very poorly clad, in skins, canvas, and buckram. They speak a language of their own and call themselves ‘Tibet’.

This province of Tibet is of immense size and lies on the confines of Manzi and many other provinces. The natives are idolaters and notorious brigands. The province is so huge that it contains eight kingdoms and a great many cities and towns. In many places there are rivers and lakes and mountains, in which gold-dust is found in great quantity. There is also great abundance of cinnamon. In this province coral fetches a high price, for it is hung round the necks of women and of idols with great joy. The province produces plenty of camlets and other cloths of gold, silk, and fustian, and many sorts of spice that were never seen in our country. Here are to be found the most skilful enchanters and the best astrologers according to their usage that exist in any of the regions hereabouts. Among other wonders they bring on tempests and thunder-storms when they wish and stop them at any time. They perform the most potent enchantments and the greatest marvels to hear and to behold by diabolic arts, which it is better not to relate in our book, or men might marvel over-much. Their customs are disagreeable. They have mastiffs as big as donkeys, very good at pulling down game, including wild cattle, which are plentiful there and of great size and ferocity. They also have a great variety of other hunting dogs, besides excellent lanner and saker falcons, good fliers and apt for hawking. Before leaving Tibet, of which we have now given a full account, let me make it clear that it belongs to the Great Khan, as do all the other kingdoms and provinces and regions described in this book, except only the provinces mentioned at the beginning of our book which belong to the son of Arghun, as I have told you. So you may understand from this, without further indication, that with this exception the provinces described in this book are all subject to the Great Khan.

We will tell you next of the province of Kaindu, which lies towards the west. It has only one king. The people are idolaters and subject to the Great Khan. It has cities and towns in plenty. The chief city, also called Kaindu, lies near the entrance to the province. There is also a lake in which are found many pearls — pure white but not round, being rather knobbly as though four, five, six, or more were joined together. The Great Khan will not let anyone take them; for if all the pearls that were found there were taken out, so many would be taken that they would be cheap and lose their value. So the Great Khan, when he has a mind, has pearls taken from it for his own use only; but no one else may take them on pain of death. There is also a mountain there in which is found a sort of stone called turquoise. These are very fine gems and very plentiful. But the Great Khan does not allow them to be taken except at his bidding.

Let me tell you that in this province there prevails a usage concerning women such as I will describe to you. A man does not think it an outrage if a stranger or some other man makes free with his wife or daughter or sister or any woman he may have in his house. But it is taken as a favour when anyone lies with them. For they say that by this act their gods and idols are propitiated, so as to enrich them with temporal blessings in great abundance. And for that reason they deal with their wives in the following open-handed fashion. You must know that when a man of this country sees that a stranger is coming to his house to lodge, or that he is entering his house without intending to lodge, he immediately walks out, telling his wife to let the stranger have his will without reservation. Then he goes his way to his fields or vineyards and does not return so long as the stranger remains in his house. And I assure you that he often stays three days and lies in bed with this wittol's wife. And as a sign that he is in the house he hangs out his cap or some other token. This is an indication that he is within. And the wretched wittol, so long as he sees this sign in his house, does not return. This usage prevails throughout the province. The Great Khan has forbidden it; but they continue to observe it nonetheless, since, as they are all addicted to it, there is no one to accuse another. There are some residents in the villages and homesteads perched on crags by the wayside who have beautiful wives and offer them freely to passing traders, And the traders give the women a piece of some fine cloth, perhaps a yard or so, or some other trinket of trifling value. Having taken his pleasure for a while, the trader mounts his horse and rides away. Then the husband and wife call after him in mockery; ‘Hi, you there — you that are riding off! Show us what you are taking with you that is ours! Let us see, ne'er-do-well, what profit you have made! Look at what you have left to us — what you have thrown away and forgotten.’ And he flourishes the cloth they have gained from him. ‘We have got this of yours, you poor fool, and you have nothing to show for it!’ So they mock at him. And so they continue to act.

Let me tell you next about their money. They have gold in bars and weigh it out by saggi; and it is valued according to its weight. But they have no coined money bearing a stamp. For small change they do as follows. They have salt water from which they make salt by boiling it in pans. When they have boiled it for an hour, they let it solidify in moulds, forming blocks of the size of a twopenny loaf, flat below and rounded on top. When the blocks are ready, they are laid on heated-stones beside the fire to dry and harden. On these blocks they set the Great Khan's stamp. And currency of this sort is made only by his agents. Eighty of these blocks are worth a saggio of gold. But traders come with these blocks to the people who live among the mountains in wild and out-of-the-way places and receive a saggio of gold for sixty, fifty, or forty blocks, according as the place is more isolated and cut off from cities and civilized people. Here the natives cannot dispose of their gold and other wares, such as musk, for want of purchasers. So they sell their gold cheap, because they find it in rivers and lakes as you have heard. These traders travel all over the highlands of Tibet, where the salt money is also current. They make an immense profit, because these people use this salt in food as well as for buying the necessities of life; but in the cities they almost invariably use fragments of the blocks for food and spend the unbroken blocks.

There are vast numbers here of the beasts that produce musk, and hunters catch them and take great quantities of the musk. There are plenty of good fish, which are caught in the same lake that produces the pearls. There are also lions, lynxes, bears, stags, and roebuck in plenty, and birds of every sort abound. There is no grape wine, but wine is made of wheat and rice with many spices, and a very good drink it is. The province is also a great source of cloves, which grow on a little tree with leaves like laurel but slightly longer and narrower, and little white flowers like clove-pinks. There is also ginger in abundance and cinnamon, not to speak of spices that never come to our country.

When the traveller leaves the city of Kaindu, he rides for ten days through a country not lacking in towns and villages, and well stocked with game, both bird and beast. The people have the same manners and customs as those I have described. At the end of these ten days he reaches a great river called Brius, which is the farther boundary of the province of Kaindu. In it are found great quantities of gold dust. The district is also rich in cinnamon. This river runs into the Ocean.

On the farther side of the river Brius lies Kara-jang, a province of such size that it contains no less than seven kingdoms. It lies towards the west, and the inhabitants are idolaters and subject to the Great Khan. Its king is his son, whose name is Essen-Temur, a very great king and rich and powerful. He rules his land well and justly; for he is a wise and upright man.

After leaving the river, the traveller continues westwards for five days, through a country with numerous cities and towns which breeds excellent horses. The people live by rearing animals and tilling the soil. They speak a language of their own, which is very difficult to understand. At the end of the five days he reaches the capital of the kingdom, which is called Yachi, a large and splendid city. Here there are traders and craftsmen in plenty. The inhabitants are of several sorts: there are some who worship Mahomet, some idolater, and a few Nestorian Christians. Both wheat and rice are plentiful; but wheat bread is not eaten because in this province it is unwholesome. The natives eat rice, and also make it into a drink with spices, which is very fine and clear and makes a man drunk like wine. For money they use white cowries, i.e. the sea-shells that are used to make necklaces for dogs: 80 cowries are equivalent to 1 saggio of silver, which is worth 2 Venetian groats, and 8 saggi of fine silver may be taken to equal 1 of fine gold. They also have brine wells, from which they make salt that is used for food by all the inhabitants of the country. And I assure you that the king derives great profit from this salt. The men here do not mind if one touches another's wife, so long as it is with her consent.

Before leaving this kingdom let me tell you something which I had forgotten. There is a lake here, some 100 miles in circumference, in which there is a vast quantity of fish, the best in the world. They are of great size and of all kinds. The natives eat flesh raw — poultry, mutton, beef, and buffalo meat. The poorer sort go to the shambles and take the raw liver as soon as it is drawn from the beasts; then they chop it small, put it in garlic sauce and eat it there and then. And they do likewise with every other kind of flesh. The gentry also eat their meat raw; but they have it minced very small, put it in garlic sauce flavoured with spices and then eat it as readily as we eat cooked meat.

On leaving Yachi and continuing westwards for ten days, the traveller reaches the kingdom of Kara-jang, the capital of which is also called Kara-jang. The people are idolaters and subject to the Great Khan. The king is Hukaji, a son of the Great Khan. In this province gold dust is found in the rivers, and gold in bigger nuggets in the lakes and mountains. They have so much of it that they give a saggio of gold for six of silver. Here too the cowries of which I have spoken are used for money. They are not found in this province, but come here from India.

In this province live huge snakes and serpents[2] of such a size that no one could help being amazed even to hear of them. They are loathsome creatures to behold. Let me tell you just how big they are. You may take it for a fact that there are some of them ten paces in length that are as thick as a stout cask: for their girth runs to about ten palms. These are the biggest. They have two squat legs in front near the head, which have no feet but simply three claws, two small and one bigger, like the claws of a falcon or a lion. They have enormous heads and eyes so bulging that they are bigger than loaves. Their mouth is big enough to swallow a man at one gulp. Their teeth are huge. All in all, the monsters are of such inordinate bulk and ferocity that there is neither man nor beast but goes in fear of them. There are also smaller ones, not exceeding eight paces in length, or six or it may be five.

Let me tell you now how these monsters are trapped. You must know that by day they remain underground because of the great heat; at nightfall, they sally out to hunt and feed and seize whatever prey they can come by. They go down to drink at streams and lakes and springs. They are so bulky and heavy and of such a girth that when they pass through sand on their nightly search for food or drink they scoop out a furrow through the sand that looks as if a butt full of wine had been rolled that way. Now the hunters who set out to catch them lay traps at various places in the trails that show which way the snakes are accustomed to go down the banks into the water. These are made by embedding in the earth a stout wooden stake to which is fixed a sharp steel tip like a razor-blade or lance-head, projecting about a palm's breadth beyond the stake and slanting in the direction from which the serpents approach. This is covered with sand, so that nothing of the stake is visible. Traps of this sort are laid in great numbers. When the snake, or rather the serpent, comes down the trail to drink, he runs full-tilt into the steel, so that it pierces his chest and rips his belly right to the navel and he dies on the spot. The hunter knows that the serpent is dead by the cry of the birds, and then he ventures to approach his prey. Otherwise he dare not draw near.

When hunters have trapped a serpent by this means, they draw out the gall from the belly and sell it for a high price, for you must know that it makes a potent medicine. If a man is bitten by a mad dog, he is given a drop of it to drink — the weight of a halfpenny — and he is cured forthwith. And when a woman is in labour and cries aloud with the pangs of travail, she is given a drop of the serpent's gall and as soon as she has drunk it she is delivered of her child forthwith. Its third use is when someone is afflicted by any sort of growth: he puts a drop of this gall on it and is cured in a day or two. For these reasons the gall of this serpent is highly prized in these provinces. The flesh also commands a good price, because it is very good to eat and is esteemed as a delicacy.

Another thing about these serpents: they go to the dens where lions and bears and other beasts of prey have their cubs and gobble them up — parents as well as young — if they can get at them.

Let me tell you further that this province produces a sturdy breed of horses, which are exported when young for sale in India. And you must know that it is the custom to remove two or three joints of the tail-bone, so that the horse cannot flick the rider with its tail or swish it when galloping; for it is reckoned unsightly for a horse to gallop with swishing tail. The horsemen here ride with long stirrups after the French fashion — long, that is, in contrast to the short stirrups favoured by the Tartars and most other races who go in for archery, since they use their stirrups for standing upright when they shoot.

For armour they wear cuirasses of buffalo hide. They carry lances and shields. They also use crossbows, with all the quarrels dipped in poison. All the natives, women as well as men, especially those who are bent on evil courses, carry poison about with them. If it should chance that anyone is caught after committing a crime for which he is liable to suffer torture, rather than face the penalty of the scourge, he puts the poison in his mouth and swallows it, so as to die as quickly as possible. But, since the authorities are well aware of this trick, they always have some dog's dung handy, so that if a prisoner swallows poison for this purpose he is immediately made to swallow the dung and so vomit up the poison. Such is the remedy they have found for this practice, and it is a well-tried one. Another practice of theirs, before they were conquered by the Great Khan, was this. If it happened that a gentleman of quality, with a fine figure, or a ‘good shadow’, came to lodge in the house of a native of this province, they would murder him in the night, by poison or other means, so that he died. You must not suppose that they did this in order to rob him; they did it rather because they believed that his ‘good shadow’ and the good grace with which he was blessed and his intelligence and soul would remain in the house. In this way many met their deaths before the conquest. Since then — that is, during the last thirty-five years or so — they have abandoned this evil practice for fear of the Great Khan, who has strictly forbidden it.

注释

[1]Polo's account of ‘Tebet’ applies primarily to districts now included in the provinces of Sze-ch'wan and Yün-nan to the east of the present Tibetan frontier.

[2]Evidently crocodiles.

译者导读

普鲁塔克（Plutarch，约46—120），罗马帝国时代的希腊作家，出身于希腊中部波奥提亚地区喀罗尼亚城（Chaeronea）一个有文化教养的家庭，其父亚里斯托布鲁斯（Aristobulus）是一位传记作家和哲学家。普鲁塔克幼承庭训，养成了对知识的爱好。青年时期游学雅典，曾受业于名师阿谟尼乌斯（Ammonius），受过数学、哲学、修辞学、历史学以及医学等方面的训练。普鲁塔克还曾遍游希腊各地，到过爱琴海诸岛，访问过埃及、小亚细亚、意大利。所到之处，他都极为留心搜集当地的历史资料和口碑传说，从而成为一名饱学之士。后来，他来到罗马讲学，研究罗马的历史，同时结识了许多名人。普鲁塔克一生经历了罗马帝国前期的3个王朝—尤利乌斯·克劳狄王朝、弗拉维王朝和安敦尼王朝。据说，他曾经为帝国的两个皇帝—图拉真和哈德良讲过课，并博得了他们的赏识，图拉真曾授予他执政官的高位，后来哈德良又提拔他担任希腊财政督察。普鲁塔克的作品在文艺复兴时期大受欢迎，蒙田对他推崇备至，莎士比亚不少剧作都取材于他的记载。

“普鲁塔克”这个名字在西方已经远远超出学院的门墙，它几乎成为一个文化符号，一种时代精神的代表，一种政治文化的象征。《慰妻书》是普鲁塔克在4岁女儿夭折后，写给他的妻子提摩泽娜的安慰信。文如其人，这段感人的文字让我们感受到其孝涕友爱的立身之道，非常真实地展示了其温良而敦厚、和善而豁达、恬静而不慕虚荣的性格。在书中，普鲁塔克用了很多看似平常的道理安慰妻子，让我们感同身受般地体会其在悲痛中的坚守与克制，同时也为我们描述了关于道德与情感、嫉妒与憎恨、悲伤与欢乐的深意看法。他对人生、社会乃至宇宙的认知，都那么充满智慧，让人有醍醐灌顶的感觉，读时一边会意微笑，一边不禁沉思，这么朴素的道理应该是生活中最基本的东西，却被我们在不经意间遗失了。在一个物质极度膨胀的现代世界里，留给我们思考的空间太小，最本真的人性也似乎只能在物质的缝隙间苟且偷生！

书中，普鲁塔克与提摩泽娜夫妻相爱甚笃、和睦美满的家庭生活跃然纸上，我们可以读出两人携手共渡难关、相互扶持、风雨同行的恩爱。文字的描述成为触碰你我灵魂的精华，在如今这个浮躁的商业社会里，读一点普鲁塔克的文章，培养一点人文精神吧！不需大段时间，抽空浅斟慢饮，细细品啜，犹如炎热夏日，饮一杯碧绿的龙井，真的让人感觉舒爽。

慰妻书

希望你收到此信时，一切安好。你派来向我通报孩子不幸夭折的人，可能在他去雅典的路上与我错过了。我到达塔纳格拉时，从孙女那儿听闻了这一噩耗。我想，现在葬礼已经结束了吧。希望这次葬礼过后，无论是现在还是将来，你不再有任何悲伤。如果因为你想听听我的意见，还有什么事情你想做却还没做，而你认为做完这件事就不会那么难过了，那就去做吧。切记不要大张旗鼓，也不要陷入那些迷信的无稽之谈。我想你应该不会犯这样的错误吧。

亲爱的，我唯一的要求就是，在悲伤的同时，我们两个人，我，还有你，都要懂得节哀。我的意思是，不幸已然发生，我们要悲伤有度。如果我发觉你过度悲伤，那将比失去女儿更令我不安。你知道，我并非铁石心肠。我们一起养育了这么多孩子，他们都是在自己家里长大的，没有要任何人帮忙。我了解，继4个儿子之后，你诞下渴望已久的女儿是多么欣喜。因为她，我才有机会以你的名字给孩子命名，而且，父母对这个年纪的孩子尤其疼爱有加。这种爱带来的快乐很单纯，没有一丝一毫的愤怒和苛求。女儿生性温顺而随和，懂得感情回报，她是那么惹人喜爱，不仅带给我们快乐，也让我们看到了她的善良和无私。她总是让乳母把乳汁喂给其他的孩子，甚至是那些她最喜爱的玩具，她无私地要把她拥有的美好事物以及她最喜爱的东西与她最喜爱的人分享，待他们犹如上宾。

亲爱的，她有生之年带给我们这些快乐的点点滴滴，如今回忆起来，我找不出任何理由为之难过和悲伤。反之，我担心的是，我们可能因为要躲避悲伤而遗忘对她的记忆。如此，便会变得像克里谟奈一样。她曾说：“我讨厌山茱萸木制的弯弓！我宁愿世上没有体育馆！”她总是害怕忆起儿子，并且避免这样做。因为与回忆相伴的是痛楚，所以人会本能地逃避。不，我们的女儿是这世上最可爱，最令人想拥抱、注视和聆听的孩子。正因为如此，我们一定要让她长驻心间，她带给我们的快乐远远超过悲伤。我们通常劝慰别人的那些话，在我们困难之际也能适时地帮助我们自己。我们不能沮丧消沉，自我封闭，用数倍的忧伤来抵消那些欢乐。

那些参加葬礼的人有些吃惊，他们说你连丧服都没有穿，你和侍女们并没有遵从陈规陋习。你衣着得体，葬礼也没有奢华的排场，一切从简，静默肃穆。对此我并不以为奇。你去看戏或参加公众游行时也从不打扮，你认为奢侈无益，铺张亦无乐趣可言。因此，你在伤痛之时坚持自然和简朴。

关键在于，体面的妇女不仅应该在酒神节的狂欢中保持纯洁不堕落，而且应该在悲痛中认识到，需要克制悲痛带来的情绪不稳和困扰。这种自我克制不是常人所想的那样对情和爱的压抑，而是对心的宽容。思念、崇敬和怀念已故之人是人之常情，但是无尽的悲痛让我们恸哭、哀号，这就和放纵的享乐主义一样可鄙，尽管情有可原。虽然可鄙，但随之而来的并非快乐，而是更多的悲伤和痛苦。摒弃过度的纵情欢笑，却允许源自同一理由的痛哭流涕，或者像某些丈夫们一样，因为妻子抹着奢侈的头发香水、穿着俗丽的衣服而与她们争吵，却在她们哀悼时剪去头发、染黑衣服、坐姿难看或以不舒服的姿势斜靠在桌旁时表示服从，还有什么比这更荒谬的呢？最恼人的是，他们抗拒和阻止妻子过分而不公平地惩罚仆人，却忽视了当她们受到情感和不幸的影响时所遭受的恶毒、严厉的惩罚，实际上此时更需要的是轻松和宽容的心态。

亲爱的，我们之间已非常默契，从来没有为一点小事而争吵，而且我想我们永远也不会为此而争吵。一方面，与我们相处过、了解我们的每位哲学家无不对你朴素的穿着打扮和谦逊的生活方式印象深刻，我们每一个同胞都见证了你在宗教仪式、祭祀典礼和剧场观演时的自然淳朴；另一方面，之前在你失去长子、我们可爱的卡龙又过早地离开我们时，你的表现足以证明，你可以在这种情况下保持镇定。我记得，当孩子夭折的噩耗传来时，我带着来访者从海上归来，他们还有其他人聚集在我们家。他们后来告诉别人，看到我们家如此平静安宁，还以为并没有什么可怕的事情发生，不过是传出了毫无根据的谣言罢了。通常在这样的时刻，一片混乱也是情有可原的，而你仍然负责任地把家里安排得井然有序。你亲自给孩子哺乳，乳头发炎后还做了手术。这都是出于母爱的高尚之举。

值得注意的是，大多数母亲是等别人把孩子清洗干净、打扮漂亮之后再把他们抱在怀里。她们把孩子当作是玩物。如果孩子夭折，这些母亲们就会沉湎于空洞、虚伪的悲痛之中。这种悲痛并非出自合理而可敬的热烈情感：她们对肤浅的信仰有着强烈的倾向，再加上一点儿本能的情绪，于是乎悲痛猛然爆发，不但激烈、狂躁，而且难以自抑。伊索显然意识到了这一点：他说，当宙斯在众神之间分配赞誉时，“悲伤之神”也请求得到一份；于是宙斯应允了他—但这份赞誉只能来自那些有心想要给予悲伤之神以荣誉的人。

起初，确实如此：悲伤入侵的只是一个个体；然而一段时间之后，它便成为一个永久的姊妹，一种习惯性的存在，无论如何也挥之不去。这就是为何我们在一开始就要将它拒之门外的原因，不要为之挑选特别的着装、打理特别的发型或是做其他诸如此类的事情，以免它在我们心中驻扎生根，日复一日地折磨、贬低、束缚和封闭我们的心灵，使我们变得无动于衷或忧心忡忡，就好像为了表现悲痛而挑选的服装和作出的事情将我们与欢笑、光明以及聚餐等社交行为隔绝开来。这种痛苦的状态让人忽视身体，厌恶给身体涂油、洗澡和其他日常养生。情况本该相反，应保持健康的身体，这样才有助于缓解纯粹的精神痛苦。身体安定，心灵悲痛便会大大减轻、平息和消散，犹如天气晴朗时，波浪会平息。如果生活规则紊乱，导致身体变得肮脏污秽，对心灵没有任何良性的影响或是益处，带来的只有切肤而难忍的悲伤和痛苦，即使渴望恢复的人也会发现难以达成。心灵受到如此虐待，便会深陷于种种障碍和不适之中。

不过，我没有理由担心会出现最严重的、最令人担忧的失常情形—“恶女入侵”，她们悲痛的哀号和表现使悲痛更加深刻和厚重，从而无法随着外部因素影响而减退或自然消散。我能体会你最近的痛苦挣扎，你去帮助席恩的姐妹，抵抗妇女们的恸哭哀号—这一行为无异于以火攻火。我的意思是，当人们看到朋友的房子着火时，他们会努力尽快扑灭火焰；但是当看到这个朋友的心灵燃起火焰时，人们却会火上加油！有人眼部受到感染时，不会同意任何人去触碰它，也不去治疗炎症，但伤心人却会坐下来，让每个过路人刺探自己的伤痛（可以这么说），从而使情况变得更糟。这就好比一个本来微不足道的发痒的痛处，爆发成为真正难耐的痛苦折磨。无论如何，我相信，你对此会有所防范的。

你一定要时常试着把自己的思绪带回到女儿出生以前，那时的我们没有理由抱怨命运，然后将此时与彼时联系起来，想象我们现在的境况与原先没有不同。你瞧，亲爱的，如果我们发现和女儿出生前相比，现在要抱怨的事情更多，说不定会后悔生了女儿。我们不应将这两年的记忆抹去，因为它带给了我们幸福和快乐，我们应该把它视为快乐的缘由。美好的事物总是短暂的，但不应因而把它看作是长期的不良影响：我们不应该因为命运不再施与我们更多的希望，就对我们曾经拥有的毫不领情。

关键在于，对诸神要态度虔诚，对他人要宽厚仁慈，对命运要心平气和，只有这样才能始终收获美好而愉悦的报偿。任何人如果处于我们这种境地，都会特别注意突出对美好事物的记忆，不去思忖生活的黑暗面和尘世纷扰，而是多想想光明的未来和璀璨的生活，他们要么完全摒弃任何带来痛苦的事物，要么将悲痛与欢乐融为一体，这样至少可以减轻和掩饰痛苦。正如香水，闻起来清香怡人，但也可以用来消除难闻的气味；同样，将美好的事物铭记于心能使我们在苦难的时候得到必要的支持，对于那些不惧怕回忆美好时光、不怨天尤人的人，这就好比一剂良方。我们应当尽量避免这样一种情况—抱怨综合征。生活就像一本书，尽管其他页面干干净净，但有一个污迹，有人仍会对此百般挑剔。我想说的是，你常常听人说，幸福是为了达到一种稳定状态而正确使用理性思维的结果，偶然的变故可能使人偏离方向，但并不构成人生大逆转，也并不意味着人生大厦的坍塌和毁灭。

假如我们也要遵从惯例，被外在环境所左右，对命运的安排耿耿于怀，在意他人评判我们是否幸福：即便如此，你也不应该老想着当前那些吊唁者的哭泣和哀悼，这不过是毫无意义的社会风俗促使他们每每在这种情况下如此表现而已。最好是牢牢记住，你的孩子、家庭和生活方式在别人眼里依然是令人羡慕的。只要有人乐于选择你这样的命运，甚至包括我们目前的悲伤，你就不该因为遭受这样的命运而抱怨连连，反而应该从痛苦的根源出发，认识到我们应该为仍然拥有的一切而心怀感激。若非如此，你就会像那些从荷马的作品中摘取无头无尾的句子，却忽视许多精彩绝伦的篇章的人那样：对生活中的缺点吹毛求疵、抱怨不止，对优点却含糊其辞、一掠而过，这样一来，你的表现与那些贪婪吝啬的人并无二致，囤积了大量财富却不充分利用，一旦失去却又唉声叹气、抱怨连天。

如果你为女儿未曾结婚生子就已离开人世而感到惋惜，那么你还是可以找到其他的理由振作起来，因为你已然了解和经历过这两件事。我的意思是，对于未经历过结婚生子的人来说，结婚生子也就那么回事，而对已经历过结婚生子的人来说，那可是人生中意义重大的事情，所以幸福与否并不取决于是否经历过这些事。事实上，女儿已经步入一个没有痛苦的世界，我们不必为之悲伤。既然已经没有什么能够令她痛苦了，我们又为何要因她的离世而伤心呢？如果某样事物到了无人需要的地步，那么对它再大的损失也都不会引起痛苦了；更何况你的提谟克塞娜承受的损失甚少，因为她所熟知和觉得有趣的东西并不是什么重要的事物，至于她所不知道的、从未进入她脑海或吸引她的东西—又怎能说她已经失去它们了呢？

再者，你还听到一种人们普遍接受的说法，即那些已经消散的东西，不可能会遭受灾难或承受痛苦。我知道，我们祖先的教导，以及我们所参加的酒神节仪式的神秘规则（我们大家都了解的东西）让你不敢相信这种说法。既然灵魂是不朽的，你可以将它所发生的一切与笼中鸟的行为作个比较：灵魂长期居于肉体之中，由于诸多的重大事件和长期的熟悉，已经习惯了这样一种生活方式，于是每次重生后依然栖息在肉体里，一而再地经历人间的悲喜祸福。不要认为晚年是因为满脸皱纹、白发苍苍和体力不支而遭人责骂：不，它最残酷的特征是，人到晚年，灵魂不再能鲜明地记忆另一个世界，却又让它和这个世界保持联系，被这个世界包围和束缚，它保持着身体给予它的形状，同时受到它的约束。那些在被捕获后只在肉体中停留片刻便被神释放的灵魂，好像又弹回其自然状态，虽然它已经被弯曲，但它依然保持其柔韧性和延展性。就像火一样，如果在熄灭之后立即点燃，它很快就重新燃起；但是熄灭的时间越长，被点燃的难度越大。因此，用诗人的话说，那些最幸运的灵魂，能够在对这个世界许多事物产生强烈的喜爱和受到如同化学品作用一般地软化、溶解并与身体合而为一之前，“轻快地通过阴间的大门”。

我们可以从远古祖先的风俗与规则中更好地看到这些事物的真相。人们不为夭折的婴儿举行祭酒仪式，也不为他们举行其他的仪式，因为这些婴儿尚未经历尘世和世俗之事。人们不在他们的葬礼上或墓穴边流连，也不为修筑死者的安身之所而拖延时间，因为法律规定禁止对在那个年龄死亡的人这样做。为即将进入一个更加美好世界的人哀悼，会被认为是亵渎神灵。既然怀疑这一点比相信这一点更加困难，那就让我们的外在行为遵守禁令，并保持内心世界不被玷污，比外在行为更纯洁、更自制。

认识德行的进步

苏希乌斯·塞涅乔，如果一个人感到他的德行在不断进步，但事实上并未消除愚昧，因为不道德的行为限制了每个阶段的进步，并恰好抵消了这些进步，好比“铅锤使渔网下坠”一样，他的道德水平不断下降，那么，有没有一种说理方式能够让人意识到自己的德行在进步呢？就拿音乐或文化素养来说，一个人如果在学习过程中没有减少对这些领域的无知，就可能无法认识到自己在这方面的进步，他的无知水平将永远保持不变。如果医疗手段未能减轻一个患者的不适或在某种程度上缓解病情，使病情得到控制和减轻，直到身体完全复原，并且通过治疗使疾病完全消失不见，患者就无法感知到病情好转。

事实上，如果人们感知不到这些领域的变化，就不会取得进步，因为进步的工具是消除抵抗人们进步的阻力（好比站在一架天平上，被一股向上的力量提起，与之前下落的运动相抗衡）。同样，在哲学上，如果一个人不能从思想上免于犯错并得到净化，反而在获得绝对至善的时刻仍然陷入于绝对至恶的混沌，就不能假设取得了进步和意识到进步。当然，智者只需片刻，一瞬间，就能从极度罪恶达到尽善尽美的境界。尽管长期来看他的罪恶没有丝毫消除，但在这一瞬间他却完全脱离了恶习。

不过，我敢肯定你已经知晓，持这种观点的人会为自己的断言陷入极其尴尬的境地，也会给“浑然不觉的智者”带来许多麻烦。一个人实际上已经变得聪明了，但是，他自己却并不知道，在一个渐进而漫长的过程中，他丧失了某些品质，也获得了某些品质，在不知不觉中他不断进步，就像一条铺就的道路，平稳地把他引向具有美德的境地。变化的速度和规模非常之大，一个在早晨还一无是处的人到了晚上就能成为一个完美的圣徒；也可能发生这样的巨变，入睡前还是一个没用的傻瓜，醒来时却是一个圣明的智者，他的心灵中所有的谬误和缺点都被涤荡干净，他不禁惊呼：“再见吧，荒谬的梦境，你其实什么也不是！”如果这一切真是如此，谁又能意识不到这种巨大的变化，感觉不到智慧的光芒突然照耀着他呢？我宁愿相信像凯纽斯那样的人祈祷自己从女人变为男人，却未能注意到自己的转变；也不相信一个胆怯、愚蠢、懦弱的人变得坚强、睿智、勇敢，或者一种野蛮的生活变得神圣之后，他自己对这些顷刻间的变化却毫无知觉。

有种正确的说法是：人应该“修整石头对齐直线，而不是修改直线去对齐石头。”有些人不愿意根据事实去修正观点，而是强迫事实去符合自己的臆测，这是不符合自然规律的，因而产生了大量的哲学难题，其中最大的难题是：除了完美无缺的人以外，所有人都被划入不道德这一鱼龙混杂的类别。这个难题使得人们对“进步”一词讳莫如深：所谓的“进步”与极度愚蠢只差一步之遥，这种进步使得尚未摆脱各种情感和缺陷的人依然与尚未摆脱最大恶性的人一样可悲。总之，这些思想家是在自我否定。他们在演讲中将阿里斯泰德斯与法拉里斯的伤风败俗相提并论，把布拉西达斯与多伦的怯懦视同一致，甚至认为柏拉图与梅利多斯的愚昧无知也如出一辙；但他们在生活实践中，却禁戒这几组人中后者的行为，认为他们冷酷无情，追随并信任这几组人中的前者，认为他们对最重要事物方面的论述具有重要意义。

我们要注意每一种罪恶都在程度上有多少之别，尤其是那些不确定、不可估量的心灵上的罪恶。同样，消除罪恶也有不同程度的进步，当理性逐渐启迪、净化灵魂时，人的不足就会像黑暗被光明击退一样向后退却。因此，对那些正在被推出深渊的人而言，我们并不认为他们认识到这些变化的看法是不合逻辑的，相反，我们认为这种认识具有明确的、可以描述的道德概念观念。

在此，无须多费周折，请首先考虑第一个道德观念。正如那些扬帆远航的人通过流逝的时间和风力的强度来计算他们航行了多远，他们根据一定风力驱使下花费的一定时间来估量他们可能完成的行程。在哲学中亦如此。一个人能够通过推理过程中取得进步的连续性和延续性，加之新的努力和动力使停顿与波折很少出现，以便能够持久地顺利、匀速向前，并利用理性确保这个过程没有障碍，从而彻底弄清楚自己的进步。“一点一点地积累并持之以恒”这个忠告不仅对于财富的积累有效，而且对一切事物都具有普世价值，特别是对于德行的进步意义重大，因为理性会因此获得许多良好习性的帮助，带来收获。

哲学研究者良莠不齐，有一些生性愚钝，他们在取得进步的道路上延误徘徊，甚至倒退，因为人一旦放弃追求、虚度光阴，恶习就会抓紧时机对他们进行伏击，进而把他们拽回并推向相反的方向。数学家告诉我们，行星若停止向前运动，就会静止，但在哲学研究中，即便停止进步，也不会出现间断、静止的情形，因为人性总是在不断变化中，好像天平上不断变化倾斜的两端，或是受好的影响向更好的方向发展，或是受坏的影响向更坏的方向发展。如果你遵守神谕“日夜与克亥人战斗”，而且你清楚要抵抗恶习，日复一日永不停休，或者至少你几乎没有放松警惕，也没有经常耽于享受、欢娱，因为它们就好像是恶习派来进行妥协谈判的特使，那么你就可以勇敢无畏、激情饱满地向未来前进。

即便一个人的哲学研究会被打断，但如果以后的研究比以前更稳定、更持久，那么这就是一个好的迹象，表明勤奋工作和不断努力能够逐渐消除懈怠。然而，过了一段时间之后，挫折持续不断地出现，饱满的热情逐渐退却，就会出现不良现象。比如，一根芦苇开始生长，没有阻力，其成长也不被干扰，就会保持旺盛的长势，长出长而光滑的芦苇秆子；后来，似乎由于呼吸困难，它的长势变弱，甚至不再长高，因为高度被苇秆中的许多带有空心的结节给限制了，它的生命力受到了冲击。这只是一个形容哲学研究的比喻：一方面，有的人刚开始精力充沛、兴致勃勃，随后不断地遭遇大量障碍与干扰，同时看不见任何进步，最后忍受不了而无奈放弃；另一方面，有的人为哲学惠益所激发，如虎添翼，加上因取得成就而产生了动力和热情，便把种种拦路虎一样的借口横扫一边。

当你与喜欢的人在一起时，并不是幸福感使你意识到你已坠入爱河（因为并非只有爱情才会让你感到幸福），而是当你和对方分开时会感到痛苦和伤心，这才是恋爱的标志。同样，许多人被哲学所吸引，兴致勃勃地开始学习，但如果由于别的因素使他们放弃学习，他们的热情就会消退，不再关心哲学了。“一个人若是被心爱的人所伤”，他在进行哲学讨论时会表现得平静和温顺，但当他远离哲学讨论时，他会焦躁不安，对一切心怀不满；他对哲学的向往会使他变得好像失去理智，忘记了身边的朋友。关键问题是，我们对待讨论不应该像喜欢香水那样，没有香水的时候，不会到处寻找香水，不会浑身难受，而应该是当脱离哲学讨论时（不论是结婚、航海、交友，还是兵役导致这种隔离），我们能体验到一种类似于饥渴的感受，这种感受能使我们保持真正的事业进步。一个人从哲学中获益越多，离开哲学时，他的不快也会越多。

我们所说的进步与古代赫西奥德对“进步”的阐述基本相同，或者非常相似—道路不再陡峭，不再是上坡路而变为平坦大道，仿佛是不断付出的努力造就了坦途，仿佛这段旅程为哲学带来了希望和光明。在哲学中，学生在学习之初困惑迷茫，游移不定，好比水手离开他们熟知的陆地，却看不到作为目的地的陆地，因为他们放弃了正常的、熟悉的事物，却又没有获取新的知识，拥有更美好的事物，于是他们就在这一过程中原地打转，甚至经常返回原点。

罗马人沙斯提乌斯就是一个例子：为了哲学，他放弃了政治舞台上的显要位置，但是，他在哲学学习中缺乏耐心，发现学习哲学异常困难，差点想跳楼。还有一个类似的故事，讲的是西诺普的第欧根尼最初投身哲学研究的事：在雅典的一个假日，人们举行盛大宴会，在剧院上演节目，派对接二连三，狂欢通宵达旦，而此时第欧根尼蜷缩在广场的角落里试图入睡。他心烦意乱，脑子里满是自我毁灭的想法，他一直想弄清楚，在没有外力强迫的情况下，他曾经如何按照自己的自由意愿，采用了一种劳其筋骨、异于常人的生活方式，并摒弃了所有那些美好的事物。然而，就在那时（据传），一只老鼠爬了上来，不管不顾地咀嚼他掉下的面包屑。第欧根尼开动脑筋，反思自己，仿佛自我批评、自我蔑视地说：“第欧根尼，你在想什么？你吃剩的东西竟成了一只小老鼠的美食？然而你，一个堂堂的男子汉—就因为你不能躺在华丽的软椅上醉酒狂欢，就这么怨声连连、唉声叹气吗？”当那种坏心情偶有发生时，理性会很快介入，好像战败后重整旗鼓一样，帮助我们摒弃和消除坏心情，轻而易举地驱散我们心头的焦虑与不安，于是我们便可坚信我们的进步有了坚实的基础。

哲学研习者自身的弱点不是导致他们踟蹰和倒退的唯一因素，朋友们热心的忠告和批评者的冷嘲热讽也会歪曲、削弱他们的决心，甚至使一些人完全放弃哲学。因此，如果一个人能心绪平静地面对这些不利因素，听到人们提及自己的同行如何在皇宫里飞黄腾达，或是如何通过婚姻得到一大笔钱，或是如何经过民众选举进入元老院担任政法要职，而不会意志消沉或心烦意乱，这就说明他已经取得了良好的进步。对一个人来说，在此类情形下不惊慌失措或摇摆不定，这就清楚地表明他学习得法，牢牢掌握了哲学的精髓。绝大多数人赞赏的行为唯独他不去效仿是不可能的，除非这个人已经习惯于赞赏美德；即使在愤怒和疯狂的时候，人也有能力立足于人前，但是藐视被普世赞赏的行为，如果没有真正崇高的、坚定的意志，这是不可能的。

这也是人们与他人的心态相比而引以为豪的原因，如梭伦所说：“我们决不会拿我们的美德去与他们的财富作交易，因为拥有美德是恒久稳固的，而钱财却是暂时拥有的。”第欧根尼曾反复移居于科林斯与雅典，并因此以波斯王自比。波斯王春天居于苏萨，冬天居于巴比伦，夏天居于米堤亚。阿格西劳斯也曾这样评价波斯王：“他比我更伟大只是因为比我更有德。”亚里士多德在写信给安提帕特时提到亚历山大，他指出不能因为亚历山大统治着许多人，他就是唯一有权感到骄傲的人：任何人只要真正地信奉诸神，就能拥有同样的权利。当芝诺看到色奥弗拉斯托斯受到为数众多的学生景仰时，他说：“虽然他的合唱队人数更多，但我的合唱队唱得更悦耳动听。”不管怎样，将美德与外在形式对立起来，能够消除你对他人的嫉妒和猜忌，所有让哲学初学者困惑沮丧的事物也将烟消云散，这时你则可以认为这是你取得进步的明显表现。

一个人言谈中发生的变化也是一个很重要的迹象。哲学初学者几乎无一例外地倾向于能提高自己声誉的言谈方式。一些人就像飞鸟一样浅薄自大，想要一蹴而就，达到科学辉煌的顶峰；另一些人则像柏拉图所说，“如小狗一样，喜欢拖拉撕咬”，他们喜欢找人理论、诡辩以解决难题。许多初学者沉迷于哲学争论之中，并以此作为诡辩的武器。还有的人到处搜集格言和语录，就如阿拉卡雪斯曾经说道：在他看来，希腊人拥有钱财只是为了计算数额，他们会数钱却不会用钱，同样这些希腊人也只会清算他们所拥有东西的数量，而不去积累对他们有益的其他东西。

所有这一切的结果都有安提法奈斯的言论为证，并被应用到柏拉图的回环法中。安提法奈斯曾经讲过一个有趣的故事：在某个城市，只要开口说话，话一出口就被冻成了冰，等到了夏天解冻之后，人们才听到在冬天里说的话。他指出，柏拉图对人们年轻时候所说的话，其实也是同样的道理。直到很久以后，人们都已经老态龙钟，此时大部分人才意识到其中的深意。人们学习任何形式的哲学也是这样的经历，只有当人的判断合理、可靠，才开始形成能渗透到道德品质和道德范畴的原则，并开始寻找一种话语，这种话语的踪迹，借用伊索的比喻，深入人心，而不流于表面。索福克勒斯曾说，他首先减轻了埃斯库罗斯语言的厚重，接着处理他自己夸张和造作的风格，之后才开始第三步，改变语言的特点，因为语言对道德和德行最具影响力。以此类推，只有当哲学研究者停止利用争论进行卖弄和造作，转而寻找一种能表达他们的个性和内心感受的话语，他们才会开始获得真正的、谦逊的进步。

首先，你要确定自己在阅读哲学著作、聆听哲学演说时是否过于重视语言而忽略了主题，是否更在意晦涩难懂的只言片语而不是有用的、充实的、有益的文章。其次，你研究诗歌和历史的时候要多加小心，不要忽略了那些表达恰当、能促进品性、缓和情感的东西。就像西蒙尼德斯在谈到花丛中的蜜蜂时说：“（蜜蜂）专注的是琥珀色的蜂蜜。”然而别的人关注的却只是花的颜色和香气。因此，当人们为了开心娱乐而研读诗歌时，若有人靠自己的努力寻找并搜集了一些有价值的东西，那么就可以认为他的习惯以及对美好和谐事物的喜爱已经使他能够欣赏诗歌中美好和谐的东西了。

例如，有些人喜欢柏拉图和色诺芬的语言，但是只专注于他们朴实的阿提卡语言风格（就好比它是鲜花雨露一般）。对这些人的唯一评价就是：他们喜欢药物的适口和芳香，却不关心甚至无法辨识药物的镇痛和通便的效用。相比之下，那些不断取得进步的人能够从所见的、所处的环境中而不是从所说、所写的字词中受益，并能获得合适的、有用的东西。

在埃斯居罗斯和其他类似的典故中可以证明这一点。例如，埃斯居罗斯在科林斯地峡运动会上观看一场拳击比赛，只要一名拳击手被击中，观众就会爆发雷鸣般的喊声，埃斯居罗斯用肘轻轻碰了下基沃斯的伊翁，对他说：“看见这训练的结果了吧？被击倒的人一声不吭，而看客却高声大叫。”布拉西达斯捡到一些干的无花果却被这些无花果里的一只老鼠咬了一口，他赶紧把它扔掉，他说道：“多么不可思议啊！不管多么弱小的生命，只要有勇气自卫，就能活下去！”第欧根尼看见有人用手喝水，就立刻从包裹里掏出自己的杯子扔掉。

这些故事都说明，只要专心致志并持续努力，就一定能从任何事物中看到并汲取其中隐含的美德。如果用理论对实践加以补充，这个结果就更易出现。不仅仅是像修昔底德说的“在险境中坚持研习”，而且要在开心愉快或争论不休的时候，在参与决策的时候，在法庭诉讼答辩和处理政务的时候，切实展示自己的信念，或是通过实践树立自己的信念。但是对于那些仍在学习的人来说，通过思考自己能从哲学中获得什么来充实自己，使自己能够在政治论坛上、年轻人的聚会上或是王宫的宴会上信手拈来，这些人并不能被称为哲学家，而是像被称为医生的江湖郎中罢了，或许更确切一点地描述这种诡辩家，就如荷马所描述的鸟一样，因为他只是反刍给自己的学生，仿佛他们是他羽翼未丰的幼鸟，如果他不对自己有利的东西进行思考或是对学到的东西进行消化吸收，那么任何他接受的东西都只是囫囵吞枣罢了。

对我们来说弄明白以下方面至关重要：首先，我们利用语言优化自我；其次，相对其他人而言，我们这样做不是为了得到虚幻的荣耀或公众的认可，而是我们想要学习和传授一些东西。我们首先得确保研究问题时，不再有竞争和争论，不再用争论武装自己，就像在拳击赛中用手套和指节套去攻击他人，为把对方打倒在地而欣喜，而是把重点放在学习和传授上。在讨论中彬彬有礼，不争先恐后，也不怒气冲冲地结束，在赢得辩论后不自鸣得意，在输掉辩论后也不怨天尤人，这些都是一个人在德行上有进步的标志。

亚里斯提卜给我们做了榜样：他在一次辩论中败北，赢得了辩论的人信心满满，这非常愚蠢、浅薄。亚里斯提卜看到那人胜出后兴高采烈、被胜利冲昏头脑的样子，说：“我要回家了，尽管我输了，但我今晚将美美地睡上一觉，虽然你赢了，但我会睡得比你香。”

我们公开说话时，也可以估量自己的德行：出乎意料地看到有一大群人来听演讲，我们不怯场；听众寥寥无几，我们也不沮丧气馁；要求面向公众或官员讲话时，我们能够把握机会，尽管没有充分准备，也能应对自如。德摩斯提尼和亚西比德就能这样做。亚西比德善于把握演说的主题，但却对演说的表达技巧缺乏自信，结果有时把自己给绕进去，甚至是经常说到一半的时候，总是停下来搜肠刮肚地去想用一些难懂的词或短语，导致听众嘘声四起。相比之下，荷马并不发愁开始几行没有韵律，他的才能使得自己对剩下的诗歌内容信心十足。因此，我们大可以想象，那些努力为美德和优点奋斗的人会很好地利用机遇和主题，而不在意他们演讲的语言是否引起听众激昂的欢呼。

这对言谈举止同样适用，每个人应该确保自己关注的是有用的东西，而不是为了炫耀，追求的是真理，而不是为了显摆。如果对一个年轻人或女子的真爱不需要别人的见证，就算是秘密满足自己的追求也能收获快乐的果实，那些爱好美德和智慧、通过自己的举止体现美德的人，更有可能对自己内在的魅力保持沉默，而不需要有人欣赏。曾经有人在家命令自己的女佣，对她大声叫道：“看着我，迪奥尼西娅，我不再自以为是了。”与此类似，做了一些善事之后便到处对人说，很明显，他依然关注的是外界对自己的赞赏和公众对自己的认可，这也表明他并没有见识过真正的美德，他在虚幻的梦想阴影里任意表演，从未真正醒悟，还要把自己的行为示人，就像展示一幅画一样。

由此可见，在帮助朋友或熟人之后，却不到处宣扬，这就是德行进步的标志。当周围的人都堕落腐化时仍坚守诚实，拒绝向富人或权贵可耻地折腰，唾弃贿赂，在夜晚渴望喝酒时能克制不饮，像阿格西劳斯那样克制自己不与漂亮的姑娘亲吻—一个人能默默坚守这些也是德行进步的标志。像这样的人能够获得自我认可，不会被人轻视，亲眼见证了自己行善时会感到快乐满足，这表明理性已经在他内心得到滋养并在他身上扎根，如德谟克里特所说，他“正习惯于成为自己快乐的源泉”。

农民喜欢看到饱满的稻穗弯腰垂向大地，他们认为那些空瘪的昂首挺立的稻穗是些没有分量的冒牌货。立志成为哲学家的年轻人也是如此：那些没有内涵、毫无分量的人喜欢出风头，行为举止矫揉造作、趾高气扬，脸上满是鄙夷的神情，蔑视一切事物，但是当他们从学习中有了收获变得充实时，他们就会抛弃浅薄自大。正如空容器中加入液体时，里面的空气受到挤压会排出去一样，当人被真正好的东西充实时，他们的自负造作就会土崩瓦解，不再因为蓄着胡子穿着破旧的礼服而自得，而是将努力学到的东西铭记于心。他们严于律己，宽以待人。他们改变了以前的陋习：不再以哲学的名义、以学习哲学获得好名声。相反，如果一个内心善良的年轻人被别人称为“哲学家”，他会变得惊慌不安，尴尬地笑着说：“瞧你，我不是神，为什么将我视为神呢？”正如埃斯库罗斯所说：“年轻姑娘经历了爱情，她的眼睛闪耀的光芒就会出卖她。”年轻人获得了真正哲学上的收获时，萨福的话就非常贴切：“我张口结舌，浑身激情燃烧。”尽管他的双眸无忧无虑、平静镇定，但你却渴望听他说话。

当入会仪式开始时，参加者聚集在一起，声音嘈杂，互相推搡，可当仪式开始举行时，他们立刻安静下来，全神贯注，充满敬畏。这就像是学习哲学之初，许多人站在哲学的门槛外，充斥着无序、嘈杂和自信，粗鲁地推搡着，努力获得哲学带来的名声；但是当人发现自己入门之后，沐浴着耀眼的哲学之光，仿佛神殿开启，他就会惊讶得呆住，变得安静，“用谦逊和克制去遵从”理性，就像遵循神明一样。对于这些人，墨涅德摩斯的戏言似乎形容得更加绝妙。他说，大量远渡重洋来雅典学习的人都会经过以下历程：他们一开始充满智慧，后来变成了爱智者，再后来成了哲学家，随着时间的推移，他们又成了普通人。他们获得理性越多，就越会逐渐抛弃自负和虚荣做作。

当人们牙疼或手指受伤需要治疗时，他们会直接去看医生；发烧时，会请医生上门，请求医生为自己看病；但如果患病比较严重—得了忧郁症、脑膜炎或精神错乱，他们有时会忍受不了医生上门看病，要么将医生赶走，要么逃避看病，因为他们的病已严重到意识不到自己疾病缠身了。犯错的人也是如此：对责备、训斥自己的人恼怒生气，举止蛮横挑衅，这样的人是无可救药的，然而对那些能忍受责备，不对抗的人来说，情况要缓和得多。有些人犯了错误，但是愿意接受别人的批评，指出自己的错误，不隐藏自己的错误，不为做了错事未受惩罚而窃喜，也不为别人未辨认出自己是一个怎样的人而窃喜，而是承认错误，请求别人训诫自己，这绝对表明他在进步。这也是第欧根尼之认为的为了寻求安全，人应该注意寻找一位挚友或一个劲敌，这样才能通过两种方式之一—受到责难或是受到照顾—摆脱恶习。

试想一个人的衣服上有明显的污迹或印渍，或是鞋子上有裂口，在外面却把这些当作妄自菲薄的借口，或是以自己身材矮小或驼背自嘲来展示自己的嬉皮精神。这样做无非是在掩盖自己丑陋的灵魂，隐藏他生命的缺陷，他的卑鄙猥琐、享乐主义、怨天尤人、心怀不满，就仿佛这些是脓肿，不让任何人碰触或看见它们，因为害怕受到责备，那么这样的人的进步就微乎其微了，甚至是没有进步。当然，与这些缺点战斗的人，尤其是他能够也愿意向自己展示这些缺点，并为此痛心，接着他能够也愿意接受别人的苛责，他的灵魂必将在这些磨难中得到净化，恰恰是这样的人真正地憎恶卑贱，确确实实地愿意消除卑贱。

虽然，避免受辱难堪甚至是坏名声对每个人都很重要，但是，有的人厌恶现实的罪恶更甚于卑劣的坏名声，如果目的是促进德行进步的话，那么他既不回避别人对自己的责难，也不苛责别人。例如，在一家客栈里，第欧根尼看见一个逃跑出来的年轻人，跑进这家客栈，他巧妙地说了一句：“你越往里跑，你就越会在这客栈里。”一个人对缺陷否认得越多，他就越沉沦、越被禁锢在这些缺陷里。本是穷人却要假装富有，他的虚伪只会使得他更加贫乏。希波克拉底记录下自己无法理解头骨的缝合，并公布了这一事实，为正在努力进步的年轻人树立了榜样。希波克拉底通过宣示自己的弱点去帮助别人避免重蹈覆辙；而一个致力于绝对正确的人往往不敢接受别人的谴责，或承认自己的荒谬无知。

事实上，彼翁和皮罗的主张不仅表明德行进步，而且指的是一种更美好、更完美的境界。彼翁告诉自己的朋友们，如果听到辱骂就好比听到这样的一些话：“朋友，你看起来并不邪恶，也不愚蠢，祝你健康、快乐，愿神明保佑你万事如意。”那么你就应该认为自己德行进步了。皮罗的故事是这样的：他曾经在海上航行时遭遇了风暴，身陷险境，他指着一头正津津有味地吃着漏掉的大麦的小猪，对同伴说：一个人若不想被任何事干扰，就要用理智和哲学使自己有着这猪一样的超脱。

请注意芝诺所说的—一个人的梦想应该是使自己意识到他的德行在进步，在睡眠中对可耻的事情感到不快，不纵容也不做可怕的骇人听闻的事情，相反，他就像在彻底的宁静祥和中顿悟，灵魂中的幻想和情绪被理智驱散了。柏拉图显然在芝诺之前就意识到了这一点，他简要地描述天生暴戾的灵魂中幻想的非理性方面在睡眠中的所作所为：“它妄图乱伦，”对各种美食有着难以抗拒的冲动，想干伤风败俗、越轨的事，像自己所渴望的那样随心所欲，这些事情在白天因为受道德习俗约束使人感到羞耻和惧怕，在梦里就解除禁锢了。

驯服的牲畜不会想要偏离队列而走失，即使它们的主人松开了缰绳，它们也会井然有序地列队前行，保持自己的节奏，老老实实地按照路线行进。同样，人们非理性的方面已经被理性教化，变得文明后，即使是在睡梦中或是生病时，人们也不会放纵欲望伤风败俗、为所欲为。相反，人们时时注意保持理智并牢记在心，因为理智能赋予我们集中注意力的力量和能量。如果通过训练，身体的各部分能够协调一致—甚至是整个身体以及它的任一局部都能控制自如—不会因满目疮痍而泪流满面，因惊骇万状而怦然心跳，因情投意合而冲动越轨，那么，这自然增加了训练掌握灵魂中情感因素的程度，可以说，通过消除包括睡梦中的各种幻想和感官刺激，能使情感优雅有度。

有一则关于哲学家斯提尔波的故事能证实这一点。他在梦中看到海神波塞冬对他怒气冲冲，因为他没有向海神祭献一头公牛（给波塞冬的常规祭品），但是斯提尔波丝毫没有忐忑不安，他说：“波塞冬，您什么意思，难道您是因为我没有破产到让这座城市充满祭品的焦味，而是在家倾我所有向您适度进献，才会像个幼稚的孩子来此抱怨的吗？”然后他梦见波塞冬笑了，向他伸出右手说，看在斯提尔波的份上，我要让迈加拉的沙丁鱼丰产！

因此，不管怎样，那些有着愉快的、清新的、无忧无虑的美梦的人在梦里感受不到任何可怕的、恐怖的不正常之事，这是他们德行取得进步的明显特征。那些痛苦、奇异的梦境—在梦中狂热、兴奋，像懦夫一样逃避危险，经历孩童般的悲喜—犹如波涛此起彼伏，这是因为人们还不能自我掌控心灵，仍然受到世俗和规则的约束，所以当他在睡觉的时候，灵魂远离这些约束，重获自由，依然受到情感的影响。现在，请你和我一起思考，我所说的这些现象的根源是属于进步还是源自于一种建立在理智之上的心态，一种稳重、可靠的心态。

绝对的超凡脱俗是崇高而神圣的，进步之于这种境界，就好像感情的减少和节制，因此，重要的是要审视我们的情感，比较各种不同的情感，区分它们之间的不同。我们必须要将现在的情感和过去的情感相比较，看看我们现在的欲望、敬畏和激情是否没有过去那么强烈，因为我们通过理智能很快消除这些强烈和热切的情感；我们必须要将各种情感相互比较，看看我们现在的羞耻之心是否比我们的敬畏之心更锐利，更愿意与人竞争而不是妒忌他人，重名誉而轻钱财。简而言之，我们必须通过比较不同的情感，用音乐家的话说，才能知道我们是否对多利安模式过宽而对利地安模式过严，我们的生活模式是否更趋于禁欲主义而不是享乐主义，我们的行动是否变得稳重而不是冒进，我们看待论点和人物的眼光是否是惊奇而不是鄙夷。就疾病而言，当它转移到身体非致命的部位，便是健康恢复的一个好迹象；同理，就恶习而言，当正在努力进步的人用高尚的情感来审视自身的恶习，这些恶习便会逐渐被消除。弗里尼斯在七弦琴上额外加了两条琴弦，于是长官们就问他是切掉顶端的两条弦还是切掉底端的两条弦，因为通常是七根琴弦，我们首先要弄清楚什么是必须的，如果两端的琴弦都要被切掉的话，是否就是处在中间不偏不倚的位置，其次是德行进步始于我们情感的极端和强度的削减，就像索福克勒斯所说，“贪欲使人过度劳累”。

我们已经提到将想法付诸行动，别让语言只是文字游戏而要落实到行动上，这才是特别典型的德行进步的表现。首要的是，要效仿我们称道的行为，渴望去做我们钦佩的事，而不愿去做甚至不能容忍我们诟病的事。例如，米太亚德因其勇气和胆量在雅典受到广泛赞美，但是，狄米斯托克利却说米太亚德的战利品使他难以安寝甚至让他无法得到片刻休息，很明显狄米斯托克利不仅仅是在表达对米太亚德的敬仰和赞美，而且被米太亚德折服要去效仿他。因此，如果我们对成功事物的赞美流于表面，而不足以激励我们去效仿的话，那么我们取得的进步就微乎其微。

爱慕之情并不是改变一个人的力量，除非与之相随的是渴望效仿。赞誉美德如果不能激励我们，指引我们去效仿美好的事物，而是心怀嫉妒，那么这种赞美就不是热烈、有效的。亚西比德强调了心灵为贤达的话所打动而泪流满面的意义，不仅这样，真正进步的人将自己的行为与优秀的榜样相比较，意识到自己的不足而深感痛心，也因内心充满希望而欢欣鼓舞，满怀一种永不停歇的劲儿。用西摩尼得斯的话形容，就好比一匹奔跑在母马身边未断奶的马驹，因为他渴望成为完美的人。实际上，我们喜爱有些人的性格，极力模仿他们的行为，而且在自觉模仿时伴有良好的意愿，愿给予他们敬意和荣誉，这样的过程才是典型的真正的德行进步。若有人争强好胜，对比自己强的人心怀嫉妒，那他一定要意识到让自己生气的只不过是对某种名誉或能力的嫉妒，而并不是对美德的敬慕和赞赏。

因此，当我们仰慕贤达时，如柏拉图所说，我们不仅认为有责任的人是幸运的，而谁要听到这样有责任的人说的话也是幸运的。我们喜欢他们的姿势、步态、面容和微笑，渴望追随他们，紧紧相随，那么，我们就可以名正言顺地认为自己正在取得真正的进步。还有一种更为合情合理的情形，假如我们对完美者的仰慕并不仅仅是他们成功的一面，而是如爱人一般，即使他们口齿不清、面容苍白，也会毫不犹豫地深爱对方：尽管不幸和悲惨使潘德亚痛苦哭泣，但依然打动了阿拉斯普斯的心，同样，我们不应该因为阿里斯提德的流亡、阿拉克萨戈拉的囚禁、苏格拉底的贫穷、福基翁的获罪而退缩，因为我们坚信，即使是在那样恶劣的环境下美德依然是值得我们追求的。只要内心有追求我们就应该向美德靠拢，用欧里庇得斯的话说：“品格高尚的人对污秽的东西视若无物。”人若受到足够的鼓舞激励，即使面对貌似可怕的事物，也会心怀敬意，并去效仿，而不是疏离它们，那他一定永远不会脱离美好的事物。在已经成为这样的人的经历中，无论是处理事务、担任公职或是遭遇险境，都会想象过去的贤达完美之人，并且自省：“若是柏拉图在此境遇会怎样？伊帕美农达斯会如何说？吕库古斯、阿基希劳斯会怎样处理？”他以他们为镜，把自己置于镜前对照，或是调整自己的立场，或是克制自己不说卑劣的话，或是控制情感的爆发。有的人获知伊达山山神达克提尔众多的名字并不断诵读每一个名字，就好像是用来驱赶恐惧的符咒，同样，当任何情感和艰难困苦折磨那些不断取得德行进步的人时，对完美者的思念和回忆会立刻涌上心头，并让他们不断思考，这会让他们逢凶化吉，不屈不挠。因此，这也是使你能辨认出那些德行进步之人的另一种标志。

此外，当有一位因自制力强而名声在外的人出乎意料地出现在你面前时，你能够不心慌意乱，不害羞脸红，不避之唯恐不及，也不想重新调整自己的特质，能够毫无怯意地迎上去，你就能确信自己已经意识到德行的进步了。当亚历山大看到使者愉快地大步走来，并向他伸出右手时说：“我的朋友，你带来了什么消息，是荷马重新活过来了吗？”因为他觉得自己的丰功伟绩尚需一位智者的声音为自己扬名立万。一方面，不断完善性格特性、提升自我的年轻人表达爱的方式是在真正优秀的人面前如数家珍，向他们展示自己的家庭、膳食、妻子、孩子、职业，以及口、笔头的表达能力，为去世的家长或先师不能目睹他目前的情形而悲痛不已，他最诚挚地向神灵祈祷的唯一事情就是他们能复活见证他现在的生活和所为。另一方面，对自己毫不负责而把自己毁掉的人恰恰相反，他们连在梦里碰见亲人也会焦躁不安，难以镇定。

还有一个能表明德行进步的标志，可把它作为我们前面已经讨论过的几点的补充。一方面，一个人不再认为自己的错误是微不足道的，而是严肃对待，密切关注。不再希望成为富有的人，每次花掉小数目的钱时，不以为然，因为他们认为积少成不了多，然而，积蓄增多越接近目标，渴望成为富人的愿望就越迫切。与德行相关的行为也是如此：那些从不姑息，以“这有什么大不了的？”“这次就这样了，下次会更好些”为托词的人会每时每刻认真对待，如果恶习以它的借口像蠕虫一样渗透到他最微小的错误中，他也会无法忍受，变得焦躁不安，这些人在这个过程中显然已为自己赢得了一定的纯洁，他不能接受以任何方式对自己的玷污。另一方面，一个人认为没有什么事情会或者可能给人带来奇耻大辱，就会对微小的事情粗心大意，若无其事。事实上，建一堵墙的时候，用一块奇特的木头或是一块普通的石头做地基是没有区别的，如果从坟墓里掉出来的一块石碑被放进地基，这种行为就类似德行降格的人对陈旧事物的简单堆砌。那些德行在进步的人们，他们已经打好了扎实的生命基础（就像神殿或王宫的基础一样），不会不加选择地取得事物，而是以理智为标尺促使物得其所。这在我看来，就是波利克莱图斯所指出的，他说如果用黏土雕塑时到了使用手指甲的地步，那任务就极为艰巨了。

论制怒

苏拉：丰达努斯，我认为画家们周期性地审视他们的作品，然后再进一步修饰的做法是值得称道的。如果一直对作品保持熟悉，就不会发现它们与想塑造的形象有多少差异，因此打破这种连续性，以全新的视角反复赏鉴，更易于捕捉到细微的差别。对个人来说，不可能套用这种固定的方式中断自我赏鉴的连续性来审视自我，这正是自己比他人更无法判断自我的主要原因。因此，其次的做法是定期审视自己的朋友，出于同样目的向他们展示自己，这并不是要看看他是否突然变老或者他的身体状况是好还是坏，而是指经过一段时间之后，判断他是否增进了良好的习惯和品德，或是否戒除了不良的习性。

无论如何，我离开一年多之后又回到了罗马，我和你在一起也4个多月了，我发现你与生俱来的优点进一步发扬了，并且有了如此大的进步，对此我并不特别惊讶。当我看到你强悍、暴躁的脾性变得更加顺服、通情达理，我倾向于引用这句话来评论你的性急：“如今他性情温和多了，多好！”

变得温和亲切并不曾使你懦弱无能，它用柔顺的外表及有效、有益的深度—就像一块耕耘后的田地—取代了你那人尽皆知的情绪突变。因此，你的脾气变得温和显然不是因为年龄的增长或其他自觉的因素，而是在于你接纳了良好的合理建议。我必须承认，当我们共同的朋友厄洛斯告诉我你的这些情况时，我怀疑是他对你的温情使你具备了真正善良的人们应该拥有的品质，虽然你过去并没有这些品质，但我认为这忽略了一个事实，他不是一个为了取悦他人而放弃自己立场的人。现在，我很清楚他没有瞎说。我们一起旅行时没有别的事可做，因此我想知道你是否愿意解释你是如何让自己的性情变得温柔、稳健、顺从、有担当的呢—比如，你遵从哪些规则。

丰达努斯：仁慈的苏拉，你确信不是你温暖的友情使你失去对我性格方面的判断力吗？我是说，甚至厄洛斯自己都经常无法控制自己的脾气，“保持一贯的温顺”（正如荷马所说），是正义的怒火让情绪爆发了。因此，在这些情况下我与他相比可能显得比较通情达理，正如当音阶发生变化时，高音能取代低音一样。

苏拉：这些可能性都不现实。丰达努斯，请帮我个忙，按我要求的去做吧。

丰达努斯：好吧，苏拉。穆梭留斯提出了一些极好的建议，我记得其中一条是：一生不断进行治疗，便可免受疾病侵害。问题的关键在于，当理性充当治疗剂时，在我看来—它不应该像黑藜芦一样随疾病排出体外，而是应该保留在心里，控制并审视我们的决定。从其效果来看，理性不应该被比作良药，而是应该比作有营养的食物，因为大家都习惯从食物中获得能量和健康，一旦情绪激动达到一个峰值时，忠告和责难要进行长久而艰苦的斗争，才有微小的收获，恰如嗅盐一样，能刺激晕厥无意识的人们苏醒，但不能消除实际的疾病。

即便情绪激动达到峰值时，当理性和强化物从外部进入心里时，所有其他情绪也会在某种意义上回落和消退；但是愤怒并不会完全像墨兰提俄斯说的那样—“它取代理智，犯下罪行”；事实上，只有当愤怒彻底取代理智，并将理智拒于门外时，它才会这么做。那种情形类似于人们在家中被烧死，从某种意义上说，愤怒使心里充满了混乱、厌恶和噪音，结果是人们看不到、听不到任何有益的东西。因此，在海上风暴中，一艘废弃的船更容易听取外来舵手的指挥，而被暴怒的海洋淹没的人要被外界说服则难得多，除非他自己作好了理性准备。人们没有外援就会尽其所能积累有用的东西以应付进攻。同样，特别重要的是，人们从四面八方搜集有哲理的事物，并牢记于心，用以帮助抵抗愤怒，因为当有迫切需要的时候人们往往不容易找到那些帮助。我的意思是说，喧嚣嘈杂阻止心灵听到任何外部情况，除非心灵有它自己的理性，就像船舱里的水手长，他能迅速学会并懂得每一个指令，此外，即使心灵能听到任何事物，它也会在挑衅生气的时候听不见安静、温柔的规劝。问题的关键在于，傲慢、任性和固执的脾气很难为外部动因所改变，就像根基稳固的暴政一样，只有通过内部固有的动因才能将其推翻。

如果愤怒和怨恨成为常态，心灵就会变得易怒，使人变得敏感、恶毒、令人讨厌—变得多愁善感、吹毛求疵：即便铁块被进一步锻造也会变得薄弱。如果理性分辨力当即抵抗和压制任何愤怒的爆发，不仅能挽救当前的形势，而且将来能给心灵带来活力和解脱。

就我来看，无论如何，我曾经有过两三次克制愤怒的情况，我经历过底比斯人所经历过的事情：他们在第一次击退了不可战胜的斯巴达人后，在后来的战役中就再也没有被斯巴达人打败过。因此，我树立了坚定的信念，即理性战胜一切。我认为，亚里士多德关于冷水能浇熄怒火的断言是不全面的—面对恐惧，怒火也会熄灭。此外，当然，用荷马的说法，幸福突然降临经常会导致愤怒瞬间“融化”和消散。我深信，最终的结果是，只要有这种意愿，愤怒的情绪并非完全不可救药。想想看，微不足道的事情也可能会激发愤怒：一个玩笑，一句无心的话，一个笑声，一个点头示意等，都会激发愤怒。举个例子，海伦给她的侄女写信时，以这样刺激的言辞写道：“伊利克特拉，未婚的老姑娘，在过去的岁月你耗费时间去寻找感觉，使你的家族蒙羞。”当大酒杯仍在传递时，卡利斯提尼斯的一句“我不想喝亚历山大的酒，因为随后又得去看医神阿斯克勒庇俄斯”激怒了亚历山大。

因此，正如要控制开始在兔毛、灯芯或一堆垃圾上燃起来的火焰比较容易（一旦火焰开始在有厚度的固体上燃烧，它就会以熊熊之势迅速摧毁建筑师崇高的作品，如埃斯库罗斯所说），如果有人重视初期的愤怒，意识到它是因为受到一些言论或荒谬嘲讽的刺激而逐渐开始郁积，那么就不用费多大力气。通常只要不说话、不理会那些言语，就可以消除愤怒情绪。不添加燃料就能够把火熄灭，不在刚开始生气时添油加醋、不动辄发怒就会变得明智，从而让愤怒消失殆尽。

我对希罗尼穆斯的说法不敢苟同，尽管他在别的方面有一些有用的意见和建议，但他却声称，由于愤怒发展的速度很快，它在萌芽时是不可察觉的，只有当它已经爆发并确实存在时才能被感知。我认为，所有的情感都要经历由量变到质变的过程，但没有任何情感从开始到发展是如此的明显。这也是荷马学说的巧妙之处：他曾说“痛苦的乌云遮蔽了阿基里斯”，当消息毫不迟延地传来时，他描述阿基里斯瞬间感到痛苦；但他认为阿伽门农的愤怒却是在许多刺激的言辞攻击后渐渐生成、逐步被激发的。如果相关的人在一开始没有说那些刺激的话，他们就不会争吵升级到如此程度，产生这么大的怒火。因此，每当苏格拉底意识到自己对朋友太急躁时，他深知心中的怒火“如暴风雨前汹涌的浪尖”一般涌动着，于是，他通常会压低声音，微笑着，并温和地看着对方，保持身体直立，通过向相反的方向平衡情绪，从而控制住自己的情绪。

你瞧，我的朋友，有一个克服我们暴君般脾气的最佳方式，那就是当愤怒驱使我们提高声音、涨红脸颊、胸膛起伏时，不服从它的驱使，保持安静，情绪就仿佛一种疾病，不能通过捶胸顿足和大声哭喊使它加剧。它就像开派对、唱歌和装饰门框—典型的爱侣行为—在某种程度上有一个缓和或减轻，不会令人不高兴（“我来了，但没有侮辱你：我吻了你的门。如果这是一种犯罪，我就是一个罪犯”）；哀悼者或许能够通过哭泣和泪水消除心中的悲痛，但愤怒状态下的人们激烈的行为和言语会极大地加剧愤怒的情绪。

因此，最好是保持平静，或干脆走开，默默地躲藏起来，寻找庇护，尽管我们意识到要有一种适当的方式，避免发怒，更不要怒及他人—因为我们往往首先迁怒于我们的朋友。我们感觉不到对每个人的爱、嫉妒或恐惧，而愤怒却将它们一网打尽，从而丧失和平：我们对敌人或朋友生气，对孩子或父母生气，甚至对诸神或动物或是没有生命的物体生气。例如，太阳神阿波罗的孙子塔米里斯“砸坏镀金琴架和七弦竖琴”；还有潘达罗斯，他发誓如果不“徒手把弓折断后”再把它烧掉，就进行自残。薛西斯甚至想用岩石给大海刻下烙印，使大海掀起滚滚波涛，他给山神写信道：“和天一样高的伟大的阿托斯，别再变得更加高大了，棘手的岩石已经妨碍了我的行动，不然我要把你撕碎，将你投进大海。”愤怒往往是可怕的，往往又是荒谬的：因此，它是最遭人痛恨和鄙视的情感；充分认识到这两方面又是有益的。

就我而言，不管怎样，我不知道这是否是对待愤怒正确的方式，我的方式如下：就像斯巴达人试图通过观察他们的奴隶来了解酗酒一样，我试图通过观察他人来了解愤怒。希波克拉底说，一种疾病的严重性与病人的体征变得不正常的程度成正比，我首先注意到的是，被愤怒干扰的程度和由愤怒引起的外观、肤色、步态和声音改变的程度之间也存在着相似的关系。这一情绪的反应给我留下了深刻的印象，想到我可能曾经因为愤怒变得让人害怕，使朋友、妻子、女儿错愕骇然，我感到十分不安—不仅是外在的暴怒和面部扭曲让人无法辨认，而且遇到其他熟人时用粗鲁严厉的声音说话。愤怒使人们在交往中无法保持往常一样的特征、外形、愉快的交谈、令人信服的说服力和彬彬有礼。

演说家盖乌斯·格拉古是一个直率的人，说话异常热烈，富有激情，他为自己做了一个小短笛，与音乐家用来引导自己调整嗓音的那种一样。在他演讲的时候，奴隶便拿着短笛站在他身后，吹奏出适中的、柔和的基调，格拉古根据笛声调整嗓音，便能使自己的声音听起来不刺耳，音调不严厉激愤。就好像牛仔抹了蜡的牧笛发出清晰音调奏出催眠般的旋律，格拉古的奴隶就是这样缓和了这个演说家的激愤。

假如我有一个机灵的随从也能帮我调节声音，在我愤怒爆发时举起一面镜子（刚出浴的人有时会照镜子，虽然达不到什么有用的目的），那我也不会感到不快，因为看到自己处于一个非正常的、不安的状态，有助于人们质疑自己的情绪。实际上，有一个有趣的故事。有一次，雅典娜在吹奏管乐，森林之神告诉她：“这个表情不适合你。放下你的管乐，拿起你的武器，放松你的脸颊。”她毫不在意，然而，当她看到河中倒映出自己难看的脸庞时，她非常沮丧，赶紧扔掉了乐器。

至少艺术是高雅的，这分散了人们对愤怒状态中狰狞面目的关注（玛尔叙阿斯显然是用一副类似笼头的器具和一个吹口疏导他急促的气息，矫正和掩盖他丑陋的面貌：“闪烁的黄金把两边太阳穴的头发束在一起，绳子绑在脑后，连接他那辛苦劳作的嘴巴。”）；愤怒不仅会夸张扭曲人的嘴脸，也使一个人的声音更加难听，让人生厌，而且会“扰乱镇定的心境”。我的意思是，当大海被狂风激起千层浪，喷涌出海藻和海草时，人们说大海被净化了；但是没有修养的、苛刻的、恶意的言辞使愤怒在内心激荡爆发，演讲家们深受其害。他们会因为经常有这样的言论而背负玷污社会的污名。如柏拉图所说，他们为最微小的事情—甚至一个字—付出最沉重的代价，因为它们给人的印象是违反社会公德、造谣生事、心怀恶意。

当我观察并注意到这些迹象，我便会记住并时常提醒自己：尽管狂热兴奋之时能保持巧舌如簧、轻言细语十分重要，但在愤怒之时能保持这种状态则更为重要。我是说，如果一个狂热兴奋的人说了些不合常理的话，无疑是种不好的症状，但这并不会造成更多的问题；然而，如果一个发脾气的人变得言语粗暴、有攻击性甚至出现异常言论的倾向，就会反映出一种极端蛮横无理的行为方式，对人际关系造成难以复原的破坏，也会暴露其不善交际的困扰。愤怒导致的不成熟、不和谐的后果要比烈酒更严重：烈酒导致的后果常常伴随着玩笑和歌声，愤怒的后果往往却是严重的摩擦冲突；喝酒会使一个安静的人情绪激动，给他的同伴带来困扰，但愤怒却不会使其产生任何有尊严的行为。正如同女诗人萨福所说：“当愤怒占据你的内心，提防你所有的胡言乱语。”

不断关注深陷愤怒感的人使我产生了更多的思考：它让人从其他角度理解愤怒的本质，明白其既不高尚也不刚勇、既无尊严也不体面。尽管如此，大多数人还是错把混乱当成效，错把威胁当英勇，错把顽固当坚强；甚至有的人会呼吁这种无情的勇猛、固执的勇气和粗暴的正义感，这是错误的。因为这些行为方式的提倡恰恰暴露出他的狭隘与软弱。不仅仅是愤怒的人会恶意攻击幼儿，残暴对待妇女，还认为他们惩罚狗、马和骡子是理所当然（就像泰西封的潘德拉提亚斯特脚踢骡子以泄愤）；专制君主们狭隘的不宽容也会从他们野蛮的行为中体现出来，当他们被激怒，他们的心态就会通过其毒蛇般的残忍行为体现，对任何不服从他们的人会表现出极端愤怒。肉体遭遇沉重打击后会发生肿胀；同样，越是软弱的意志越是容易被击痛，他们的愤怒感也为因此日益增强。

这也是女人为何比男人更易怒，病人、老人或者不幸的人为何比健康、成熟或成功人士更易怒的原因。贪婪的人很可能因他的上司而生气、贪食者因烹调而生气、多疑者因自己的妻子而生气、自负者因有人说他的坏话而生气；但是，正如诗人品达所言，最严重的事情莫过于“执政者过度的野心会激起民愤”。愤怒主要是由软弱导致的精神上的痛苦引起的。有人认为，愤怒是在带有自卫冲动的过程中所产生的一种过度混乱的紧张思想，因此认为愤怒是思想的力量源泉，这种观点是错误的。

无论如何，看到这些可鄙的事例不太令人愉快，但绝对是必要的。不过，在我的耳闻目见中，我认为能以冷静平和的态度处理愤怒的人都是伟大的，所以我最初的出发点是鄙视那些声称“你冤枉他了，谁能忍受被冤枉？”以及“把他踩在脚底下，踏在他的脖子上，让他俯首帖耳！”的人。这些话语颇具煽动性，有些人不正确地利用它们将愤怒从女性身上转移给男性。我认为男性的刚勇几乎都是符合道德标准的，但在涉及温和亲切的问题时却不适用，因为温和亲切的人更有自制力。恶人可能凌驾于善人之上，但是战胜愤怒代表一种强大的、不可抵抗的意志力（哲学家赫拉克莱塔斯称愤怒是“一个强大的对手，因为它以牺牲思想为代价获得它想要的一切”）—这种意志力以理性判断能力为基础，是与情绪对抗时真正的力量源泉。

这就是我不断尝试掌握和读懂这种事例的原因，不管是哲学家（聪明人认为他们不容易遭嫉恨）提供的事例，还是国王或暴君提供的事例。举个例子，当安提柯一世听到士兵在他帐篷附近咒骂他时，他愤怒地扔出长矛，长矛穿透帐篷，插在地上，他说：“哎呀，你们就不能去远点的地方批评我吗？”

阿该亚人阿卡迪亚经常批评菲利普，并建议避免“去那些居民像菲利普一样无知的地方”。然后，有一天他碰巧去马其顿，菲利普的朋友心想可不能让他不吃点苦头就轻易离开，但是，菲利普对他非常友善，并赠送了他礼物。随后他告诉他的子民去了解阿卡迪亚是怎么跟希腊人说的。结果他们发现阿卡迪亚成了菲利普杰出的拥护者。菲利普告诉他们：“所以说我是一个比你们都要优秀的医生！”在奥林匹亚，曾经有一些关于菲利普的诽谤流传开来，有的人提议，既然希腊人不顾菲利普的友善还要去批判他，就应该让他们受点苦。菲利普说：“如果我不善待他们，他们又将作出什么举动？”

同样值得称赞的还有庇西特拉图对色拉希布卢斯将军的态度、波森纳对穆裘斯的态度，以及马格斯对菲利蒙的态度。菲利蒙在他们演出的一部喜剧中公然用这样的言语嘲笑马格斯：“马格斯，这里有一封国王给你的信，可是遗憾的是你看不懂，可怜的马格斯啊！”不久，菲利蒙因遭遇暴风雨被迫逃往帕拉托尼亚，落到了马格斯的手里，马格斯让他的士兵拔出剑架在菲利蒙的脖子上，然后礼貌地离开，随后马格斯就当菲利蒙是一个智障的孩子一样给了他一些骰子和弹球，然后就让他离开了。

托勒密曾经嘲笑过一名学者的无知，质问他谁是珀琉斯的父亲，这名学者回答，如果托勒密能说出拉古斯的父亲是谁，他就回答他的问题。学者的言辞对出身低贱的托勒密来说是极大的嘲讽，所有人都被激怒了，认为这种言词是刺耳的、不恰当的。托勒密说：“如果一个国王受不了别人的嘲弄，那他也不应该嘲弄别人。”

亚历山大在涉及哲学家凯利斯尼兹和克里托斯的事情上比平时要严厉得多。当波鲁斯被亚历山大俘虏后祈求亚历山大能以一个国王应有的气度处决他时，亚历山大问：“这就足够了吗？”“‘以国王应有的气度’就可以包括一切了。”波鲁斯回答。这就是“仁者”是众神之王的一个称号的原因（尽管，我想，雅典人称其为“暴君”）：惩罚是悍妇或者半神半人之流的行径，而不是天神或是奥林匹斯山神的做法。

当菲利普夷平奥林索斯城时，有人说：“重建一座同样的城市就不是他力所能及的了。”同样地，人们可能会对愤怒说：“你擅长拆除、破坏、毁灭，但是建设、保护、怜悯以及耐心需要的是亲切、宽恕和温和的情感：这些事情需要卡美卢斯、米特鲁斯、阿里司提戴斯还有苏格拉底来实现，而瘟疫和叮咬则是蚂蚁以及老鼠的行径。”

再者，当我考虑到怀恨在心这一问题时，我发现，怀恨在心基本上对于表达愤怒是不起作用的：只会因为费尽口舌、磨破嘴皮、虚张声势的攻击以及愚蠢的威胁诅咒而筋疲力尽，其结果就像孩子们赛跑时在接近胜利目标的一瞬间，失去自我控制突然减速一样荒谬可笑。罗得斯岛人在对欢呼加油大喊大叫的罗马民众表示不满时处理得很恰当，他说：“我没有被你们的喧闹所打扰，却被别人的安静打扰了。”还有一次，索福克勒斯让尼奥普托列莫斯和欧律皮洛斯装备好武器，他说：“没有自吹自擂，也没有大声叫骂，他俩捣碎了大规模古铜色的武器装备。”

关键在于，尽管有些粗鲁之人会运用一些恶毒的计谋，但是充满理性色彩的勇气根本不需要强烈的怨恨，而气愤和狂怒却是不近人情和不健康的。无论如何，斯巴达人会在有人发生打斗时吹起管乐器来平息怒火，而且在战斗前往往会祭祀缪斯以确保理性的稳定存在；如果他们彻底击败了敌人，他们不会奋起直追，而是偃旗息鼓，就像易操作的便携式小刀一样收放自如。愤怒会导致很多恶果，许多人因坚持复仇而死：底比斯的赛勒斯将军和佩洛皮达斯将军就是这样两个例子。反之，好脾气的阿加索克利斯容忍了他所占领城市的居民对他的无礼和恶言冒犯。当有一个居民问：“波特，你从哪里弄到钱来支付你的雇佣兵呢？”他大笑着回答：“瞧这儿，就在这个我夷为平地的城市。”曾经有人在城墙上嘲笑安提柯一世的独眼残疾，他却对他们说：“我认为我很好看啊。”但是当安提柯一世占领了城邦之后，他把那些嘲讽者卖为奴隶，并发誓将保持与他们主人的接触，看看他们是否还敢嘲笑他。

我还注意到，愤怒使得律师和雄辩家犯下极大的错误。亚里士多德曾写道，萨摩斯岛的萨提洛斯的朋友在朝廷上用石蜡堵住他的耳朵，以防他被对手的辱骂激怒而把事情弄糟。而我们自己，不是经常因为仆人会害怕我们的威胁和言语恐吓而逃跑，结果对胡作非为的仆人的惩罚不了了之吗？保姆会对孩子说：“不哭就给你。”我们通常也会用同样的方法表达愤怒：“息怒，闭嘴，放轻松，你就有获得你想要的东西的可能和机会。”我的意思是说，如果一位父亲看见他的孩子试图用刀切割或雕刻东西，他把刀拿过来自己去做；如果在愤怒时用理性思维取代报复行为，那么应该受报应的人就会得到惩罚，而理性的头脑得以保持安全、健康与宝贵，免受惩罚，而愤怒的情绪往往会招致责罚。

所有情绪都需要通过训练对其中不理性和固执的部分进行引导、压制（可以这么说）和惩戒，但是如何对待仆人却是制怒的绝佳训练手段。问题在于我们对待仆人的时候不带有任何嫉妒、害怕或对抗情绪，因为我们有凌驾于他们之上的权力。日益增强的愤怒感会导致许多冲突和错误，就好像把自己置于一个光滑的下倾坡面上，却没有人会在前面接住你。我是说，涉及情感因素时，绝对的控制易于导致错误，唯一的解决办法是尽可能多地限制约束你的权力，当妻子或朋友指责你软弱、弱智时，要能够抵御他们经常的抱怨。

我本人过去曾因为上述指责对仆人非常苛刻，并且坚信如果不惩罚他们是对他们的一种姑息，但是我最终认识到：首先，耐心地容忍他们的恶劣行为要比专注于修正他们的行为好得多；其次，我注意到许多例子，当仆人没有受到明确的惩罚，他们会因为犯错而产生羞耻感，开始变得忍耐而不是怀恨在心。我向你保证，如果你能平和地处理仆人们的过错，而不是斥责或是鞭打，你会得到他们更热情的服务。所有这些都使我深信理智要比愤怒更具有说服力。有诗云：“有畏惧，才有敬重。”这是一种误解。实际上，还有这样一种说法：能够自我克制的畏惧感才能伴之产生敬重心。无休止的斥责不会使人对犯下的恶行后悔，反而会激起未来逃避处罚的侥幸心理。

第三，我时常提醒自己要牢记：箭术的学习是要学会如何射准，并非不射箭。同样，即使掌握合时宜的、适度的、有益的、适当的惩罚方法，仍然不会改变别人受惩罚的局面。于是，我尝试平息怒气的首要方式，不是剥夺被指控者给自己辩解的权利，而是聆听他们有什么要说。由于时间可以考验情感，为消磨情绪提供一定的空间，同时理性促使人们寻找到适宜的惩罚方式并了解其适合程度，因此我的方法可以奏效。而且，一个人受到处罚是因为被证明有罪而不是因为愤怒，那么他是没有理由抵抗这种应得的处罚的。同时，也排除了一种最不体面的因素，那就是当仆人比主人更占理时。

亚历山大的死讯传来时，福基翁试图阻止雅典人太快起来造反，或太容易相信这个消息，他说：“雅典的子民们，如果亚历山大今天死了，那他明天或者后天是不会活过来的。”同样，在我看来，如果某人在愤怒的驱使下，选择鲁莽地走向复仇之路，他应该提醒自己：“今天犯了罪，明天或者后天还是有罪之身。有罪之人受到应得的惩罚晚了点并无害处，但如果执行惩罚过快，容易导致因罪行不确定冤枉好人的局面，而这在过去时常发生。”我的意思是，我们中有谁会因为一个奴隶5天或10天前烧坏了一顿佳肴或是打翻了桌子或是服从命令慢了点，就去鞭笞或是惩罚他呢？这也太令人讨厌了，但是当我们真正面对这些正在发生或是刚发生过的事情时，我们往往会变得混乱、苛刻和无情。静止的事物模糊的时候看起来会变大，愤怒同样如此。

因此，我们首先应该记住这样的事实。此外，如果在明确、稳定的理性之光照耀下，一件事物仍然看起来是糟糕的，那么毫无疑问我们可以自由地释放情绪。我们应当注意的是：不要在过后忽略或放弃惩罚，如同不要在没有食欲的时候就扔掉食物一样。当我们被愤怒充斥大脑时，最好的惩罚办法就是忽视它；当怒气烟消云散之后，不再提及这个问题。这种经历就如同懒惰的划桨者在风平浪静的时候抛锚停泊，起风的时候再冒险继续航行。面对处罚，我们总会过多地指责理性力量软弱无力，但是当愤怒呼啸而来时，我们又会不计后果地仓促应对。

关键在于，饥饿的人忙于觅食，既不饿也不渴的人忙于因果报应，这些都并无不妥。为了惩罚，他不需要愤怒，也许他需要的是一道开胃菜，他务必等待，直到远远抛开惩罚的欲望，并用理性去取而代之。亚里士多德曾写道，在他那个年代，提伦尼亚的仆人会在风笛的伴奏下受到鞭打，但是，我们不能为了图一己之快而去效仿，就如同一时受自我成就感的驱动，充满报复的渴望、享受惩罚的快感（类似动物的行径），而后又感到懊悔（像个女人一样）。相反，我们应该等到快感或悲痛了无踪迹，理性之光显现，在根本不受怒气驱动的情况下进行反击。

无论如何，显然没有治疗愤怒的良方，但是可以找到避免因愤怒而犯错的方法（如谢洛尼莫斯所说，尽管过度膨胀的发怒是发烧的征兆，但是抑制这种膨胀可以减轻发烧的症状）。我试着观察愤怒事实上是如何产生的，这时，我发现，尽管不同的人有不同的触发愤怒的原因，但是几乎每个人都认为，这些原因受到了轻视或者忽略。接下来，我们应当把所有惯常行为归因于无知、必须、情绪波动或偶然事件，并尽可能拉大任何特定行动与轻视或傲慢之间的距离，从而帮助那些试图避开愤怒的人。正如索福克勒斯所言：“我的主啊，不幸的人发现，即使是他们天生固有的才智也不具有稳定性，放过他们吧。”阿伽门农把他偷走女俘布里塞伊斯的罪行归因于他被魔鬼附身，还说：“我会作出补偿，用大量礼物补偿你。”

引用这些例子的意义在于表明，如果一个人从心里藐视另一个人，那他是不会对他产生兴趣的。犯了错的人如果处于明显被羞辱的卑微状态，那他也会放弃任何藐视别人的想法，但是，任何一个愤怒的人都不应该等到这些发生，而应该坚持像提奥奇尼斯一样。当有人对他说“奥奇尼斯，他们在嘲笑你”时，他回答：“我并没有感觉到被嘲笑。”因此，愤怒的时候不要去想自己是被轻视了，宁愿以自己因软弱、性急、懒惰、吝啬、年老或是年少无知而犯错为由去藐视对方。

我们与仆人和朋友的关系必须完全消除这种印象，因为对我们而言，无能为力和无效的鄙夷在他们对待我们的态度上根本不起作用：假如我们公平地对待仆人，仆人会视我们是友善的；假如我们对朋友情深意切，他们也会视我们为朋友。但是，事实上，由于我们往往自认为被他人所厌恶痛恨，所以不仅对待妻子、仆人和朋友严厉苛刻，而且同样的想法往往给我们带来怒气冲天，导致与旅馆老板、船员、喝醉的赶骡人等发生冲突，或是对冲自己吠叫的狗、撞到自己的驴发脾气。我们这种行为就如同想要殴打赶驴人的人一样，当赶驴人大叫：“我是雅典人，”他就对驴说，“但是，你不是”，然后拳头如雨点般落到驴身上。

如今，因关注自身利益和永不满足，再加上奢华而令人疲倦的生活方式，我们逐渐在心里积累了持久不变的怨愤，伴随着奢华与软弱，那种持续不断的愤怒感逐渐在人们的思想意识中蜂拥而生。可见，受自我适应环境的能力所限，除了拥有一份从容的快乐和简单的生活方式，再没有能促使我们善待仆人、妻子和朋友的更好的方法了。另一方面，“如果谁的食物烤焦了，煮透了，或者不够熟、熟透了或者半熟，这种不满都会导致他吹毛求疵。”如果喝不到加冰的饮料、吃不到现烤的面包、拿不到一点儿用没有花纹的陶制盘子盛的食物、不能睡在床垫上（除非它能像海浪一样鼓起来）；如果总是鞭打或殴打餐桌侍者，催促他们快点，让他们跑起来、闹哄哄的、大汗淋漓，就好像他们是在卖治疗脓肿的膏药—任何这样的人都是被一种不稳定、吹毛求疵、抱怨的生活方式所奴役，并且没有意识到他正在创造这些形成他坏脾气的原材料和土壤。因为欲望越少，失望就越少，所以我们必须以一种简单的方式来培养我们的性情，使我们能够自我满足，从而更容易获得快乐。

我们应该以食物为出发点：安静地品尝手头的食物不是什么难事，不要焦虑地来回走动或取过量的食物，这会给我们自己和朋友的食物中强加入一种令人非常不快的调味料—愤怒。如果因为某种食物烧焦了、熏黑了、盐放少了，或是面包冷了，使得侍者或是妻子受到斥责与责骂，这顿饭就不可能有一点点快乐而言。阿凯西劳斯家有一次来了一些客人，他邀请朋友们共进晚餐，但是由于仆人忘了买面包，一些客人发出的尖叫声大得足以把墙震出缝来！不过阿凯西劳斯依然微笑着说：“非常棒，有知识素养的人喜欢这种酒会！”

苏格拉底有一次从摔跤学校把尤苏戴莫斯带回家，妻子粘西比对他们大发雷霆，辱骂他们，还掀翻了桌子。尤苏戴莫斯非常难过，起身准备离开，而苏格拉底说：“有天我们去你家的时候，一只母鸡飞了进来做了同样的事情，我们并没有生气啊，是不是？”

我们应该用微笑和情感友好地欢迎朋友—对仆人也不要总皱着眉头或是让他们觉得害怕和惶恐。我们还应该要求自己乐于使用任何家居用品，不要有什么特殊的偏好。有些人（听说包括马略）偏爱特殊的高脚酒杯，即使有很多别的酒杯，也拒绝用来喝酒；还有些人钟情于某一种样式的油瓶和刮身板胜过其他品种。一旦这些特殊的物品损坏或是丢失，他们会很难忍受，往往会诉诸惩罚。所以如果愤怒是你性格的弱点，最好是减少对那些诸如杯子、戒指、奇石等稀有罕见物品的偏好，因为一旦失去它们，会比失去普通、日常的物品使人不安得多。因此，当尼禄制造了一个绝顶漂亮和奢华的八角形帐篷时，塞内加说：“你已经使自己成了一个贫民，因为这个帐篷如果失去将无可复制、无法复原。”事实确实如此，尼禄的船沉没时，他也失去了这个帐篷，只是他记住了塞内加的话，没有为此过于郁闷。

不去刻意追求过多世俗之事的细节，就不会小题大做，对仆人就会变得温和亲切。一个人如果能够对仆人温和亲切，显然也会对朋友和家人和蔼亲切。值得注意的是，当奴隶被卖之后，首先他会试着去了解他的新主人是否脾气很大，而不是去了解主人是否迷信或是虚荣。事实上，一旦怒火中烧，丈夫难以忍受妻子感情淡漠，妻子则难以忍受丈夫的强烈情绪，朋友也会难以忍受彼此之间的亲密，通常情况下确实如此。因此，面对愤怒，不仅婚姻，就连友情也会变得不堪一击。而一旦愤怒消散，醉酒也不会成为一种负担。酒神狄俄尼索斯的魔杖能够对任何酒醉之人施予足够严厉的惩罚，除非愤怒之情闯入，将冷酷疯癫而不是欢欣喜悦注入酒精，在这种情况下，人们受到的惩罚要大得多。安提库拉治愈了简单的精神错乱，但是疯狂和愤怒的结合则是悲剧和神话的材料。

我们应该在快乐的时候减少愤怒，因为它会让友善变成敌意；我们应该在讨论的时候减少愤怒，因为它会使关于爱情的讨论变成争吵；我们应该在决策的时候减少愤怒，因为它会给权威增添几分傲慢；我们应该在教学的时候减少愤怒，因为它会逐渐给受教者灌输一种信任感缺失和对理性的厌恶；当我们成功时，不要有愤怒，因为它会引发嫉妒；当我们失败时，不要有愤怒，因为它容易导致和怜悯自己的人发生冲突从而损伤他人的同情心。普里阿摩斯就是这样的例子，他叫道：“滚开，你这卑鄙小人，管好你自己的事情，别来打扰我！”

反之，容易满足是一种帮助，一种点缀，或一份喜悦，其温和的特质可以克制各种愤怒和不满。以欧几里得为例。他弟弟结束争吵时说：“如果这是我能做的最后一件事，我会向你报仇。”欧几里得回答：“如果这是我能做的最后一件事，我会说服你。”这个回答迅速使弟弟改变了主意。波利门有次被一个爱好奇石、沉迷于昂贵指环的人咒骂，他未作任何回应，反而仔细端详此人的一个指环，此人很高兴，说：“波利门，如果你在阳光下而不是这里端详这个指环，将给你留下更好的印象。”

有一次，艾瑞斯迪帕斯生埃斯基涅斯的气，有人问：“埃斯基涅斯怎么了啊？艾瑞斯迪帕斯，你们的友谊呢？”他回答：“友谊睡着了，但我会叫醒它。”于是他去问埃斯基涅斯：“你是不是觉得我完全没机会、没希望了？这就是你不责备我的原因吗？”埃斯基涅斯回答他：“鉴于你在所有方面都完全胜过我，所以你是第一个知道该做什么的人，这一点儿也不令人惊讶。”

有人说：“如果一个新生儿用他的小手抚摸一只长着长鬃毛的野猪，可能比任何大力士更容易让它拜倒—女人也是如此。”但是，我们常常是把一些野生动物当宠物家养，一边把狼和狮子的幼崽抱在怀里，一边却在愤怒地影响下对我们的孩子、朋友和熟人表现出厌恶不喜欢；我们像野兽一样用愤怒攻击仆人和同胞，还错误地将其称为“正义的愤怒”以掩盖这种行为的实质。在我看来，这种行为和那些把精神疾病和折磨称为“先见之明”“独立自主”或者“敬重”没什么两样：我们的行为无非都是其中之一。

芝诺曾经说过种子（精子）是从组成人的特征的所有能力中提取而成的一种合成物或混合物。与之相似的是，愤怒看起来就是许多情感的种子汇集在一起而形成。它含有从疼痛、快乐以及自负中提取的成分；有恶意的沾沾自喜，并能从仇恨中得到格斗的方法。在这种意义上，愤怒的目的不再是避免自身的痛苦，反而是在摧残他人的同时也伤害了自己；同时，愤怒的成分之一还有一种最令人讨厌的欲望的表达形式，也就是伤害他人的一种渴望。我们走近一个无赖的家时，听到一个女孩在拂晓时分吹奏的笛声，映入我们眼帘的是“洒落的酒和撕碎的花环”，还有门口喝醉的仆人。可是，伤害他人的欲望是愤怒的一部分，这样的事实解释了为什么会在易怒的人脸上、在他们仆人的文身与镣铐上看到明显的残忍的迹象。发怒的人的嚎叫、被鞭打的管家和双手被绑起来的女仆的哭泣，是房子里出现的唯一持续的声音。这一切的结果就是，对于那些能看清参透这种伤害他人的欲望以及这种伴随着疼痛的愉悦感的人而言，愤怒实在是很可怜的一件事。

不管怎么样，任何本来出于真正的、正义的愤慨而变得习惯性易怒的人，必须使自己摆脱愤怒中过分的、不可调和的部分，连同对所遇之人的自负之气。当发生误把坏人当好人，或是遭到本以为是朋友的人的斥责或批评时，这种自负便成了加剧愤怒的主要原因。就我自身情况而言，我确信你了解我是多么出于本性而倾向于认可并信任他人，但就如同迈出一步之后就再无退路一样：我越是下决心要友善，就越容易犯错误，越容易受到伤害。今后，我或许不会削减这种对朋友的情感和热忱，但是我会用柏拉图的话来提醒自己要去抑制这种自负。由于数学家希里康本身就是一个变化无常的人，所以柏拉图对他的赞赏就是这种表达方式。他声称警惕在他所在城市长大的人是正确的，因为既然他们是人类或人类的后代，就有可能在任何时候出于本能表现出内在的弱点。

然而，索福克勒斯关于“人性中大多数可鄙的方面都将在调查研究中被发现”的论断似乎过于武断并具有局限性，但是，这种断言中悲观、吹毛求疵的论调会使我们不再那么易怒，不再那么容易发生破坏性的后果。我是说，对于我们而言，这或许是一种意想不到的、难以预见的结果。我们应该借用阿那克萨戈拉格言中总结的做法（如帕奈提乌在第一点中所言）：他的儿子去世后，他说：“我知道我养育的只是一个凡人。”而且，每当我们要被别人的错误激怒时，我们应该自我批评，并告诉自己：“我知道我买的奴隶不会是绝顶聪明的”“我理解朋友不可能是完美的，”或者“我想妻子也只是个女人而已。”如果有人不断重复柏拉图的话，“难道我不也是那样吗？”他将会对内在想法而非外在行为进行思考，谨慎地中断抱怨，并且当他领会到自己也需要更多的宽容时，他将不再把大量义愤强加给他人。但是事实上，我们还是会愤怒、会痛斥，会听起来像阿里司提戴斯和加图一样：“不要偷东西！”“不要说谎！”“怎么这么懒散？”最可鄙的事情在于我们往往因为生气，却又在狂怒之下惩罚了他人；往往因为他人在愤怒中犯下的错误又用愤怒的方式去惩罚他。我们没有像医生一样“用良口苦药排出苦的胆汁”，而是加剧了事态的进一步恶化。

在记住上述需考虑的事情的同时，我还试着削减自己的好奇心。我是说，想知道所有事情的每一个细节，想调查了解奴隶的每一项工作、朋友的每一项活动、儿子的每一项娱乐、妻子的每一句私语—这些都会导致每天一个接一个的愤怒无数次爆发，反过来这又会加剧日常生活中的不满和阴霾。尽管欧里庇得斯认为“当事态变得失去控制，上帝就会介入，只留下一些不重要的事情让人们去冒险”的观点是正确的，但我仍然认为一个明智的人不应该为不重要的事情去冒险，而是应该忽视这些不重要的事情。他应该信任自己的妻子并让她去做一些事情，应该信任仆人、信任朋友并让他们去做另外一些事情（就像统治者信任并使用监督者、会计师以及管理者一样）。而他自己，应该凭着理性，去承担一些更重要、影响更深远的事情。正如微小的笔迹也会引起关注一样，过度紧张于一些不重要的琐碎之事也会激怒、扰乱人的脾气，一旦有更重要的事情危在旦夕，这种养成的习惯是百害而无一利的。

总而言之，我开始相信恩贝多克利的格言“奉行斋戒，远离罪恶”是至关重要和鼓舞人心的。此外，不仅由于这是适当的，且因为它们不是无关紧要的实践哲学，于是，我开始在日常生活中，以虔诚之心履行这种誓言，如通过自制表达对神的敬重。要自制一年不受到性和酒精的玷污，或是自我约束在某一段指定的时期内不撒谎，或是通过自省，保证无论是漫不经心还是在重要时刻都讲实话。

然后，我把自己的承诺和这一切相比较，发现它就如同为上帝所青睐、如同宗教般神圣。我的承诺开始时，相当于几天不饮酒—花几天时间克制怒气，这样做就如同在奠酒仪式上我倒的是水或蜜而不是酒，然后1个月、2个月，一直坚持这样做……这样，随着自我约束时间的逐渐延长，通过用自制力关注自己的行为，要求自己保持冷静沉着—一种神圣的沉默，并且不为邪恶的语言、异常的举动和行为所玷污，我的容忍能力也不断得到增强。为了一种数量上不大、性质上令人讨厌的快乐形式，情绪往往会导致大量精神上的混乱，还会产生最可鄙的悔恨之心。众所周知，对于那些只是偶然变得善良、体谅、无恶意，却不曾真正拥有这些品质的人，这种冷静、沉稳、宽厚是毫无用处的，我想这就是（在上帝的帮助下）我的经历往往能阐明这些观点内涵所在的原因。

论知足

摘自普鲁塔克写给帕齐的信。

希望你收到此信时，一切安好。不久前，我收到你的来信，信中，你建议我为你写一些关于知足、关于《提马亚斯》中需要仔细解读的段落的一些东西。几乎在同一时间，我们的朋友厄洛斯因为收到一封来自著名的丰达努斯的信，突然发觉他必须航行去罗马；通常，丰达努斯会催促他快点去。一方面，我没有足够的时间掌握你让我写作的主题；另一方面，我不愿意厄洛斯离开这里到你那儿时，你却发现他两手空空。因此，我阅读了笔记本里那些实际上是为我自己所写的、关于知足这一主题的笔记。我认为你想从这封信中得到实际的帮助，而不是一篇构思精美的演讲稿。我为你感到高兴的是，尽管你有位高权重的朋友，尽管作为一名政治演说家，你声誉卓著，但是你不曾有过墨洛普斯的悲惨经历：就他而言，“民众的奉承使他疯狂”并产生了异常行为，但事实并非如此。不，你已经很用心关注别人常常对你说的话：“痛风不会因一双显贵的鞋子而减轻，甲沟炎不会因为昂贵的指环而缓和，偏头疼也不会因为一顶王冠而缓解。”财产、声望和政治上的权力究竟如何有助于拥有一种免受痛苦的精神和一份像池水一样平静的生活？除非对财产、声望和政治权力的占有和使用是令人愉快的，否则，如果这一切正在失去，没有人会因此而感到遗憾。在许多试图超越界限的场合，除了理性通常能迅速抑制—并且慎重行事—头脑中情绪化的、不理智的部分，还有什么能确保它不会泛滥或是不会偏离正常轨道？

色诺芬建议我们在繁荣兴旺的年代记住和感谢诸神，从而在我们有需要的时候，就可以满怀信心地向他们祈求，因为我们知道他们是仁慈和友好的。理性的论据在帮助我们抵制情绪时没有什么不同：任何人在任何意义上都应该在情绪被激起之前充分注意，为有效防御作足准备，从而获得更多的惠益。你很清楚，凶恶的狗会因为任何一种响亮的声音被彻底激怒，但它只会在熟悉的人面前平静下来；思想情绪在被过分刺激时也很难有效控制，除非理性论据早已存在、由来已久并且烂熟于心，激动的情绪才能得到有效抑制。

“忙于公私事务的人是不可能感到满足的”，这句话不管是谁说的，它首先使得知足成了一件昂贵的商品，如果它的价格是不作为。这就好像他对每个病人都开了同样的处方，写着“可怜的人儿，好好躺在床上休息吧”。然而事实上，不活动的状态对治疗麻木的身体是不利的，就如同精神病学方面，懒惰、软弱或是背叛朋友、家庭和国家，同样对消除心中的焦虑和悲伤不起作用。

不繁忙的人就会知足的说法也不正确。这就像是说女人因为通常只忙于家庭琐事，就会比男人更容易知足。事实上，虽然（用赫西奥德的话说）“北风不会侵袭一名年轻女子柔弱的身体”，但是悲伤、困扰和忧愁会在嫉妒、迷信、野心以及无数虚幻信仰的作用下慢慢渗入她的体内。拉厄耳忒斯花了20年时间使自己远离文明社会，“只有一位老妇人照顾他，为他做饭、端茶倒水”。尽管他避开了故乡、家庭和王国，可他这种无聊慵懒的状态还是使得痛苦成了他长期的亲密伙伴。不过，绝对的不作为在有的时候也有可能诱发不满。举个例子，“珀琉斯的儿子，宙斯的后代，快步如飞的阿喀琉斯，就总是坐在他船头尖利的船上，从不去参加能给人带来荣誉的集会，也不去参加战争，只是带着一颗渴望的心静静地坐在那里为战争哭泣”。这种极度悲伤的情绪使得他告诉自己：“我坐在我的船上，对世界而言是一种没有意义的负担。”

因此，连伊壁鸠鲁也认为安定平静的生活是不可取的；他说，想要身份和名声的人应当顺应其本性，参与政治和公共生活，因为他们天生就更容易失去平衡，容易被无为的状态伤害—未能实现愿望而受到伤害。要他向无法安定生活的人而不是向有才干的人推崇公共生活是荒谬的。满足与否的界限不在于个人活动的频繁与否，而是应该通过善恶来界定：不去做善事就和前面已经说过的犯下恶行一样让人生厌和恼火。

有些人认为，免于痛苦的状态存在于一种特别的生活方式—比如耕作、独身或是拥有王权。米南德的话对他们可以说是一种警醒：“法尼阿斯，我曾经以为富有的人因为没有外债，所以不会在夜间叹息，不会辗转反侧难以入睡，也不会发出‘我多可怜’的呻吟。我曾经以为他们能够睡一个舒适、平静的好觉。”他继续解释道，以他的经验，即便是富人也会与穷人一样经历痛苦，然后他说，“悲伤在某种程度上与生活相关吗？它与奢侈的生活相伴而生，离不开地位声望，随着贫困老去。”

想想那些害怕航海和晕船的人吧：他们心想，如果能够把小艇换成商船，再把商船换成战舰，航行就会变得轻松得多；但这是行不通的，因为他们仍有晕船的心理负担和恐惧感。这就类似于变换一种生活方式，它并没有从根本上消除使人痛苦和不安的因素，它们只是一种超现实的、缺乏辨识力的行为，无法也不知道如何让人们正确利用当下的环境去行事。这些问题如风暴一般困扰着富人和穷人，使已婚和单身人士都感到烦恼。它们促使人们逃避公共生活，结果发现安静的生活令人无法忍受；它们还促使人们去追求政治上的提拔，一旦得到却又深感不幸。“无助的状态会使病人有很多怨气”：妻子惹恼他们，他们对医生抱怨，对病床不满意，“有朋友探望是麻烦事，朋友不来探望又很无礼”，伊翁如是说。但是病痛消失之后，性情就会变得混合多样，健康的来临使得所有事物都变得美好愉悦。从这个意义上说，昨天还讨厌鸡蛋、蛋糕以及全麦面包的人，今天就有可能乐意就着橄榄和芥菜籽吃粗粮面包。

理性会带来态度的转变，在任何生活方式下都会带来一种满足感。一方面，亚历山大曾经在听阿那克萨库斯关于存在无限数量的世界的讲座时流泪。他的朋友问他怎么了，他说：“如果真的存在无限数量的世界，而我连一个都还没有掌控，难道你不认为值得流泪吗？”另一方面，克里特斯带着他的箱子和旧斗篷，像一直在度假一样把整个生命都用在讲笑话上。此外，阿伽门农曾被作为一名国王肩负的过多责任所困扰—“你会认出阿伽门农，阿特柔斯的儿子，宙斯挑选他承担恒久的艰苦工作”—但是，第欧根尼待价而沽时，他躺在地上戏弄拍卖师，并拒绝起来，还用嘲弄的语气大笑道：“想象它是一条你要卖的鱼吧！”再者，苏格拉底在狱中还一直和同伴们讨论哲学，但法厄同触到了天堂的高度却哭了，因为没有人将他父亲的马匹和战车给他。

鞋会随着脚的弧度弯曲，反过来说则不成立。同样，我们言语中蕴含的性格塑造着生命。我的意思是，了解什么是最好的生活并且选择这种生活就会感到愉悦的见解是错误的，理性的智慧才会使你拥有最好的、最快乐的生活。由此可见，我们应该净化产生满足的精神源泉。假如，我们不滥用外在的物质世界，那么我们将会发现它们与我们是和谐的、一致的。“没有必要因个人处境而生气，因为它完全是无关紧要的；但是成功只会属于那些能正确对待所处环境的人。”

柏拉图把生命比作掷骰子的游戏，重要的是不仅要掷得合适，还要充分利用投掷的任何结果。就我们的情况而言，我们无法控制骰子的投掷也许没错，但是如果我们是明智的，就会合理利用命运赋予我们的财富，并且在每个情况发生时把财富分配到相应的地方，如果分配得当，我们就可以实现利益最大化，如果这种分配不受欢迎，我们也能把损害降到最小。身体疾病会使人既无法耐寒也无法受热，那些浑浑噩噩度过一生的人也如此。在某种意义上，他们在运气好的时候狂喜，运气不好的时候悲伤，也就等于说好运和厄运都会使他们打破平衡。更确切地说，不管当他们遭遇到了好运或是厄运，都会失去自我平衡；当他们遇到任何一件可能称为好的事情也会发生同样的故事。无神论者提奥多鲁斯常说，他用右手发讲稿，但是听众却用左手接住讲稿；一个未受过教育的人，面临一个适当的、顺手的机会时，往往只能笨拙地或是用左手去抓，看起来就像个傻子。麝香草，一种最辛辣、最干燥的植物，能给蜜蜂提供蜜；同样，聪明人总能从最严峻险恶的处境中找到最合适、对自己最有用的事情。

那么，应该实施和追求的首要事情是用石头击中了后母而未击中狗的人所表现出来的态度：“那也不是一件坏事！”他说。改变机遇是可能的，所以机遇不再不受欢迎。第欧根尼被流放，“也不是一件坏事”，因为他从此开始了哲学研究。基提翁的芝诺的商船队仅仅剩下了一艘船，但当他获悉就连这一艘船也失去了、所有货物都沉没了的时候，他说：“感谢命运，驱使我穿上了一个褴褛的斗篷。”

为何我们不能以同样的方式行事？你没有得到你所追求的公共职务吗？那你可以住在乡下专注于自己的小买卖了。你向有权的人讨欢心被拒绝了吗？那你现在可以拥有没有危险和麻烦的生活了啊。你又一次开始热衷于世间的事务和烦扰了吗？呃，用品达的话来说：名望和尊重与权力相结合时，能够使“工作变得舒心愉快，使劳动不再辛苦”，与之相比，“温水让身体放松的程度就不那么重要了”。当谎言和恶意中伤弥漫在你周围，你是否面临痛苦和侮辱？如同柏拉图受友情的驱使为狄俄尼索斯效力一样，这场随之而来的暴风也会把你吹向缪斯女神和研究院。

接下来有关知足的另一重要方面是对名人的思考。他们是如何做到完全不受所处环境的影响的呢？比如，没有孩子是你面临的问题吗？看看罗马的君王，没有一个人有儿子能继承他们的王位。你在为当下的贫困而负担沉重吗？那么你宁愿成为愚笨的皮奥夏人而不是伊巴密浓达一样的将军吗？宁愿成为任何一个罗马人而不是法布里希奥斯吗？“可是我的妻子被人勾引了！”那么，你难道没有读过特尔斐的铭文吗：“为水和土的主—埃杰斯所立”。难道你没听说他的妻子泰密娅同亚西比德私通，并且压低声音对女佣说她常常称她的孩子为亚西比德吗？但是这一切仍然没有阻碍埃杰斯成为他那个时代最著名、最重要的希腊人。再举个例子，斯提尔波女儿的放荡影响了他拥有一份比任何同辈哲学家更悠闲的生活吗？事实上，当梅特克勒斯告诉斯提尔波他女儿的所作所为时，斯提尔波说：“这是我的过错还是她的过错呢？”梅特克勒斯说：“是她的过错，却是你的不幸。”“你的意思是？”斯提尔波问，“过错难道不是一种失误吗？”“当然是。”梅特克勒斯说。“那么一个失误的人难道不也在遭遇挫折吗？”斯提尔波继续问。梅特克勒斯表示同意。“那么遭遇挫折的人不也在遭受不幸吗？”斯提尔波最后说。这种冷静、哲学式的辩论表明，愤世嫉俗的中伤只是虚张声势的吠叫声而已。

尽管如此，大部分人仍然会被敌人以及朋友或亲人的错误伤害或激怒。我的意思是，傲慢、易怒、恶意、怨恨、妒忌和充满敌意的人本身不仅饱受折磨，而且会干扰或惹怒那些缺乏理智的人—无疑，邻居的急性子、熟人的坏脾气、公共管理者的不公正也是如此。我想你也不会因这些缺点免受苦恼。就像索福克勒斯的医生用“苦药冲洗排掉苦胆汁”一样，你会用愤怒和痛苦对这种情绪作出反应，但是这是不理智的，因为你受托和从事的公共事务由那些性格不够坦率、脾气不够好的人管理，就像外表精美的工具反而容易有锯齿形缺口或者弯曲。因此，无论如何你也不应该把它看成是一件容易的事，要想到理清这些事务是你分内之事。不管怎样，如果你像医生将拔牙器和手术钳用于合适的场合—当情况允许时展现你宽容和谦虚的自我，那么你会为自己的态度产生一种愉悦感，并将战胜因别人不令人满意和不公正行为而产生的痛苦情绪；你将把它们视为（狗的吠叫）一样的自然现象；不再让别人的错误不自觉地影响到自己，不让所有这些痛苦和烦恼渗入你性格弱点的低洼地带。

有些哲学家甚至是带着怜悯之心吹毛求疵。对一些运气不好的人，认为帮助其所遇到的人是对的，而分担他们的忧虑或是屈服于烦恼是不对的。更重要的是，当我们意识到自己的缺点和不完美时，他们也不允许我们不满或沮丧，反而告诉我们不要悲伤，而应该试着解决问题，这才是正确而恰当的。然后，你应该考虑到，因为与我们有关联的每个人、我们遇到的每个过客并不都是公正和善的，我们就去纵容自己发脾气和易怒，这是多么不合逻辑啊。

不，我亲爱的帕齐，我们谴责和担心所遇到的人的不公正行为只会在某种程度上，而不是在通常意义上影响到我们，你必须确定这不是自欺欺人，换言之，你必须确定我们不是受私心所驱使，而是出于对不良行为的憎恶。关键在于，如果我们过度地被公共生活所困扰，有一种莫须有的冲动和目标，或者存在毫无理由的厌恶和排斥，那么，这会使得我们对他人失去信任感并因此而感到愤怒，因为我们会认为是他们给我们造成了损失和意外。高度的满足感和冷静的心态是那些能够不焦躁、不烦恼地应对处理公共生活的人们所具备的一种特质。

记住这一点，现在让我们回到环境这一问题。当我们发烧了，任何事物尝起来都是苦的、不合意的，但是，一旦我们看见别人对同样的食物很喜欢，我们就会停止对这些食物饮品的埋怨，开始归咎于自己的病痛。同样，如果看见别人对某种处境欣然接受而不会感到不安，我们也会停止对同样处境的抱怨，也不会满腹牢骚了。因此，当令人讨厌的情况发生时，有益于产生满足感的做法是：不要无视那些我们拥有的高兴和美好的事情，并且通过协调处理应对，使生活中的积极因素掩盖那些糟糕事情的刺眼光芒。当下的情况是：尽管当我们的眼睛被过于耀眼的事物所损伤，我们会转移视线用花草的缤纷颜色来缓解；但是我们对心灵的治疗却往往大相径庭：我们竭力让它看见伤害它的方方面面，迫使它用那些令人不快的事情占据思想，几乎极端地将其与积极因素撕裂开来。对于喜欢搬弄是非的人，可以将问题转到这样的情境中妥善处理：“你这个不怀好意的人，为什么这么快发现别人的缺点，却忽视了自己的缺点呢？”因此，我们可以这样问：朋友，为什么你总是过度地专注于自己的缺点并时常使其更清晰、更显眼，而不去用心思考你所拥有的美好事物呢？拔火罐是把肉体里最糟糕的部分拔出来，同样，你也专注于自己性格中非常不好的部分上。你变得和那个卖酒的希俄斯岛人差不多，他常常向别人出售大量的优质葡萄酒，但自己吃饭时，总是品尝各种葡萄酒，直到他找到一种带酸味儿的酒；当有人问他的一个仆人：你的主人在干什么？仆人回答：“吹毛求疵。”

事实上，大多数人都会在生活中绕开好的、令人耳目一新的事物，直接寻找那些煞风景的、糟糕的部分。但是亚里斯提卜却不一样：他善于放松心情，（想象自己处在一个天平上）让自己翘起来，朝自己好的方面发展。无论如何，他曾经失去过一处好房产，很多人毫无诚意地向他表示难过和同情。他问其中一个人：“你不是只有一小块土地吗？而我仍然还有3处农场。”那个家伙说：“是的。”亚里斯提卜说：“那么，难道不是我应该向你表示遗憾吗？为什么倒过来了？”这个事情的关键点在于，不为所拥有的感到开心而为失去的感到烦恼是很愚蠢的；否则，我们的行径就如同小孩子因失去众多玩具中的一个而大哭、尖叫并且扔掉其余的玩具一样。同理，如果我们被命运击痛一次，我们的不满和怨气就会使我们失去其他一切有益于我们的事物。

有人也许会问：“但是说来什么是我们拥有的或是未拥有的呢？”名声、财产、婚姻、好友—这些是人们所拥有的东西。当塔尔苏斯的安提帕特快要死的时候，他累加了一生中所发生的所有好事情，其中甚至还包括从西里西亚到雅典的一次简单旅行。而且，我们不可忽视和他人共同分享的所有事情，好好重视它们，要感恩于我们可以拥有生命和健康；感恩于可以漫步在这个世界；感恩于无论是国内还是国外都没有战争；感恩于不管是选择耕田还是航海旅行都无所惧怕；感恩于从演讲和政治到平静、怠惰的生活都能最大可能地向我们开放。如果假想我们不曾拥有这些，并且经常自我提醒病人多么渴望健康、战乱中的人们多么渴望和平、一个生活在大城市的不起眼的陌生人多么渴望获得名声和朋友，还提醒自己失去曾经拥有的一切是多么的痛苦，那么我们的满足感会不断增强。如果我们这样做，就不会等到失去曾经拥有的事情，才会高度重视和评价它们；也不会在仍然拥有的时候将其完全忽视。我的意思是说，事实上我们不拥有某事并不能增加其价值；所以不要迫切求取，不要害怕失去而常常颤抖流泪，仿佛这些事物非常重要似的；也不应该在拥有这些东西时不理会或是忽视它们，视它们犹如毫无价值。相反，如果拥有了它们，应该首先尽情享用并从中获益，这样，一旦失去，我们就能很镇定平静地接受。阿凯西劳斯常常指出，尽管大部分人都认为用头脑去探索，用眼睛去审视他人的诗歌、绘画、雕塑的每个微小细节是一种责任，但是他们忘了，他们自己的生活能提供大量使人愉悦的方方面面。他们只是不断地关注别人，对别人的地位和财富留下印象，就如同奸夫都是被别人的妻子所吸引，却轻视和贬低自己及自己所拥有的东西。

然而，对于满足而言，另一个重要的方面就是尽最大可能限制对自己或是与自己相关的事情的审视，抑或，认为他人并不比自己富有。应该避免的是一味向富人看齐，尽管这是我们惯常的做法。例如，犯人羡慕已经被释放的人，被释放了的人羡慕一直自由的人，一直自由的人又会羡慕有公民身份的人，有公民身份的人反过来又会羡慕有钱人，有钱人又羡慕地方官员，官员羡慕统治者—因为统治者大多渴望能够呼风唤雨—统治者羡慕上帝。结果，由于他们永远得不到那些无法企及的事情，所以对身边的任何事情也都失去了感恩之心。“我对黄金满载的古阿斯的财富没什么兴趣，我从不会被嫉妒心所控制，不会去试图模仿众神，也不会渴望拥有一个王国，我不会把目光投向如此缥缈的风景。”

也许有人会说：“因为这是萨索斯岛人的言论，”可是，还有一些外地人—如来自希俄斯岛、加纳提亚或比提尼亚的人，他们为在同胞中获取一部分地位或权力感到并不满足。他们因为没有穿上贵族的袍服而哭泣；如果成了贵族，会因为没有掌握对罗马的军事控制权而哭泣；如果掌握了军事控制权，又会因为他们不是执政官而哭泣；如果成了执政官，还会因为没有在宣告时名列第一而哭泣。这些借口对财富的获得是徒劳的，所以只能说这一切是一种自我苦修或者是自作自受的一种惩罚。另一方面，任何心智健全的人都能发现，太阳看到成千上万的人“享受着在广阔土地上的劳作”而没有陷入沮丧和失望，即使有人比他们更加出名和富有。有如此多的人的生命要比成千上万的人更加完美，所以他们继续走自己的路，欢庆自己拥有的命运和生活。

奥运会上不可能选择对手并以此获取胜利，但是生命中确实会出现感受更好生活状况的机会—被羡慕而不是羡慕别人，当然，除非是百手巨人布里亚柔斯或者大力英雄赫拉克勒斯和自己互斗！所以，当你发现自己被一个坐在轿车里忘我入神的人表现出的明显优越感吓住时，务必要俯视他和那些带他离开的人们；当你发现自己妒忌薛西斯，就像赫勒斯庞特人那样，在薛西斯的浮桥横跨的著名地点，确信你也看到了他被鞭子驱逐着去挖掘阿托斯圣山，以及当桥被波涛冲毁时一派支离破碎的景象；所以，如果你也能考虑到他们的想法，你会发现他们也在羡慕你的生活和处境。

苏格拉底曾听说一个朋友评论雅典物价昂贵：“希俄斯人的葡萄酒需要1迈纳，3迈纳才能买一件紫色的长袍，1科梯勒蜂蜜需要5德拉克马。”苏格拉底拉住这个朋友给他拿出一些谷粒，并告诉他：“在雅典，1欧宝可以买半hekteus—便宜”；又拿出一些橄榄：“2个青铜币可以买1公升—便宜”；又拿出一些简易斗篷：“10德拉克马可以买到—雅典的东西便宜。”所以当我们听到有人评论目前的个人处境很微不足道并且非常痛苦时，因为自己既不是执政官也不是总督，我们可以回答：“我们的处境并不是完全不尽人意，我们的生活也是可羡慕的，因为我们不是乞丐，不是搬运工，也不是马屁精。”

尽管如此，我们还是愚蠢地习惯关注别人的生活，而不是把注意力集中在自己身上。由于人的本性中包含大量恶意嫉妒和怨恨的成分，因此结果往往是，我们对自己成功的喜悦程度要远远低于对别人成功的愤怒程度。那么，你除了必须要看到你所羡慕和嫉妒的人所具备的辉煌、优秀的特质，还必须揭开他们表面的、代表名望的绚丽面纱，走进他们的内心，你会发现他们也有大量令人讨厌的个性及很多不愉快的事情。无论如何，皮塔克斯的所言是有教育意义的，因为他以勇气、智慧和品行享有盛名：有一次他约几个朋友一起吃饭，妻子愤怒地冲进来并掀翻了桌子，朋友们愕然，但他却说：“没有人的生命是完美的，一个人如果仅仅只有像我这样的烦恼，那他的生活已经非常美满了。”

“这个男人在公共场合是被羡慕的对象，但是当他回家打开家门，他就处于一个令人同情的状态：他的妻子完全掌控了他，对他发号施令并且不断唠叨。他有相当多的理由悲伤痛苦，然而我却不是。”很多这类烦恼都是伴随财富、名望和王权而生，但大部分人没有注意到华丽外表下隐藏的这一切。“阿特柔斯的儿子，你是幸运的—你的出生受到了命运的青睐，你注定会成功”：这种荣誉以武器、马匹、大规模的军队等外在财产的形式给予他，但是从矛盾的情绪化的哭喊声中，承担着这种空虚的名声—“克罗诺斯的儿子宙斯极度疯狂地完全囚禁了我”，“我真羡慕你，老人家，我羡慕任何一个可以保护自己免受盛名所累，而安全度过一生的人。”那么，这是另外一个我们应该牢记的问题，对待命运不要过多地吹毛求疵，不要因为羡慕身边熟人的品性，而贬低和轻视自己的拥有。

现在，对于知足这一问题，最大的阻碍就是无法使自己的欲望保持收放自如，就是说，在某种程度上，是收住欲望还是打开欲望更符合当下的形势所趋。我们因为希望反而给了欲望太多的松弛空间，当我们失败的时候，却总是责备命运多舛或是运气不好，而没有看到自己的愚蠢。我们不要把一个用犁射击、用牛捕猎野兔的人描述为不幸，也不要认为一个无法用鱼篓或是曳网捕获鹿或野猪的人遭遇了坏运气：力图做一些根本不可能的事情是愚蠢糊涂的。事实上，主要原因是自负使他们在任何情境下都野心勃勃，求胜心切，是自负使他们贪婪地想拥有一切。他们不仅渴望富有、博学、强壮、活泼、愉悦、亲近君王和国家政要，而且会因为他们的狗、马、鹌鹑和公鸡不是最好的而感到不满。

老狄俄尼索斯对成为当时最著名的统治者并不满意，然而因为他写的诗比费罗萨努斯的糟糕，又因为他在哲学讨论中没有胜过柏拉图，他勃然大怒：把费罗萨努斯囚禁在采石场，把柏拉图遣到埃伊纳岛卖为奴隶。亚历山大则不同：当他和短跑运动员克利森比赛时，发现克利森故意放慢速度时，非常生气。阿基里斯在诗中也表达得很好：开头部分他写道：“战场上，任何一个身披盔甲的亚加亚人都不是我的对手，”接着又写道，“他们在集结装配上很擅长。”当波斯人迈加比佐斯参观阿佩利斯的画室并打算展开一场关于艺术的谈话时，阿佩利斯打断了他并让他闭嘴：“只要你保持安静就行了，因为你戴的那些金银珠宝、身着的那些紫色长袍，即使是我们这里研磨颜料的小伙子都在嘲笑你的胡说八道。”

现在，虽然人们可能认为，当他们听到斯多葛学派的哲学家描述的圣人不仅只是明智的、道德的、勇敢的，而且也是一位演说家、诗人、军事指挥官，或者拥有财富或是国王时，他们认为这是在开玩笑，尽管如此，他们还是希望能得到所描述的这一切，如果得不到，他们会因此而烦恼。即便是不同的神也有各自不同的职能：有的被称为战神，有的被称为预言之神，还有的被称为财富之神；而阿佛洛狄特被宙斯授权掌管婚姻爱情，正是因为她的领地不包括任何军事事务。

问题在于，有些追求本身便不是相辅相成的，而是背道而驰的。比如说，修辞训练和科学知识的获取需要的是自由、没有压力，但是一个人要想获得政治权力以及与国王的亲近，却不能摆脱繁忙、耗时的生活状态。还有“喝酒吃肉会使身体变得健康强壮，却会使智力减退”；尽管对金钱的经常关注和留意有助于增加财富，但是对金钱的藐视和轻蔑却是形成一种人生观的重要来源。因此，不是所有的事情都适合所有人：你应该遵循神的旨意，要有自知之明，然后去做一些自然而然适合你的单一的事务；你还应该避免强行或是不合规律地迫使自己去羡慕那些不同的人在不同的时间所拥有的可供选择的生活方式。“马被套上马具用来运货，牛被装上犁用来耕田；海豚因航船驶过而以极快的速度猛冲；要想捕获野猪就必须先找到一条勇敢的猎狗。”

有人因为不能同时成为“百兽之王”的狮子和被寡妇爱抚的小马尔济斯犬而感到悲伤难过，这真是疯狂的事情。更疯狂是那些既想成为恩培多克勒、柏拉图或者德谟克利特去研究宇宙和万物本源，又想象欧福里翁有个富婆情人，或者像米迪厄斯能与亚历山大成为酒友对饮的人，这种人还羡慕伊斯美尼亚的富足、羡慕伊巴密浓达的优秀，如果不能成为他们，会感到生气和痛苦。我的意思是，跑步的运动员不会因为未赢得摔跤比赛而不满，他们只在自己的领域获得自豪感和满足感。正如索伦所说：“你已经占领了斯巴达，所以信守承诺。我们不会牺牲德行去换取财富，虽然目前是稳定的，但是在不同时期拥有财富的会是不同的人。”

当自然哲学家斯特拉图获知墨涅德摩斯的学生已经远远胜过他之后，他说：“你还想要什么？一定有更多的人是想用水沐浴而不是想把油倒在身体上。”亚里士多德在写给安提帕特的信中说道：“事实上，亚历山大凌驾于众人之上，并没有使他成为唯一能真实感受到自豪的人：任何认为神才是符合公认准则的人也会拥有同样多的权利。”问题在于，就像这些故事里提到的，重视自我拥有的人不会因为发现别人也同样拥有而感到烦恼。目前的情况是，尽管我们不指望一棵葡萄树能结出无花果，一棵橄榄树能长出葡萄，但是如果我们无法同时兼具富豪、学者、军事指挥家、哲学家，以及善于奉承的马屁精、守财奴或是挥霍者们身上的优质特征，我们会胁迫自己，对自己不满，还会鄙视自己匮乏的生活和不完美的生命。

此外，还会有来自于自然界的明显提示。自然界会对不同的动物赋予不同的天性：它们不会都成为食肉动物、啄食种子的动物或掘食植物根茎的动物。同样，大自然也赋予人类广泛的生活方式：“放牧、耕种、狩猎或是依海生存”。那么我们应该做的就是选择适合我们特有本性的生活方式并付出努力，不去想别人的生活；换句话说，我们不要显露出任何像赫西奥德格言中所说的类似的缺点：“陶工会嫉妒陶工，建筑工也会互相嫉妒”。我的意思是，人们不会只试图同那些相同职业或是拥有同样生活方式的人竞争；有钱人会嫉妒学者，反过来有钱人又会被名人所羡慕，同时律师会羡慕雄辩者—尽管看起来很奇怪—自由的人和贵族又会万分敬仰一出成功戏剧中快乐的喜剧演员、舞蹈演员，还有那些在皇家法院工作的公务人员。这一切会使得这些人感到痛苦，并给自己带来许多烦恼。

从人与人的不同经历中显然可以发现，每个人都有使自己产生满足感或是不满足感的能力—罐子的好坏不在于是否放在“宙斯的门槛上”，而取决于你的想法。好的事情出现时，愚蠢的人往往会视而不见，因为他们心里总是想着未来；而聪明的人却会用记忆使它们保持鲜活，即使它们已不复存在。任何事物都是在最初很短暂的时期容易得到，但是转瞬即逝，愚蠢的人因此就认为这些事物与自己没什么关系或是不属于自己。有这样一幅画，一个男人为了从地狱里爬出去不停地编织一条绳子，谁知绳子却让外面草地上的驴吃掉了。同样，大多数人往往会屈服于盲目的、徒劳的机会，但这只会耗尽他们的生命，不会留下任何结果，也不会有任何成功、快乐、轻松、互动和喜悦的瞬间。

这种遗忘使得人们无法将过去和现在视为一个整体：它把昨天和今天区分开来，好像二者是截然不同的，同样对于今天和明天也是如此，从来不发挥记忆的作用会很快导致每个当下出现的事物变得不存在。有一种学派认为：理论上，生命的不断变迁会使得每个人日复一日地发生变化；与此类似，那些不用回忆保护或是恢复过往，而是任由其一天天流逝的人们，事实上也会使自我残缺不全、空虚，并对接下来的日子悬而不决，就好像去年、近期以及昨天发生的事情都与自己没有关系，或者简言之就根本没发生过一样。

这是动摇满足感的又一个因素，但不如接下来我们必须考虑的这个因素重要。你知道停在镜子上的苍蝇是如何滑过光滑的镜面而附着在粗糙或有划痕的地方的；同样可以类比人类是如何掠过快乐、合适的事项，而陷入对不愉快的事情的回忆中。还有一个更好的类比是这样一个故事：在奥林索斯，有一个被称为“甲虫必死之地”的地方，甲虫飞进去后再也不可能活着出来：它们只能在里面周而复始地转圈圈直至死亡。同样，有人不会注意到这点，而是不断陷入糟糕的回忆却不愿意唤醒自己。

我们应该把思想看作一幅画，把所有的回忆看作各种颜色，从而突出那些明亮的、鲜艳的颜色，而把那些沮丧郁闷的记忆全部放在背景的阴影部分。我的意思是，阴暗的方方面面不可能完全根除或者消失：“世界是一个矛盾结合体，就像竖琴和琴弓”，人类社会没有简单纯粹的事情。音乐有低音符和高音符，语法有元音和辅音，对音乐的鉴赏能力以及文学写作能力不会是来自对某一个音符、某一个音标的厌恶和排斥，或者也不会来自另一个极端，但可以从中学会如何使用剧场去欣赏音乐，如何把各种音标巧妙地组合成优美的文字。万物都有对立面，就如同欧里庇得斯的诗句：“好和坏是不可分割的，但混合在一起使事情变得更好是可能的。”继续上述比喻，面对矛盾，我们不要产生不满情绪或是放弃，而应该表现得像专业的音乐家一样：如果某个人演奏得不好，他们可以通过别的好的演奏削弱不好的影响，也可以用正确的音符掩盖错误的部分。因此，我们应该让生活充满协调的音符，实现各种因素的和谐共处。

我的意思是，米南德关于“每个人从出生的那一刻起，都会有神灵的陪伴，如同优秀的向导引领你探寻生命之谜”的说法是错误的。而恩培多克勒的观点或许是正确的，他认为每个人从出生时就开始受到两种命运之神的掌控：“地球与太阳、血腥冲突与宁静和谐、美与丑、快与慢、公平真理与黑暗质疑。”既然我们承认每个人从出生起就具备了上述经历的可能，那么每个人就会天生具有矛盾性。任何人在任何意义上都会祈求更加美好，但同样也会对他人心存期待，而且从来不会采取过多的行为对待这两种对立面。首先，如伊壁鸠鲁所言：“对于未来，快乐的增多取决于减少对它的需求。”其次，对财富、名誉、权力、地位的享受感的增强取决于减少失去它们时的恐惧。从这个意义上说，对它们的强烈欲望会逐渐导致一旦失去时的强烈恐惧，因此把它们当作不过是风口上燃烧的蜡烛，减少或弱化对它们的兴趣吧。如果一个人理性地容许自己勇敢而不畏惧地面对命运，并认为：“命运的馈赠固然受欢迎，但即使好运逝去也不算什么太大的痛苦，”那么这种勇气和无畏会使得他完全享受目前的生活状态（因为他知道失去也并不是不可容忍的）。亚拉萨哥拉的儿子去世后，他声称：“我只不过是养育了一个凡人，”你可能不会为他说出这种话的气魄所驻足欣赏，但是可以从他无论面对任何命运时的态度中反映出他的这种性格—“我知道我所拥有的财富是暂时的、不牢靠的”“我知道应该把我现在的地位归功于有权力调配它们的人”“我知道我有一个好妻子，但毕竟她只是个女人，而我的朋友才是天性多变的物种—人类中的一员，如同柏拉图所言”。

关键在于，如果发生的事情是不受欢迎的，但又是意料之中的话，没有任何余地让你认为“这不是我所想象的”“这不是我的预期”或“我并不希望如此”，所以不要捶胸顿足，迅速解决当下的混乱与忧愁，回到最初的状态吧。卡尔尼亚德斯经常提醒那些从事重要事务的人们，意外是痛苦和不满的终极目标。例如，想想马其顿王国比罗马王国小多少？但是当珀尔修斯失去马其顿时，不仅他自己痛苦地抱怨命运，大家也普遍认为他绝对比其他人更倒霉和不幸；然而当埃米利乌斯（他打败了珀尔修斯）放弃了对世界上差不多所有土地和海洋的控制权时，大家一致认为他是快乐的，并因此举行了盛宴和祭神仪式。有一个原因可以很好地对此作出解释：埃米利乌斯已经得到了一种地位并且知道总有一天会传给别人，但对于珀尔修斯而言，这种失去却是意料之外的。荷马有一些关于意外发生时会怎么样的好的论点：奥德修斯的狗向他摇首摆尾时他哭了，可是面对正在啜泣的妻子他却冷漠地坐了下来；原因就在于他对妻子是一种平淡的、理性的、可预见的感情，但是当他陷入其他不可预料的情境—意外的本性将会使之表现出悲伤忧郁。

笼统地说，当不愉快的事情发生时，由于其独有的特性，必然会带来烦恼和痛苦，但是，就所关注的多数这类事情而言，其实是我们自己的思想决定和引导我们去抱怨。因此，当面临后面这一类令人厌烦的事情时，有效遵循米南德的建议总是有益的：“没有什么经历是可怕的，除非你使它可怕。”他隐隐提出了这样一个问题：举个例子，如果你的父亲不是贵族，或者你的妻子有一些风流韵事，你没能赢得奖品，或者你失去了在剧院坐在前排的权力，那么除非真正影响到了你的身体和思想，否则又有什么差别呢？这些事情的发生并不会导致一个人失去良好的身体和精神状态。关于前面所提到的看起来是由其本质导致痛苦的那一类事情—比如疾病、压力、朋友或是孩子的去世—那么可以看看欧里庇得斯的著名言论：“我说‘可怜的我啊’—但是为什么呢？我只是经历了人类所应该经历的啊。”你看，没有什么理性的论据能制止情绪的低落，就像有人提醒我们：要和所有人一样，感恩这个世界，因为有些事情我们无法避免。由于生命的真实感，这种必然性只在人类的命运中存在，但是这种肉体的真实感只是人类诸多本性的一个部分，在最权威、最重要的方面，因此人们仍然保持坚定和无所畏惧。

当德米特里厄斯俘获墨伽拉之后，他问斯提尔波是否所有东西都被掠走了，斯提尔波回答，他没有看见任何他称为“我的”东西被带走。即使钱财被盗，所有东西都从我们眼前被拿走，我们仍然还拥有一些诸如“希腊人无法拿走”的东西。因此，不要全盘贬低和轻视我们身上诸如软弱、易变、对命运绝对顺从之类的本性。相反，我们知道一个人身上的缺点和不足（和对命运的依赖）只是很小的部分，我们自己掌控着好的部分，这一部分牢牢地容纳了我们所得到的最重要的惠益—正确的信仰、学到的东西和有助于养成美德的理由—永远存在，无法消除也无法被破坏。如果我们意识到这一点，就不再会害怕未来。关于命运，就像苏格拉底对陪审员所说的（尽管他表面上是对检察官说）—阿尼图斯和迈雷托能够判他死刑，但却无法真正伤害到他。

命运也许会使人面对疾病、被剥夺财富、被毁掉与他人或是与统治者之间的亲密关系，但是命运无法使一个优秀、勇敢、有着高尚思想的人变得恶劣、胆怯、卑鄙、低俗、心胸狭窄或是充满恶意，更无法使我们丧失一种永恒的人生态度，这种态度将指引着我们的人生方向，比大海航行中的舵手更重要、更有益。面对波涛汹涌的大海和狂风，舵手往往是无能为力的，他无法做到只要需要就能停泊在安全的港口，也无法自信、无所畏惧地忍耐所发生的一切：只要他不放弃，凭借他的技术，“就能通过把船的主帆正确地收至桅杆底部而逃离地狱般黑暗的海洋”，但是当波涛翻涌而来，他只能胆战心惊地坐在那里。反过来说，一个聪慧的人却可以避免产生大多数身体方面的问题：因为他的自我控制能力、有责任感的生活规则以及适度的身体锻炼都可以将疾病消除在萌芽状态；如果出现外部感染，就像暴风雨来临般，那么，如阿斯克莱庇阿德斯所言，“他收起船帆，渡过难关”；如果一些意想不到的重大事件突然来袭，安全港口就在附近—他可以从船的缝隙中迅速游离。

你知道，不是对生命的渴望，而是对死亡的恐惧，会使无知者过多地依赖自己的身体并想牢牢抓住（他想起由于奥德修斯对卡律布迪斯的害怕使他不得以抓住了一棵无花果树的故事），“当暴风来袭，既无法停泊也不能继续航行”，他对其中一个选项不满意，对另一个选项又心存恐惧。任何一个人如果开始了解思想的本质，不管是以何种方式，并且领会到面对死亡，思想上所经历的变化或者是为了向更好的方向发展，或者至少不会变得更糟糕，那么他就不再会害怕死亡，而是作好充分的准备知足地去面对生活。但凡不仅能享受到志趣相投的愉悦这种人生最高境界，而且还能在面对一些过多的讨厌之事和与其本性格格不入之人时，做到毫不畏惧地离开，并认为“上帝会宽恕我对它们宽恕”的这种人，决不会为生活中任何事情而烦恼、生气，或被打倒。

不管是谁说“命运啊，我已经先发制人地与你抗争，并且已经消除了你的所有漏洞”，他的这种自信并不是建立在螺栓、锁以及坚固防御的基础上，而是一种可以对任何需要之人行之有效的信念。这种信念不应该引起任何程度的放弃或怀疑，而是应该带来赞赏、效仿、热忱，以及对微不足道小事的调查研究和自我检视，从而为更重要的事情作好准备，如此一来，对这一切人们无法避开、转移注意力，或是以“这可能是我所遇到的最难的事情”为由逃避。至于如果思想上自我放任，或是总以最简单轻松的路线运行，并且逃避一些令人讨厌的事情，只是夸大其中的快乐，那么结果会造就一种缺失进取心的软弱无能的现象。如果只是训练思维并竭力将其用来合理地设想自己生病、疼痛，或者被流放的情境，就会发现，在这些明显的问题和恐怖的事情中，每一件都提供了许多不现实性、表面性和不可靠性，有详细的合理的论据可以证明这一点。

即使米南德的名言“任何活着的人都不能说‘这将不会发生在我身上’”让很多人不寒而栗；但这只是因为他们没有意识到可以通过有效的训练增强张大眼睛直视命运的能力，从而避免一定程度上的痛苦；他们也不知道如何避免形成自己“软弱且未经世故”的形象，就像那些享受不到阳光，只是在众多希望中成长的人，面对任何困难时，常常会选择放弃并且不具备任何抵抗能力。不过，我们也可以像米南德那样说同样的话：“任何活着的人都不能说‘这将不会发生在我身上’”—但是要补充一句，任何活着的人都可以说“我决不会说谎、不会欺骗、不会偷窃、不会耍阴谋”，这是完全可能的。因为这是在我们操控范围内的，而且，它对是否知足这一问题的贡献也不是微不足道的，而是巨大的。因为如果不这么做，就会“使我意识到自己犯下的错误”，从而给思想打下懊悔的烙印，就像身上的伤口一样不断流血并刺痛。

你知道，尽管通过理性可以消除所有不快，但是当良知刺痛心灵，或是内心受到良心的谴责，理性自身就会产生悔恨。因为寒冷而颤抖或是因为感冒而发热要比受外部冷热环境的影响所产生的同样感觉痛苦糟糕得多。同样，忍受随机偶发事件所引发的痛苦也要容易得多，因为这种痛苦源自外部环境；但是，如果为犯下的错误而悔恨—“发生这样的事情不能怪别人，是我自己的错”，由于这是一种源于内心、源于自己的感受，因此所产生的羞愧感带来的疼痛就会让人难以忍受。这就是为什么一幢豪宅、大量财富、优越的出身，以及高职位、好口才都不可能增加生命的美好程度的原因。平静的生活只会源于未曾被坏行为、坏动机所玷污的心灵，也正是这种心灵赋予了生命宁静、清澈的特性。这样的特征是获得完美成就的源泉，它不仅使当下的活动生机勃勃、令人愉悦，带来自豪感，而且还能使过去的记忆比未来更加有意义、有安全感，如品达的诗句所述：“晚年依然记忆犹新”。卡尔尼亚德斯说过：“即使香炉被清理干净，但它释放的香味依然会维持很长时间。”这不正说明美好的行为留给聪慧心灵的印象依然是愉悦清新的吗？并且，由于快乐得到灌溉而茁壮成长，你就能够不受那些悲叹、抱怨生活、把生命当作放逐灵魂的世俗之地的人们的影响。

我很喜欢第欧根尼的妙言：曾经有一次他去斯巴达参观时，看见主人热忱积极地为节日作准备，于是他说：“把每一天都当成节日一样难道不是一个好人的标志吗？”如果我们能正确看待事物，每一天不也都是一个特别光荣的节日吗？世界是一座最高神灵的庙宇，没有什么地方比这里更适合神灵。人们以出生的方式被带到这个世界，不用去考虑那些既有的、静止的景象，而要去观察柏拉图所描述的那些可以感知的明白易懂的事物，这些神圣的事物表现为一种容器，容纳了生命的内在法则和万物之运动—太阳、月亮、星星、不断流出再生水源的河流，以及为动植物提供营养的土壤。生命是探究这些事物的开始，再没有比生命更完美的方式来赞美这些事物了；因此，生活应该充溢着满足与快乐，我们不要再犯那些通常易犯的错误，不要等到类似克罗诺斯、宙斯、雅典娜的纪念日那样的重大日子才去享受快乐，也不要只在通过给小丑或是舞者付费这种买来的娱乐中才能振奋起精神、活力四射。

此外，尽管在下列场合我们会井然有序地静静地坐下—当他加入时没有人抱怨、观看达尔菲游戏时没有人嘀咕、在克罗诺斯的纪念日也不会有人喝酒，但是，在上帝安排和指引的节日里，人们还是会因为把其余时间消耗在了对生活的抱怨、丧气和担忧中而感到羞愧。尽管人们喜欢欣赏乐器演奏出的美妙音乐和鸟儿的动人歌声，喜欢观看动物的嬉闹玩耍，而且当动物发出怒吼声、狂吠声或是看起来有攻击性的时候又会心生害怕和忐忑不安，但是，当人们发现自己的生活很古板、压抑，还会时常受到令人不悦的各种经历、事件或者焦虑的约束和限制时，他们也不愿意寻找一些方式让自己恢复或是放松。而即使当他人试图提供帮助，比如，帮助他们如何做到毫无瑕疵地面对当下的处境，帮助他们回忆过往免于承担忘恩负义之恶名，或是帮助他们无忧无虑、乐观积极地拥抱未来，他们也会拒绝所有这些建议和帮助。

In consolation to his wife

FROM PLUTARCH TO HIS WIFE. I hope this finds you well. The man you sent to give me the news of our child's death seems to have missed me during his overland journey to Athens, but I heard about it from my granddaughter when I got to Tanagra. I imagine that the burial rites are over by now, and I hope they were conducted in a way that makes the chance of your feeling distress at the burial both now and in the future as remote as possible. But if there is something you haven't yet done, even though you want to, because you are waiting to hear what I intend to do, and it is something which you think would make things easier to bear, then it will happen too, with no fuss and superstitious nonsense - not that you are at all liable to these faults.

All I ask, my dear, is that while reacting emotionally you make sure that both of us - me as well as you - remain in a stable state. I mean, the actual event is a known quantity and I can keep it within limits, but if I find your distress excessive, this will discompose me more than what has happened. Nevertheless, I was not born 'from oak or rock', as you yourself know, given that you have been my partner in bringing up so many children - all brought up with no one else's help in our own home - and I know how overjoyed you were with the birth, after four sons, of the daughter you longed for and with the fact that it gave me the opportunity to name her after you. In addition, one's love for children of that age is peculiarly acute, since the pleasure it affords is absolutely unsullied and untainted by any element of anger and criticism. Also, she was inherently wonderfully easy to please and undemanding, and the way she repaid affection with affection and was so charming was not only delightful, but also made one realize how unselfish she was. She used to encourage her wet-nurse to offer and present her breast not only to other babies, but also to her favourite playthings and toys: she was unselfishly trying to share the good things she had and the things she most enjoyed with her favourites, as if they were guests at her very own table.

However, my dear, I fail to see any reason why, when this and similar behaviour pleased us during her life, it should upset and trouble us when we recall it now. I worry about the alternative, however - that we might consign the memory of her to oblivion along with our distress. This would be to act like Clymene, who said, 'I hate the curved cornel bow! I wish there were no gymnasia!': she was always nervous about recalling her son, and avoided doing so, because distress was its companion, and it is natural to avoid anything painful. No, our daughter was the sweetest thing in the world to hug and watch and listen to, and by the same token she must remain and live on in our thoughts, and bring not just more, but a great deal more pleasure than distress - if it is plausible to expect that the arguments we have often deployed on others will help us in our hour of need - and we must not slump in dejection or shut ourselves away and so pay for those pleasures with distress that vastly outweighs it.

People who were with you also tell me, with some surprise, that you haven't adopted mourning clothes, that you didn't make yourself or your maids follow any ugly or harrowing practices and that the paraphernalia of an expensive celebration was absent from the funeral - that instead everything was conducted with discretion and in silence, and with only the essential accoutrements. It was no surprise to me, however, that you who never tricked yourself out for the theatre or a public procession, and never saw any point in extravagance even where your pleasures were concerned, maintained unaffectedness and frugality in sad circumstances.

The point is that Bacchic rites are not the only circumstances which require a decent woman to remain uncorrupted: she should equally assume that the instability and emotional disturbance which grief entails call for self-control, which is not, as is popularly supposed, the enemy of affection and love, but of mental indulgence. Affection is what we gratify by missing, valuing and remembering the dead, but the insatiable desire for grief - a desire which makes us wail and howl - is just as contemptible as hedonistic indulgence, despite the notion that it is forgivable because, although it may be contemptible, it is accompanied not by any pleasure gained from the desire, but rather by distress and pain. Could there be anything more absurd than banishing excesses of laughter and mirth, and yet allowing the floodgates of tears and lamentation, which spring from the same source as merriment, to open to their fullest extent? Or - as some husbands do - quarrelling with their wives about extravagant hair perfume and gaudy clothing, and yet submitting when they cut off their hair in mourning, dye their clothes black and adopt ugly postures when sitting and uncomfortable ones when reclining at table? Or - and this is the most irritating of all - resisting and restraining their wives if they punish their servants of either sex excessively and unfairly, and yet ignoring the vicious, harsh punishments they inflict upon themselves when they are under the influence of emotion and misfortunes which actually call for a relaxed and charitable attitude?

Our relationship, however, my dear, is such that there never has been any occasion for us to quarrel on the one score, and there never will be any occasion for us to quarrel on the other, I am sure. On the one hand, every philosopher who has spent time with us and got to know us has been impressed with the inextravagance of your clothing and make-up, and with the modesty of your lifestyle, and every one of our fellow citizens has witnessed your unaffectedness during rituals and sacrifices and at the theatre. On the other hand, you have already demonstrated in the past that you can remain stable under these circumstances, when you lost your eldest child and again when our lovely Charon left us before his time. I remember that I brought visitors with me on my journey from the coast at the news of the child's death, and that they and everyone else gathered in our house. As they subsequently told others as well, when they saw how calm and peaceful it was, they thought that nothing terrible had happened and that a baseless rumour had got out, because you had behaved so responsibly in arranging the house at a time when disarray is normally excusable, despite the fact that you had nursed him at your own breast and had endured an operation when your nipple got inflamed, which are noble acts stemming from motherly love.

It is noticeable that most mothers take their children into their arms as if they were playthings (after others have cleaned them and smartened them up), and then, if the children die, these mothers wallow in empty, indecent grief. They are not motivated by warmth of feeling, which is a reasonable and commendable emotion: their strong inclination towards shallow beliefs, plus a dash of instinctive emotion, causes outbursts of grief which are fierce, manic and unruly. Aesop was apparently aware of this: he said that when Zeus was distributing recognition among the gods, Grief asked for some as well; so Zeus allowed Grief to be acknowledged - but only by people who deliberately wanted to acknowledge it.

This is certainly what happens at the beginning: only an individual lets grief enter himself; but after a while it becomes a permanent sibling, a habitual presence, and then it doesn't leave however much one wants it to. That is why it is crucial to resist it on the threshold and not to adopt special clothing or haircuts or anything else like that, which allow it to establish a stronghold. These things challenge the mind day in and day out, make it recoil, belittle it and constrict it and imprison it, and make it unresponsive and apprehensive, as if the wearing of these clothes and the adoption of these practices out of grief cut it off from laughter and light and the sociability of the table. The consequences of this affliction are physical neglect and an aversion to oiling and bathing the body and to other aspects of the daily regimen, when exactly the opposite should happen: purely mental suffering ought to be helped by physical fitness. Mental distress abates and subsides to a great extent when it is dispersed in physical calm, as waves subside in fair weather, but if as a result of a bad regimen the body becomes sordid and foul and transmits to the mind nothing benign or beneficial, but only the harsh and unpleasant fumes of pain and distress, then even those who desire it find that recovery becomes hard to achieve. These are the kinds of disorders that take possession of the mind when it is treated so badly.

Nevertheless, I have no cause to worry about the worst and most worrying disorder which occurs in such cases - 'the invasion of malignant women', with the cries and expressions of sympathy which they use to polish and hone distress, and to prevent its being diminished either by external factors or of its own accord. For I know about the battles you recently had when you went to assist Theon's sister and defended her against the incursions of the women who came with their weeping and wailing - behaviour which is exactly the same as fighting fire with fire. I mean, when people see a friend's house on fire, then everyone contributes what he can to put it out as quickly as possible; but when that same friend's mind is on fire, they bring fuel! And although when someone has an eye infection, people don't let just anyone touch it or treat the inflammation, people who are grieving sit and let everyone who comes by prod at their running sore, so to speak, and aggravate the condition, until instead of being an insignificant itching irritation, it erupts into a seriously disagreeable affliction. Anyway, I know that you will be on your guard against this.

Please try, however, to use your mind as a vehicle for often returning to the time when this child of ours had not yet been born and we had no reason to blame fortune; and then connect that time with the present, and imagine that our circumstances are no different again. You see, my dear, we will seem to regret that our child was ever born if we find more to complain about now than in the situation before her birth. We must not erase the intervening two years from our memories, but since they brought happiness and joy, we must count them as pleasant. The good was brief, but should not therefore be regarded as a long-term bad influence; and we should not be ungrateful for what we received just because our further hopes were dashed by fortune.

The point is that a reverential attitude towards the gods and being charitable and uncomplaining with regard to fortune always yield a dividend which is both fine and enjoyable, and anyone who, in a situation like ours, makes a particular point of highlighting the memory of good things and turning his mind away from the dark and disturbing aspects of his life towards the bright and brilliant ones instead either completely extinguishes whatever it is that is causing him pain, or at least decreases and obscures it by blending it with its opposite. Perfume is always nice to smell, but it is also an antidote to unpleasant odours; likewise, bearing good things in mind serves the extra purpose of essential support, in times of trouble, for people who are not afraid to recall good times and do not critically hold fortune entirely responsible for every bad thing that happens. And that is a condition we should avoid - the syndrome of whingeing if the book of our life has a single smudge while every other page is perfectly clean. I mean, you have often been told that happiness is a consequence of correctly using the rational mind for the goal of a stable state, and that if it is a chance event which causes one to deviate, this does not constitute a major reversal and does not mean that the edifice of one's life has collapsed and been demolished.

Suppose that we too were to follow the usual practice of being guided by external circumstances, of keeping a tally of events due to fortune and of relying on any casual assessment of whether or not we are happy: even so, you should not take into consideration the current weeping and wailing of your visitors, which is trotted out on each and every occasion, prompted by pointless social customs. You would be better off bearing in mind that they continue to envy you for your children, your home and your way of life. As long as there are others who would gladly choose your fate, even including our present upset, it is awful for you, as the bearer of the fate, to complain and grumble, instead of letting the very source of your pain bring you to the realization of how much we have to be grateful for in what we still have. Otherwise, you will resemble those people who pick out Homer's headless and tapering lines, and ignore the many extensive passages of outstanding composition: if you do this, and nitpickingly whinge about the bad features of your life, and gloss over the good points in a vague and sweeping fashion, you will be behaving like those mean and avaricious people who build up a considerable hoard and don't make use of what they get, but still moan and grumble when they lose it.

If you feel sorry about our daughter dying before she was able to marry and have children, then again you can find other reasons for cheering yourself up, in that you have known and experienced both these states: I mean, they cannot simultaneously be significant and insignificant blessings, depending on whether or not one has been deprived of them! And the fact that she has gone to a place of no pain ought not to be a source of pain to us. Why should she cause us to suffer, if there is nothing that can now cause her pain? Even huge losses cease to be a source of distress when the point is reached at which the objects are no longer missed, and your Timoxena suffered only minor losses, since what she was familiar with and what she found pleasure in were not things of great importance. And as for things she was unaware of, which had never entered her mind or caught her fancy - how could she be said to have lost them?

Then there is that other idea you've come across, which is commonly accepted, that it is quite impossible for anything to harm or distress something which has been dissolved. But I know that both the doctrine we've inherited from our ancestors and the maxims of the Dionysian Mysteries (which those of us who are in the group are privy to) prevent you believing this idea. So, since the soul cannot be destroyed, you can compare what happens to it to the behaviour of caged birds: if it has made a physical body its home for an extended period of time, and has allowed a plethora of material events and long familiarity to domesticate it to this way of life, then it resumes its perch inside a body and doesn't let go or stop its involvement, through rebirth after rebirth, with worldly conditions and fortunes. If old age is the butt of calumny and slurs, you should appreciate that this is not because of wrinkles, grey hair and physical enfeeblement: no, its most cruel feature is that it makes the soul lose touch with its memories of the other world, attaches it to this one, wraps it and constricts it (since it retains the shape it gained while it was acted on by the body). On the other hand, a soul which, although captured,〈remains only a short while in a body before being released〉by the gods and departing, springs back up to its natural state as if, although it had been bent, it retained its suppleness and malleability. Just as fire is quickly rekindled again and returns to its former state if it is relit straight after being extinguished,〈but the longer the interval, the harder it is to relight, so too the most fortunate soul is the one which is able, in the poet's words,〉'to pass as swiftly as possible through Hades' portals', before a strong love of the things of this world has been engendered in it and before it has become moulded to the body by being softened and melted as if by chemicals.

Our ancient ancestral customs and rules are a better guide to the truth in these matters. People do not pour libations for their infant children when they die or perform any of the other rites that in other cases one is expected to perform for the dead, because babies have not been pervaded by earth or any earthly things. Again, people do not linger over their burial or at their grave or in laying out their bodies, because the laws regarding death at that age do not allow it, on the grounds that it is irreligious to grieve for those who have exchanged this world for a fate, and a place too, that is better and more divine. Since mistrusting these laws is more problematic than trusting them, let us make sure that our external actions conform to their injunctions, and that our internal state is even more untainted, pure and restrained than our external activity.

On the avoidance of anger

SULLA: Fundanus, I think the painters' practice of periodically examining their paintings before adding the finishing touches is commendable. Continuous familiarity hides the ways in which something might vary slightly from what is required; so by interrupting their viewing, they use repeated discrimination to keep the viewing fresh and more likely to catch minor variations. But it is impossible for a person to apply himself to himself only periodically, by separating himself and interrupting the continuity of his self-awareness - and this is the main reason why everyone is a poorer judge of himself than of others. Therefore, a second-best course is for him periodically to inspect his friends and to make himself available to them for the same purpose, which is not to see if he has suddenly grown old or if his body is in a better or worse condition, but for them to examine his habits and character, to see if over a period of time any good features have been added or bad ones subtracted.

Anyway, I've come back to Rome after over a year away, and I've been with you for over four months now. I don't find it particularly surprising that the good points you were already innately endowed with have developed and increased so much; but when I see how much more amenable and submissive to reason that strong, fiery temper of yours has become, I am inclined to comment on your impetuosity by quoting the line, 'It is amazing how much more gentle he is.'

Nevertheless, this gentleness has not made you ineffective or languid, but it has replaced your notorious sudden changes of mood with a smooth surface and an effective, productive depth - like a cultivated field. It is also clear, therefore, that your temper is not waning because advancing age has made it start to decline, or because of any other automatic factor, but because it is being treated by good rational advice. But I must confess that when our mutual friend Eros told me this about you, I suspected that his warmth towards you was making him attribute to you qualities which truly good people ought to have, even though you didn't have them - and I thought this despite the fact that, as you know, he is the last person to renounce an opinion just in order to please anyone. But I now see that he is not guilty of perjury. Since we have nothing else to do while we're travelling, I wonder if you would explain how you made your temper so tame, moderate, and amenable and obedient to reason - what regimen you followed, so to speak.

FUNDANUS: You're too kind, Sulla. Are you sure that your warm friendship towards me is not blinding you to some aspects of my character? I mean, even Eros himself often fails to restrain his temper and 'keep it steadily compliant' (as Homer puts it); it is righteous indignation that makes it boil over. So it is possible that I seem amenable compared to him on these occasions, just as high notes can take the place of low notes, relative to other high notes, when one scale changes into another. SULLA: Neither of these are realistic possibilities, Fundanus. Please, as a favour to me, do what I asked.

FUNDANUS: All right. Musonius came up with some excellent suggestions, Sulla, and one of them, as I recall, was that a life of constant therapy guarantees immunity. The point is that when reason is the therapeutic agent, it should not - in my opinion - be flushed out of the system along with the illness, as hellebore is, but should remain in the mind and contain and watch over our decisions. In its effects, the analogy for reason is not medicine, but nourishing food, since anyone who becomes accustomed to it gains energy and well-being from it, whereas when emotions are at a peak of fermentation, advice and reproof struggle long and hard for slight gains, and exactly resemble smelling-salts, which arouse people who have a fit and fall unconscious, but don't get rid of the actual ailment.

Still, even at the time of their peak, all the other emotions do in a sense fall back and make way when reason with its reinforcements enters the mind from outside; but anger does not act in quite the way Melanthius says - 'It displaces intelligence and then commits criminal acts'; in fact, it does so after having replaced intelligence altogether, and shut it out of the house. And then the situation is similar to when people burn to death in their houses, in the sense that anger makes the inside full of chaos, smoke and noise, with the result that the mind is incapable of seeing or hearing anything beneficial. This is why it is easier for an abandoned ship to take on a helmsman from outside in the middle of a storm and in the open sea, than it is for someone who is being tossed in the sea of fury and anger to accept reason from an external source, unless he has made his own rationality ready. People who anticipate a siege and expect no help from outside accumulate and amass all the useful things they can; similarly, it is particularly important for people to gather from far and wide everything philosophy has to offer that will help combat anger, and to store it up in the mind - because the time when the need is crucial is also when they will not readily find it possible to introduce such assistance. I mean, the din stops the mind even hearing anything external, unless the mind has reason of its own, like an internal ship's boatswain who smartly picks up and understands every instruction; otherwise, even if the mind does hear anything, it despises quiet, gentle words and bridles at any which are more defiant. The point is that since a temper is arrogant, wilful and hard for an external agent to dislodge, it is like a secure tyranny which can be brought down only by an internal, inbred agent.

If anger becomes constant and resentment frequent, the mind acquires the negative condition known as irascibility, which results in prickliness, bitterness and a sour temper - that is, when the emotions become raw, easily distressed and hypercritical: think of a piece of iron which is already weak and thin being further filed. On the other hand, if rational discrimination immediately defies and bears down on any outburst of anger, it not only remedies the current situation, but also gives the mind energy and detachment for the future.

In my own case, at any rate, what happened is that once I had defied anger two or three times, I experienced what the Thebans did: once they had repulsed the apparently invincible Spartans for the first time, they were never subsequently defeated by them in battle. I mean, I gained the firm conviction that rationality can win. I saw that Aristotle's claim that anger ends when cold water is sprinkled on it is not the whole story: it is also quenched when faced with fear. Moreover, of course, the onset of happiness frequently causes the instantaneous 'melting', to use Homer's term, and dispersal of anger. The net result was that I became convinced that, provided the will is there, this emotion is not entirely irredeemable. You see, anger might well be aroused by something slight and meagre: often even a joke, a light-hearted remark, a laugh, a nod of assent, and so on and so forth, provoke anger. For example, when Helen addressed her niece as 'Electra, long-time spinster', she incited her remark, 'You have taken your time to see sense; in the past you left your home in disgrace.' And Callisthenes irritated Alexander by saying, when the large bowl was being passed around, 'I don't want to drink Alexander and then need Asclepius.'

Therefore, just as it is easy to control a flame which is starting to catch in hare's fur or on a wick or in a pile of rubbish (whereas if it catches in a solid object with depth, it quickly destroys and devastates 'with lively zest the lofty work of builders', as Aeschylus puts it), so anyone who pays attention to the early stages of anger and is aware of it gradually starting to smoulder and ignite as a result of some remark or rubbishy sarcasm doesn't need to exert himself a great deal, but often puts an end to it simply by keeping quiet and ignoring the remark. Anyone who doesn't fuel a fire puts it out, and anyone who doesn't feed anger in the early stages and doesn't get into a huff is being prudent and is eliminating anger.

I was accordingly not happy with Hieronymus, despite his useful comments and advice elsewhere, when he claims that because of its speed, anger is not perceptible when it is arising, but only when it has arisen and already exists. I mean, all the emotions go through the phase of gaining mass and movement, but in none of them is this arising and growth so obvious. So Homer's teaching on this is skilful: when he says, 'So he spoke; and dark clouds of anguish overshadowed Achilles', he is portraying Achilles as feeling sudden pain, when word reached him, with no lapse of time in between; but he portrays his anger at Agamemnon as slowly building up, and as gradually being ignited while a great number of words were being spoken. But if any of the people involved had withdrawn their words at the beginning and had resisted speaking them, their quarrel would not have escalated to such a degree and got so big. That is why whenever Socrates realized that he was getting too nasty to one of his friends, then because he was being driven 'as it were before a storm on the crest of an ocean wave', he used to lower his voice, smile and stop looking stern - and so keep himself upright and in control by counterbalancing the emotion and by moving instead in the opposite direction.

You see, my friend, there is a first-rate way to bring down our tyrant-like temper, which is not to listen or obey when it is ordering us to raise our voices, look fierce and beat our breasts, but to keep quiet and, as if the emotion were a disease, not aggravate it by thrashing and yelling. It may be that partying, singing and decorating doors - typical lovers' behaviour - do somehow afford an alleviation which is not unpleasing or inelegant ('I came, but did not call your name: I kissed your door. If this is a crime, I am a criminal'); and it may be that mourners eliminate a lot of their grief as well as their tears in the release of crying and weeping; but anger is made considerably more intense by the behaviour and speech of people in an angry state.

It is best, therefore, to keep calm, or alternatively to run away and hide and find refuge in silence, as though we realized that we were about to have a fit, and wanted to avoid falling, or rather falling on someone - and it is friends above all whom we most often fall on. We do not feel love or jealousy or fear for everyone, but anger leaves nothing alone, nothing in peace: we get angry at enemies and friends, at children and parents, and even at gods and animals and inanimate objects. For example, there is Thamyris, 'breaking the gilded frame, breaking the structure of the strung lyre'; and Pandarus swearing harm against himself, if he failed to burn his bow 'after shattering it with his bare hands'. And Xerxes even tried to brand and flog the sea, and sent a letter addressed to the mountain: 'Great Athos high as heaven, don't make huge, intractable rocks interfere with my actions, or else I will tear you to pieces and hurl you into the sea.' Anger can often be terrifying - but often ridiculous: that is why it is the most hated and despised of the emotions; and it is useful to be aware of both of these aspects.

In my case, at any rate - I don't know whether or not this is the correct way to go about it - I started my treatment as follows: just as the Spartans tried to understand drunkenness by watching their helots, I tried to understand anger by watching others. Hippocrates says that the severity of an illness is proportionate to the degree to which the patient's features become abnormal, and the first thing I noticed was a similar proportion between the degree of distraction by anger and the degree to which appearance, complexion, gait and voice change. This impressed upon me a kind of image of the emotion, and I was very upset to think that I might ever look so terrifying and unhinged to my friends, wife and daughters - not only fierce and unrecognizable in appearance, but also speaking in as rough and harsh a tone as I encountered in others of my acquaintance, when anger made them incapable of preserving their usual nature, appearance, pleasant conversation and persuasiveness and courtesy in company.

The orator Gaius Gracchus had a brusque personality and used to speak rather too passionately, so he had one of those little pipes made for himself which musicians use to guide their voices gradually note by note in either direction. His slave used to hold this and stand behind him while he was speaking, and sound a moderate, gentle keynote which enabled Gracchus to revoke his stridency and get rid of the harshness and anger of his tone. Just as the cowherd's 'wax-joined reed pipes in clear tones a sleep-inducing tune', so Gracchus' slave mollified and allayed the orator's anger.

If I had an ingenious attendant who was attuned to me, however, I would not be displeased if he employed a mirror during my outbursts of anger - as is occasionally done, though for no useful purpose, for people who have just bathed - since to see oneself in an unnatural state, all discomposed, plays a not unimportant part in discrediting the emotion. Indeed, there is an amusing story that once when Athena was playing the pipes, a satyr told her off by saying, 'This expression doesn't suit you. Put down your pipes, take up your weapons and compose your cheeks.' She paid no attention, however, but when she saw in a river how her face looked, she got upset and threw away the pipes.

At least art is tasteful, and this distracts one's attention from the ugliness. (Marsyas apparently used a kind of halter and a mouthpiece to channel the force of his breath, and to rectify and conceal the irregularity of his features - 'gleaming gold joined the hair of one temple to the other and thongs, bound behind, he attached to his hard-working mouth'.) Anger, on the other hand, not only disfigures the features by inflating and distending them, but also makes one's voice even more ugly and unpleasant, and 'moves the unmoved strings of the heart'. I mean, when the sea has been whipped up by winds and disgorges kelp and seaweed, people say that it is being purified; but the undisciplined, harsh and snide remarks which anger casts ashore from a mind in turmoil pollute primarily the speakers, and contaminate them with the opprobrium of having always had these remarks inside them, bursting to get out, and of being exposed by their anger. That is why, as Plato says, they pay the heaviest of penalties for the lightest of things - a word - since they give the impression of being antisocial, slanderous and malicious.

So when I observe and notice all this, I end up committing to memory and reminding myself pretty constantly of the fact that although when feverish it is good to have a soft, smooth tongue, it is even better when angry. I mean, if the tongue of someone with a fever is unnatural, it is a bad sign, but it does not cause any further problems; but if the tongue of someone in a temper has become rough and offensive and inclined towards abnormal language, then it manifests an insolence which causes an incurable breakdown of relationships and which betrays festering unsociability. Anger is worse than undiluted wine at producing undisciplined and disagreeable results: wine's results are blended with laughter, jokes and singing, while anger's results are blended with bitter gall; and anyone who is silent while drinking is irritating and annoying to his companions, whereas there is nothing more dignified than silence while angry, as Sappho recommends: 'When anger takes over your heart, guard your babbling tongue.'

However, constant attention to people who have been trapped by anger affords more than these reflections: it allows one to understand the nature of anger in other respects too, to see that it is not magnificent or manly, and that it has neither dignity nor grandeur. Nevertheless, most people mistake its turmoil for effectiveness, its menace for courage, its inflexibility for strength; and some people even call its callousness prowess, its stubbornness energy and its asperity righteous indignation. But this is wrong, because the actions, behaviour and conduct it prompts betray its pettiness and weakness. It is not just that angry people viciously assault little children, treat women harshly and think they should punish dogs, horses and mules (as Ctesiphon the pancratiast felt obliged to return his mule's kick); it is also that the narrow intolerance of tyrants is obvious in their cruelty, and their state is betrayed by their behaviour, so that their bloodthirstiness resembles the bite of a snake which, when enraged and in agony, directs its extreme inflammation at anyone who has hurt it. When flesh is hit hard, a swelling occurs; likewise, the most infirm minds are most liable to pain, and consequently their anger is greater because their weakness is greater.

This is also why women are more irascible than men, and sick, old or unlucky people are more irascible than healthy, middle-aged or successful people. An avaricious person is very likely to get angry with his business manager, a glutton with his cook, a jealous man with his wife, a vain person when something bad has been said about him; but the worst of all are, as Pindar says, 'political men who court ambition too much: they stir up open grief'. So it is from mental pain and suffering that anger arises, thanks above all to weakness; and whoever said that anger is, as it were, the mind's sinews was wrong: it is the straining and spraining of a mind being unduly dislocated in the course of its defensive impulses.

Anyway, observing these despicable cases was not pleasant, but simply necessary. But because I regard people who cope with fits of anger in a calm and composed manner as outstanding both to hear about and to witness, my starting-point is to despise those who say, 'You wronged a man: should a man put up with this?', and 'Tread him underfoot, tread on his neck, force him to the ground!', and so on: these are provocative things to say, and some use them improperly to transpose anger from the women's quarters to the men's. I think that manly courage is compatible with morality in all other respects, but incompatible only where gentleness is concerned, because gentleness is more self-contained. It is possible for worse men to overcome better men, but to set up in one's mind a trophy of victory over anger (which Heraclitus claims makes 'a difficult opponent, since it purchases whatever it wants at the expense of the mind') is a sign of great, overwhelming strength - a strength based on the faculties of rational judgement, which are the real sinews and muscles in the fight against the emotions.

That is why I constantly try to get hold of and read this kind of case, and not only when they are provided by philosophers (whom intelligent people regard as not being liable to gall), but even more when they are provided by kings and tyrants. For example, there is Antigonus' behaviour towards some of his soldiers who were cursing him near his tent, and didn't know he could hear them: 'Oh dear,' he said, poking his staff out of the tent and on to the ground, 'can't you go somewhere further away to criticize me?'

Arcadion the Achaean was always criticizing Philip and recommending escaping 'to a place whose inhabitants are ignorant of Philip'. Then he happened to turn up in Macedonia, and Philip's friends thought that he should punish him and not let him get away with it. Philip dealt with him kindly, however, and sent him presents and gifts; later he told his people to find out what report Arcadion had given to the Greeks. They all vouched for the fact that he had become an outstanding advocate of Philip, and Philip remarked, 'So I am a better doctor than you!' And once in Olympia some slander was being spread about him, and some people suggested that the Greeks ought to be made to suffer, since they were criticizing him despite his good treatment of them. 'What will they do, then,' he asked, 'if I treat them badly?'

Also fine was Pisistratus' behaviour towards Thrasybulus, Porsenna's towards Mucius and Magas' towards Philemon. Philemon made fun of Magas in one of his comedies, publicly in the theatre, with the lines: 'Here's a letter from the king for you to read, Magas ... Poor Magas, what a pity you can't read!' Later, Philemon was forced into Paraetonium by a storm, and fell into Magas' hands. Magas told a soldier to unsheathe a sword and simply touch Philemon on the neck with it, and then politely leave; and he sent him dice and a ball, as if he were a witless child, and then let him go.

Ptolemy was once mocking a scholar for his ignorance and asked him who Peleus' father was; the scholar replied that he would tell him, if Ptolemy told him first who Lagus' father was. His remark was a mocking reference to the king's low-class birth, and everyone was offended, feeling that the remark jarred and was uncalled for. Ptolemy said, 'If a king can't take mockery, then he shouldn't mock either.'

Alexander had been more harsh than usual in the affairs involving Callisthenes and Clitus. So when Porus was taken prisoner by Alexander he entreated him to deal with him as a king should. 'Is that all?' asked Alexander. '"As a king should" covers everything,' replied Porus. That is why 'the benevolent' is an epithet of the king of the gods (though the Athenians call him 'the tempestuous', I think): punishment is the work of the Furies and demigods - it is not divine and Olympian.

When Philip had levelled Olynthus, someone remarked, 'But rebuilding an equivalent city will be beyond his capabilities'; likewise one might say to anger, 'You're good at demolition and destruction and ruination, but construction, preservation, mercy and patience require gentleness, forgiveness and moderation of passion: they require Camillus, Metellus, Aristides and Socrates, whereas plaguing and biting are what ants and mice do.'

Moreover, when I also consider vindictiveness, I find that anger's version of it is ineffective, by and large: it exhausts itself in lip-chewing, tooth-grinding, empty assaults and curses consisting of mindless threats, and the result is as ridiculous as when children in a race fall down before they reach the goal for which they are striving, because they are not in control of themselves. It follows that the Rhodian put it nicely when he said to the Roman general's servant, who was yelling and coming on strong, 'I'm not bothered by your words, but by his silence.' And once Sophocles has Neoptolemus and Eurypylus equipped with weapons, he says, 'Without making boasts, without hurling insults, the two of them smashed into the massed bronze weaponry.'

The point is that although some savages treat their weapons with poison, courage has no need of bitter gall, since it is imbued with reason, whereas anger and rage are brittle and unsound. At any rate, the Spartans play pipes to quell anger in their men while they are fighting, and before a battle they sacrifice to the Muses to ensure the stable presence of reason; and if they rout the enemy, they do not set off in pursuit, but revoke their passion, which is like those handy-sized knives in that it is retractable and manageable. Anger, however, has caused many, many people to die before exacting their revenge: Cyrus and Pelopidas of Thebes are just two examples. Agathocles, on the other hand, good-temperedly put up with insults being hurled at him by the inhabitants of a city he was besieging, and when one of them asked, 'Potter, where will you get the money to pay your mercenaries?', he replied with a laugh, 'Here, if I raze your city!' Once some people mocked Antigonus for his deformity from their city walls, and he said to them, 'But I thought I was good-looking!' But when he had taken the city, he sold the mockers into slavery, and swore that he would keep in touch with their masters, to see if they ever insulted him again.

I also notice that anger makes lawyers and orators commit great mistakes; and Aristotle records that the friends of Satyrus of Samos blocked his ears with wax when he was in court, in case he messed things up by getting angry at being abused by his opponents. As for ourselves, don't we often bungle the punishment of a slave who is misbehaving, because they get frightened at our threats and at what we are saying, and run away? Nurses say to children, 'Stop crying and you can have it', and we could usefully address anger in the same way: 'Simmer down, shut up, slow down, and you will improve the chances and the probability of getting what you want.' I mean, if a father sees his child trying to cut or carve something with a knife, he takes the knife himself and does it; and if the rational mind takes over from anger the job of retribution, then the person who deserves it receives the punishment, and the rational mind remains safe and sound and valuable, instead of being punished itself, which is what often happens thanks to anger.

All the emotions need schooling, to tame (so to speak) and discipline by training the part of oneself that is irrational and recalcitrant; but one's servants provide a better training ground for anger than for any other emotion. The point is that our dealings with servants contain no element of envy, fear or rivalry, and constantly getting angry with them causes a lot of conflict and error and, because we have power over them, our anger puts us on a slippery downward slope, as it were, with no one to stand in our way and restrain us. I mean, absolute control cannot fail to be liable to error when emotion is involved: the only solution is to use considerable restraint to restrict your power and to resist the frequent complaints of wife and friends, as they accuse you of being weak and feeble.

I myself used to get very needled at my servants because of these accusations, and used to believe that by not punishing them I was spoiling them. But eventually I realized, first, that it is better to make them worse by patiently tolerating their badness than to concentrate on correcting others while allowing harshness and anger to corrupt oneself. And second, I saw plenty of cases where, precisely because they were not being punished, they were ashamed of being bad, let forbearance rather than retaliation initiate change in them and, I assure you, more enthusiastically served those who quietly sanctioned their actions than those who used flogging and branding: all this convinced me that reason is more authoritative than passion. The poet got it wrong when he said, 'Where there is fear, respect follows too.' It is actually the other way round: respect engenders in people the kind of fear which entails self-restraint, while non-stop, relentless flogging does not instil remorse for past misdeeds, but rather the intention to get away with it in the future.

In the third place, I constantly remind myself and bear in mind that when we were learning archery, we were not told not to shoot, but not to miss; likewise, learning how to punish in a well-timed, moderate, beneficial and appropriate way will not stop one punishing altogether. So I try to quell my anger above all by not denying the defendants the right to justify themselves, but by listening to what they have to say. This helps because time checks emotion and gives it space to dissolve, and also because rationality finds what method of punishment is appropriate, and how much is fitting. Moreover, the person who gets his just deserts has no excuse left for resisting correction, given that he is being punished not in anger, but because he has been convicted; and the most shameful factor is excluded, which is when the servant has a more just case than the master.

After Alexander's death, Phocion tried to stop the Athenians revolting too soon, or too readily trusting the news, by saying, 'If he is dead today, citizens of Athens, then he will be dead tomorrow and the day after tomorrow.' In the same way, in my opinion, anyone being driven headlong towards retaliation by anger ought to whisper to himself, 'If he is guilty today, then he will be guilty tomorrow and the day after tomorrow; and no harm will be done if he gets his just deserts later rather than sooner, but if he goes through it quickly, there will always - it has often happened in the past - be uncertainty as to his guilt.' I mean, which of us is horrible enough to flog and punish a slave for having five or ten days ago burned a savoury or knocked over a table or been rather slow to obey an order? But these are the things which make us upset and harsh and pitiless when they have just occurred and when they are still in the recent past. Solid objects seem bigger when it is misty, and the same happens to things when one is angry.

Our first reaction, therefore, should be to remember facts like this; and if in the clear, steady light of reason the deed still seems bad, when there is no doubt that we are free of the emotion, then we should attend to it: we should not at this later date neglect or abandon the punishment, as we do food when we have lost our appetite. Nothing is so conducive to doling out punishment when anger is upon us as having failed to punish, having let the issue drop, when anger had left us: the experience is identical to that of lazy rowers, who lie at anchor when the weather is calm and then run the risks of a voyage when the wind is up. We too accuse rationality of being weak and feeble when it comes to punishment, and so rush on recklessly before the wind of anger when it comes.

The point is that it is proper for someone who is hungry to engage in eating, but it is proper for someone who is neither hungry nor thirsty for it to engage in retribution. He should not need anger in order to punish, as he might need a savoury, but it is essential that he waits until he has greatly distanced himself from the appetite for punishment and introduced rationality instead. Aristotle records that in his time servants were flogged in Tyrrhenia to the accompaniment of pipes; but we should not follow suit and, for the sake of personal pleasure, be driven by a desire for satisfaction, as it were, to gorge ourselves with retaliation - to enjoy punishing (which is to behave like an animal), and then regret it later (which is to behave like a woman). Rather, we should wait until there is no trace of either pleasure or distress, and rationality is present, and then take reprisal without being motivated at all by anger.

Anyway, as may be obvious, this is not a cure for anger, but a means of postponing and protecting oneself against making mistakes while angry (despite the fact that, as Hieronymus says, although a swollen spleen is a symptom of fever, reducing the swelling alleviates the fever). But when I was trying to see how anger actually starts, I noticed that although different factors trigger its onset in different people, there is almost always present a belief that they are being slighted and ignored. It follows that we should help people who are trying to evade anger by putting the greatest possible distance between any given action and contempt or arrogance, by attributing the action instead to ignorance or necessity or emotion or accident. As Sophocles says, 'My lord, unfortunate people find that even their innate intelligence has no stability, but deserts them.' And Agamemnon attributes his theft of Briseis to his being possessed, but still says, 'I want to make amends and give you vast gifts of recompense.'

The point of this quote is that no one can make an appeal to someone if he despises him; and by being demonstrably humble, the offender gets rid of any impression of contempt. But anyone who is angry should not just wait for this to happen, but should of his own accord cling to what Diogenes said: 'Those people are laughing at you, Diogenes,' someone said; 'But I don't feel laughed at,' he replied. So anyone who is angry should not think that he is being despised, but should rather despise the other person, on the grounds that his offence was caused by weakness, impetuosity, laziness, meanness, old age or youth.

However, our dealings with servants and friends must be completely free of this impression, since contempt for us as powerless or as ineffective plays no part in their attitude towards us: our servants regard us as good, on the assumption that we are fair to them, and our friends regard us as their friends, on the assumption that we are affectionate towards them. In fact, however, it is not only wife, servants and friends that we behave harshly towards because we think we are despised by them, but the same idea often brings us into angry conflict with innkeepers, sailors and drunken muleteers, and makes us get cross with dogs for barking at us and donkeys for bumping into us. We are just like the man who wanted to hit a donkey driver, and then when he shouted, 'I'm an Athenian citizen', he said to the donkey, 'Well, you aren't', and began hitting it and raining blows on it.

Now, those continuous, constant feelings of anger which gradually gather in the mind like a swarm of bees or wasps are engendered in us above all by self-regard and discontent, coupled with a luxurious and enervating way of life. It follows that there is no more important means of promoting kind behaviour towards one's servants, wife and friends than being easy to please and having a simple lifestyle, as a result of the ability to adapt oneself to immediate circumstances and not to need a lot of extras. On the other hand, 'anyone whose discontent makes him critical, if his food is over-baked or over-boiled, or under- or over- or medium-seasoned', and who can't have a drink without ice, or eat shop-bought bread, or take a morsel of food served on plain or earthenware dishes, or sleep on a mattress unless it billows like the sea in a deep swell, and who flogs and beats his table servants, forcing them to hurry, making them rush about, create a hubbub and work up a sweat as if they were bringing poultices for boils - anyone like this is enslaved to a feeble, nit-picking, complaining way of life, and fails to realize that he is creating for his temper the kind of raw and oozing condition which a chronic cough or constantly bumping into things causes. So we must train the body, by means of frugality, to be self-sufficient and hence easily pleased, because people who want little are seldom disappointed.

Food should be our starting-point: it is no great hardship quietly to make do with what is to hand, and not worry and fuss about a considerable proportion of our food, which imposes upon ourselves and our companions the most disagreeable flavouring of all - anger. It is impossible to conceive of a less pleasant meal than when servants are beaten and wife is cursed because something is burned or smoky or has insufficient salt, or because the bread is too cold. Arcesilaus once had some visitors staying and he invited friends over to dinner, but when the meal was served, there was no bread, because the servants had forgotten to buy any - which would make anyone scream loud enough to crack the walls! But Arcesilaus smiled and said, 'It's a good thing that intellectuals like a drinks party!'

Socrates once brought Euthydemus home from the wrestling-school, and Xanthippe laid into them angrily, hurled insults at them and eventually overturned the table. Euthydemus was very upset, and got up to go, but Socrates said, 'When we were at your house the other day, a hen flew in and did exactly the same, but we didn't get cross, did we?'

We should welcome friends gladly, with smiles and affection - without scowling and without instilling fear and trepidation in our servants. And we should also condition ourselves to be happy to use any utensils, and not to have preferences: some people (including Marius, we hear), having once chosen one particular goblet or cup, refuse to drink out of any other, even when they have plenty available; others are the same way about oil-flasks and strigils, and love one set above all others; and then, when any of these special things gets broken or lost, they can hardly bear it and they resort to punishment. So anyone whose weakness is anger should get rid of rare and unusual things like cups, rings and precious stones, since their loss is more unsettling than the loss of common, everyday things. That is why, when Nero had an amazingly beautiful and lavish octagonal tent made, Seneca said, 'You are a self-convicted pauper, because this tent is irreplaceable if lost.' And in fact the tent was lost, as it happened, when its ship went down; but Nero remembered what Seneca had said, and did not get too upset.

Being unfussy about mundane things makes one unfussy and gentle with one's servants; and if one is gentle with one's servants, then obviously one will also be gentle with one's friends and dependants. It is noticeable that the first thing slaves try to find out about their new owner, after they have been bought, is not whether he is liable to superstition or envy, but whether he has a temper. In fact, it is generally true that where anger is present, husbands cannot tolerate their wives' impassivity, or wives their husbands' passion, or friends one another's familiarity. So when anger is present, neither marriage nor friendship is endurable; but when anger is absent, even drunkenness is no burden. Dionysus' wand provides punishment enough for anyone who gets drunk, unless anger intrudes and imbues the wine with the god of cruelty and madness, rather than of ecstasy and dance. Anticyra cures straightforward insanity, but the combination of madness and anger is the stuff of tragedy and myth.

We should eliminate anger from our lighter moments, because it imposes enmity on affability; from our discussions, because it turns love of debating into love of disputing; from our decision-making, because it tinges authority with arrogance; when we are teaching, because it instils lack of confidence and a distaste for rationality; when we are doing well, because it promotes envy; when we are doing badly, because it deters sympathy by making people fight irritably with anyone commiserating with them. Priam is an example of this, with his 'Go away, you vile wretches! Haven't you got problems of your own? Why have you come to bother me?'

Being easy to please, on the other hand, is either a help or an embellishment or a delight, and its gentleness overcomes anger and discontent of all kinds. Consider Euclides, for instance: when his brother ended an argument by saying, 'I'll get my own back on you, if it's the last thing I do', Euclides replied, 'I'll win you over, if it's the last thing I do', and immediately made him alter course and change his mind. And Polemon was once being cursed by a man who was fond of precious stones and obsessed with costly rings; Polemon did not respond at all, but began to study one of the man's rings closely. So the man felt pleased and said, 'You'll get a far better impression of it, Polemon, if you examine it in sunlight rather than here.'

Once Aristippus was angry with Aeschines, and someone asked, 'What's happened to Aeschines', and your friendship, Aristippus?' He replied, 'It's sleeping, but I'll wake it up.' He went to Aeschines and said, 'Do you think there's absolutely no chance for me, no hope at all? Is that why you don't tell me off?' And Aeschines' response was: 'Given that you're inherently better than me in all respects, it's not at all surprising that you were the first to see what to do.'

It has been said that 'A new-born child, stroking a bristle-maned boar with his young hand, may - and so may a woman - bring him down more easily than any wrestler.' We, however, domesticate and tame wild creatures, and carry wolf and lion cubs around in our arms, but then under the influence of anger we reject children, friends and acquaintances; and we use our anger like a wild beast to assault our servants and fellow citizens, and misguidedly gloss over it as 'righteous indignation'. There is no difference, in my opinion, between this and calling other mental affections and afflictions 'foresight' or 'independence' or 'respect': it cannot free us from any of them.

Now, Zeno used to say that seed is a compound, a mixture of extracts from all the faculties which make up a person's nature; and analogously, anger seems to be a kind of conglomerate of emotional seeds. It contains elements extracted from pain and pleasure and arrogance; it has the gloating pleasure of spite, and also gets its method of grappling from spite, in the sense that the avoidance of its own suffering is not the purpose of its efforts, but it accepts harm to itself while destroying the other person; and one of its ingredients is the form of desire which is the most disagreeable of all, the longing to hurt someone else. When we approach reprobates' houses, we hear a pipe-girl playing at dawn and the sights that greet our eyes are, to quote, 'sediment of wine and shreds of garlands' and inebriated servants at the door; but the fact that the longing to hurt others is an aspect of anger explains why you will see the manifest signs of cruel and irascible people on the faces and in the identification tattoos and chains of their servants; and 'wailing is the only constant refrain to arise in the house' of an angry man - the wailing of estate-managers being flogged and serving-women having their arms twisted inside the house; and the consequence of all this is that anger is pitiful to anyone who can see that its desires and its pleasures involve pain.

Despite what has been said, anyone who is commonly susceptible to anger because of genuine righteous indignation must rid himself of the excessive, unmitigated part of his anger, along with his overconfidence in the people he comes across. This overconfidence is one of the chief causes of the aggravation of anger, which is what happens when someone assumed to be good turns out to be bad, or when a supposed friend gets cross or critical. In my own case, I'm sure you know how much I am naturally inclined towards thinking well of people and trusting them. It is like when you take a step, but there is nothing there to tread on: the more I commit myself to being friendly, the more I go wrong and get hurt by my mistakes. I might well not be able at this late stage to lessen this excessive susceptibility to and enthusiasm for friendship; but I can use Plato's words of warning to bridle my overconfidence. Plato says that his praise for the mathematician Helicon is couched the way it is because Helicon is a member of an inherently inconstant species; and he claims to be right to be wary of people brought up in his city, because since they are human and the offspring of humans, they might at any time reveal the weakness inherent in their nature.

However, Sophocles' assertion that 'Most aspects of humanity will be found on investigation to be contemptible' seems excessively harsh and restrictive. Still, the pessimistic, carping tone of this judgement does make us less liable to anger and its consequent disruptiveness; I mean, it is what is unexpected and unforeseen that throws us. We should (as Panaetius said at one point) make use of the attitude summed up in Anaxagoras' dictum: when his son died, he said, 'I knew that I had fathered a mortal.' Likewise, whenever we get irritated by someone's mistakes, we should comment, 'I knew that the slave I bought was unintelligent', or 'I knew that my friend was not flawless', or 'I knew that my wife was a woman.' And if one also keeps reiterating Plato's saying, 'Am I not like that too?', he will turn his thinking inward instead of outward, and will interrupt his complaining with caution, and will consequently not employ a great deal of righteous indignation towards others when he sees that he himself requires a lot of forbearance. But as it is, every one of us gets angry and lashes out, and sounds like Aristides and Cato: 'Stop stealing!', 'Don't tell lies!', 'Why are you slacking?' And the most despicable thing of all is that we angrily reprimand others for being angry, and we furiously punish others for mistakes made because they were infuriated: we do not behave like doctors who 'use bitter medicine to flush out bitter bile', but we aggravate and exacerbate the condition.

At the same time as bearing in mind these considerations, I also try to cut back a bit on my nosiness. I mean, knowing every single detail about everything, investigating and eliciting a slave's every occupation, a friend's every action, a son's every pastime, a wife's every whisper - this leads to many outbursts of anger, one after another every day, and these in turn add up to habitual discontent and surliness. Although Euripides is right to say that it is when things get out of hand that God 'intervenes, while leaving minor matters to chance', I still think that a sensible person ought to entrust nothing to chance, and ought to ignore nothing: he should trust and make use of his wife for some matters, his servants for others and his friends for others (just as a ruler trusts and makes use of overseers, accountants and managers), while being himself, by virtue of his rationality, in charge of the most far-reaching and important matters. For just as tiny writing irritates the eyes, so the extra strain of trivial matters chafes and unsettles one's temper, and it acquires a habit which is detrimental when more important matters are at stake.

All in all, therefore, I began to think that Empedocles' dictum 'Observe a fast from evil' is crucial and inspired; furthermore, not just because they are agreeable, but also because they are not irrelevant to the practice of philosophy, I began to commend those familiar pacts, pledged with devotion, such as to honour God with one's self-control, by keeping oneself for a year untainted by sex and alcohol; or again to refrain from lying for a prescribed period of time, by paying attention to oneself to make sure that one always tells the truth, in both unguarded and serious moments.

And then I compared my own pledge with these, and found it just as pleasing to God and just as sacred. My pledge was to begin by spending a few days doing the equivalent of going without drinking and alcohol - avoiding anger, and doing so as if I were pouring ritual libations of water and of honey, but not of wine; and then to spend a month, two months, doing this ... In this way, by experimenting on myself, the period of time gradually got longer and I progressed towards increased tolerance, by using self-control to pay attention to myself and to keep myself composed and imperturbable - maintaining a holy silence - and to remain untainted by pernicious speech, unnatural actions and emotion. Emotion leads, for the sake of a form of pleasure which is small in quantity and disagreeable in quality, to enormous mental confusion and the most despicable remorse. And this, I think, is why (with God's assistance too) my experience tends to clarify the meaning of the well-known view that this composure, calmness and charity is nowhere near as kind and considerate and inoffensive to those who come across it as it is to those who possess it.

On contentment

FROM PLUTARCH TO PACCIUS. I hope this finds you well. Not long ago, I got your letter, in which you suggested that I write down for you something about contentment, and about those passages in Timaeus which need rather careful interpretation. At pretty much the same time, our friend Eros suddenly found he had to sail to Rome, since he had received a letter from the illustrious Fundanus; typically, Fundanus told him to hurry. On the one hand, I didn't have as much time as I wanted to get to grips with the topics you were asking me to address; but on the other hand, I couldn't bear the idea of Eros leaving here, going to you and being found to be completely empty-handed. So I read those bits of my notebooks, written in fact for myself, which covered the topic of contentment. I imagined that what you too wanted from this discourse was practical help, not a lecture whose aim was elegant composition; and I share your pleasure in the fact that although you have friends in positions of authority, and although you have a preeminent reputation as a political speaker, you have not experienced what Merops did in the tragedy: it is not the case, as it was with him, that 'the adulation of the masses has driven you mad' and into abnormal behaviour. No, you have taken to heart what you have often been told: 'gout is not alleviated by a patrician shoe, nor a whitlow by an expensive ring nor a migraine by a crown.' How on earth can assets or a reputation or power at court contribute towards having a mind that is free of distress and a life that is as calm as a millpond, unless their possession and use are pleasant, but at the same time they are never missed if they are lacking? And what else guarantees this except rationality which has become accustomed to quickly restraining - and taking care to do so - the emotional, irrational part of the mind on the many occasions when it tries to exceed its bounds, and not conniving at its flooding and racing away from what is actually there?

Xenophon recommends that we remember and acknowledge the gods particularly in times of prosperity, so that when we are in need, we can confidently petition them in the knowledge that they are predisposed to be charitable and friendly. It is no different in the case of rational arguments which help us combat the emotions: anyone with any sense should pay attention to them before emotion arises, so as to widen his defensive preparations and thereby increase the benefit he gains. You know how aggressive dogs get thoroughly agitated at any and every loud voice and are calmed down only by the one with which they are familiar; so the mind's emotions too are hard to restrain when they are overexcited, unless rational arguments are already there, ingrained and familiar, to check the agitation.

Whoever it was who said that 'Contentment is impossible for anyone who busies himself with personal or public affairs' makes contentment, in the first place, an expensive commodity if its price is inactivity. It is as though his prescription for every invalid is to say, 'You poor thing, stay perfectly still in your bed', whereas inertia is in fact no good as a treatment for a body suffering from numbness and, as psychiatry, it is equally ineffective to try to remove agitation and distress from the mind by means of laziness, weakness and betrayal of friends, household and country.

Moreover, in the second place, it is not true that anyone who is not busy is content. It would follow that women are more content than men, since they generally deal only with domestic matters; but in fact, although (in Hesiod's words) the north wind 'does not reach a young woman's tender body', nevertheless distress, disturbance and depression trickle into the women's quarters through the agency of jealousy, superstition, ambition and innumerable empty beliefs. Laertes spent twenty years by himself away from civilization, 'with an old woman to look after him, who served his food and drink', and although he shunned his country, home and kingdom, nevertheless his inactivity and ennui had distress as a constant close companion. Even absolute inactivity is likely to induce discontent in some cases: for example, 'But swift-footed Achilles, Peleus' son, descended from Zeus, stayed sitting by his sharp-prowed ships and never went to assembly, which brings men prestige, or to battle, but stayed there with his heart pining in longing for the war cry and for battle.' The depth of his feeling and his grief caused him to say to himself, 'I sit by my ships, a pointless burden to the world.'

This is why not even Epicurus thinks that a quiet life is desirable; he says that people who want status and fame should go along with this aspect of their nature and engage in politics and public life, because they are inherently more likely to be thrown off balance and to be harmed by inactivity - by failing to fulfil their desires. But it is ridiculous for him to recommend public life, not to those with talent, but to those who are incapable of living peacefully. Contentment and discontent should be defined not by the frequency or rarity of one's actions, but by their goodness or badness: the omission of good deeds is - and this has been said before - just as annoying and disturbing as the commission of bad deeds.

There are people who think that freedom from distress resides in one way of life in particular - for instance, in farming or bachelorhood or kingship. What Menander said can act as a reminder for them: 'Phanias, I used to think that rich people, because they have no debts, don't sigh at night, or toss and turn, or moan "Poor me!"; I used to think they slept a pleasant, peaceful sleep.' He goes on to explain that, in his experience, even the rich suffer exactly as the poor do, and then says, 'Is grief related in some way to life? It consorts with a life of luxury, is inseparable from a life of fame, grows old with a life of poverty.'

Consider people who are scared of sailing or who get seasick: they imagine that the voyage will pass more easily if they exchange a skiff for a merchant ship, and then the merchant ship for a trireme; but this gets them nowhere, because they take their sickness and fears with them. This is an analogy for exchanging one way of life for another; it does not eradicate from the mind the factors which make it distressed and disturbed, which are unworldliness, lack of discrimination and not being able, or not knowing how, to make proper use of one's present circumstances. These are the storm winds that vex both rich and poor, trouble both married and single; they make men shun public life and then find a quiet life intolerable; they make men pursue promotion at court and be miserable as soon as they get it. 'Helplessness makes sick people a peevish lot': their wives irritate them, they complain about their doctors, grumble about their beds and 'for a friend to come is a nuisance, to leave is an offence', as Ion says. But when the illness has dissolved and the humours are differently blended, health comes and makes everything nice and pleasant, in the sense that someone who yesterday detested eggs and cakes and bread made from fresh wheat, today is even glad to eat coarse bread with olives or mustard seeds.

The engendering of rationality within us causes this kind of satisfaction with, and change of attitude towards, any way of life. Alexander once shed tears while listening to Anaxarchus lecture on the existence of an infinite number of worlds. His friends asked him what the matter was, and he replied, 'Don't you think tears are called for, if there are an infinite number of worlds, and I've not yet gained control of just one?' On the other hand, Crates, with his bag and threadbare cloak, spent his whole life joking and laughing as though he were on holiday. Moreover, Agamemnon was troubled by his extensive responsibilities as king - 'You will recognize Agamemnon, son of Atreus, whom Zeus has singled out for constant hard work' - but when Diogenes was up for sale, he lay on the ground and teased the auctioneer by refusing to get up when told to, but joking and saying with a laugh, 'Imagine it's a fish you're trying to sell!' Or again, Socrates went on discussing philosophy with his companions while he was in prison, but Phaethon used to weep when he had scaled the heights of heaven, if no one gave him his father's horses and chariot.

It is the shoe that bends along with the foot, not the other way around; and likewise, an implication of what we have been saying is that disposition moulds life. I mean, the notion that familiarity makes the best life pleasant for anyone who has chosen it is wrong: it is rational intelligence which makes the life one already has both the best one and the most pleasant one. It follows that we should purify our innate well of contentment and then external things will be in harmony with us too, provided we don't maltreat them, and will seem congruent and congenial. 'There's no point in getting angry with one's situation, because it is utterly indifferent; but success will accrue to anyone who treats the situations he encounters correctly.'

Plato compared life to a game of dice in which it is not just important to throw something appropriate, but also to make good use of it however the throw turns out. And where our situations are concerned, it may be true that we do not control the throw of the dice, but it is our job, if we are sensible, to accommodate ourselves to whatever fortune deals us and to allocate everything to a place where, as each situation arises, if it is congruent, we can maximize its benefit, and if it is unwelcome, we can minimize its harm. A physical illness can make people incapable of enduring either heat or cold, and those who muddle unintelligently through life are like that, in the sense that they get ecstatic at good fortune and depressed at bad fortune - which is to say that both good and bad fortune knock them off balance, or rather that they knock themselves off balance when they encounter either of them; and it is the same story when they encounter anything that one might term good. Theodorus the Atheist (as he was called) used to say that although he delivered his lectures with his right hand, the audience caught them in their left hands; and uneducated people, faced with a favourable or right-handed opportunity, often take it up awkwardly or left-handedly and make fools of themselves. Thyme, the most acrid and dry of plants, provides bees with honey; and likewise intelligent people can invariably find something congruent with and useful to themselves from the most forbidding of situations.

The chief thing, then, to practise and pursue is the attitude exemplified by the man whose stone missed his dog and hit his stepmother: 'That's not bad either!' he said. It is possible to change opportunities so that they are no longer unwelcome. Diogenes was exiled; 'That's not bad either', because he subsequently took up philosophy. Zeno of Citium had just one ship left from his merchant fleet; when he was told that this one too was lost, sunk with all its cargo, he said, 'Thank you, fortune, for helping to drive me into a threadbare cloak.'

Why can't the rest of us behave in the same way? Have you failed to capture some public position you were after? You can live in the country, minding your own business. Have you been spurned while courting the affection of someone in authority? You can now live a life free of risk and bother. Is your time again taken up with worldly business and worries? Well, to quote Pindar, 'the extent to which warm water relaxes a body is nothing' compared to how fame and respect, conjoined with power, make 'work pleasant and labour non-laborious'. Are you faced with misery and insults because lies or malicious tales are being spread about you? This is a following wind, blowing you towards the Muses and the Academy, as Plato was driven by the storm winds of his friendship for Dionysius.

It follows that another thing that is important for contentment is to reflect on famous men, and how they have not been affected at all by circumstances identical to one's own. Is childlessness your problem, for example? Look at the kings of Rome, none of whom had a son to whom he could bequeath his kingdom. Are you weighed down by poverty at the moment? But is there any Boeotian you would rather be than Epaminondas, any Roman rather than Fabricius? 'But my wife has been seduced!' Well, haven't you read the inscription at Delphi which goes 'Erected by Agis, lord of water and of earth'? And haven't you heard that this is the man whose wife Timaea was seduced by Alcibiades, and that in an undertone to her serving-women she used to call her child Alcibiades? Yet this did not stop Agis from being the most famous and important Greek of his day. Nor, for example, did the promiscuity of Stilpo's daughter stop him living a more carefree life than any of his philosophical contemporaries. In fact, when Metrocles told him off for his daughter's behaviour, Stilpo's response was, 'Is it my fault or hers?' Metrocles said, 'Her fault, but your misfortune.' 'What do you mean?' asked Stilpo. 'Isn't a fault a mistake?' 'Certainly,' said Metrocles. 'And isn't anyone making a mistake also suffering a setback?' continued Stilpo. Metrocles agreed. 'And isn't anyone suffering a setback also suffering a misfortune?' Stilpo concluded. This calm, philosophical argument showed the Cynic's aspersion to be empty barking.

Still, most people are hurt and provoked, by their enemies' flaws, as well as by those of their friends and relatives. I mean, being inclined towards insolence, anger, spite, malice, jealousy and hostility not only plagues those people who have these weaknesses, but also annoys and irritates foolish people - as, of course, do a neighbour's short temper, an acquaintance's grumpiness and a public administrator's iniquity. And I think that you too are very far from failing to get upset at these flaws; like the doctors in Sophocles who 'use bitter medicine to flush out bitter bile', you react to these affections and affictions with rage and bitterness. But this is unreasonable, because the public business which has been entrusted to you and which you conduct is managed by people whose characters are not straightforward and good, as well-made tools should be, but are invariably jagged and warped; and you should not, therefore, consider it to be your job - or at any rate you should not consider it to be an easy job - to straighten them out. However, if you use them as a doctor uses tooth extractors and wound clamps - that is, as being made just the way they are - and if you show yourself to be as lenient and moderate as circumstances permit, then your pleasure in your own attitude will outweigh your distress at others' unsatisfying and iniquitous behaviour, you will regard them as doing what comes naturally to them (as dogs are when they bark) and you will stop unwittingly being infected by others' flaws, which is to let plenty of distressing factors seep into the sunken and low-lying land of this pettiness and weakness of yours.

Some philosophers find fault even with compassion, when it is felt for people who are out of luck, on the grounds that while helping people one comes across is a good thing, sharing their troubles and giving in to them is not. More importantly, they forbid us to be discontented or depressed even when we realize that we ourselves have flawed and defective characters; they tell us instead not to get distressed, but just to try to cure the problem, as is right and proper. You should consider, then, how utterly illogical it is for us to connive at ourselves getting cross and irritated because not everyone with whom we have dealings and who crosses our paths is fair and congenial.

No, my dear Paccius, you must make sure that we are not deceiving ourselves by denouncing and being worried about the iniquity of people we come across only in so far as it affects us, rather than in general - that is, you must make sure that we are not being motivated by selfishness, but by hatred of badness. The point is that if we are unduly discomposed by public life and if we have unwarranted impulses and aims, or alternatively unwarranted aversions and antipathies, then this makes us suspicious of people and irritated by them, because we think that they are the causes of our losses and accidents. A high degree of contentment and calmness in relating to people is an attribute of someone who has trained himself to cope with public life without fuss and bother.

Bearing this in mind, let us return to the matter of one's situation. When we have a fever, everything tastes bitter and unpleasant, but once we have seen other people taking the same food without revulsion, we stop blaming the food and drink, and start to blame ourselves and our illness. In the same way, we will stop blaming and being disgruntled at circumstances if we see other people cheerfully accepting identical situations without getting upset. So when unwelcome incidents occur, it is also good for contentment not to ignore all the gratifying and nice things we have, but to use a process of blending to make the better aspects of our lives obscure the glare of the worse ones. But what happens at the moment is that, although when our eyes are harmed by excessively brilliant things we look away and soothe them with the colours that flowers and grasses provide, we treat the mind differently: we strain it to glimpse the aspects that hurt it, and we force it to occupy itself with thoughts of the things that irritate it, by tearing it almost violently away from the better aspects. And yet the question addressed to the busybody can be transferred to this context and fit in nicely: 'You spiteful man, why are you so quick to spot someone else's weakness, but overlook your own?' So we might ask: why, my friend, do you obsessively contemplate your own weakness and constantly clarify it and revivify it, but fail to apply your mind to the good things you have? Cupping-glasses extract from flesh anything particularly bad, and likewise you are attracting to yourself the very worst of your attributes. You are making yourself no better at all than the Chian who used to sell plenty of quality wine to other people, but for his own meal used to taste wines until he found a vinegary one; and when someone asked one of his servants what he had left his master doing, the servant replied, 'Looking for bad when surrounded by good.'

As a matter of fact, most people do bypass what is good and refreshing in their lives, and make straight for the unpleasant, bad elements. Aristippus was different, however: he was good at lightening himself and raising himself up (imagine him on a pair of scales) towards the better aspects of his situation. At any rate, he once lost a fine estate, and people were insincerely saying how sorry and sympathetic they felt. He asked one of them, 'Haven't you got just one little plot of land, while I have still got three farms?' The fellow said yes, and Aristippus said, 'Why, then, am I not feeling sorry for you, rather than the other way round?' The point is that it is crazy to be upset about what one has lost and not feel happy about what one has kept; otherwise, we are behaving like little children who, when deprived of just one of their many toys, wail and scream and throw all the rest of their toys away. In the same way, if we let fortune distress us just once, then our whining and resentment deprives everything else as well of any benefit for us.

Someone might ask, 'But what can we be said to have or not to have?' Fame, property, married status, a good friend - these are the things people have. When Antipater of Tarsus was close to death, he added up the good things that had happened to him, and included even the easy voyage he had had from Cilicia to Athens. And we must not overlook even things we share with others, but take them into account, and be thankful that we have life and health and that we walk the earth; that there is no war, either foreign or civil, but that we may, if we so choose, farm the land and sail the seas without fear; that the full range of possibilities is open to us, from oratory and politics to a quiet, inactive life. When we have these shared things, we will increase our contentment with them if we imagine that we do not have them, and frequently remind ourselves how desirable health is to sick people, peace to people at war, and the acquisition of fame and friends to an obscure stranger in a city as big as yours, and also remind ourselves how distressing it is to lose these things if they have been ours in the past. If we do this, then we will not rate and value any of these things highly only once it has been lost, while discounting it altogether as long as it is in our keeping. I mean, the fact that we do not own something does not increase its value; and we should not be acquisitive as if these things were important, and be constantly trembling in fear of losing them as if they were important, but ignore them and belittle them, while we have them, as if they were worthless. Instead, while we have them, we should above all use them for our enjoyment and profit from them, so that, in the event of their loss, we can endure this too with greater equanimity. Arcesilaus used to point out that although most people think it their duty to use their minds to explore and their eyes to examine other people's poems, paintings and statues in precise and minute detail, yet they forget their own lives, which could provide plenty of areas for pleasurable reflection: they constantly look outwards and are impressed by other people's fame and fortune, just as adulterers are by other men's wives, but belittle themselves and what they already have.

Nevertheless, another thing that is important for contentment is to restrict one's inspection as much as possible to oneself and those things which are relevant to oneself, or else to consider people who are less well off than oneself. What one should avoid is lining oneself up against people who are better off, despite the fact that this is the usual practice: prisoners, for instance, envy those who have been freed, who envy people who have always been free, who envy those with citizen status, who in turn envy rich people, who envy province commanders, who envy kings, who - because they almost aspire to making thunder and lightning - envy the gods. Consequently, since they never attain things which are out of their reach, they are never thankful for the things that are relevant to them. 'Gold-laden Gyges' possessions are of no interest to me; I have never yet been gripped by envy, nor do I seek to emulate what the gods do, nor do I desire a great kingdom. I do not set my sights on such distant views.'

Someone might say, 'That's because this is a Thasian speaking.' But there are other provincials - from Chios, Galatia or Bithynia - who are dissatisfied with having obtained a portion of status or power among their compatriots, and who weep because they do not wear patrician robes; and if they do, then because they have not yet held military command at Rome; and if they have, then because they are not consuls; and if they are, then because when the announcement was made, they did not head the list. The only possible description of this is self-mortification and self-inflicted punishment, as a result of scrabbling for reasons to be ungrateful to fortune. On the other hand, anyone whose mind sanely reflects that the sun sees countless thousands of humans - 'all we who enjoy the broad land's produce' - does not slump into depression and despondency if there are people more famous and rich than himself; there are so many human beings that his life is a thousand times more perfect than thousands of people's, so he continues on his path, celebrating his own destiny and life.

It may be impossible to choose one's opponents in the Olympic Games and so gain victory that way, but life's situations do often present one with opportunities for appreciating one's better position - for being envied rather than envying others - unless, of course, it is Briareus or Heracles one pits oneself against! So when you find yourself overawed by the apparent superiority of a man who is being carried in a sedan chair, make sure you look down and also see those who are keeping him off the ground; and when you find yourself envying Xerxes, as the Hellespontian did, on the famous occasion of Xerxes' pontoon crossing, make sure you also see the men being driven by whips to excavate Mount Athos and the men with faces mutilated when the bridge was destroyed by the waves; if you take their thoughts into consideration as well, you find that they are envying your life and your situation.

Socrates once heard one of his acquaintances remarking how expensive Athens was: 'A mina for Chian wine, three minae for a purple-dyed robe, five drachmae for a kotyle of honey.' Socrates grabbed hold of him and showed him some grain - 'An obol for half a hekteus - Athens is cheap'; and then some olives - 'Two bronze coins for a choinix - Athens is cheap'; and then some simple cloaks - 'Ten drachmae - Athens is cheap.' So when we too hear someone remarking on how trivial and terribly distressing our personal situations are, because we are not consuls or governors, we can reply, 'Our situations are not at all unprepossessing, and our lives are to be envied, because we are not beggars or porters or flatterers.'

Despite all this we habitually live, out of stupidity, with our attention on others rather than on ourselves. So since human nature contains plenty of malicious envy and spite, with the result that the degree of pleasure we feel in what is ours is less than the degree of irritation we feel at others' successes, then you must not only notice the splendid and pre-eminent features of the people you envy and admire, but you must also remove and draw aside the florid veil, so to speak, of their reputation and their façade, and get inside, where you will notice that they contain plenty of unsavoury features and plenty of unpleasantness. At any rate, something Pittacus said is instructive, since he is outstandingly famous for courage, wisdom and morality: he once had some friends round for dinner, and his wife burst in angrily and overturned the table; his friends were astounded, but he said, 'No one's life is perfect; anyone with only my troubles is very well off.'

'In public this man is an object of envy, but as soon as he opens the door of his home, he's in a pitiful state: his wife is in complete control, she bosses him about and argues all the time. He's got rather a lot of reasons to be miserable, whereas I've got none.' Plenty of these kinds of troubles accompany wealth, fame and kingship, but most people fail to notice them under the showy veneer. 'Son of Atreus, you are fortunate - your birth was favoured by fate and your destiny is to prosper': this kind of accolade is given for weaponry, horses and an extensive army, for external possessions, but from within come the contradictory emotional cries, bearing witness against this hollow fame - 'Zeus the son of Cronus has thoroughly imprisoned me in deep madness' and 'I envy you, old man, and I envy anyone whose life is at an end, if he has kept himself safe by avoiding recognition and fame.' Here is another point we should bear in mind, then, to enable us to carp less against fortune and to decrease the extent to which, by admiring our acquaintances' attributes, we belittle and denigrate our own.

Now, a major impediment to contentment is the failure to keep our desires furled or unfurled, so to speak, in a way which is commensurate with the prevailing potential. Instead, we give them too much slack through our hopes, and then when we fail, we blame fate and fortune, but not our own stupidity. We wouldn't describe as unfortunate anyone who wanted to shoot with his plough and hunt hares with his cow, nor would we say that anyone who fails to capture deer or boar with fishing-baskets or seines is being opposed by bad luck: it is stupidity and silliness which are setting him to impossible endeavours. The chief cause is in fact selflove, which makes people ambitious and competitive whatever the situation, and makes them greedily take on everything: they not only expect to be rich, erudite, strong, outgoing, pleasant and intimate with kings and leaders of nations, but they are discontented if their dogs, horses, quails and cocks are not the best at what they do.

Dionysius the Elder was not satisfied with being the most important tyrant of the time, but because his verse was worse than that of Philoxenus the poet, and he failed to do better than Plato at philosophical discussion, he got furiously angry - he imprisoned Philoxenus in the quarries, and he sent Plato to Aegina to be sold into slavery. Alexander was different: when the sprinter Crison was racing with him and gave the impression of deliberately slowing down, Alexander was very cross. And Achilles in the poem does well too: he starts off saying, 'None of the bronze-clad Achaeans is my equal', but goes on, 'in war; but there are those who are better in assembly.' On the other hand, when Megabyzus the Persian visited Apelles' studio and tried to start a conversation about art, Apelles shut him up by saying, 'As long as you kept quiet, you seemed to be someone because of your golden jewellery and purple-dyed clothes, but now even these lads here who grind the pigment are laughing at you for talking nonsense.'

Now, although people might think, when they hear the Stoic description of the sage not only as wise, moral and courageous, but also as an orator, poet and military commander, as possessing wealth and as a king, that they are joking, nevertheless they expect all these descriptions for themselves and are annoyed if they don't get them. Yet even different gods have different functions - one being called the god of battle, another the god of prophecy, another the god of profit; and Aphrodite is ordained by Zeus to preside over marriage and sex, precisely because her domain does not include military matters.

The point is that some pursuits inherently do not go together, but rather tend in opposite directions. For instance, rhetorical training and the acquisition of intellectual disciplines need freedom and no pressure, but political power and intimacy with kings do not accrue without one being busy and using up one's time. Moreover, 'drinking wine and overeating meat may make the body strong and robust, but they weaken the mind'; and whereas constant concern and care for money increase affluence, yet disdain and scorn for money constitute an important resource for philosophy. So not everything is for everyone: one should follow the Delphic inscription and know oneself, and then engage in the single activity for which one is naturally suited; and one should avoid forcibly and unnaturally compelling oneself to envy alternative ways of life - and different ones at different times. 'A horse is harnessed to a cart, an ox to a plough; a dolphin darts with great rapidity by a ship; and whoever plans death for a boar must find a courageous dog.'

Anyone, however, who is upset and distressed because he is not simultaneously a lion, 'mountain-reared, confident in his might', and a little Maltese dog protected in the lap of a widow, is crazy - but no crazier than anyone who wants to be Empedocles, Plato or Democritus, writing about the universe and the way things really are, and at the same time a Euphorion, with a rich older woman for a lover, or a Medius, hobnobbing with Alexander as one of his drinking companions, and gets irritated and distressed if he isn't an Ismenias, admired for his affluence, and an Epaminondas, admired for his goodness. I mean, runners aren't discontented because they don't win the wrestling competition: they find pride and satisfaction in their own prizes. 'You have obtained Sparta, so do it credit.' And, as Solon says, 'We will not exchange our virtue for their wealth, since the one is stable, but different people have money at different times.'

When Strato, the natural philosopher, was told that Menedemus' students far outnumbered his, he said, 'What else would you expect? There are bound to be more people who want to bathe than want to put oil on their bodies.' And Aristotle wrote to Antipater, 'The fact that Alexander rules over a lot of people does not make him the only one who can legitimately feel proud: anyone whose thinking about the gods is correct has just as much right.' The point is that people who value what they have, as in these stories, are not upset by whatever anyone else they come across has. But what happens at the moment is that although we do not expect a vine to produce figs or an olive to produce grapes, yet if we don't have the advantages of both plutocrats and scholars, military commanders and philosophers, flatterers and those who speak their minds, misers and big spenders, all at once, we bully ourselves, are dissatisfied with ourselves, and despise ourselves as living deficient and unfulfilled lives.

In addition, there are also clear reminders from nature. Different animals have been differently equipped by nature to provide for themselves: they have not all been made carnivores or seed-peckers or root-diggers. In the same way, nature has granted a wide variety of means of living to human beings - 'to shepherd, ploughman, bird-catcher and to the man whose livelihood comes from the sea'. What we should do, then, is choose what suits our specific natures, work at it and forget others' occupations; in other words, we should not show up any deficiency in Hesiod's assertion that 'Potter is jealous of potter, builder of builder.' I mean, people do not try to emulate only others with the same profession and same way of life; instead, rich men envy scholars and are in turn envied by famous people, while lawyers envy professional orators and - strange though it may seem - free men and aristocrats are utterly in awe of what they see as the happiness of comic actors in successful plays, and of dancers and servants in the royal courts. The result is that they distress and discompose themselves a great deal.

It is clear from the differences between people's experiences that everyone has within himself the resources which may lead to contentment or discontent - the jars of good and bad do not sit 'on Zeus's threshold', but lie in our minds. Foolish people overlook and ignore good things even when they are present, because their thoughts are always straining towards the future; intelligent people, on the other hand, use their memories to keep them vivid for themselves even when they are no longer present. Anything present is accessible for the minutest fraction of time and then escapes perception, and consequently foolish people think that it ceases to be relevant to us, or ceases to be ours. There is a painting of a man in Hades weaving a rope, who lets it out to a donkey at pasture, which eats up what he is weaving; in exactly the same way, most people succumb to blind, ungrateful oblivion, which consumes them and leaves no trace of any event, any moment of success, pleasant relaxation, interaction or delight.

This oblivion prevents life being a unity of past events woven with present ones: it divides yesterday from today, as if they were distinct, and likewise treats tomorrow as different from today, and it immediately consigns every occurrence to non-existence by never making use of memory. The school of thought which eliminates growth on the assumption that being is in constant flux makes each person, in theory, different from himself, and then different again; similarly, those who don't use memory to protect or recover what has gone before, but let it trickle away, day by day, make themselves in fact incomplete and empty and in suspense for the day to follow, as if the events of last year, the recent past and yesterday had no bearing on them or, in short, didn't happen to them.

So this is another thing that unsettles contentment, but not as much as the next factor we must consider. You know how when flies settle on mirrors, they skid off the smooth parts but cling on to places which are rough and scratched; this is an analogy for how people slide away from happy, congenial matters and get caught up in their memories of unpleasant things. An even better analogy might be based on the story that in Olynthus there is a place (called 'Beetle-death') which beetles fall into and are unable to get out of: they go round and round in circles until they die there. Likewise, without noticing it, people slip into recalling their bad times and are unwilling to revive or resuscitate themselves.

What we should do is treat the mind like a painting, and the events the mind recalls like the colours, and so give prominence to what is bright and vivid, and push anything gloomy into the obscurity of the background. I mean, it is impossible to eradicate and exclude the gloomy aspects altogether: 'The world is fitted together by interchange between opposites, as are a lyre and a bow', and nothing in human life is pure and unalloyed. In music there are low notes and high notes, and in grammar there are vowels and consonants, and musicianship and literacy do not come from disliking and avoiding one or the other extreme, but from knowing how to make use of them all, and how to blend them into an appropriate mixture. Events too contain polarity: as Euripides says, 'Good and bad are inseparable, but blending is possible, to make things fine.' So, to continue our simile, we should not get discontented or give up when faced with discrepancy, but should behave like expert musicians: if someone plays bad music, they lessen its impact by playing better music, and they enclose wrong notes within right ones. So we should make our life's mixture harmonious and congruent with ourselves.

I mean, Menander is wrong when he says, 'From the moment of birth onwards, everyone is attended by a deity, who is an excellent guide through the mysteries of life.' Empedocles is more likely to be right with his view that each of us has two destinies or deities, which take us in hand and into their power when we are born: 'Earth was there, and far-seeing Sun, bloody Discord and tranquil Harmony, Beauty and Ugliness, Speed and Slowness, fair Truth and dark-locked Doubt.' Consequently, since at birth we admitted, all together, the potential for each of these experiences, and since we therefore inherently contain plenty of inconsistencies, anyone with any sense prays for the better things, but expects the others as well, and copes with both sets by never behaving excessively. For, in the first place, as Epicurus says, 'Increased pleasure in approaching the future depends on decreased need of it'; and in the second place, increased enjoyment of wealth, fame, power and status depends on decreased dread of their opposites, in the sense that a strong desire for each of them instils a very strong fear of their departure, and so weakens and destabilizes the pleasure, as if it were a candle flame in a draught. Anyone whom rationality allows to stand up to fortune fearlessly and unflinchingly, and say, 'You are welcome if you bring a gift, and no great ordeal if you leave', is enabled by his courage and fearlessness (because he knows that its departure would not be unbearable) thoroughly to enjoy whatever his present situation is. When Anaxagoras' son died, he declared, 'I knew that I had fathered a mortal'; and it is possible not to stop at admiring his character, which enabled him to say this, but also to mirror him by saying, whenever fortune intrudes, 'I know that the wealth I have is transitory and unstable'; 'I know that I owe my position to people who have the power to remove it'; 'I know that although my wife is good, she is a woman, and that my friend is human - a member of an inherently inconstant species, as Plato remarked.'

The point is that, if anything happens which may be unwelcome, but is not unexpected, this kind of preparedness and character leaves no room for 'I couldn't have imagined it' and 'This isn't what I'd hoped for' and 'I didn't expect this', and so stops the heart lurching and beating fast and so on, and quickly settles derangement and disturbance back on to a foundation. Carneades used to remind people who were involved in important affairs that unexpectedness is the be-all and end-all of distress and discontent. Consider, for example, how much smaller the Macedonian kingdom was than the Roman empire. Nevertheless, when Perseus lost Macedonia, not only did he complain bitterly about his own destiny, but it was universally held that his misfortune and fate were worse than absolutely everyone else's; but when Aemilius (who had defeated Perseus) resigned from his position of controlling more or less all the lands and seas in the world, he was fêted and he performed sacrifices to the gods for his acknowledged happiness. There was a good reason for this: Aemilius had accepted a position knowing that he would one day pass it on, whereas Perseus had lost his position unexpectedly. Homer too makes some good points about what happens when things are unexpected: Odysseus wept when his dog greeted him, but sat down impassively next to his sobbing wife; the reason is that he reached his wife with his emotions tamed and controlled by rational foresight, but he fell into the other situation without anticipating it - its surprising nature made it come out of the blue.

To express the matter generally, while some unwelcome events do by their very nature entail distress and pain, nevertheless, where the majority of such events are concerned, it is our minds that condition and teach us to resent them. Therefore, when faced with this latter category of unwelcome events, it is useful always to have available Menander's line, which says, 'No experience is terrible unless you make it so.' He is implicitly asking the question: Unless your body or mind are actually affected, what difference does it make to you if, for example, your father was not an aristocrat, your wife is having an affair, you fail to win some prize or you lose your right to the front seats in the theatre? For these occurrences do not stop a man being in excellent physical or mental condition. And where the former events are concerned, the ones which do seem by their very nature to cause distress - such as illness, stress and a friend's or child's death - then there is Euripides' famous line: 'I say "Poor me!" - but why? I am only experiencing what it is to be human.' You see, no rational argument checks the downward slide of our emotions as well as one which reminds us that, in common with others and thanks to our nature, there are things which we cannot avoid; this necessity, which is due to corporeality, affords fortune its only hold on human beings; but corporeality is just one part of man's mixed nature, and in his most authoritative and important aspects he remains secure and stable.

When Demetrius had captured Megara, he asked Stilpo whether anything of his had been looted; Stilpo replied that he had seen nothing being carried off about which he would want to say 'mine'. So, if fortune steals and removes from us everything else, we still have something in us which is such that 'the Achaeans cannot carry or take it away'. It follows that we should not completely belittle and denigrate our nature as being weak, unstable and entirely subject to fortune; on the contrary, we know that the part of man which is flawed and unsound (and so liable to fortune) is small, and that we ourselves control the better part, which safely contains the most important of our benefits - correct beliefs, things we have learned and arguments conducive to goodness - which therefore subsist indelibly and indestructibly. If we are aware of this, the future doesn't dismay or terrify us and, where fortune is concerned, we say what Socrates said to the jurors (though he was apparently addressing his prosecutors) - that Anytus and Meletus can kill him, but not harm him.

The point is that fortune can make us fall ill, can deprive us of our wealth, can ruin our relationship with the people or the king, but it cannot make someone who is good, brave and high-minded into a bad, cowardly, mean-spirited, petty and spiteful person, and it cannot deprive us of the permanent presence of an attitude towards life which is a more helpful guide in this sphere than a helmsman is on a sea voyage. A helmsman is incapable of quelling a rough sea or the wind, and he cannot at will happen upon a safe harbour when he needs one, and he cannot endure whatever happens confidently and without flinching: as long as he doesn't give up, and relies on his skill, 'he escapes the hell-dark sea by reefing the mainsail right down to the bottom of the mast', but when the waves loom over him, he sits there quaking and trembling. On the other hand, a wise person's attitude calms the majority of physical matters, since his self-control, responsible regimen and moderate exercise get rid of the preconditions of illness; and if some external source of infection crops up, like the onset of a squall, then, in Asclepiades' words, 'he furls and lightens the sail, and rides it out'; and if some major unpredictable event overtakes and overwhelms him, the harbour is close by - he can swim away from the uncaulked hull of his body.

You see, it is not desire for life, but fear of death which makes an unintelligent person depend on his body and grasp on to it (one is reminded of how Odysseus' fear of Charybdis below him made him grasp on to the fig tree), 'when winds make both stopping and sailing impossible', and he is dissatisfied with one option and afraid of the other. However, anyone who has come, by whatever route, to understand the nature of the mind, and who appreciates that at death the change the mind undergoes is either for the better or at least not for the worse, is well equipped by this lack of fear of death to be content about his life. Anyone who can not only enjoy life when the pleasant and congenial aspect of it is uppermost, but who, when faced with an excess of events which are antipathetic and incongruent with his nature, can also depart without fear and with the words, 'The god himself will free me, when I will it' - well, it is inconceivable that such a man could be annoyed or angry or upset by anything that happened to him.

Whoever it was who said, 'Fortune, I have made a pre-emptive strike against you, and I have deprived you of every single loophole', was not basing his confidence on bolts, locks and fortifications, but on principles and arguments which are available to anyone who wants them. And this kind of argument should not induce any degree of resignation or disbelief, but admiration, emulation, enthusiasm, and investigation and observation of oneself in relatively trivial circumstances, to prepare oneself for the more important matters, so that one does not avoid them or divert one's mind from attention to them or take refuge in excuses like 'That's probably the most difficult thing I'll ever come across.' For if the mind is self-indulgent, and takes the easiest courses all the time, and retreats from unwelcome matters to what maximizes its pleasure, the consequence is weakness and feebleness born of lack of exertion; but a mind which trains and strains itself to use rationality to conceive an image of illness and pain and exile will find that there is plenty of unreality, superficiality and unsoundness in the apparent problems and horrors each of them has to offer, as detailed rational argument demonstrates.

Nevertheless, even the line of Menander which goes 'It is impossible for anyone still living to say, "That won't happen to me"' produces a shiver of fear in many people; but this is because they are unaware to what extent distress can be avoided by the beneficial practice of training oneself to gain the ability to look straight at fortune with open eyes, and not to form in oneself images which are 'soft and unweathered', like someone who has been brought up away from sunlight, in the shade of numerous hopes which constantly give way and provide no resistance against anything. However, we can also say the same thing as Menander - 'It is impossible for anyone still living to say, "That won't happen to me"' - but add that it is possible for anyone still living to say, 'Here's what I will not do: I will not lie, I will not mislead, I will not steal, I will not intrigue.' For this lies ready to hand, within our power, and its contribution towards contentment is not inconsiderable, but huge, since the alternative is for 'the realization of knowing that I have committed crimes' to mark the mind with remorse, which continually bleeds and stings like a bodily wound.

You see, while all other discomforts are eradicated by reason, it is reason itself which creates remorse, when the mind with its conscience is pricked and punished by itself. People who shiver from a chill or feel hot from a fever are more troubled and worse off than people who have the same sensations because of external heat or cold; likewise, chance events entail distress which is easier to endure, because it comes from an external source; but when 'What has happened to me is no one else's fault but my own' is the lament over one's mistakes, then because it comes from an internal source, from oneself, the result is a pain which one's sense of shame makes harder to bear. This is why a magnificent house, massive wealth, a splendid genealogy and high office, eloquence and fluency, are all incapable of giving life the degree of fair and calm weather that is afforded by a mind which is untainted by bad actions and intentions, and which bases life on a character that is calm and clear. A character like this is a fountain-head of fine achievements which entail not only present activity that is exuberant and happy and a source of pride, but also past memories that are more rewarding and secure than hopes which, as Pindar says, 'sustain one in old age'. Carneades said, 'Even if thuribles have been cleared out, they emit their scent for a long time.' And is it not the case that fine deeds leave behind in an intelligent person's mind an impression which remains pleasant and fresh, and thanks to which happiness is irrigated and thrives and he is enabled to rise above the level of those who moan and complain about life as being a vale of tears or a place designated for our soul's exile down here?

I like Diogenes' quip: once when he was visiting Sparta, he saw his host zealously getting ready for a festival day, and he said, 'Isn't it the mark of a good man to regard every day as a festival day?' And a particularly glorious festival too, if we see things aright. The world is a temple of the highest sacredness, and nowhere could be more suitable for divinity; and man is introduced into this world by means of his birth not to view manufactured, immobile images, but to gaze upon what Plato describes as the perceptible likenesses of intelligible things which divine intelligence has manifested as containers of an inherent principle of life and movement - the sun, moon and stars, the rivers with their continuous discharge of renewed water, and the earth with its supply of means of nourishment for plants and creatures. Life is an initiation into these things and there is no more perfect way to celebrate them; life, therefore, should be full of contentment and joy, and we should not make the usual mistake of waiting for occasional days like the holidays sacred to Cronus, Zeus or Athena for the opportunity to enjoy and revivify ourselves by paying mimes and dancers for bought entertainment.

Moreover, although we sit quietly and in good order on these occasions - for no one complains while he is being initiated or whinges while he is watching the Pythian Games or is drinking during the festival of Cronus - nevertheless, people bring shame on the festivals, which are arranged and conducted by God, by spending most of the rest of their time in complaints, despondency and exhausting worry. And although people enjoy listening to the delightful sounds of musical instruments and the singing of birds, and enjoy watching the play and frolics of animals, and conversely get perturbed when they growl and roar and look threatening, nevertheless when they see that their own lives are unsmiling, depressed and constantly constrained and restricted by disagreeable experiences and events and innumerable anxieties, they are unwilling to find some means of supplying themselves with recuperation and relaxation. But even when other people try to assist, they resist any argument which could help them come to terms with their current situation without finding fault with it, remember the past without ingratitude and approach the future happily and optimistically, without fear and without apprehension.

论复仇

复仇乃是一种对公道的粗暴寻求，人的本性愈是趋向于此，法律愈是要将其禁止。之前别人的罪行，诚然已经触犯了法律，但针对此罪行的复仇却是将法律置于不顾。固然，一个人采取复仇行为不过是为了与其仇敌相互扯平，但若能既往不咎，他便更胜一筹，因为宽恕乃是内在于贵族气质的。我确信所罗门曾言：“宽恕人的过失，便是自己的荣耀。”[1]过去的已经逝去，亦无法挽回，智者在当下和未来所要处理的事何其之多，让自己缠绕于过去的纷扰不过是徒增负担。没有人是为了犯罪而去犯罪，不过是为了使自己从中能获得利益、愉悦或者名誉等诸如此类的好处罢了。既然如此，我何必因为一个人爱他自己胜过爱我而耿耿于怀呢？即使有人纯粹出于其邪恶的本性而去犯罪，那又如何呢？也就像是荆棘一般，除了刺扎擦划，其所能及不过如此。最可容忍的一类复仇是针对那种没有相应的法律可以主持公道的罪行所实施的报复，但即便如此，实施复仇的人也需注意不要触及刑律，否则其仇敌仍然占上风，而且复仇者遭受的困苦会是其仇敌的双倍。有些时候，当给予复仇时，人们会希望对方明白这报复从何而来。这是更为宽宏的一种做法，因为复仇带来的快感似乎不在于使对方受到伤害，而在于使其悔过。但卑鄙奸诈的懦夫却喜欢暗箭伤人。佛罗伦萨大公科斯莫斯[2]对那些背信弃义或忘恩负义的朋友有过一番极端的言论，仿佛那些罪行是不可饶恕的，他说：“圣书教诲我们原谅仇敌，但却从未教诲我们原谅自己的朋友。”还是约伯的精神格调更高，他说：“难道我们从神手里得福，不也受祸吗？”[3]由此推及朋友一定程度上也应如此。可以肯定的是，一个人若对复仇念念不忘，那么他的伤口也将久久不能愈合，若非如此他的伤口应早已痊愈。报公仇者多半幸运：如为恺撒[4]被刺、为珀尔提那克斯[5]被杀、为法兰西国王亨利三世[6]被害此类事件而进行的复仇，但报私仇者则不然。与之相反，欲报私仇者过着妖巫般的生活，他们生时于人有害，死时亦不得善终。

论双亲与子女

双亲的欢愉是秘而不宣的，他们的悲伤和恐惧也是如此：他们既难以言述他们的欢愉，也不会表达他们的悲伤和恐惧。子女既使得艰辛变得甘甜，也使得不幸更为苦痛：他们增添了双亲生活的负担，也减轻了他们对于死亡的忧惧。繁衍自身将血脉永存延续，对于其他动物来说都是一样的，但名留青史、建立功勋和创造伟业则是人类特有的。的确，不难看到有些最为卓越的成就和建树来自没有子嗣之人，在他们肉体形象不能得到延续之时，他们寻求以精神形象的方式实现自身的延续。所以，没有子嗣的人实际上是最为关心后代的。那些家族创立者对于子女也最为溺爱，他们不仅将子女视为家族的后裔，也将其视为他们事业的继承者。所以，在他们眼中，子女既是后代又是事业。

双亲倾注在几个子女身上的情感在许多时候是不平均的，有时甚至是不合理的，在母亲身上表现得尤为突出。如所罗门所言：“智慧之子使父亲欢乐，愚昧之子叫母亲蒙羞。”[7]通常可见的是，在一个子孙满堂的家族中，一两个最年长的子女受到器重，最年幼者则被娇惯纵容，但处在中间的几个似乎处于被遗忘的境地，然而他们却往往成了最优秀的。父母在零用钱方面对子女若太吝惜是错误的，这会使得他们的子女感觉卑微，使之变得善于说谎，使之与小人为伍，使之在有了大量的钱财后容易贪欲无度。因此双亲对子女保持权威，而不是捂紧自己的钱包才是最为恰当的。人们（父母、教师、仆人皆如此）有一种并不明智的习惯，创造和培养一种氛围，让子女们在孩提时代就开始竞争，其结果往往使得他们长大成人时，难以同心同德，并且使家庭分崩离析。意大利人将子女、侄甥和近亲的孩子都视为己出，只要这些孩子同出一门，是否为自己亲生，他们并不看重。并且在自然界实际上也有些类似的情况，有时，我们看到侄子更像他的叔伯而不像他的父亲，这是血气使然。为父母者，应及早选择他们希望子女将来从事的职业和所学的课程，因为孩子越长大就越不容易塑造。但是为人父母者也不应过多地将自己的想法强加于子女身上，认为自己最感兴趣的也是对子女最有益处的。如果子女的性情和才能确实卓尔不群，不去妨碍其实是较好的。一般来说如下的格言是很好的：“作最佳选择，若养成了习惯就会使之充满乐趣和轻松。”[8]兄弟之中的年幼者通常有这种幸运，但如果兄弟之中的年长者被剥夺了继承权，上述情况则很少甚至不会发生。

论婚姻和独身

有妻子和子女的人已经向命运作了抵押，因为家室乃是大事业的累赘，不论是成就一番美德还是要践行一番恶举。毋庸置疑的，对于大众而言的一流作品和最善之举，都来自于那些独身或没有子女的人士，这些人士在情感上以大众为伴侣，在物质上其钱财也捐赠给了大众。然而，那些有子女的人最心系未来才是合情合理的，因为他们必须把子女托付于未来。有些人虽然过着独身的生活，他们的想法却不会超出自我之外，对未来也漠不关心。不但如此，有些人将妻子和子女视同一叠索费账单。更有甚者，也就是那些愚蠢而富有的悭吝人反而以没有子女为豪，因为他们认为这样在别人眼中他们就更为富有了。或许他们曾有耳闻这样的话：“这人可真是个大富翁。”但其他人却反驳说：“是啊，但是他有一堆儿女要照顾呢。”仿佛这会削减他的财力似的。但导致独身生活的最普遍原因是此类生活的自在清净，对于那些具有容易自我满足和幽默感心灵的人尤为如此。这类人对于任何约束都十分敏感，以至于他们会将自己的腰带和袜带也视为束缚和桎梏。独身的人是最可靠的朋友，最善良的主人，最令人满意的仆人。但并不总是最恭顺的臣民，因为他们很容易一走了之，并且几乎所有的逃亡者都属于这种没有牵挂的类型。独身生活对于教会中的人士是适合的，因为善举若先注满一池，则难以润泽四方。对于法官和地方官员来说则不一样，因为如果他们易被人左右且贪污受贿，你会发现一个公仆带来的祸害能比一个妻子带来的多出五倍还多。对于军人而言，我发现将军们在训导中通常让他的部下将妻儿铭记在心，并且我认为土耳其人对婚姻普遍的不尊使得他们粗鄙的士兵更为不堪。的确，妻子和子女是对人性的一种训练。而独身的人，虽然他们本可以更为慷慨，因为他们在财务上支出不多。但实际上他们却更为冷酷和铁石心肠（去做审讯官倒是不错），因为他们的恻隐之心并不那么常常被触发。通常深爱妻子的丈夫是本性端庄、受风俗教化，从而忠贞不渝的，就如尤利西斯[9]被称道的：“他愿为糟糠之妻舍弃长生不老。”[10]贞洁的妇女常常骄傲自负，因为她们自认为保持操守就有此资本。若一个妇女认为她的丈夫是有才识的，那就是她守住贞洁和顺从丈夫的最好维系条件之一。但如果发现丈夫生性猜忌，她就不会那么做。妻子是青年人的情人，中年人的伴侣，老年人的看护，所以一个人若要结婚是不会缺乏理由的。然而有一个智者，当有人问他“人应该什么时候结婚”的时候，他这样回答：“青年人结婚还为时尚早，老年人则完全不必结婚。”常可见到的是，性格不好的丈夫往往有温柔贤惠的妻子。或许当丈夫性情和善时，让人更觉可贵，又或者这类妻子以自己的耐性为荣。但有一点绝对错不了，那就是如果妻子不顾亲友的意见，选择嫁给性格不好的丈夫，她们就不得不为自己的愚蠢行为付出代价。

论妒忌

除了爱情和妒忌之外，没有哪种情感能使人神魂颠倒和心醉神迷。爱情与妒忌都包含着强烈的愿望，它们能使自身很容易陷入幻想和联想；它们容易在眼神中流露，尤其是相关对象出现在眼前之时。如果类似的事物存在的话，这些便是导致迷醉的原因。我们在《圣经》中读到过将妒忌称为“凶眼”的表述，并且占星家将星宿的不利影响称为“凶相”，为此，妒忌的行为似乎总是被认为与目光灼灼伤人的样子相连。不仅如此，有一些爱探究的人注意到，当妒忌的目光最伤人的时候，正是被妒忌的一方最得意得志之时，这正使得妒忌之心越发显露了。除此之外，在这种时候被妒忌之人扬扬自得的情绪表露无遗，所以易受打击。

将这些奇趣怪谈放在一边（虽然在适当的时候它们也并非不值得思考），我们将讨论什么样的人倾向于妒忌别人，什么样的人最容易招致别人的妒忌，以及公妒与私妒有何区别。

自身缺乏美德的人在任何时候都妒忌别人的德行。因为人的心灵不是充盈着自身的善，便是塞满了别人的恶，而且缺乏自身之善者必将以他人之恶补之。然后无望能及他人美德的人，会通过贬损他人的幸福来寻求平衡。

多事好问之人通常是好妒忌的。之所以费心费力打探别人的许多事情，不会是因为这些都与他自身有利害关系，因而他在看待别人的命运时，必然持有一种幸灾乐祸的心态。只专注于自身事务的人不会发现有多少值得妒忌的事情。因为妒忌是一种飘忽不定的情绪，总是在街上游荡，而不肯守在家中：“爱穷根究底的没有不心怀恶意的。”[11]

出身高贵之人对正在上升的新贵是充满妒意的。因为他们之间的距离改变了，就像观察中的错觉，当别人向自己前进时，自己却以为自己向后退了。

残疾之人、宦官、老人和私生子是好妒忌的。因为他们不太可能改变自己的处境，所以便尽其所能去损害别人……

对于那些经历了灾祸和不幸之后东山再起的人来说也有类似的情况存在。他们如同那些时代的弃儿一般，将他人所受到的伤害视为对自己痛苦的补偿。

那些渴望在各个方面出人头地的，过于浮躁和自负的人也每每富于妒忌之心。他们不缺乏能让他们心生妒意的事，因为在各类事情当中他们不可能事事都独占鳌头，总有那么几件事情别人比他们要稍胜一筹。这就类似于哈德良皇帝[12]的性格：他对诗人、画家和工匠都抱有极其嫉妒的心理，因其本人在这些人从事的领域中也有些过人的才华。

最后，近亲、办公室同事和一同被培养的人，在侪辈得到升迁提拔之时更容易犯妒忌的毛病。因为这种状况对他们而言，映衬出自身命运之不济，就像是对他们的谴责，并且无时无刻不在敲打着他们的记忆，使得他们更为留意这些发迹的侪辈，而且言谈和名声的传播使得妒忌倍加炽热。该隐对他兄弟亚伯的妒忌更为恶劣且恶毒，因为亚伯的贡品被视为更好的但没有人见证到。[13]以上这些就是关于那些容易产生妒忌的人的讨论。

再说说那些或多或少招致妒忌的人。首先，那些德高望重的人，当他们的德行累积越多，妒忌他们的人也就越少。因为他们的好运气似乎是应得的，没有人会对债务的偿还感到嫉妒，但对获得的报酬和慷慨大方的馈赠却不然。其次，妒忌总是伴随着人与自身的比较，如果没有比较，就没有妒忌了，从而君王只是被其他君王所嫉妒。然而我们注意到，默默无名者显贵之初最容易招致妒忌，但随后妒忌却慢慢消减了。不过与之相反的是，功名在身的人荣耀持续很久时，最不容易摆脱妒忌。因为到了那个时候，虽然这些建功立业的人美德依旧，但已不如当初那样闪亮，新出现人物的光辉掩盖了他们的光芒，使其黯然失色。

出身名门者的成功不那么容易让人妒忌，因为这似乎与其家世是相称的。此外，他们的成功似乎对其好运也未再有所增益。而妒忌就像阳光一样，照耀在河岸或陡坡上时比照耀在平地上要热得多。出于相同的原因，那些一步步升迁的人比起那些一步登天、一跃而飞黄腾达的人所遭受的妒忌要少一些。

那些荣誉与他们艰辛的付出，操劳忧虑，出生入死的经历成正比的人较少受到别人的嫉妒。因为人们觉得他们的这些荣誉来之不易，甚至有时还会对他们表示怜惜，而怜悯则可以将妒忌治愈。这是为什么人们可以观察到，越是老练稳重的政坛中人，在其身处高位、鼎盛之时，越是哀叹他们一生之不济，吟诵着“我们遭受了多少痛苦”！他们并非真有这样的感受，而仅仅是为了减弱妒忌的锋芒。不过这对于那些被强加事务在身的人尚可理解，但对于那些自己想要如此的人就不是这样了。因为没有什么比不必要地、雄心勃勃地热衷于各种事务更容易增长别人的妒忌。并且，如果一个大人物能做到保护他所有下属的充分权利及杰出地位，那么没有什么比这更能够将妒忌的乌云驱散的。因为这意味着在他和他的敌人之间竖起了道道屏障。

那些最容易招致妒忌的，是那些对自己的好运带着极其傲慢无礼态度的人，如果他们不显示自己有多伟大，他们就会觉得不舒服，他们或通过外在赤裸裸的炫耀，或通过对抗和竞争来压倒别人成就自己。然而也有一些明智的人愿做妒忌祭坛上的献品，有时在与其自身干系不大的事情上有目的地忍受别人的倾轧和压制。纵然如此，如下也是事实，即如果对成就怀以一颗平常心，并且处以一种开放的心态（不带有骄傲自大和虚荣自负的成分），比起使用欺诈狡猾的手段，招致的嫉妒要少。因为在后一种方式中，这种人简直就是在否定自己的好运，并且好像意识到自己不配拥有这样的运气。由此，他竟是教导别人来妒忌他了。

最后，作为对这一部分的结束语：我们在一开始已经了解到妒忌的行为与巫术有几分关联，那么要治愈妒忌，只有借助治愈巫术的良方，也就是将那“歹运”（人们所谓的）除去并加于别人身上。为此目的，一些比较聪明的大人物总是将一些人推到台前，从而将那些针对自身的妒忌分散到那些人身上。有时妒忌旁落到臣子或仆人身上，有时落到同事或同伙身上，诸如此类。就此来说，总不缺乏某些生性鲁莽冲动的人，为了获得权利和地位，不惜一切代价。

现在，谈一谈公妒。公妒还有些好处，然而私妒就一点儿好处也没有了。因为公妒乃是一种放逐，将那些势力增长得太快的人的风头压制住。从而公妒对于其他大人物也是一种约束，能使他们的行为不超越界限。

这种妒忌，在拉丁文中称为invidia，在现代语言中用“公愤”一词表达，我们将在处理叛乱的文章中进行讨论。它是一种在国家中容易传染的疾病，就像传染病一样，把身体中本来健康的部分感染了，当妒忌传入一个国家，它甚至会中伤最好的行为，并将其变为一种声名不佳的行为。因此，即便再施行一些善举，胜算也是很小的。那样做不过是显示了对妒忌示弱和惧怕，只会火上浇油越来越糟。通常就像传染病一样，如果你害怕它们，反而会被它们传染。

这种公妒似乎主要冲击身居要职的官员和大臣，而不是针对国王或是权制本身。但有一个确定的规则，如果对某位大臣的妒忌太盛，而该大臣本身引起妒忌的原因并不大，或者妒忌在某种意义上已经指向了一个国家中的所有大臣，那么这种妒忌（虽然是隐藏的）实际上是施加在国家身上的。这些就是关于公妒或公愤，及其与前面最开始就讨论过的私妒的区别。

我们就触动妒忌这一情感再说几句，与其他所有情感相较，这种情感是最为胡搅蛮缠和没完没了的。因为其他的情感都不过是偶尔有之。因此常言道：“妒忌从不休假。”因为它总是在影响某些人。此外，还可以注意到的是，爱情和妒忌使人憔悴，而其他情感则不会这样，因为其他情感不像爱情和妒忌那样连续。妒忌也是最恶劣的情感，最堕落的情感，因此它是魔鬼的固有属性，魔鬼就是“那个夜间在麦子中播撒稗子的妒忌者”。[14]就像一直以来那样，妒忌狡猾地在黑暗中行事，对诸如麦子等好的东西造成损害。

论爱

相较人生而言，舞台从爱那里得益更多。因为在舞台上，爱几乎都是喜剧的素材，有时也是悲剧的素材。但在生活中，爱带来的是灾祸，有时像希腊神话中那位用歌声诱惑水手的海妖，有时像是复仇女神。你能注意到，在一切伟大和杰出的人物（不论是在古代还是在今日，只要是被人们所铭记的）当中，没有谁是因爱这种强烈的情绪而癫狂的。这表明，伟大的灵魂和伟大的事业能将这种软弱的情感排斥在外。不过你可能会反驳说，曾执掌罗马帝国半壁江山的马克·安东尼[15]，以及曾为十人执政官之一的立法者阿庇乌斯·克劳狄乌斯[16]是这方面的例外：前者确实是沉溺酒色之人，并且过着放纵无度的生活，而后者却是一个严肃朴实和聪明的人。因此，看起来（虽然并不多见）爱不仅可以进入坦荡的心胸，也可以遁入严格设防的心灵——如果看守不严的话。伊壁鸠鲁[17]曾说过一句不怎么高明的话：“在别人眼里，我们个个都是一出大戏。”[18]仿佛人类生来就应沉思天宇和各种高贵事物的造化，除了在一个渺小的偶像面前五体投地、俯首称臣之外别无作为，虽然不是作为口舌的奴隶（如野兽那样），但却是眼睛的臣子。眼睛被赋予人，是出于更高贵的目的。留意到这种情感的过度，以及这种情感对事物本性及其价值的违抗，是令人惊异的，因为没完没了的夸张只在爱当中才显得打动人心，而在其他地方就什么都不是。这不仅仅是俗语而已，因为早就有一句话是这么说的：第一阿谀者就是人自己，与之比起来其他那些微不足道的阿谀者都还是有头脑的。毋庸置疑的是，情人要比这第一阿谀者更为过分。因为一个骄傲自负的人无论能把自己荒谬地想得多么不可一世，也比不上情人对他奉承谄媚。所以曾有人说：“不可能在爱中保持明智。”[19]这种弱点也不是仅仅显露给旁观者，而不会显露给被爱的一方，其实在被爱者那里尤为明显，除非这爱是相互回应的。因为一条真实的规则是，爱总是要获得回报，要么获得对方的心，要么获得对方秘而不宣的轻蔑。由此，更多的人应提防这种情感，在这种情感中失去的不仅是其他的一切，更失去了自身……因为不论是谁，若对情爱过于痴迷，就会同时失去财富和智慧。爱这种情感在人有弱点的时候最容易泛滥成灾，也就是一个人春风得意或者困顿不幸之时（当然后一种情况不那么容易见到）。当这样的境况将爱的火焰点燃，就会让它燃烧得更为热烈，从而表明情爱不过是愚蠢的产物罢了。那些做得很好的人，如果他们不得不接纳情爱，也仍能保持适度，并将情爱与他们生活的重要事务和行动完全分开。因为情爱一旦与事业混淆，它就会对人的运程产生不利的影响，使得人们无法忠实于自己的目标。我不知道为什么会是这样，尚武之人总是容易为情爱所俘，我想这或许就像他们容易为杯盏所俘一样，因为危险通常需要以欢愉作为补偿。在人的本性当中，存在着爱他人的隐秘倾向和意向，这种隐秘的倾向和意向如果不能施于某人或某些人身上，便会自然而然地被播撒到众人身上，使人变得仁慈和宽厚，就像有时在修道士身上可看到的那样。夫妻之爱使人类繁衍不止生生不息，朋友之爱使人更完美，放荡不羁的爱使人堕落卑微。

论高位

身处高位的人是三重身份的仆从：君主或国家的仆从、名声的仆从、事务的仆从。所以他们是没有自由的，既没有个人的自由，也没有行动的自由，更没有时间的自由。奇怪的欲望致使人们在寻求权力的同时失去了自由，或是在寻求驾驭别人的权力时失去了支配自身的权力。升迁到高位是一个艰苦的过程，但人们却喜欢通过付出痛苦的代价换取更大的痛苦。这个过程有时是卑劣的，人们通过不光彩的手段去获得尊贵的地位。居于高位并不稳固，高位的倒退若不是地位崩塌，至少也是黯然失色，都是令人叹息的。“当你不再是你曾经所是，就没有了继续活下去的理由。”[20]不仅如此，人在希望能引退的时候往往不能如愿以偿，然而在有理由引退的时候他又不情愿，即便是上了年纪或遭受病痛的折磨需要退居二线，他们也不甘于离群索居，就像城里有些老人喜欢坐在他们家临街的门口，尽管这样会让别人嘲笑他们已经一把年纪了。当然，大人物们需要借助别人的看法使自己感觉幸福，因为如果只通过他们自己的感觉进行判断，他们难以感受到幸福。但如果他们想到别人是如何看待自己的，想到别人都以自己为楷模，他们就会表现出非常高兴的样子，即使在内心里或许他们是感到矛盾的。因为他们是那种对自己的不幸反应最迅速的人，虽然他们也是那种最后才发现自己过失的人。的确，那些正走红运的人对于自身就像陌生人一样，当他们被纷繁事务缠扰之时，根本无暇顾及自己身体上或精神上的健康。“一个著名人物为众人所知，然至死对自己却一无所知，死亡对于他可谓突如其来。”[21]在高位时，人既可以为仁从善，也可以为非作歹，而后者却是招致诅咒的。因为对于为恶来说，最好的就是不想这样做，其次才是不能这样做。但从善的权力却是真正且合法的追求目标。因为善的想法，虽然被上帝所接受，但对于人来说，如果不能诉诸行动的话，也不过是比美梦稍稍强些罢了。而行善没有权力和地位作为一定的有利条件是不能实行的。功绩与善行是人行动的目标，并且在内心里能认同这一点才能使人心有所安。因为如果一个人能参与上帝的丰功伟业，那么他同样可以参与上帝的安息。“于是上帝转身看他手造的一切，看见它们都是很好的”，[22]那么接着就是安息日了。履行你的职责时，应将楷模放在自己心中，因为仿效他们就仿佛学习一整套箴言。过了一段时间后，将你自己摆在楷模面前，以此严格地考察你最初的所作所为是否有不妥之处。不能忽视那些同样职位的人曾经做得不好的例子，不是要通过斥责别人的过失抬高自己，而是要提醒自己避免犯同样的错误。从而你在进行改革时，不要带着对前一时期和前人否定或诬蔑的心态，而是把它视为在前人的基础上再开创先例。将事物还原至其最初的状态，并观察它们是在哪方面如何退化的，但仍然向两个不同的时代寻求忠告：向古代追问什么是最好的，向现代探询什么是最合适的。尝试将你的行为举止规范起来，这样人们能事先预知什么会发生。但不要过于绝对和专断，在违背了自己原则的时候，把原因解释清楚。保持你的位置所拥有的权力，但不要引发管辖权上的争议，宁可不声不响地实际掌有这种权力，也不要去声张和质疑这种权力。同样的，维护下属相应的权力，并且以作为主要指导者为荣而不是事必躬亲。包容和征求涉及你职务执行的帮助和建议，不要把那些给你带来信息的人当作爱管闲事的人驱赶，而是应该乐于接纳他们。当权者的弱点有四类：拖延、腐败、粗暴和易被左右。就拖延来说，应让人们容易接近；遵守时间的约定；将手头的事情尽快地完成；将必要之事放置在首位，避免杂事的掺杂。就腐败而言，不仅要将自己约束好，同时对你的手下要严加管教，以制止受贿，也要对那些请求者表明态度，以杜绝行贿。培养正直的品性可以约束自身和下属。一旦这种正直的品性宣扬开来，并且表明对贿赂的憎恶，即是对那些企图行贿者的告诫。并且不仅要避免犯腐败的过失，也要避免被认为腐败的嫌疑。不管是谁，如果被发现变化无常，并且发生了明显的改变却缺乏明显的理由，那么就容易被别人猜疑为贪污之人。从而当你改变自己的观点或行为方式时，永远记得一定要将此事坦然地公布于众，并且同时将促使你改变的理由也宣布出来，千万不要偷偷摸摸地去做改变。一个仆从或一个你欣赏的人，如果被纳入你的圈子里，而他没有其他明显值得敬重的理由，通常会被认为是有秘不可宣的行贿门道。至于粗暴，它是不满的不必要原因：严厉产生畏惧，粗暴造成仇恨。甚至来自当权者的斥责也应该是严肃的，而不应该是辱骂嘲弄。至于易为人左右，它比贿赂更为糟糕。因为贿赂只是偶尔发生，但如果胡搅蛮缠和无用的关系网将一个人牵制，他就从此陷入泥沼而难以脱身。正如所罗门所说：“看情面是不好的，因为这样的人会为了一块面包而枉法。”[23]有一句极为真切的古语说：“地位显示了人的本色。”[24]而地位显示了有些人是属于更好的那一类，也显示了有些人是属于更糟糕的那一类。“如果他没有做过皇帝，大家都会认为他是适合做皇帝的。”这是泰西塔斯[25]对加尔巴[26]的评价[27]。但对维司巴西安[28]的评价，泰西塔斯说：“维司巴西安是因为居于皇帝之位而变得更善的唯一一个皇帝。”[29]不过前者指的是才能的充分，后者指的是风度和情感。一个人的荣耀增进了，是此人可敬和慷慨精神的确切证据。因为荣耀乃是或者应该是德行之所在，就像在自然界当中，事物移向自己的位置时是猛烈的，而待在自己的位置上时则是平静的。所以德行在心怀抱负时是显著的，而在当权时则安稳平静。所有升至高位的途径都像是蜿蜒曲折的楼梯。如果存在着派系的分别，当一个人向上升迁时加入一方是不错的选择，而在他已经身居高位时应保持平衡中立。公平和温和地对待你的前任的名声，因为如果你不这样做的话，它就是一笔当你卸任之时不得不偿还的债务。如果你有同僚，要敬重他们，宁可在他们不希望被召见的时候召见他们，也不要在他们有理由被召见的时候将其拒之门外。不要在公开谈话和私下回复请求者时对你的职位过于敏感和时时放在心上，宁可让别人说：“在执行职务时，他完全就是另一个人。”

论善与本性之善

我所采用的“善”的含义，就是有益于人的幸福，也就是希腊人称之为“爱人”（philanthropia），而“人道”（humanity）一词用来表述它就有些分量不足。我将“爱人”称为“善”，而将天然的倾向称为“本性之善”。在心灵的所有美德和品质中，“善”是最为崇高的，是上帝的品性。如果没有这种品性，人就是庸庸碌碌、为恶为害、卑鄙可怜的躯壳，比虫虱高不了几分。“善”符合神学上德性之仁慈，并且没有过度之说，而只有错误。对权力的过度渴望导致天使折断了翅膀从天堂坠落；对知识的过度渴求使人堕落；但对于仁慈来说，没有所谓的过度，天使或人都不会因为过度的仁慈而陷入危险。对善的倾向被深深刻印在人的本性之中，如果如果对人没有这种善的倾向，那么善就会在对待其他生灵时表现出来：就像在土耳其人那里可看到的，虽然他们是残忍的民族，然而他们对牲畜是和善的，对狗儿和鸟儿也会施舍。布斯拜洽斯[30]曾记述说，一个信奉基督教的少年在君士坦丁堡试图以硬撑开一只长喙鸟的喙为乐，这使其差点葬身于人们投掷的石块之下。善或仁慈的美德也确实会犯错误。意大利人有一句不礼貌的谚语说：“他如此之好，以至于他一无是处。”作为意大利博学之人的一分子，尼古拉斯·马基雅维利[31]也自信地将其诉诸笔端，而且几乎是用非常清晰的语言表达的，他说：“基督教把善良的人变成鱼肉，贡献给那些专横无道的人。”[32]他所说的，在于的确没有哪种法律或宗教派别或思想观念像基督教信仰那样对“善”如此颂扬。从而，为了避免诽谤和危险，对“善”这种如此优秀的习惯会导致的错误有清醒的认识就是完全必要的。在别人身上发掘善的品质，但不要被他们的外表和个人好恶所束缚，因为那样会容易为人左右或软弱屈从，这使得诚实正直的人的心灵被桎梏……上帝的例子给我们真切的教训：“他降雨给有义之人，也给不义的；叫日头照好人，也照歹人。”[33]但他不将财富或光辉的荣耀以及美德平等地施舍于每一个人。普通的好处应惠及所有人，但特殊的福利则应有所选择地施与。并且我们应谨防在临摹的时候把原型损毁，因为神学认为我们对自己的爱是原型，而我们对邻居的爱是对这种原型的仿效。“去变卖你所有的，分给穷人，并且来跟从我，”[34]但除非你要来跟随我，否则不要把你拥有的都变卖掉。也就是说，除非在可以使用非常少的钱财做非常多的事情那方面你赋有天职，否则对支流的灌注会使得源泉枯竭。为正确理由所引导的善的习性是存在的，而同时在一些人的本性当中也存在着作为善的对立面，即本性的恶毒以及对这种恶毒的倾向。因为有些人的本性就不与人为善。这种恶毒当中较轻的类型变为一种执拗或刚愎顽固的个性，或是喜于与人作对的倾向，或是难以相处的性格等。但较重的类型，就变为妒忌和纯粹的恶意中伤。这样的人，当别人处于不幸之时，在某种程度上，正是感觉良好，并且还不断地火上浇油唯恐天下不乱。他们还比不上舔舐麻风病人拉扎勒斯疮口的那些狗儿，[35]而是像那些围绕着暴露的伤口嗡嗡直叫的苍蝇。“愤世嫉俗者”惯于将人引向自缢的树枝，但他们的园子里却连供人自缢的树都没有一棵，不像泰门的花园。[36]这样的性情是人类本性的极大错误，然而却是造就伟大政治最合适不过的材料。就像弯曲的木料，用于制造注定要颠簸的船只是很合适的，而对于建造稳固坚实的房屋则不合适。善的作为和表现有许多种：如果一个人对异乡人亲切温和而彬彬有礼，那显示出他是世界的公民，并且他的心不是与其他陆地隔绝开来的孤岛，而是与之相连接的大陆。如果他对别人的困难抱有同情之心，那表现出他的心就像一棵珍贵的能出药的树木，它从自己的伤口中奉献出能给人疗伤的药膏。如果他能轻易地原谅和宽恕别人的过失，那说明他的心灵是扎根在高于伤害的地方，所以他不会被伤害击中。如果他对微小的获益也心存感激，那表明他重视的是人心，而不是那些其他无用的方面。但首要的是，如果他有圣保罗的完美，他为了弟兄们获得拯救而不惜被基督诅咒，[37]那就显示出一种天赐的本性，并且是一种与基督本身相一致的本性。

论游历

游历对年轻人来说是教育的一部分；对于年长者而言，是经验的一部分。在尚未学习过一门语言之前到某个国家旅行，是去上学而不是去游历。青年人在家庭教师的带领下或在忠诚仆人的陪伴下进行游历，我是非常赞同的。家庭教师或仆人通晓当地的语言，或曾经到过当地，就能告诉青年人在这些国家中什么是值得去看的，什么人他们应当结交，这些地方可以提供什么样的锻炼和训练。因为若不是这样，青年人就像是蒙住脑袋去到这些地方，在国外所能看到的也微乎其微。一件奇怪的事情是，在航海旅行中，人们虽然除了天空和大海什么都看不到，却常常写下日记；但在陆地的旅行中，可以观察到如此之多的事物，大部分却往往被人们所忽略，仿佛偶然的际遇比观察到的事物更值得记录。所以书写日记还是有必要的。游历中应当观览考察的事物是：国君的宫廷，尤其是当他们接见外国使节的时候；法庭，尤其是法官开庭审讯的时候；教堂和修道院，以及其中的历史遗迹；城市及镇子里的城墙和堡垒，以及港口和泊船之地；古迹和废墟；图书馆、大学、论辩和讲演——如果那里有的话；航运和海军；大城市附近的高大建筑和美丽庭院；兵工厂、军械库、弹药库；交易所、国库、仓库货栈；马术训练、击剑以及士兵的操练等；剧院，上流人士常常流连之所；珠宝和华丽服饰；私人收藏和珍奇物品，以及作为总结，在他们游历所到之处任何值得纪念的事物。家庭教师和仆人应对所有这些都事先进行过详细的考察。至于凯旋庆典、化装舞会、节日盛宴、婚礼、葬礼、死刑的执行等这些方面，则不需要人记在心上，虽然也不至于全然被忽略掉。如果你让一个青年人将其游历局限在一个小小的地方，并且只给他较短的时间去获取大量的东西，以下就是你所需要做的。首先，如前所述，他应当在去游历之前略通当地的语言。然后，就像之前谈到的那样，他应该有一位了解那个国家的家庭教师或仆人。让他带着一些描述待游历国家的卡片或书籍，这些将会是有助于他探索的好钥匙；让他坚持写日记；让他不要在一座城市或市镇中停留过久，时间的长短视此地所具有的价值而定，但不能太久。而且，在他居留于一个城市或市镇时，让他变换自己居住的地方，从市区的一端搬到另一端，这样才能认识更多的人。他应该使自己与同乡保持一定的距离，不要与他们为伍，并且在能结交当地人民的地方用餐。当他从一个地方去往另一个地方时，应使之设法获得推荐，让他无论去哪里都能获得当地名流的款待，从而能够利用这种有利条件去浏览和了解他所想知道的。如此他就能在他有限的游历中获益匪浅。至于在游历中应结交的人，最有益的就是与那些各国使节的秘书和雇员结交，因为虽然是在一个国家中游历，他应该获取更多国家的经验。他也应该参见和拜访各类著名人士，也就是那些在国外也享有盛名者，从而他能够辨别现实与名望之间是否相符。对于争吵，他们应该小心谨慎地避免。争吵一般都是因为情妇、杯中之物、座次和言语不和而起。并且，游历之人应在与性格暴躁和好争斗的人相处时小心谨慎，因为他们会将他卷入他们自己的纷争中。当游历者返回家乡时，不要让他将曾经游历过的国家抛在脑后，而是应与他所结交的人中最有价值的那些通过书信保持联络。让他的游历经历体现在他的言谈中，而不是体现在他的服饰或举止上。并且在他的言谈中，让他更审慎地用词，而不是迫不及待地夸夸其谈。让大家看到他不是想以外国的那些风俗将自己本国的风俗取代，而仅仅是将他在国外学到的某种最好的事物输入[38]到自己国家的风俗中。

论君权

所欲者甚少而所惧者甚多是一种可怜的状态。而对于君王来说这是非常普遍的情形，他们身处地位和权力的顶端，却缺乏渴求之物，这使得他们的心灵更为萎靡。与此同时，他们又有许多危险和不祥的想象密布在心头，这就使得他们的心智更为不清醒。这是致使《圣经》说“君心难测”[39]的一个原因。因为大量的猜忌，以及缺乏一个占主导地位的欲望，其他欲望得不到统领和规整，这会使得任何一个人的心都难以捉摸和把握。因此，君王们常常为自己制造欲望，并将他们的心思放在一些玩物上：有时是一座建筑，有时是要建立一种秩序，有时是要提拔一个人，有时是要拥有某一项艺术或技艺之长——就像尼禄爱好弹奏竖琴，图密善精于弓箭射术，康茂德善于骑术，卡拉卡拉喜欢驾驭战车[40]等都是如此。对于那些不了解如下道理的人来说，这似乎不可思议，即人的心灵往往因为得益于一些细枝末节的事情而感到愉悦和振奋，这种愉悦和振奋比身处高位带来的还多。我们也能看到，在即位之初是幸运的征服者的君王们，后来无限地推进他们的战果是不太可能的，但他们往往被自己曾经的成就所局限，在位晚年变得迷信和阴郁，如亚历山大大帝[41]、戴克里先[42]和被我们铭记在心的查理五世[43]等。因为已经习惯于不停地向前，而一旦发现停顿下来时，就自轻自弃，变得不再是曾经的自己了。

现在谈谈君权的调和之道：这是难以实现和保持的事情，因为调和与失调都是由对立面组成的。但将对立面相互交融是一回事，而将对立面相互交换又是另一回事，阿波尼罗对维斯佩西安所说的话就充满了极好的教训。维斯佩西安问他说：“尼禄覆灭的原因是什么？”他回答道：“尼禄虽然在竖琴的调试和弹奏方面是非常擅长的，但在统治方面，他有时把琴弦调得太高，有时又任其太低而不顾。”[44]没有什么比在权力上过分压制和过度松懈，这种不平衡和不合时宜的交替对权威的破坏更甚，这是肯定的。

一件事实是，近代所有讨论君王事务的学问都热衷于分析如何转移和改变那些逼近君王的危险和灾祸，而不是探究那些坚实稳固的方针以做到未雨绸缪。但这种做法不过是试图做命运的主人罢了。君王们应该警惕，他们要小心谨防为自己所疏忽和坐视不管而酝酿的麻烦：没有人能禁止火花的迸发，也没人能辨出这些火花来自何方。在君王的事业中，困难重重并非难以克服，但最大的困难仍然来自他们的内心。因为对于君王而言（泰西塔斯曾说），有矛盾的欲望是非常普遍的：“帝王们的欲望大部分都是热烈的，同时是互不相容的。”[45]因为权力的谬误在于，想要拥有结果，却不能忍受手段的应用。

君王需要打交道的包括他们的邻国、妻子、子女、高级教士或神职人员、贵族、次一级的贵族或绅士、商人、百姓以及战士，如果不小心和慎重的话，在这些打交道的过程中都有可能产生危害。

首先就他们的邻国来说，没有现成的普遍规则可以获取（因为情况是如此多变），但有一点是应该把握的。这就是，作为一国之君应该保持警觉，不要让他们的邻国势力增长到足以威胁自己国家的安全的地步（不管这些邻国是通过领土的扩张，还是通过贸易的包围，或是通过外交辞令，以及其他的方法）。要预见这种情况并防止这种情况发生，普遍的做法是设立一个委员会。英格兰国王亨利八世、法兰西国王弗朗西斯一世和皇帝查理五世三人在位执政的时期，就有这样的相互制约机制，他们三者当中没有谁能多占一寸土地。如果任一国家多占哪怕巴掌大小的土地，其他两个国王会立刻进行协调，或使用结盟的方式，或者如果需要的话，使用战争的方式，总之无论如何不会在利益面前保持不作为的态度。就像那不勒斯的国王费迪南多、佛罗伦萨统治者洛伦佐·美狄斯和米兰统治者卢多维克斯·斯福尔扎米所结成的同盟所起到的作用那样（即被奎恰迪尼称为意大利的安全保障）。[46]一些经院学者持有一种不足取的观点，他们认为：发起一场战争只有基于对方先前的伤害和挑拨才是正当的。这是毋庸置疑的，但对即将发生的危险的惧怕，虽然这即将到来的危险还未造成严重的打击，也是战争的合法原因。

就他们的妻子来说，有许多残忍的例子。里维亚因为把自己的丈夫毒杀而臭名昭著；苏里曼的妻子罗克塞拉纳，就是毁灭了著名的苏丹穆斯塔法王子的人，并且在王室中为所欲为，干扰王位继承；[47]英国国王爱德华二世的皇后[48]在废黜她丈夫的王位并将其谋杀的事件中要负最主要的责任。这种类型的危险是需要提防的，尤其是在君王的妻子密谋将自己亲生的孩子立为王位继承人的时候，或者她们有通奸行为的时候。

就他们的子女来说，发生在他们身上的类似悲剧不胜枚举。一般而言，父王对他们的子女一旦开始猜疑，结果总是不幸的。穆斯塔法的毁灭（我们之前提到过）对于苏里曼统治的延续是致命的打击，土耳其王位的继任从苏里曼至今都被怀疑有猫腻，且恐怕已经落入别的血统之手，因为塞里姆斯二世被认为是私生子。克里斯普斯是一位难得的性格温和的年轻王子，被他的父亲——君士坦丁大帝亲手摧毁了，也造成了君士坦丁王室的致命伤：因为君士坦丁大帝的两个儿子君士坦丁和康斯坦斯，都死于暴力冲突；而他的另一个儿子君士坦提乌斯，结局没那么惨烈，他确实是死于疾病，但也是在尤里安与之兵刃相向之后因病而亡的。[49]马其顿菲利普二世的儿子德米特里厄斯，他的毁灭给其父王带来报应，使之在悔恨中死去。[50]这样的事例还有很多，但几乎没有做父亲的能从这种不信任的关系中得到好处，除非做儿子的公然举兵反抗父王，就如塞里姆斯一世与巴杰扎特对抗，以及英格兰国王亨利二世与他的三个儿子之间的对决。

就他们的高级神职人员来说，当这些人踌躇满志不可一世的时候，就会产生危害。安塞姆和托马斯·贝克特时代就是如此，他们两位都是坎特伯雷大主教，都试图以手中的牧杖与君王的权杖相抗衡，但他们都遇到了强硬和骄横的国王——威廉·鲁夫斯、亨利一世以及亨利二世。[51]危害并非来自这种抗衡的情形，而是当这种情形有外国的权势作为支撑时，或者是教士职位的产生和当选不是通过国王的册封或特别的指派，而是通过民众选举的时候。

至于贵族，应与他们保持适当的距离。对贵族进行压制虽然会使得君王在权力上更为不受限制，但却不那么安全，并且使得君王去实现他的愿望变得不那么容易。我在关于英国国王亨利七世的历史著作中曾经提及，亨利七世对他的贵族进行压制，导致的后果就是，在他统治期间充满了各种难题和动乱。因为贵族们虽然仍然效忠于他，但他们并不协助他完成他的事业，所以实际上他不得不自己去做所有的事情。

就次一级贵族来说，作为一个分散的群体，他们倒是不会产生太多的危害。他们有时会高谈阔论，但通常是只说不做。此外，他们与地位更高的贵族之间形成了一种力量的抗衡，使得后者力量的扩张不至于过于强劲。最后，他们在老百姓当中具有最直接的影响力，在平息大众骚乱时他们的作用可以发挥到最大。

就商人来说，他们是门静脉，如果商人们不活跃兴盛，一个王国就会空有良好的四肢，而血管里却没有血液流淌，并且得不到什么滋养。向他们征收税费和贡金对君王的财政收入没有明显的好处，因为虽然在百户区[52]那里获利了，他却在郡那里失利；个别的税率增加了，但贸易的总额度却反而下降。

就平民来说，平民基本上不会有太大的危害，除非他们当中出现了伟大的、具有强大影响力的领袖，或者除非你对他们的宗教思想、风俗、谋生手段进行干涉，那就有可能带来危害。

就战士而言，当他们作为一个整体生活和存在，并且习惯于无功受禄，这就是一种危险的状态。关于这方面，我们可以看看土耳其的近卫步兵[53]和罗马禁卫队[54]的例子。不过，对战士进行训练，将其部署在各地，由几位指挥官进行管辖，并且不要给予赏赐，这是防御的需要，没有什么危害。

君王就像天空中闪烁的星辰，会带来福运，也会招致灾祸，他们拥有许多的景仰，但疲惫而不得休憩。所有关于君王的戒律实际上包含在如下应铭刻在心中的话语：要记住你是一个人，并且要记住你是一个神或者神的代表。前者约束他们的权力，后者约束他们的意志。

论狡猾

我们将狡猾视作一种邪恶或不正当的聪明。狡猾的人和聪明的人之间存在着巨大的不同，这不同不仅仅在是否正直这一点上，还在能力方面。有人能理牌，但玩牌玩得不好；有些人很善于游说拉票及结党营私，但在其他方面却表现平平。再则，善解人意是一回事，而通晓事理又是另一回事，因为许多人对人的性情把握得十分透彻，但在实际事务中的能力却不怎样。一个人如果只是把心思放在研究人上边，而没有对书本进行研读就会变成这样。这样的人更适合去与人打交道，而不适合去提供建议和作计划，并且他们也仅仅是在他们的地盘上才能发挥良好，让他们面对新的环境，想做好就不那么容易了，所以正如那条将愚昧之人和智者区分开来的规则所表达的：“把他们赤裸裸地放置到陌生人当中，你就能区分出来”。[55]但这条规则对狡猾之人几乎不适用。因为这些狡猾的人就像经营小百货的杂货商人，所以不妨把他们店铺中的商品一一陈列出来。

狡猾之术其中一点在于交谈时用你的眼睛紧盯着你的交谈对象，就像耶稣会信徒被教导的那样，因为许多贤人心中的秘密会透过他们的面容展现出来。不过在这样做的时候，有时应矜持地低垂你的眼帘，耶稣会信徒也是这样做的。

另一点狡猾之术在于，当你有急事需要马上办理，你通过勾起别的话题，使你所要求助的人感到心情放松和愉悦，从而他就不会那么清醒地反对。我知道有一位枢密院顾问官兼国务大臣从来不用需要签署的文件直接烦扰英国的伊丽莎白女王，他总是将女王先引入一些关于国事的讨论中，然后她对那些文件就不会那么在意了。

就像要获得出其不意的效果往往是通过迅速的行动那样，当对方在匆匆忙忙之中，难以花时间静下来特地考虑你所提议的事情时，往往能达成效果。如果一个人想要阻挠一件事情，而针对这件事情唯恐别人会采取敏捷而有效的行动时，他最好假装非常赞同此事且自己把事情提出，但提出的方式足以令此事难以成行。

在很有交谈的兴致时，在谈话中间忽然打住，仿佛要自我收敛，这足以勾起交谈对象更大的兴趣，使他想了解更多。

并且，当情况的知晓好像是从你那里询问得来的时候，效果要比你主动地讲述出来要更好。你可以设置一个产生问题的诱饵，即显示出一副与你平时惯于展示的面容大相径庭的面部表情，其目的在于给对方一个机会询问是什么事情造成了这种改变……

至于那些棘手和令人不愉快的事情，较为合适的处理办法是让那些言论无足轻重的人打破僵局，进而再让那些有分量的人看似巧合地加入问题的探讨中，这样他会被问起关于前人发言中的问题，从而把话题打开……

一个人如果不想把自己卷入某些事情当中，一个狡猾的办法就是借用街谈巷议的名义，比如说，“人们都是怎样说的，或者，现在大家都如何谈论这个事情”。

我知道这样一位仁兄，当他写信时，总是把那最最重要的事情写在信件的附言里头，而不是写在正文当中，就仿佛这事情不过是顺带说一下罢了。

我还认识另外一位先生，当他发表讲演的时候，他总是将他最想谈论的事情略过，而继续说其他的，绕去绕来最后才回到最想谈论的主题上，似乎他差点儿把这件事情忘记了一般。

一些人有时装成很意外的样子，仿佛与那些他们要拜托的人是偶然相遇，并且相遇之时被发现手中正握着一封信，或是正在做一些他们自己不习惯做的事情，这样他们就能够把自己放置在那些他们想要表述的事情上，使对方能够自然而然地问起这些事情。

还有一个狡猾的招数就是以个人的名义先无意中说出一些话来，这些话别人听了会学习和使用，随即就可以对此进行利用了。我知道伊丽莎白女王在位时，有两个人竞争国务大臣的职位，但彼此之间仍然保持着适当的距离，也会就此事务进行商议。他们其中的一位说，在君主制衰落之时担任国务大臣一职是甚为棘手的事情，所以他对此不是那么有兴趣。另外一位立即拣取了这些话，并在自己的朋友中散布说，在君主制衰落之时，他没理由去渴望担任国务大臣的职务。第一个说出这种话的人便抓住这个机会，想方设法地把这个事情送到女王耳边，而听到君主制衰落，女王感到非常愤怒，从此她不会再听另外一个的禀报了。

有一种狡猾，在英国我们称为“锅里翻猫”，也就是说，当一个人向别人说了什么，他把这事情说成是别人讲给他听的。说实话，当这样的事情在两个人之间发生，要弄清楚谁是第一个说出这事情的人，可不是那么容易……

有些人准备了许许多多的传说和故事，他们能把想要含沙射影的事情统统都用传说和故事的形式包装起来，这一方面使得他们不必因为说了什么而面临危险，另一方面也使得别人更乐于去传播这些事情。

一个狡猾的好点子是，用自己的语言和建议将想要获得的答案提供出来，这就使得对方不那么固执己见。

令人奇怪的是，一些人在讲出他们想要说的某些东西时，会等待很长的时间，会绕很大的弯子，会拉扯许多其他无关的事情，最后才切入正题。这需要极大的耐心，然而用处不可谓不大。

一个突然的、大胆的和未曾预料到的问题通常会使一个人感到惊讶，而使之敞开内心。就像一个改了名字的人，在圣保罗大教堂里走着，另一个人突然在他身后叫出他的真实姓名，他肯定会立刻回头去看看的。

但是这些零星技巧和狡猾的方子是无穷无尽的，不过给它们列个单子倒不失为一件好事，因为如果在一个国家里一个狡猾的人能冒充贤人的话，真是没有会比这造成的祸害更甚的了。

不过确实有一些人，他们知晓事务的来龙去脉，却不能把握其要点所在。就像一座房屋有便捷的楼梯和门户，却没有一个像样的房间一样。从而，你可以看见，他们能在结论中找到许多纰漏之处，但缺乏检验或者分析原因的能力。然而他们通常却善于利用自己不擅长之处，让人认为他们具有管理的才智。一些人将自己的地位建立在对别人的诽谤，和（如我们现在所说的）捉弄他人之上，而非自身在为人处世过程中的踏实努力。所罗门说的就是如此：“智者自慎其步骤，愚者转向欺骗他人。”[56]

论利己的学问

蚂蚁是一种很会为自己打算的聪明的动物，但在果园和花园中却是不受欢迎的。同样的，那些只关心自己的人对于大众来说没有什么益处。在为私和为公之间应有清晰的区隔，并且应自求问心无愧，对他人也应言而有信，对你的君王和国家尤其应该如此。一个人行为若以其自身为中心，那是十分糟糕的。地球牢牢地以自身为中心是确实的事情，然而天穹中的其他物体却是围绕着非自我的中心运动的，同时也从中获益。事事都考虑有利于自己的方面，如果就至高无上的君王来说，还尚可接受，因为君王不仅仅代表他们自己，他们的善和恶都关乎着大众的命运，决定着大众的安危。但如果就君王的臣仆，或者共和国中的公民来说，事事只考虑自身，就是无可救药的邪恶。因为无论什么事情，只要经由这样的人之手，他只会不择手段地将事情引向有利于自己目的的方面，而这与其主人或国家的目的往往是背道而驰的。从而，君王或者政府应避免选择有这种不良品性的人做臣子或属下，除非他们只想让这种人完成一些无伤大雅的事务，而不让他们参与到其他重要的方面。所有的事情都以利己为目的最致命的影响是使得整个比例完全失调。将臣仆的利益放置在主人的利益之上已经非常不当了，然而更为极端的是，因臣仆的微小利益而将主人的巨大利益置之不顾。那些不良的官员、掌管财务之人、驻外大使、军队统领，以及其他那些狡诈虚伪和贪污腐败的臣仆都是这样的例子，他们做事行为不端，以自己的蝇头小利和私欲为导向，破坏了他们所宣誓效忠之人的伟业和大局。不过就大多数情况而言，这些臣仆获得的利益是与他们财富相符的，但他们为了获得利益而造成的伤害是与他们的君主的财富相称的。极端自私自利者的本性的确是这样的，他们会仅仅为了煎烤鸡蛋而不惜把房子引燃。然而这种人却常常深得主人的信任，因为他们钻研的就是如何取悦主人从而实现中饱私囊的目的。他们为了达到取悦主人和有利自己这两方面目的的任何一个，都会将主人的利益抛在脑后。

利己的学问，从许多方面来说，都是堕落卑下的东西。这种学问是老鼠的狡猾：老鼠在房屋倒塌之前一定会弃屋而去。这种学问是狐狸的狡黠：獾掘出自己居住的洞穴，狐狸却把獾驱逐出去，将其洞穴占为己有。这种学问是鳄鱼的虚伪：当鳄鱼吞食猎物时会流下眼泪。但需要特别注意的是，（就像西塞罗[57]对庞培[58]所说的）这些人“爱他们自己胜过任何旁人”，3很多时候是不幸的。尽管他们将所有的时间都贡献给了自己，但最后也将自己当作祭品献给了命运的反复无常，而本来他们是幻想能用利己的学问将命运的双翼捆缚住的。

3.出自西塞罗给他的兄弟克温图斯的信，第3卷，第8篇。原文为拉丁文。

论新事物

生命在诞生之初并不是那么赏心悦目的，而作为时间产物的各种新事物都是如此。尽管如此，就像那些最早给他们的家族带来荣耀的人通常比他们的继承者更值得尊敬和更厉害一样，很少能够通过模仿来达到第一个先例（如果这个先例还不错）的高度。因为恶对于那些误入歧途的人的本性来说是自然而然的行为，在持续的变化中达到最强烈；而善，作为一种被驱动的行为，在初始时表现得最为强烈。确实，甚至医药也是一种新事物，那些不愿意使用新的药品的人，就会遭受新的疾病的困扰。时间是最大的革新者，如果时间自然地让事物变得坏朽，而智慧学识和忠告谏言都不能使之向好的方向转化，那么结局会是怎样呢？事实的确如此，约定俗成的东西，虽然并不那么好，但至少是适宜的。而且，那些长期相互协调的事物彼此之间已经结合在了一起；反之，新事物要与之契合却不那么容易。虽然新事物在功用上肯定是有所补益的，但却因为与旧事物不一致而会有冲突。此外，新事物就像异乡人一样，虽然能博得比一般人更多的羡慕，但比起一般人来说却更不容易被认同。如果时光的河流静止不动的话，上述所说的都千真万确；然而时间的流转永不停歇，以至于固执地保持旧风俗就像固执地坚持革新一样，会把一件事情搅乱，对旧时代过于尊敬就是对现代的不屑。所以，人们如果在变革中能以时间为榜样，那就很好，时间确实会产生极大的变革，但是过程是平静的，并且是通过几乎难以察觉的渐变实现的。如果不是如此，任何新的事物都会被认为是意想不到的，而且新的事物会对一些旧的事物进行修补，也会与其他的事物相呼应。那些得益于新事物的人会将其作为一笔财富，并感谢时运；而那些利益因此受损的人，则会将新事物视为错误，并将其归咎于变革的主导者。在国家中不要进行革新的试验也是对的，除非这种需要非常之迫切或者效用非常之显著；要清醒地留意到，变化是凭借改革而产生，而不是因想要变化而佯称改革。最后，对于新颖的事物，虽然不应该将其拒斥，但对它仍可保留一种怀疑的态度，正如《圣经》上说的：“我们应当立足于古道瞻顾四周，见有正直的大道，然后行于其上”。[59]

论消费

财富用于消费，而消费是为了荣耀或做善事。从而特殊的消费应该根据其相应的价值是否得当来进行约束，因为自觉地放弃一些不必要的花销对于国家财富的积累及对于身后进入天国都是有好处的。日常的支出应以一个人财产的状况为限度，并且加以细致的管理，应在其实际能力范围之内进行消费，不要受仆人的欺骗，也不要让仆人滥用掌管收支的权力。如果要显示自己理财有道，实际所支付的费用应少于别人的估计。一个人如果要达到收支平衡，他的日常花费应该只占到他收入的一半；而如果他想使自己的财富增长，那就应该将自己的支出控制在收入的三分之一。对于一个大人物来说，亲自过问和打理自己财产并不是一件令人颜面扫地的事情。但有些人却避免去管理自己的财务，不仅是觉得在这些方面自己会犯粗心大意的毛病，而且考虑到管理中会出现财务状况的问题，他们也怀疑对这类事情的处理会把他们带入一种消沉的情绪中去。但如果不进行检查，创伤是难以治愈的。那些从来不理会自己财产状况的人，在两方面都必须做好，一方面要对雇佣的人严格把关，另一方面需要不时更换人手，因为新手通常胆小谨慎并且不那么奸诈狡猾。那些有能力却较少过问自己财产状况的人，应该对一切收支都了然于心。一个人如果在某一方面支出较多，那他在其他的方面就应当节俭。例如，如果他在饮食方面开销颇大，在服饰方面的开支就应该有所节俭；如果他在厅堂中花费很多，在马厩中的支出就应该减少，诸如此类。因为那种在所有方面都花钱如流水的人，家业的衰落是指日可待的。要清偿一个人的债务，操之过急将对自身产生不利的影响，与拖欠过久不管所造成的影响是一样的。因为仓促地将财产变卖来还债，与承担越来越高的利息一样，通常都是不利的。此外，一次性将债务清空的人会重蹈覆辙，因为一旦他发现自己摆脱了困境，又会回到之前的不良习惯中去；而那些逐步归还债务的人会培养起一种节俭的习惯，使他的心理和财务状况都因此受益。

当然，那些需要扭转财务危机状况的人不要轻视细微方面的开支。通常来说，节省一些琐碎的费用开支并不是那么可耻，相较于要屈尊才能获得微小的收益来说都算不上什么。对于某类花费，一旦开始就没完没了，一个人在开始这类花费时应小心谨慎；但对于那些不会再有下次的类似开销，就可以表现得更为大度。

论养生

健康之道是一门学问，不是医学的规则所能涵盖的。一个人的自我观察是他保持健康的灵丹妙药，因为这些自我观察里包含着什么是对他有益的，什么是对他有害的体验。不过更稳妥的结论是“这个不适合我，所以我不会继续这样做”，而不是“我发现这个对我没什么害处，所以我会用它”。年轻时体质强韧，可以承受一些过度的行为，但这些行为到人年老时终将产生不良的后果，就像欠的债务总要归还一样。要清醒地意识到自己年岁的增长，并且应明确不能再做和年轻时候一样的事情，因为变老的趋势是不容藐视的。要注意在饮食这一重要环节不可突然改变，如果是迫不得已必须如此，也应使其他方面与之相适应。因为其奥妙在于，不论是在自然界还是在国家之中，改变多方面的事物比改变单独一个事物要更为安全可靠。对饮食、睡眠、锻炼、穿着等方面的习惯进行一一审视，看有哪些方面对你的健康是会造成损害的，一点一点地逐步将其戒除。如果改变后你觉得并不适应，就恢复原来的习惯，因为很难在如下两者之间进行区分，即一般人普遍认为是好的和有益健康的习惯，以及适合自己身体状况的特殊习惯。在吃饭的时候、睡觉的时候及锻炼的时候，保持轻松愉悦的心情，把烦恼放在一边，这是延年益寿的要诀之一。至于头脑中的情绪和思虑，应避免妒忌、焦虑恐惧、内在的愤怒烦躁、过于敏感以及绞尽脑汁的冥思苦想、过度的喜悦和兴奋、压抑心底的悲伤。怀抱希望，尽情欢笑，而不是狂喜，享受各种喜悦而不是过度地沉浸其中，有好奇心和赞美之心（从而对生活保持新鲜感），用辉煌灿烂的事物充实心灵（如历史、寓言及对自然的沉思等）。如果你在健康状况方面从来不求医问药，当你不得不需要这样做的时候，你的身体就会很不适应。如果你在求医问药上过于频繁，当疾病来临之时，医药就不会有特别的效果了。我推荐的是，随季节变换调整饮食，而不是常常求助于医药，除非药物的使用已经变成一种习惯，因为日常饮食对身体的补益更大，且不会对身体造成不良影响。不要对身体产生的新问题视而不见，而是要询问医生相关的建议。若身体抱恙，要多遵从有助恢复健康的准则；如果身体康健，则应多活动以保持良好的状态。因为对于那些身体较为强健的人来说，倘若染上的不是重症急病，大多数情况下只需调节饮食和多加休养就能痊愈。塞尔苏斯[60]兼医生和智者于一身，单纯作为医生和单纯作为智者的塞尔苏斯都很难道出他曾说过的如下这番健康长寿之道，他说，一个人应该尝试各种，甚至截然相反的习惯，不过应更倾向对自己有益的那一种：在禁食和饱食之间，更偏重饱食；在不眠与睡眠之间，更侧重睡眠；在不锻炼与锻炼之间，更注重锻炼，诸如此类。这样做，会使体质得以增强，体魄更强健。一些医生对病人的性情十分理解和包容，以至于他们对疾病无法实施真正有治愈效果的措施；还有一种医生严格地遵守治疗的程序，而没有充分地考虑病人的具体情况。看病时，应选取介于两种类型医生之间的那一种；或者，如果不能找到同时调和这两种类型的医生，那就各找一位然后将两者的优点结合起来。并且就医时，除了去找德高望重以技艺扬名的医生，也不要忘记去找那位最熟悉你身体状况的医生。

论猜疑

人心思中的猜疑就像鸟类中的蝙蝠[61]，它们总是乘着暮色起飞。猜疑的确应被抑制，至少应该被小心防范，因为它们使得心灵布满乌云，使得朋友敬而远之，而且扰乱事务，使得事情不能顺利和始终如一地继续进行。猜疑使君王变得暴虐，使丈夫变得嫉妒，使聪明的人变得优柔寡断和阴郁消沉。猜疑是缺点，这种缺点并非源于内心而是源于头脑，因为它们在最坚强勇敢的人身上也会发生，如英格兰的亨利七世。与他相比，没有更喜欢猜忌的人了，但也没有比他更坚毅的人了。在这样的性情构成中，猜疑所造成的危害倒是不大，因为通常有此类性情的人，对所猜疑之事并不急于接受，而是要调查考证是否的确如此。然而对于那些生性软弱的人来说，猜疑就像种子落到肥沃的土壤中那样快速地生长起来。越是知之甚少，人越是容易疑心。从而人应当通过增长见识来对猜忌进行补救，而不是试图将他们的猜疑闷在心里。人想要得到什么呢？难道他们以为他们所雇佣和打交道的人都是圣人吗？难道他们不想想这些人也有自身的打算？难不成对雇主和他人比对自己还要忠诚？所以除了将猜疑的事情当作真的，而同时将这些事情当作假的来约束自己的猜疑之心外，没有缓和猜疑的更好方法。因为一个人应将猜疑用作一种预防，如果他所猜疑的事情是真的，那么他就不会受到太大的伤害。自己心中产生的猜疑集聚的不过是蜂虫的嗡鸣声，而通过闲言碎语和小道消息，以及人为的添油加醋在人头脑中产生的猜疑则是有如蜂之蜇人毒刺。诚然，在猜疑的密林中开路的最好办法是与其猜忌的对象进行直接和坦率的交流，从而自己比之前能了解更多的实情，并且可以更加谨慎以避免给对方造成新的猜疑。但这对那些本性卑劣的人不会奏效，因为对于他们而言，如果他们发现自己曾被别人猜忌，他们就不会再保持忠诚。意大利人说：“猜疑允许忠诚远走高飞。”好像猜疑给忠心发放了通行证似的，但实际上猜疑应当使忠心更坚定从而解除自身的重负。

论言谈

有些人渴望在他们的言谈中表现出一种受人赞赏的风趣，希望能够在其言谈中包罗万象，而忽略了能识别真伪的判断力的重要性，仿佛言谈的技巧比思考的能力更值得称赞。有些人的确有一些老生常谈的话题，他们擅长于此，但缺乏变化。这种话题的贫乏大多让人觉得枯燥乏味，一旦人们觉察到这一点，就会感到荒谬可笑。交谈过程中最可敬之处在于引起话题，并对话题进行适当的控制进而引向其他话题，就像一个人在领舞时所做的那样。在交谈和会话中，能够改变和混合一些不同的风格就很好，在陈述之中兼有讨论，在故事当中蕴涵哲理，在提出问题的同时也有观点的表达，诙谐而不失真诚。因为倦怠使人厌烦，而且就如通常说的那样，使人精疲力竭。至于言谈之中的幽默，在如下几个方面确定无疑是不适用的：姓名、信仰、国家的状况、伟人、任何人正在从事的重要事务，以及任何值得怜悯同情的事例。然而有些人会觉得他们的聪明才智不能发挥显现出来，除非他们能锋锐辛辣、伤人之心。那是一种应该约束的说话方式。

“孩子啊，少用鞭子，多用缰绳。”[62]

一般来说，人应该能区分出什么是咸的，什么是苦的。那些说话爱挖苦别人的人，他使得别人对他话语中的机智生畏，他必然也要畏惧他在别人记忆中留下的形象。那些总是喜欢提问的人，会学习到更多的东西，言谈也更能令人满意，尤其是当他所提的问题正切中被提问人的长处时，因为这样他就给被提问人提供了侃侃而谈的机会，同时他也能够不断地获得知识。但要注意的是，所提的问题不应过于刁难，因为那样就显得装模作样了，并且他应该确保其他人在交谈过程中也有机会说话。不仅如此，如果有人一直滔滔不绝地在大部分时间中掌握着话语权，他应该想办法让这些人从这种状态中解脱并且将其他人带入谈话中来，就像乐师们对那些长期跳轻快活泼的双人舞的人所采取的技巧那样。如果你假装不知道某件事情，而别人认为你是知道的，那么下次真有你不知道的事情的时候，别人也会认为你知道了。应尽量避免谈论到自己，若谈到时也应谨慎。我知道有一个人惯于用蔑视的口吻说话：“他那么喜欢谈论自己，想必是个聪明人吧。”只有在一种情况下，一个人可以自夸而不失风度，这就是在称颂别人美德的时候，尤其是这种美德是为称颂者也引以为豪的时候。伤及他人的话语应尽量少用，因为交谈应该像一片原野，没有通向某个人家里的道路。我认识两位英国西部的贵族，其中的一位喜欢嘲弄别人，但在家中常大摆宴席，规格堪比王室；另一位会问那些到前一位贵族家中赴宴的人：“实话告诉我，席间难道没有侮辱或者讽刺打击[63]的事发生？”客人对此回答说：“这种事的确有。”这个贵族说：“想来他把一桌好菜都毁了。”言语中的谨慎比口才的雄辩更为重要，与打交道的人言语相合，比言谈中使用华丽的辞藻或使用精心安排的顺序更重要。一番连续不断的精彩发言，如果没有好的交流互动，就会显得节奏缓慢；而一份好的应答或附和，如果没有进一步的落实，也会显得浅薄无力。正如我们在兽类中所看到的那样，那些不善于急速奔跑的动物在转向上格外灵活，猎狗和野兔的区别就在于此。在切入正题之前老在外围绕来绕去是令人厌烦的，而过于直截了当又生硬突兀了。

论财富

我认为将财富称为德行的负担是最合适不过的。罗马话对财富的表达更好，称为“辎重”（impedimenta）。因为辎重对于军队，就像财富对于德行一样。它既不能被略去，也不能弃于身后，但它的确妨碍了行军。并且，对它的关注有时使胜利白白从手中溜走或对获取胜利造成了很大的阻碍。巨大的财富没有什么真正的用途，除了能够分发出去，其余的用途不过是幻想罢了。故而所罗门有言：“大富之所在，必有许多人消耗之，而它的主人除了能饱眼福以外，还能享受到什么呢？”[64]一个人的财富达到一定程度就超越了个人享受的范围，他可以对这些财富进行看管，施舍或者捐赠，或是因这些财富而获得一定的名望，但对于财富的拥有者来说，都不是实实在在的用途。难道你没看到小小的宝石和稀罕之物都被赋予了不实的价值？而人们从事那些虚有其表的工作，只不过是因为这似乎显示了巨额财富的某些用处罢了？然而你也许会说，财富可以救人于危难或解除人的困境。如所罗门所说：“在富人的想象中，财富有如一座坚城。”[65]这话表达得非常好，也就是说，这不过是存在于想象中的事，而不总是在事实上如此。因为被“多财”出卖之人比被其收买的人要多得多。不要追求以财富炫耀于人，而是应追求在财富的获取上公平、使用上有节制、给予别人时开心愉快、对保留下来的财富感到满足。但对财富也不必持有一种不问世事之人或托钵僧般的蔑视。而是应该区别对待，就像西塞罗对拉毕里乌斯·波斯杜穆斯[66]的中肯评价那样：“他对财富的追求，显得他所求的并不是为满足贪婪，而是要得到一种为善的工具。”[67]也应聆听所罗门的教诲，对急遽敛财的行为加以警惕：“欲急速致富者将不免于不义。”[68]诗人们描述说，当普路托斯（即财神）被朱庇特[69]差遣的时候，他走得步履蹒跚、慢慢吞吞；不过他若是被普鲁托[70]派遣，则健步如飞、脚下生风。意思是，通过正当的手段和诚实的劳动获得财富是缓慢的，而别人的故去（例如通过遗产、遗嘱等方式）使财富滚滚而来。不过把普鲁托看作是魔鬼，也同样适用。因为当财富来自魔鬼（例如通过欺骗、压迫和不公正的手段）时，也会迅速积累起来。致富的途径有许多种，但其中绝大多数都是肮脏不堪的。吝啬是致富的途径中最好的，但也并非清白无辜，因为吝啬使人与慷慨解囊和乐善好施的行为绝缘。获取财富最自然的途径是对土地进行耕耘，因为它是伟大母亲大地的恩赐，但通过它获取财富是缓慢的。此外，拥有大量财富的人若愿意从事农耕的话，他们的财富会成倍地增长。我认识一位英国贵族，算是我所处的时代中最有钱的人：他既是一个大草原主、畜牧大户、大木材供应商、大煤矿主、大农场主、大宗铅和铁的贸易商人，还是其他各种农牧业的经营者，所以大地对他来说就像取之不尽用之不竭的大海，源源不绝地给他提供财富。有一个人切身体会到，要赚取一点点财富很不容易，而获得大笔财富反而简单，这倒是实在的。因为，当一个人的财富储备多到足以使他等到市场的全盛时期，他可以做那些获利颇丰但一般人财力所不能及的交易，并且还可以参与属于年轻人的产业，所以他就不用为他的财富增长而发愁。日常的贸易和职业的收益是诚实可信的，主要由两种事物促进增长：勤奋努力，还有就是童叟无欺、公平交易的良好信誉。但当一个人将交易建立在别人的迫切需要之上，或者通过拉拢仆人和其他手段接近买主而破坏交易公平，或是奸诈狡猾地把其他那些更守信誉的商人打发走，以及使用诸如此类工于心计的做法时，通过交易获利就会令人质疑。至于买卖中的大肆讨价还价，当一个人购进不是为了持有，而是为了倒卖获利时，这就是对之前的卖家和之后的买家进行双重剥削。如果经过挑选的合作伙伴是值得信赖的话，合伙做生意能创造大量的财富。放高利贷是最有把握获利的途径，但也是最糟糕的途径，因为这样做的人是使别人汗流满面来谋自己的生计；[71]除此之外，在星期日也要耕田犁地不休息。不过虽然这种方式是有把握的，但也有其缺点，因为代理人和中间人会为了自己的利益将信誉不佳者鼓吹为有价值的放贷对象。在一项发明或特权上具有优先权的好运气，有时也会带来财富惊人的暴涨，就像卡纳列斯群岛上第一个经营糖业的商人一样。因此，如果一个人在思维的缜密性上能够与逻辑学家媲美，既善于判断又善于发明，尤其是在适宜的时机时，他就能成就一番大事业。那种依赖固定收入的人很难拥有巨额的财富，那种把自己的所有财产都用于风险投资的人通常会破产和沦为一贫如洗。因此以能撑得住损失的一定收入来抵御投资带来的风险才是恰当的。对货物进行垄断和囤积以再销售，如果不受管制的话，是致富的良方，尤其是当投资者能够睿智地预见何种东西会紧缺时，事先大量购入必然会带来不少收益。通过服务获得的财富，虽然属于来源最佳的行列，然而如果是通过阿谀奉承、谄媚讪笑及其他奴颜婢膝的行为获取的，它们就被归入最恶劣的行列。至于那些谋取遗嘱和遗嘱执行人职责的行为（就像泰西塔斯谈到塞内加[72]时说的那样：“他就像用网子一样把那些遗嘱和监护权一并拽在手中”[73]），就更为卑劣，在屈从献媚于比自己更卑贱的人这一点上，这种人比起那些谄媚的服务人员更为过分。不要太过于相信那些似乎鄙视财富的人，他们鄙视财富是因为他们对财富的获得感到绝望。当财富来临之时，没有人会比他们更拜金。不要因小失大，财富是长着翅膀的，有时它们会自己飞走，有时它们需要被放飞才能带更多回来。人的财富不是留给他们的家人亲属，就是交付给公众，在这两方面进行适度的分配最有助于财富的繁荣。如果继承人在年龄和见识方面都还不够成熟稳重，那么一份丰厚的遗产就像是一块诱饵，会把周围所有的猛禽都引过来啄食他。同样的，华美的赠品和捐款就像是没有放盐的祭品，只不过是被粉饰过的施舍的坟墓，里面很快就会腐朽。因此不应当以数量来衡量你的馈赠，而应使其用之有度并用之有道。此外，不要等到死之将至才着手进行慈善事业，确切地说，如果一个人认真地考虑此事就能想到，这样做的人并非慷慨地捐出自己的钱而是慷慨地把别人的钱捐掉。

论野心

野心就像胆汁一样，如果它不被阻碍的话——它是一种令人积极、认真、敏捷和活跃的体液。不过如果它被阻碍，不能随心所欲的话，它就变得阴郁枯槁，恶毒尖酸。故而有野心的人，如果他们打开了升迁之路，并且平步青云的话，他们通常是忙碌的而不是危险的；然而如果他们的愿望被阻，他们就会变得暗中愤愤不平，而且对人和事都用恶毒的眼光去看待，事情变得越糟糕他们就越开心，这可以说是一个君主或一个国家的臣仆所能具有的最坏的品质。因此，对于君主来说，如果他们任用有野心的人，要使之不断升迁而不被贬黜才好。但这样做总是免不了遇到麻烦，所以不任用具有这样性格的人倒是更为省事。因为如果他们职位高升而工作不见提高的话，一旦被贬职他们就会有意地将这些工作弄得和自身一样失败。但因为我们已经说过，不去任用那些有野心性格的人才好，除非他们是不可或缺的。那我们来说说在什么情况下是不得不用他们的。在战争中优秀的指挥官是必不可少的，即使他们的野心空前之大，因为任用他们在工作上产生的益处可以把那些弊端忽略掉。并且，任用一名没有野心的军人，就像是把他马靴上的马刺扯掉了一样。在君王处于危险和受到妒忌时任用那些有野心的人来为其掩护也是很好的，但一般来说没有人会愿意接受这样的角色，除非他像一只蒙住眼睛的鸽子，使劲地不断向上扑腾，以至于他留意不到自己。有野心的人还可以被用于清除任何高高在上、权高盖主的对象……因为他们应被任用于这类情况中。那么接下来得谈谈应如何约束他们，使他们没有那么危险。如果他们出身卑微，那么就不会有太大危险，而如果他们出身高贵则会比较危险；如果他们本性相当苛刻，就比那些本性优雅和随和的人危险性更小；如果他们最近刚刚得到提拔，比起那些以奸诈狡猾的手段而获得牢固高位的人来说危险性也更小。有的人认为，君王有自己的宠臣是一个弱点，但这其实是对付那些有野心之人的所有方法中最好的一个。因为当赏赐和惩罚都出自宠臣之手，其他人就不能超越其上。另一个抑制他们的手段是通过那些像他们一样自负的人与之抗衡。但因此也需要一些不偏不倚的议事大臣来保持局势的稳定，因为船如果没有压舱物就会过于颠簸不平。至少，君王可以鼓动和扶植一些更卑贱的人来与野心家们作对。就打击这些鄙夷可憎的人来说，如果他们生性懦弱，上述方法会起到很好的作用；但如果他们无惧无畏，这会导致他们图谋不轨并酿成祸害。至于将这些有野心的人从其位置上撤下来，如果事务的处理需要如此，而又不能突然行事且同时也需要确保万无一失的时候，唯一的途径是让他们时而得宠时而失宠，使他们不知道能够期待什么，就像在密林中不辨方向、不知何去何从那样。就野心而言，那种要在大事上取胜的野心，比起那种在任何事情上都要占优势的野心来说危害要小，因为那种凡事斤斤计较的野心滋生混乱，损害事务。不过，让一个野心勃勃的人忙于处理事务，而不是让他拉帮结派，也同样是危害较小的。想要在有能力的人当中出类拔萃是很繁重的任务，而这对公众来说是好事。不过，那种谋划想成为众多无名小卒中唯一大人物的人，会败坏整个时代。追求高位包含着三个意图：获得可以做善事的有利地位，能接近君王和显要，以及提升自身的运气。一个有雄心壮志的人，若他能把握这些意图中最好的那一种，他便是一个诚实正直的人；一位君主，若能够明辨有志之人心中所怀的这种意向，他便是一位贤明的君主。一般而言，君主和国家选择臣子时，应选择那些视责任义务高于升官加爵的人，还有那些对事业的热爱不是基于炫耀之心而是凭借着良心的人。所以应该将那些本性好事者与心甘情愿服务的人区分开来。

论美

美德就好比一块宝石，朴素的装饰最能映衬它的价值。无疑，美德存在于外表动人者身上最好不过，不过若没有精致的容貌，在气质方面展现出的庄重大方也会胜过容貌的姣美。此外，拥有俊俏容颜者也拥有杰出的德行是不多见的，仿佛大自然太过于繁忙只求没有差错而已，而不愿意在塑造卓越上花费更多的工夫，因此这些人虽然拥有标致的外貌，却没有优秀的精神气质，对行为举止的钻研热情要高于对德行的追求。但情况也不总是如此，因为奥古斯都·恺撒、提图斯·维斯帕西亚努斯[74]、法国国王美男子菲利普[75]、英国国王爱德华四世[76]、雅典的亚西比德[77]、波斯统治者伊斯梅尔，都志存高远、气宇轩昂，并且也是他们所处时代中第一等的美男子。就美而言，容貌之美要胜过肤色之美，而优雅得体的举止之美又胜过容貌之美。美最摄人心魄之处，是用图画也难以表达的，是第一眼难以发现的。任何一种精妙绝伦的美在其比例上都会有一些独特和奇妙之处。一个人很难说出阿佩里斯[78]和阿尔伯特·丢勒[79]谁更为不明智。他们中的一位，用几何比例来画人；另外一位，取若干面孔的最佳部分来构造一张完美的脸庞。这样画出来的人，我想，除了能取悦画家自己，谁也取悦不了。我不是认为一位画家不能描绘出一张前所未有的俊美面孔，而是认为他应该在创作时运用一种巧妙的画法（就如音乐家在谱曲时蕴涵的神韵），而不是依据规则来创作。如果你对人的脸进行一部分一部分的仔细观察，那你是找不到一张能视为美的面庞的，人应该将面孔作为整体来看，这样才能发现其动人之处。如果美的主要部分是存在于端庄的举止中这句话是真的，那么确实不会令人惊奇的是，有些人历经岁月风霜后却似乎更为可爱了，“美之迟暮也是美的”。[80]因为如若不宽容，并且将青春年少本身视为对美的弥补，就没有青年人能算是美丽的。美就像是夏日的水果，容易腐坏，不易长久保持；并且大多数情况下，美造就了放荡不羁的青年人，也造成了悔恨的老年时代。但仍然确定无疑的是，如果美能适当地起作用的话，它会使美德闪耀，使恶习赧颜。

论残疾

有残疾的人与造物主通常是互不亏欠的，因为造物主既然对他们不公，他们对造物主也同样如此。他们中的绝大多数（如《圣经》中所说的）都天性凉薄，从而他们以此方式报复了造物主。的确，身体与心灵之间是存在着一种一致性的，当造物主在一方面出了错，在另一方面就有风险。但因为人可以自己构筑心灵，不像身体，只能受命于自然，所以决定天性的星宿有时会被修养和德行的太阳光辉所遮掩。因此这样去做才是可取的，即不应将残疾仅仅看作一种表象，那会更使人受到蒙蔽，而是应视其为一种原因，这种原因通常都会产生一定的结果。那些身体上有着无法改变的某些缺陷的人，这些缺陷的确会致使别人对他不敬，但同时他们也拥有了将其自身从被鄙视的境况中解救出来的永恒动力。从而，所有身体有残缺的人都是极其勇敢的——最初是在作为被鄙视的对象时对自身尊严的维护，随着时间的推移，便成了一种普遍的习惯。此外，这对他们的勤勉也有所裨益，尤其是在注意和观察别人的弱点时，这使得他们在回敬之时不会毫无准备。此外，对比他们更有优势的人而言，残疾的状况能平息针对他们的妒忌，因为这些人认为身体残缺的人不过是任人藐视的对象而已。而且这也会使得他们的竞争者和对手麻痹大意，因为他们决不相信身有残疾的人会有升迁的可能性，直到他们看到这些人获得了相关的职位。所以，就这些情况而言，残疾的人若有过人的才智，其残疾反而是使其晋升的优势。古代的君主（并且在一些当代的国家中依然如此）惯于对宦官施以极大的信任，因为宦官妒恨一切人，对于专制君主是会更为依赖和更为尽职的。然而虽然君主们对宦官加以信任，但更多的是将其作为有用的耳目和告密者，而并非作为清正廉明的官员和政府职员来加以任用。对于身形残疾的人情况也多半类似。然而，最根本的是，如果他们有志气，他们应努力使自己从被鄙视的境况中解脱，可凭借的办法无外乎美德或邪念。因此若这些人之中产生了优秀的人才也不足为怪，例如，阿格西劳斯[81]、苏里曼的儿子赞格、伊索[82]、秘鲁总督加斯卡。对于一些人来说，苏格拉底[83]也可以算是他们中的一员。

论建筑

房屋是建造来居住的，而不是建造来观赏的，因此其用途应当优先于其样式，除非这两者可以兼具。将那些仅仅是出于美观的目的而建造起来的、有着金碧辉煌装饰的房屋都留作诗人笔下的魔幻宫殿吧，他们建造这些宫殿实在花费不了什么成本。建造了一幢好房屋，但地理环境不好，就等于犯了将自己囚禁起来的错误。我所认为的不佳环境，不仅指那里的空气有害健康，而且也指那里的空气流动不均。就像许多精巧的屋舍坐落在小山丘上，周围更高的山将其环抱，从而太阳散发出的热量都郁积于此，而且风汇集于此犹如水槽之聚水一般，所以会忽然之间感觉到极其明显的热或冷，就好像同时居住在几个不同的地方一样。除了空气状况不好导致地理环境不佳之外，道路状况的不好、集市状况的不良，以及（如果你征求执掌嘲笑和非难的莫默斯神的意见）邻居的不善，也都是房屋位置不好的原因。我还没有提及更多的因素：水源的匮乏；林木、阴凉之处、庇护之所的不足；丰饶土地的缺乏，以及各种类型的土地混合；景色的稀缺；开阔平坦土地的缺少；近距离范围内适宜放鹰狩猎或竞速运动的场所的缺失；太靠近海边，或太偏离海边；未拥有河流可通航之便，拥有河流容易泛滥之不便；距离大城市太远，这会阻碍事业发展，或者距离大城市太近，这会使得人们过于依赖商贸，使得开销高昂；一个可以使人积聚大产业的地点也会使人局促不能发展。所有的这些，因为任何一个地方不可能同时都具备，所以对其有所了解并有所打算是错不了的，一个人应尽其所能让自己的居所拥有更多的优势。如果能够有好几处房产的话，他可以各取所长，一处所短缺的在另一处可以得到。卢库勒斯[84]对庞培的巧妙回答即是如此，当庞培在卢库勒斯的一处住宅看到富丽堂皇的走廊和十分宽敞明快的房间，问道：“这的确是消夏的好地方，但你冬天怎么办呢？”卢库勒斯回答说：“为什么，难道你认为我还不如一些在冬天来临之时就变换了自己住所的鸟类聪明吗？”

从房子的处所说到房屋本身。我们将像西塞罗在其演讲术中所做的那样展开论述。西塞罗撰著了几本《论演说家》的书，以及一本名为《演说家》的书，前几本书中他陈述了演讲之术的规律，后一本书是关于演说的至高境界。因此我们先描述一个君王的宫殿，使之作为一个简单的模型。因为令人奇怪的是，如今在欧洲，虽然有梵蒂冈和埃斯科里亚尔[85]，以及其他的大型建筑，但是仍然缺少一个非常宜人而堪称典范的房间。

因此，首先我认为，如果你的宫殿没有两个不同的侧楼，就不能算是完美的宫殿。一部分用于酒宴筵席，就像《旧约·以斯帖书》中所说的那样，而另一部分用于日常家居生活；一部分用于盛会和庆典，另一部分用于居住。按我的理解，这两部分不必都仅限于建筑的后部，也可以部分位于前部。虽然内部分隔为几个不同的部分，但在外观上合为一体，并且这两部分应位于宫殿前部正中高大庄严的塔楼的两侧，那么就像是塔楼将它们从两侧连接了起来。我认为在用于宴请的那一部分前部，楼上只安排一个舒适的房间就可以了，这个房间约40英尺高，其下部的房间用于更衣打扮或在举行庆典的时候作为准备的场所。另外一部分，也就是用于家居生活的部分，首先我希望它分为大厅和小教堂（中间要分隔开来），这两处都要设计得当和宽敞。并且它们不要将所有的空间都占据，在更远的末端分别有一个冬天和夏日的会客室，这两个会客室都应该装饰得当。在这些房间的底层，要有一个好用并且宽大的地窖，以及一些带有食品酒类储藏室和餐具室的私人厨房等。就前面提及的高塔来说，我认为在其两翼之上应该高出两层，每一层应有18英尺高，顶部以优质铅皮覆盖，并围以栏杆，其间布以雕像为装饰。塔楼也应分出具有不同功用的房间。通向高处房间的楼梯，应使之修建在外露的螺旋中柱上，用漆有黄铜色图案的雕木对栏杆进行修饰，并在顶部设置一个非常适宜观景的平台。但要这样做的话，必须是你没有将下部的房间指定用于仆从用餐，否则你进餐后又要闻仆从的饭菜——因为饭菜的气味会升腾上来，就像在隧道里一般浓郁不散。对于宫殿的前部就说这么多了。不过还有一点，我认为第一层楼梯的高度应为16英尺，也就是楼下房间的高度。

除了前面部分之外，宫殿还应有一个漂亮的庭院，但庭院的三面建筑都应该比宫殿前部低许多。并且在这座庭院的四个角上都应有角楼，其外部有精致楼廊而不是在建筑内部修建楼梯。但这些角楼不能高于前部建筑，应与建筑相互协调。在庭院中不必铺路，因为那样会使得在夏日非常炎热而在冬日十分寒冷。但一些边上和贯穿庭院的小路是需要的，其余的地方种植草皮，并使之常得到修剪，但修剪也不要过于频繁。举行宴会那一部分建筑的后部，应全部建为精巧的走廊。在这些走廊上，根据其距离长短设置有三五个圆顶阁，距离均等，并精心修饰以绘有各种图案的彩绘窗扇。在用于居家生活的一侧，应有会客之所和一般的休闲娱乐之所以及一些卧房；让三面的房间都呈门门相对的布局，而不是让一面的房间始终暴露于光照中，这样不论上午或下午，都有能够避开阳光直射的房间。你也应该将房间建造成同时适用于夏天和冬天的，使之在夏天的时候阴凉，在冬天的时候温暖。你有时也会遇到一些满是玻璃窗的美丽房子，让人在其中不知如何避开日晒和寒冷。就内弓形的窗户来说，我认为它们有很好的用途（的确在城市中，竖式的窗户更好，考虑到街道两侧需要整齐划一来说），因为它们可以将用于会议的房间与外界很好的隔离开来。除此之外，它们也将风吹和日晒阻隔开来，因为那些能贯通室内的风和日光很难透过此类窗户。但这种窗户也不宜过多，在面朝庭院的两边墙上共有四个就可以了。

在这个庭院后边，还应有一个面积和高度都与之相当的内院，被四面的花园所环抱；在其内部四周则筑以回廊，配以美丽大方的拱门，高度与第一层楼相当。在面朝花园的底层部分，应修建为洞室，或纳凉之地或消夏之所。它们的开口和窗户都只面向花园，并且与地面保持水平，而不沉入地下哪怕一点，以避免各种潮气湿气。此外，在这个庭院的中间，还应有一座喷泉，或者一些精雕细琢的雕像。其道路铺设与其他庭院相同。这些房屋中，位于两侧的供个人居住使用，位于后面的则供个人秘密使用。还有你必须在这些房屋中设置一间养病室，以备君王或任何一位要人生病之需，并配有会客室、卧房和前厅后室。这个养病室位于第二层。在第一层，设置一个雅致的、开放式的、下有柱子的游廊；在第三层也是如此，设有立柱的开放式游廊。能在其中饱览花园中的美景和呼吸清新空气。在更远处的两个角上，与之相呼应，可修建两个精美华丽、铺陈高雅、装饰美轮美奂、以水晶般的玻璃精心修饰的小阁，中间配以华美的圆屋顶，其他各种各类可以想到的精妙物件作为装饰。在较高的游廊那里，我也希望如果条件允许，应有一些喷泉从墙面的若干个地方流下，同时配备良好的排水设施。以上这些就是关于宫殿的模型，除此之外，在通向宫殿前面建筑之前，应有三个庭院。首先是一个简单朴素的绿色庭院，有围墙；其次是一个类似的庭院，但装饰更丰美，有小角塔，或者在墙面上进行大量的修饰；第三个庭院，在宫殿前面形成一个广场，既不需要什么建筑，也不需要无装饰的墙将其围住，而是以平台将其环绕，上面覆以铅质屋顶，并在三面进行奢华的装饰；内部设以游廊，用柱子而不用拱门支撑。至于办公场所，应与宫殿保持一定的距离，用一些低的游廊将它们与宫殿连接起来。

论花园

万能的上帝是花园的第一个缔造者。的确，赏花弄草是人类乐趣当中最为单纯的一种。花园对于振作人的精神有着不可估量的效果，如果建筑和宫殿没有花园，那就不过是粗俗的作品罢了。一个人可以了解到，当时代日益向文明和高雅发展时，人们通常先谈及高大的建筑然后才谈及精巧的花园，仿佛花园是更为完美的。我确实认为，在皇家花园的设计上，应该是一年当中12个月都有美景。其中，每个季节的几种最美的花木依次呈现。就12月和1月，以及11月的后半部分来说，你应该种植那些整个冬日都常青的植物：冬青、常春藤、月桂、杜松、柏树、紫杉、林刺葵、枞树、迷迭香、薰衣草；白色、紫色和蓝色的长春花；石蚕草、菖蒲；橙树、柠檬树；桃金娘，如果它们能被种植在温室里的话；还有香墨角兰，也需要保暖。接着，对于1月的后半部分和2月，应种植即将开放的丁香花树；番红花，黄色和灰色均可；报春花、银莲花、开得较早的郁金香、风信子、小鸢尾、贝母。到了3月，应该有紫罗兰，尤其是那种单瓣蓝色的盛放最早；黄水仙、雏菊、盛开的杏树、开满花的桃树、正在开花的山茱萸树、多花蔷薇。在接着到来的4月中，有重瓣的白色紫罗兰、桂竹香、康乃馨、黄花九轮草、鸢尾花，以及各种各样的百合花；迷迭香、郁金香、重瓣牡丹、淡色水仙、法国忍冬；樱花、李花和梅花、枝繁叶茂的山椃、丁香树。在5月和6月里，出现的是各类石竹，尤其是浅粉红色的石竹；各种玫瑰，除了麝香玫瑰之外——因为它开放得较晚；忍冬、草莓、牛舌草、耧斗菜；非洲万寿菊、果实累累的樱桃树、醋栗、果满枝头的无花果树、树莓、葡萄花、盛开的薰衣草、开白花的香兰；麝香兰、山百合、开花的苹果树。7月当中，有多种多样的紫罗兰、淡粉色的玫瑰、酸橙花、挂果较早的梨树和结果的李子树、苹果树、未熟的小苹果。8月中各色各样的李子和梅子都成熟了，还有梨子、杏子、伏牛花、榛子、甜瓜、各种颜色的附子。在9月中，有葡萄、苹果、万紫千红的罂粟花、桃子、榅桲、油桃、山茱萸、冬梨、柑橘。在10月和11月的前半个月中能营造景观的，有枸杞、西洋李，通过修剪或移植使之较晚开放的玫瑰、蜀葵等，诸如此类。这些花草植物是根据伦敦的气候挑选出来的，但是我的意思显而易见，也就是你根据地方的特点因地制宜，就能拥有永恒的春天。

因为飘洒在空气中而不是在人的手中，鲜花的芬芳更为香甜（就像乐曲中的颤音一样婉转缠绵），因此要了解哪些花儿和植物的气味最为馥郁，最有助于获得这种乐趣。粉红色品种和红色品种的玫瑰都不是容易散发出香味的花，所以当你经过一整排这种玫瑰时，却嗅不到一点它们的芳香，即便是在满布朝露的清晨也是如此。月桂在生长的过程中也不散发香气，迷迭香也很少散发香气，香墨角兰也是这样。其他在空气中散发香气的花儿当中，香味最为浓郁的莫过于紫罗兰，尤其是白色的重瓣紫罗兰，一年绽放两次，一次是在4月中旬，一次是在8月24日的圣巴塞洛缪节之时；其次就是麝香玫瑰；此外就是草莓叶枯萎的时候，带着一种最为怡神的气味；然后就是葡萄花，它是一种微小的花朵，就像苇草的小花，起初是成簇生长开放的；再则就是甜石楠；还有黄色紫罗兰，种植在会客室或低层房间的窗外最惹人喜爱；接着还有石竹花和康乃馨，尤其是花坛石竹和丁香康乃馨；其次就是酸橙花的花香味；还有就是忍冬花，所以它们得种得远一些才好。我没有谈论到豆类的花，因为它们属于田间花朵。但在其他方面，那些最能让空气芬芳怡人而并非供人在一旁流连忘返，而是被踩踏和挤压的，有三种，那就是地榆、野麝香草以及水薄荷。因此你应将小径旁种满此类植物，当你漫步或徜徉的时候可以尽情享受它们的香气带来的愉悦。

对于花园来说（上述的种种当然都是关于君王的花园，就像我们讨论建筑时那样），其面积应不少于30英亩，并且应划分为三个部分：在入口处是一片如茵绿地；在出口处应该是一片荒地或沙地；中间的是主花园，两边是小路。并且我认为应有4英亩的土地用于绿地，6英亩的土地用于荒地，两边各用4英亩，12英亩作为主花园。绿地有两种妙用：其一，没有什么比看到精心修剪的绿色草地更为舒适悦目；其次，因为绿地的中间会给你提供一条美丽的小径，将你引向一道气派庄严并将花园围绕的树篱前。但因为小径会比较长，并且在一年或一天之中最热的时候，你应不必冒着日晒行走在绿地的小径去花园乘凉，因此你应在绿地的两侧设置可遮阳的小路，由木匠来建造，约12英尺高，这样你可以在阴凉中走到花园中。至于用各种颜色的泥土安设花坛、形成图案，它们可以位于花园旁边房屋的窗户下边，这些都是小巧的玩意儿而已，你在糖果点心那里可能已经多次看到这样的设计了。花园最好是正方形的，四周围绕着气派的有拱门的树篱，这些拱门矗立在木匠修建的柱子上，约有10英尺高和6英尺宽，拱门之间的距离应与拱门的宽度一致。在拱门之上还有约4英尺高的整道树篱，也是由木工构建而成的。并且在更高一层的树篱之上，在每个拱门上方，都有一个小的角塔，其中部凸起的空间，恰恰能容纳一个鸟笼。在拱门之间的上方可布置一些小雕像及宽大的圆形镀金彩色玻璃，让阳光可以尽情地挥洒。但这个树篱我想要建造在慢坡上，不能陡峭，而是平缓的斜坡，约6英尺高，上边种植各色花儿。并且我认为这个正方形的花园不应该占据土地整个面积，而是应在两侧留有足够的空间，可用于各种小径的营造，前面提到的绿地间的遮阳小路可以将你引向这些小径。不过，在这个树篱围绕的花园的两端应没有带树篱的小路。在通向花园的一端不设有这种小路，是为了保证从绿地望过来时，你的视野能触及那精心设计的树篱；在更远的一端也不设有这种小路，是为了使你从树篱的拱门中望出去，能看到花园背后的荒地。

至于高大的树篱内部花园的布置，我认为应该给风格各异的设计留下发挥的空间，无论你要将花园设计成何种风格，要奉劝的忠告是：首先，不可太过于烦琐或繁杂。在这一点上，就我个人而言，我并不喜欢在杜松或其他花园里的树木上雕刻图案——这是给孩子们看的。我非常喜欢低矮的小树篱，修剪成圆形，就像衣饰上的绲边一样，再配以一些漂亮的棱锥，在一些地方，设有木工雕刻的美观柱子。我也同样喜欢将小路设计得宽阔大方。在花园两侧你可以修建有顶篷的小道，但在花园的主体部分则不适宜这样做。我也希望，在花园的正中，有一座精致的小山，拾阶而上共有三层，其道路的宽度可供四人并肩而行。我也认为道路可以完全环绕于小山，无须扶栏或浮雕装饰。整座小山30英尺高，并设有宴会厅，其中装有整洁考究的壁炉，不要安装太多的玻璃窗。

喷泉是非常美丽和赏心悦目的。水塘则会有损花园的风貌，使得花园不益于健康并且充斥着苍蝇和青蛙。我认为喷泉有两种类型：一种是喷水或者冒水的，另一种是澄澈的蓄水池，约30或40英尺见方，其中既不养鱼也无淤泥和泥浆沉底。就第一种喷泉来说，若以镀金或大理石材质的雕像作为装饰品，会很不错，但问题的关键在于使水潺潺流动，而不是在水钵和水槽中停滞不畅。不流动的水会被污染，从而发绿、发红或诸如此类，要不然就是聚集了苔藓或各种腐败物。除此之外，喷泉应每日及时清洁。喷泉若饰以一些阶梯，同时周围配以一些精心铺设的路面，也会有良好的效果。至于另外一种类型的喷泉，我们可将其称为浴池。它承载着许多遐思和拥有许多美观的设计，我们就不必自找麻烦了。例如，池子底部应精心铺设，装饰以图案，池子的两侧也是如此，并且用彩色的玻璃，以及其他有光泽的物品进行修饰，以有小雕像的精巧栏杆环绕之。然而论及这种喷泉的要点，与我们谈论前一种喷泉时是相同的，也就是让水能够长流不止，通过比池子更高的水提供源头，并通过精良的喷管进行输送，然后用均等大小的出水孔由地下将水排出，这样水就不会积郁池中。至于那些精妙的设计，例如使水流如虹而不溅或使水以各种形状喷洒（羽毛的形状、酒杯的形状、华盖的形状等），它们都十分宜人眼目，但对于修身养性没有什么裨益。

就园中的荒地来说，也就是我们园林规划中的第三部分，我认为应该尽可能地设计出具有真正自然的荒野气息。我想其中不必栽种树木，但可种植一些灌木，除了多花蔷薇和金银花之外，再有一些野葡萄间杂其中。地上多种植紫罗兰、草莓和樱草，因为这些草木可以散发香气，在荫庇之处也会茂盛生长。而且这些草木在荒地之中的种植是随意的，到处都可以，并没有什么既定的次序。我也喜欢有些堆积的小土丘，性质与鼹鼠的窝一样（就像是在真正的荒野中那样），有些种上野生的百里香，有些种上石竹花，有些种上会长出悦目花儿的石蚕草，有些种上长春花，有些种上紫罗兰，有些种上草莓，有些种上黄花九轮草，有些种上雏菊，有些种上红玫瑰，有些种上山百合，有些种上红色的美洲石竹，有些种上熊掌花以及类似的虽不名贵，却同样芬芳和好看的花卉。一些小土丘的顶部可以种植直立挺拔的小灌木，另一些则不必。此类小灌木有玫瑰、杜松、冬青、伏牛花（但要分散开来种植，因它们的香气浓郁）、红醋栗、醋栗、迷迭香、月桂、多花蔷薇等，诸如此类。但这些直立的灌木都应时常修剪，以免生长凌乱而不成形状。

就两侧的土地来说，可以在其中建造各种幽僻的小路。其中的一些小路，无论太阳有多大，都是浓荫遮蔽的。还可以将其中的一些小路建成能遮风挡雨的，当风狠狠刮着的时候，你就犹如在一个避风的走廊里行走。而且这类小路的两端都应建有树篱，可将风阻挡在外。这些有遮蔽的小路应该用碎石更为细致地铺设，不要种草，因为容易打湿鞋袜。在许多这些小路边，你应种植各式各样的果树，使之或依墙而立，或排列成行。然而一般来说，需要遵循的是，你的这些果树在小路边的种植应雅致、宽阔和低矮，不宜过高。果树的周围应种植秀丽的花卉，但稀疏和分散地种植就好，以免妨碍树木的生长。在两侧土地的尽头，我认为应各有一座有一定高度的小山，山上的树篱围墙应与胸齐平，在上面可眺望田野。

就主体花园来说，我不反对在两侧设美观大方、植有果树的小路。园中还应有种植着果树的小丘，有布置得大方有序的设座椅的凉亭。但这些不应布置得过于紧凑，而使主花园被封闭起来，空气也要可以自由流通。至于荫凉之处，我想主要依靠两侧地面的小路来获得，如果愿意，你可以在一年或一日的炎热之时，到那里去散步。但主花园是为一年之中最温和宜人的时节设计的；在炎热的夏季，则是针对清晨和黄昏，或阴天。

至于鸟舍，我并不喜欢，除非它们巨大到可以在其中铺设草皮，并且其中种植有草木，那样鸟儿才能有更多的活动范围和自然栖息之所，在鸟舍的地面上也不会有污秽物出现。

至此我已经把一个君王的花园大致勾勒了一番，部分是通过建议，部分是通过描绘，还不能算是一个模型，仅仅是花园的一些大致线条而已。在这方面我也不惜成本，但成本对于王公贵族来说算不了什么，因为他们大多时候都采纳工匠的建议，不惜斥巨资去装点他们的花园。有时为了壮观宏伟、堂皇富丽还添加雕像等诸如此类的物品，但这些对于花园的真正乐趣却是毫无助益。

论交涉

一般而言，通过言谈进行交涉比通过书信要好，而通过第三者进行调解又比本人出面要好。书信在如下情况中应用是好的，即当一个人想要通过反馈的信件获取一个答复时，或者一个人将来在辩护中可以出示他个人的信件时，又或者交涉被打断或者只是被只字片言地听到的时候。亲自进行交涉较好的情况是，当一个人的容貌能够令人肃然起敬时，就像通常在下属面前那样；或者在一些微妙的场合下，当看着谈话对象的面容就能把握说话的尺度时；还有一般情况下，当一个人需要给自己保留一定的自由，不论是否认的自由还是解释的自由的时候。在调解人的选择上，最好是选择那种性格坦率的人，这种人会按要求完成他们的使命，并且回来如实地汇报其成绩；而不是选择那种狡诈的人，这种人会设法用别人的功绩来荣耀自己，并且在报告中将事情描述得无往不利以使委托人满意。同样的，也应任用那些一经雇用便尽职尽责的人，因为这会使得事半功倍。并且应任用那些才能与其职责相当的人，例如大胆的人适合告诫，精于言辞的人适合说服，灵活的人适合调查和观察，顽固荒诞的人适合处理那些不符情理的事务。而且也应雇用那些此前你任用他们处理事务时拥有幸运和占有优势的人，因为这些经历会增加他们的自信，并且他们会尽力去保持自己的名声。与人打交道、交谈时由远及近较好，而不是一开始就直奔主题，除非你旨在通过一些突然的提问让其感到意外和惊讶。与那些有所欲求的人打交道，比起与那些已经达到他们目的的人打交道要好。如果一个人与另一个人打交道是建立在一定条件上的，那么事情的开端或者所采取的第一个行动就是至关重要的。一个人没有理由要求对方先行，除非事情的本质确定了谁应首先采取行动；或者你能说服另一方，使其确定在其他事情或方面他仍然是有利用价值的；又或者他被抬举为一个相当有信誉的人。所有交涉的实践无非就是去发现，或者去任用。人在被信任时、情绪激动时、未察觉未戒备时、迫不得已时，也就是当他们要办成某事而缺乏恰当的借口时，最能显现自我。如果你要任用某些人，你不仅要知道他的品性和风格，以便对其进行引导；还要了解其目标，以便对其进行说服；或者要知道他的短处与长处，以便能使其感到敬畏；或者要了解其他与其有利害关系的人，以便对其进行控制。在与老奸巨猾的人打交道时，我们必须明确他们的目的，以理解他们的言谈。对他们出言简约而谨慎是错不了的，言谈也应使他们出乎意料为佳。在所有艰难的交涉中，一个人不应当希冀同时播种和收获，而是应当细心和充分地为交涉的事务进行准备，并逐步促使其成熟。

论请托者

许多肮脏的勾当和谋划都有人包揽承担，然而私人求情的的确确败坏了公众的利益。许多很好的事情被心术不正者承担。我在这里所说的不仅仅是那些腐败堕落的人，也包括那些并不打算真正做事情想要投机取巧的人。一些接受求情之托的人实际上根本没有想要去做一些实际的事情，但如果他们看到借助其他人这件事情会有起色的时候，他们就会心安理得地去获得感谢，或接受第二次酬谢，又或者至少与此同时对请托者的希望能造成一定影响。一些人接受别人的请托仅仅是为了有机会对其他人进行阻挠；或是凭此制造一些信息用于他们一直没有适当借口来对付的那些人，当这些行为得以实现后，他们并不关心被请托之事的动向；或者，一般而言，接受请托之人是将别人的事务作为一种能有利于自身事务发展的事情来看待的。而且，有些人承应下别人的请托，是抱着让这些事情不能做成的想法，其目的在于取悦对立的一方或竞争者。的确，在每一件请托的事情中，都是有一定的对错之分的。如果是一场纠纷的请托，就有公平公正的对错问题；如果是一桩请愿的请托，则有功过的问题。如果在审判中一个人受到感情的左右偏向了错误的一方，他最好使用他的影响力去和解这件事情，而不是做得太过分。如果私情使得一个人偏向了在功绩方面不占优势的一方，他在这样做的同时，最好不要贬损或伤害成就更突出的一方。在一个人遇到不甚了解的请托案例时，不妨去请教一些值得信任和有见地的朋友，从他们那里能够知晓这些请托的事务的处理是否会涉及信誉。但这些咨询者的选择应当审慎，因为弄不好就会被别人牵着鼻子走。请托者对于拖延和辜负十分地厌恶，所以如果要拒绝接受请托，一开始就要坦率地讲清楚，要么就仅仅在事成之后再进行报告，还有就是不索取超过自己应得的酬谢，这不仅仅是高尚的，而且也是得体的。在被接受的请托中，谁第一次提出请托往往是没什么分量的。我们应考虑的是请托人的信任，如果不是因为他，关于此事的一些消息就难以获得，我们不能从中获取了好处却让他继续用其他方法到别处再寻求帮助，而是应该在一定程度上补偿他的发现。对被请托之事价值的无知是愚蠢；而对被请托之事是非的无知就是良知的缺乏。请托过程中行事机密是最为可取的方法，因为对请托之事鲁莽地大肆声张会使得一类请托者感到泄气，但也使得另一类请托者行动迅速和更为清醒。时机得当对于请托之事至关紧要。我认为，时机得当不仅仅指受请托之人会将事情应承下来，同时也指不会受到其他人的阻挠。一个人在选择需要任用的人时，应选择最适合的人，而不是选择最有权势的人，应选择专门处理该事务的人而不是选择统管一切的人。如果一个人初次请托遭到拒绝时表现得既不沮丧也非不满，那么所获得的补偿就是会使得下一次请托成功。在一个得到宠爱的人那里，“应要求得比适当的更多，这样你才能得到你所应得到的”[86]不失为一条好准则，反过来对于请托之事要求的提出只能是渐进的，因为一开始就冒险的话会失去他的请托者。而以后若还是如此的话，他就不仅会失去他的请托者，同时也会失去他之前获得的好感。对一个大人物索要一封推荐信被认为是最容易不过的事情，然而如果缺乏一个好的推荐理由，那么这个大人物的名誉就会大打折扣。再没有比如今这些替人奔走、包揽请托的人更糟糕的了，因为他们只是妨碍公共事务的毒药和传染病。

论学问

治学益于陶冶情操、修身养性、增长才干。陶冶情操体现于独处和隐居之时；修身养性体现在言谈举止之间；增长才干则体现于对事务的判断和处置。行家里手虽能践行，并且可能在特殊事务上能够逐一进行判别，但就统筹兼顾及事务的策划和统领来说，只有那些有学识的人才能做得最好。在学问上花费过多的时间容易使人懒惰；将学问过多地用于修身养性是矫情；完全依赖学问中的规则作出判断是读书人的学究气。治学使得性情更为完善，并且学识也通过经验得到完善。因为天赋的能力有如野生的植物，需要通过治学来修剪；而学问本身给予的方向引导又过于宽泛，除非它们得到经验的约束。狡猾的人蔑视学问，单纯的人钦佩学问，聪明的人使用学问。学问的传授并不包括如何使用学问，学问的运用是在学问之外并且高于学问的一种智慧，要通过观察来获得。读书不是为了要辩驳，也不是要盲目信从，更不是为了寻找谈资和讨论的话题，而是为了权衡和思考。一些书籍是需要慢慢品味的，而其他的一些则可以囫囵吞枣，还有少数的书籍需要咀嚼和消化。也就是说，一些书籍只需阅读其中的部分章节；另一些可以阅读，但不需非常仔细；而为数不多的一些书应勤勉地、全神贯注地从头至尾阅读。一些书籍也可以请人代为阅读，并请其将书中的内容摘录好，但这只能用于书中那些并不十分重要的论述，以及那些层次不很高的书籍，否则对书籍的提炼就像对水的过滤一样，只留下浮光掠影之物。读书使人充实，交谈使人机敏，写作则使人严谨。因此，如果一个人几乎不写作，那么他需要有很强的记忆力；如果一个人交谈甚少，那么他需要机智的头脑；如果一个人读书很少，那么他需要许多狡猾的伎俩，使得他看起来像是知道那些他所不了解的东西一样。读史使人明智，读诗使人聪慧，数学使人精细，自然哲学使人深沉，伦理学使人庄重，逻辑学和修辞学使人能够论辩自如。“学问塑造人的个性”。[87]而且，没有什么才智中的阻滞和障碍不能通过适当学问的锤炼来解除，就像躯体中的疾病可以通过适当的锻炼来排除一样。滚球有益于肾脾，射箭有益于胸肺，缓和的步行有益于肠胃，骑马有益于头脑，诸如此类。所以如果一个人的才智偏离了正道，就让他学习数学，因为在证明中，如果心思有一点点偏移，他就不得不从头再来。如果他的才智不善于区分或发现差异，就让他学习经院哲学，因为经院哲学家非常注重细节（吹毛求疵）。如果他不善于对事物深入探究，并且不善于使用一件事情证明或是说明另一件事情，就让他学习律师办案。由此，心智的各种缺陷都可以通过学习得到弥补。

论虚荣

伊索有一则寓言十分精彩，[88]“苍蝇坐在战车车轮的轮轴上说：‘看我扬起了多大一片尘土啊！’”一些爱慕虚荣的人也是如此，不管事情是自己发展的或是受到更大力量的推动，如果能与其拉上一点关联，他们就认为那是自己推动的。那些好炫耀的人必然是好搞派系活动的，因为所有夸耀的勇气都立足于比较之上。他们必然会极度地将自己大肆吹嘘。他们也不可能保守秘密，因此没有什么效用，如同法国谚语所说：“空话讲得多，却不做实事。”不过这种品性在民政事务中却有一定的用处。当一个具有美德和善意的观点或名声需要造就时，这类人便会是很好的鼓吹者。再有，就如提图斯·李维[89]在安太阿卡斯[90]和埃托利亚人的案例[91]中所注意到的，“对双方都说谎有时会造成惊人的效果”。如果一个人在两个君王之间进行交涉，要将他们联合起来对付第三方，就会对一方将另一方的力量夸大。有时他在人与人之间周旋，就会在一方那里佯称他与另外一方有着更大的利益关系，从而在两边都抬高自己的声誉。在这类情况中，结果通常是无中生有，因为谎言足以产生看法，而看法会带来实际的行为。在军队统领和士兵那里，自负是必不可少的要点，因为就像铁与铁的磨砺会使其更锋利，夸耀使得一个人的士气能鼓舞另一个人。在那些需要冲锋陷阵和出生入死的大事业中，有虚荣自傲的人参与，无疑会为事业注入活力，而那些有扎实敦厚和稳重清醒性格的人更像是船的压舱物而不像是风帆。在学识的名声上，如果没有值得炫耀的羽毛，那么飞黄腾达必然是迟缓的。“写《虚荣之轻视》一书的人，也不反对让自己的名字出现于扉页上。”[92]苏格拉底、亚里士多德[93]、盖伦[94]都是具有炫耀性格的人。虚荣心的确能助使一个人名垂千古，而美德却无法依靠人的本性而使人流芳百世，因为它是人们后天获得的。西塞罗、塞内加、小普林尼[95]的美名能经久不衰，这与他们的虚荣心也密切相关，就像涂油漆一样，油漆不仅使天花板发亮而且也使之能够持久。但说了这么多，当我说到虚荣时，我指的不是泰西塔斯描述的缪西阿努斯[96]的那种性格——“他有一种能够漂亮地炫耀他的一切言行的本领”。[97]因为这样的行为并不是虚荣，而是自然而然的宽宏和审慎，并且在一些人身上，这不仅仅是动人的，而且是优雅高尚的。道歉、礼让和适度的谦逊，都是夸耀的技巧。而在这些技巧当中，没有人能比小普林尼所指出的那种更为巧妙了，也就是在自己也具有的优点方面，毫不吝啬地慷慨赞扬和夸赞他人。普林尼在这一点上风趣地写道：“夸赞别人是对的，因为被夸赞的人在你所夸赞的那一点上不是比你强就是比你弱。如果他比你弱，那么既然他能得到夸赞，你就应该得到更多；如果他比你强，那么如果他不被夸赞，你就更不应该被夸赞。”[98]虚荣的人被聪明的人诟病，被愚昧的人钦佩，被寄生虫们追捧，同时他们也是自己吹嘘炫耀的奴隶。

论愤怒

追求完全地把愤怒消除，只不过是斯多葛学派的夸口罢了。我们有更好的神谕：“可以生气，但不要犯下罪过。不要让你的怒气到太阳落山还没有消除。”[99]愤怒应被加以限制和抑制，不论是在性质上还是在时间上。我们将首先谈谈如何缓和与平息发怒的自然倾向和习性；其次，谈谈如何抑制有特定动因的愤怒，或至少使其不要造成危害；最后，谈谈如何激起或平息他人的愤怒。

就第一点来说，除了对愤怒造成的后果，以及它会如何干扰人们的生活进行深入的思考，绝无其他方法。这样做的最佳时机是在愤怒的爆发完全过去之后，再对其进行回顾。塞内加说得很好：“愤怒就像毁灭，当它落到一个东西上时它自己也粉身碎骨”。[100]《圣经》劝诫我们：“要以耐性保持我们的灵魂。”[101]若有人失去耐性，也就失去了他的灵魂。人不能变成蜂，把它们的生命留在所蜇的伤口之中。[102]

愤怒的确是一种卑下的品性，因为它通常充分地暴露在它所统治的那些人的弱点中，如儿童、妇女、老人、病人。人们最好注意到的是，发怒时应带着轻蔑而不是带着恐惧，如此便能使其看起来超越了伤害而不是被伤害所击倒。这是容易做到的，如果一个人在这件事情上严于律己的话。

就第二点来说，愤怒的原因和动机主要有三类。首先，对于伤害过于敏感，因为没有人会因为自己未感到受伤害而愤怒的。因此脆弱娇嫩的人必然常常发怒，他们有太多的事情烦扰，而这些事情对于更强健的性格来说根本算不了什么。其次就是在受到伤害的情形中，领悟或构想到伤害中充满了轻蔑和侮辱。因为轻蔑会直接导致愤怒，不仅与伤害导致的愤怒相当，甚至更甚。从而，当人们善于从状况中分辨出轻蔑，他们无疑会将自己的怒火燃烧得更旺。最后，触及一个人声誉的意见将会促使愤怒加剧。在这一点上的补救办法是，一个人应该拥有如冈佐洛[103]所习惯说的：“一张绳索更为粗大的荣誉之网。”不过在抑制愤怒的所有方法中，最好不过的就是时间，并且让一个人相信，他报复的时机尚未来临，但他可以预见它到来的时刻，所以其间他会保持平静，蓄势待发。

如果怒气已经将一个人完全占据，要将愤怒抑制而不至于犯错，那有两件事情你必须要特别注意。其一，避免极端尖酸刻薄的语言，尤其如果它们是尖刻且切中要害的，“一般的恶言相向”倒不会有太大问题；再则，怒气当头时，人也不可失信泄密，因为那样会使得自己在社会中被排斥。其二，你不可因怒火中烧而独断地中止任何事务。不管你如何显示你的怨恨和恼怒，不要作出任何让事情无法挽回的举动。

就激起和平息他人的愤怒来说，关键在于选择时机。当人们最烦心和情绪最糟糕时，即是激怒他们的时机。同样，可以通过收集（就像前面所论及的）所有你能找到的事例，使轻蔑变本加厉。而对怒气的平息有两种正好相反的办法：针对前者，当第一次和一个人论及一桩令人恼怒的事务时，要选择好的时机，因为第一印象是非常深刻的；而针对后者，则是去尽可能地割断，将伤害与轻蔑侮辱之间的联系割断，将它归为误解、恐惧、热情，或任何你愿意归为的东西。

Of Revenge

Revenge is a kind of wild justice, which the more man's nature runs to, the more ought law to weed it out. For as for the first wrong, it doth but offend the law; but the revenge of that wrong putteth the law out of office. Certainly, in taking revenge a man is but even with his enemy, but in passing it over he is superior, for it is a prince's part to pardon. And Solomon, I am sure, saith, It is the glory of a man to pass by an offence.[〔1〕]That which is past is gone and irrevocable, and wise men have enough to do with things present and to come: therefore they do but trifle with themselves that labour in past matters. There is no man doth a wrong for the wrong's sake, but thereby to purchase himself profit or pleasure or honour or the like. Therefore why should I be angry with a man for loving himself better than me? And if any man should do wrong merely out of ill nature, why, yet it is but like the thorn or briar, which prick and scratch, because they can do no other. The most tolerable sort of revenge is for those wrongs which there is no law to remedy: but then let a man take heed the revenge be such as there is no law to punish; else a man's enemy is still beforehand, and it is two for one. Some, when they take revenge, are desirous the party should know whence it cometh. This is the more generous, for the delight seemeth to be not so much in doing the hurt as in making the party repent. But base and crafty cowards are like the arrow that flieth in the dark. Cosmus, Duke of Florence,[〔2〕]had a desperate saying against perfidious or neglecting friends, as if those wrongs were unpardonable: You shall read (saith he) that we are commanded to forgive our enemies; but you never read that we are commanded to forgive our friends. But yet the spirit of Job was in a better tune: Shall we (saith he) take good at God's hands, and not be content to take evil also?[〔3〕]And so of friends in a proportion. This is certain, that a man that studieth revenge keeps his own wounds green, which otherwise would heal and do well. Public revenges are for the most part fortunate: as that for the death of Caesar, for the death of Pertinax, for the death of Henry the Third of France, and many more. But in private revenges it is not so. Nay rather, vindicative persons live the life of witches, who, as they are mischievous, so end they infortunate.

注释

〔1〕　From Proverbs 19.11.

〔2〕　Cosimo de' Medici, d. 1574: the saying has not been traced.

〔3〕　Job 2.10.

Of Parents and Children

The joys of parents are secret, and so are their griefs and fears: they cannot utter the one, nor they will not utter the other. Children sweeten labours, but they make misfortunes more bitter: they increase the cares of life, but they mitigate the remembrance of death. The perpetuity by generation is common to beasts, but memory, merit, and noble works are proper to men. And surely a man shall see the noblest works and foundations have proceeded from childless men, which have sought to express the images of their minds, where those of their bodies have failed. So the care of posterity is most in them that have no posterity. They that are the first raisers of their houses are most indulgent towards their children, beholding them as the continuance not only of their kind but of their work; and so both children and creatures.

The difference in affection of parents towards their several children is many times unequal, and sometimes unworthy, especially in the mother. As Solomon saith, A wise son rejoiceth the father, but an ungracious son shames the mother.[〔1〕]A man shall see, where there is a house full of children, one or two of the eldest respected, and the youngest made wantons, but in the midst some that are as it were forgotten, who many times nevertheless prove the best. The illiberality of parents in allowance towards their children is an harmful error, makes them base, acquaints them with shifts, makes them sort with mean company, and makes them surfeit more when they come to plenty. And therefore the proof is best when men keep their authority towards their children, but not their purse. Men have a foolish manner (both parents and schoolmasters and servants) in creating and breeding an emulation between brothers during childhood, which many times sorteth to discord when they are men, and disturbeth families. The Italians make little difference between children and nephews or near kinsfolks; but so they be of the lump, they care not though they pass not through their own body. And, to say truth, in nature it is much a like matter, insomuch that we see a nephew sometimes resembleth an uncle or a kinsman more than his own parent, as the blood happens. Let parents choose betimes the vocations and courses they mean their children should take, for then they are most flexible. And let them not too much apply themselves to the disposition of their children, as thinking they will take best to that which they have most mind to. It is true that if the affection or aptness of the children be extraordinary, then it is good not to cross it: but generally the precept is good, Optimum elige, suave et facile illud faciet consuetudo [Choose what is best, and habit will make it pleasant and easy].[〔2〕]Younger brothers are commonly fortunate, but seldom or never where the elder are disinherited.

注释

〔1〕　Proverbs 10.1.

〔2〕　A saying ascribed to the followers of Pythagoras, in Plutarch, On Exile, 8 (Moralia, 602B).

Of Envy

There be none of the affections which have been noted to fascinate or bewitch, but love and envy. They both have vehement wishes; they frame themselves readily into imaginations and suggestions; and they come easily into the eye, especially upon the presence of the objects: which are the points that conduce to fascination, if any such thing there be. We see likewise the Scripture calleth envy an evil eye, and the astrologers call the evil influences of the stars evil aspects, so that still there seemeth to be acknowledged, in the act of envy, an ejaculation or irradiation of the eye. Nay, some have been so curious as to note that the times when the stroke or percussion of an envious eye doth most hurt are when the party envied is beheld in glory or triumph, for that sets an edge upon envy: and besides, at such times the spirits of the person envied do come forth most into the outward parts, and so meet the blow.

But leaving these curiosities (though not unworthy to be thought on in fit place), we will handle what persons are apt to envy others; what persons are most subject to be envied themselves; and what is the difference between public and private envy.

A man that hath no virtue in himself ever envieth virtue in others. For men's minds will either feed upon their own good or upon others' evil; and who wanteth the one will prey upon the other; and whoso is out of hope to attain to another's virtue will seek to come at even hand by depressing another's fortune.

A man that is busy and inquisitive is commonly envious. For to know much of other men's matters cannot be because all that ado may concern his own estate: therefore it must needs be that he taketh a kind of play-pleasure in looking upon the fortunes of others. Neither can he that mindeth but his own business find much matter for envy. For envy is a gadding passion, and walketh the streets, and doth not keep home: Non est curiosus, quin idem sit malevolus [No one is inquisitive without being malevolent as well].[〔1〕]

Men of noble birth are noted to be envious towards new men when they rise. For the distance is altered, and it is like a deceit of the eye, that when others come on they think themselves go back.

Deformed persons and eunuchs and old men and bastards are envious. For he that cannot possibly mend his own case will do what he can to impair another's […]

The same is the case of men that rise after calamities and misfortunes. For they are as men fallen out with the times, and think other men's harms a redemption of their own sufferings.

They that desire to excel in too many matters, out of levity and vainglory, are ever envious. For they cannot want work, it being impossible but many in some one of those things should surpass them. Which was the character of Hadrian the Emperor, that mortally envied poets and painters and artificers in works wherein he had a vein to excel.

Lastly, near kinsfolks and fellows in office and those that have been bred together are more apt to envy their equals when they are raised. For it doth upbraid unto them their own fortunes, and pointeth at them, and cometh oftener into their remembrance, and incurreth likewise more into the note of others; and envy ever redoubleth from speech and fame. Cain's envy was the more vile and malignant towards his brother Abel, because when his sacrifice was better accepted there was nobody to look on. Thus much for those that are apt to envy.

Concerning those that are more or less subject to envy. First, persons of eminent virtue, when they are advanced, are less envied. For their fortune seemeth but due unto them, and no man envieth the payment of a debt, but rewards and liberality rather. Again, envy is ever joined with the comparing of a man's self, and where there is no comparison, no envy; and therefore kings are not envied but by kings. Nevertheless it is to be noted that unworthy persons are most envied at their first coming in, and afterwards overcome it better; whereas, contrariwise, persons of worth and merit are most envied when their fortune continueth long. For by that time, though their virtue be the same, yet it hath not the same lustre, for fresh men grow up that darken it.

Persons of noble blood are less envied in their rising, for it seemeth but right done to their birth. Besides, there seemeth not much added to their fortune; and envy is as the sunbeams, that beat hotter upon a bank or steep rising ground than upon a flat. And for the same reason those that are advanced by degrees are less envied than those that are advanced suddenly and per saltum [at a bound].

Those that have joined with their honour great travails, cares, or perils are less subject to envy. For men think that they earn their honours hardly, and pity them sometimes; and pity ever healeth envy. Wherefore you shall observe that the more deep and sober sort of politic persons, in their greatness, are ever bemoaning themselves what a life they lead, chanting a quanta patimur [how many things we suffer!]. Not that they feel it so, but only to abate the edge of envy. But this is to be understood of business that is laid upon men, and not such as they call unto themselves. For nothing increaseth envy more than an unnecessary and ambitious engrossing of business. And nothing doth extinguish envy more than for a great person to preserve all other inferior officers in their full rights and pre-eminences of their places. For by that means there be so many screens between him and envy.

Above all, those are most subject to envy, which carry the greatness of their fortunes in an insolent and proud manner, being never well but while they are showing how great they are, either by outward pomp, or by triumphing over all opposition or competition. Whereas wise men will rather do sacrifice to envy, in suffering themselves sometimes of purpose to be crossed and overborne in things that do not much concern them. Notwithstanding, so much is true, that the carriage of greatness in a plain and open manner (so it be without arrogancy and vainglory) doth draw less envy than if it be in a more crafty and cunning fashion. For in that course a man doth but disavow fortune, and seemeth to be conscious of his own want in worth, and doth but teach others to envy him.

Lastly, to conclude this part: as we said in the beginning that the act of envy had somewhat in it of witchcraft, so there is no other cure of envy but the cure of witchcraft; and that is, to remove the lot (as they call it) and to lay it upon another. For which purpose, the wiser sort of great persons bring in ever upon the stage somebody upon whom to derive the envy that would come upon themselves; sometimes upon ministers and servants, sometimes upon colleagues and associates, and the like; and for that turn there are never wanting some persons of violent and undertaking natures, who, so they may have power and business, will take it at any cost.

Now, to speak of public envy. There is yet some good in public envy, whereas in private there is none. For public envy is as an ostracism, that eclipseth men when they grow too great. And therefore it is a bridle also to great ones to keep them within bounds.

This envy, being in the Latin word invidia, goeth in the modern languages by the name of discontentment, of which we shall speak in handling sedition. It is a disease in a state like to infection. For as infection spreadeth upon that which is sound, and tainteth it, so when envy is gotten once into a state, it traduceth even the best actions thereof, and turneth them into an ill odour. And therefore there is little won by intermingling of plausible actions. For that doth argue but a weakness and fear of envy, which hurteth so much the more; as it is likewise usual in infections, which, if you fear them, you call them upon you.

This public envy seemeth to beat chiefly upon principal officers or ministers, rather than upon kings and estates themselves. But this is a sure rule, that if the envy upon the minister be great, when the cause of it in him is small, or if the envy be general in a manner upon all the ministers of an estate, then the envy (though hidden) is truly upon the state itself. And so much of public envy or discontentment, and the difference thereof from private envy, which was handled in the first place.

We will add this in general, touching the affection of envy, that of all other affections it is the most importune and continual. For of other affections there is occasion given but now and then. And therefore it was well said, Invidia festos dies non agit [Envy keeps no holidays], for it is ever working upon some or other. And it is also noted that love and envy do make a man pine, which other affections do not, because they are not so continual. It is also the vilest affection, and the most depraved, for which cause it is the proper attribute of the devil, who is called the envious man, that soweth tares amongst the wheat by night;[〔2〕]as it always cometh to pass that envy worketh subtly and in the dark, and to the prejudice of good things, such as is the wheat.

注释

〔1〕　Plautus, Stichus, Ⅰ.3.54.

〔2〕　Matthew 13.25.

Of Empire

It is a miserable state of mind to have few things to desire and many things to fear. And yet that commonly is the case of kings, who, being at the highest, want matter of desire, which makes their minds more languishing; and have many representations of perils and shadows, which makes their minds the less clear. And this is one reason also of that effect which the Scripture speaketh of, that the king's heart is inscrutable.[〔1〕]For multitude of jealousies, and lack of some predominant desire that should marshal and put in order all the rest, maketh any man's heart hard to find or sound. Hence it comes likewise that princes many times make themselves desires, and set their hearts upon toys: sometimes upon a building; sometimes upon erecting of an order; sometimes upon the advancing of a person; sometimes upon obtaining excellency in some art or feat of the hand - as Nero for playing on the harp, Domitian for certainty of the hand with the arrow, Commodus for playing at fence, Caracalla for driving chariots,[〔2〕]and the like. This seemeth incredible unto those that know not the principle, that the mind of man is more cheered and refreshed by profiting in small things than by standing at a stay in great. We see also that kings that have been fortunate conquerors in their first years, it being not possible for them to go forward infinitely, but that they must have some check or arrest in their fortunes, turn in their latter years to be superstitious and melancholy; as did Alexander the Great, Diocletian[〔3〕]and in our memory Charles the Fifth[〔4〕]and others. For he that is used to go forward, and findeth a stop, falleth out of his own favour and is not the thing he was.

To speak now of the true temper of empire: it is a thing rare and hard to keep, for both temper and distemper consist of contraries. But it is one thing to mingle contraries, another to interchange them. The answer of Apollonius to Vespasian is full of excellent instruction. Vespasian asked him, What was Nero's overthrow? He answered: Nero could touch and tune the harp well; but in government, sometimes he used to wind the pins too high, sometimes to let them down too low.[〔5〕]And certain it is that nothing destroyeth authority so much as the unequal and untimely interchange of power pressed too far, and relaxed too much.

This is true, that the wisdom of all these latter times in princes' affairs is rather fine deliveries and shiftings of dangers and mischiefs when they are near, than solid and grounded courses to keep them aloof. But this is but to try masteries with fortune. And let men beware how they neglect and suffer matter of trouble to be prepared: for no man can forbid the spark nor tell whence it may come. The difficulties in princes' business are many and great, but the greatest difficulty is often in their own mind. For it is common with princes (saith Tacitus) to will contradictories: Sunt plerumque regum voluntates vehementes, et inter se contrariae [The desires of kings are mostly vehement, and incompatible with one another].[〔6〕]For it is the solecism of power to think to command the end, and yet not to endure the mean.

Kings have to deal with their neighbours, their wives, their children, their prelates or clergy, their nobles, their second-nobles or gentlemen, their merchants, their commons, and their men of war; and from all these arise dangers, if care and circumspection be not used.

First for their neighbours: there can no general rule be given (the occasions are so variable), save one which ever holdeth. Which is that princes do keep due sentinel that none of their neighbours do overgrow so (by increase of territory, by embracing of trade, by approaches, or the like) as they become more able to annoy them than they were. And this is generally the work of standing councils to foresee and to hinder it. During that triumvirate of kings, King Henry the Eighth of England, Francis the First, King of France, and Charles the Fifth, Emperor, there was such a watch kept, that none of the three could win a palm of ground but the other two would straightways balance it, either by confederation or, if need were, by a war, and would not in any wise take up peace at interest. And the like was done by that league (which Guicciardini saith was the security of Italy) made between Ferdinando, King of Naples, Lorenzius Medices, and Ludovicus Sforza, potentates, the one of Florence, the other of Milan.[〔7〕]Neither is the opinion of some of the Schoolmen to be received, that a war cannot justly be made but upon a precedent injury or provocation. For there is no question but a just fear of an imminent danger, though there be no blow given, is a lawful cause of a war.

For their wives: there are cruel examples of them. Livia is infamed for the poisoning of her husband; Roxolana, Solyman's wife, was the destruction of that renowned prince, Sultan Mustapha, and otherwise troubled his house and succession;[〔8〕]Edward the Second of England his queen[〔9〕]had the principal hand in the deposing and murther of her husband. This kind of danger is then to be feared chiefly when the wives have plots for the raising of their own children, or else that they be advoutresses.

For their children: the tragedies likewise of dangers from them have been many. And generally the entering of fathers into suspicion of their children hath been ever unfortunate. The destruction of Mustapha (that we named before) was so fatal to Solyman's line, as the succession of the Turks from Solyman until this day is suspected to be untrue and of strange blood; for that Selymus the Second was thought to be supposititious. The destruction of Crispus, a young prince of rare towardness, by Constantinus the Great, his father, was in like manner fatal to his house: for both Constantinus and Constance, his sons, died violent deaths; and Constantius, his other son, did little better; who died indeed of sickness, but after that Julianus had taken arms against him.[〔10〕]The destruction of Demetrius, son to Philip the Second of Macedon, turned upon the father, who died of repentance.[〔11〕]And many like examples there are, but few or none where the fathers had good by such distrust; except it were where the sons were up in open arms against them, as was Selymus the First against Bajazet, and the three sons of Henry the Second, King of England.

For their prelates: when they are proud and great, there is also danger from them. As it was in the times of Anselmus and Thomas Becket, archbishops of Canterbury, who with their crosiers did almost try it with the king's sword; and yet they had to deal with stout and haughty kings, William Rufus, Henry the First, and Henry the Second.[〔12〕]The danger is not from that state but where it hath a dependence of foreign authority, or where the churchmen come in and are elected, not by the collation of the king or particular patrons, but by the people.

For their nobles: to keep them at a distance, it is not amiss; but to depress them may make a king more absolute, but less safe, and less able to perform anything that he desires. I have noted it in my history of King Henry the Seventh of England, who depressed his nobility; whereupon it came to pass that his times were full of difficulties and troubles, for the nobility, though they continued loyal unto him, yet did they not co-operate with him in his business. So that in effect he was fain to do all things himself.

For their second-nobles: there is not much danger from them, being a body dispersed. They may sometimes discourse high, but that doth little hurt; besides, they are a counterpoise to the higher nobility, that they grow not too potent; and lastly, being the most immediate in authority with the common people, they do best temper popular commotions.

For their merchants: they are vena porta [the gate vein], and if they flourish not, a kingdom may have good limbs, but will have empty veins and nourish little. Taxes and imposts upon them do seldom good to the king's revenue, for that that he wins in the hundred,[〔13〕]he loseth in the shire, the particular rates being increased, but the total bulk of trading rather decreased.

For their commons: there is little danger from them, except it be where they have great and potent heads, or where you meddle with the point of religion or their customs or means of life.

For their men of war: it is a dangerous state where they live and remain in a body, and are used to donatives; whereof we see examples in the janizaries,[〔14〕]and Praetorian bands[〔15〕]of Rome. But trainings of men, and arming them in several places, and under several commanders, and without donatives, are things of defence, and no danger.

Princes are like to heavenly bodies, which cause good or evil times, and which have much veneration, but no rest. All precepts concerning kings are in effect comprehended in those two remembrances: Memento quod es homo, and Memento quod es Deus, or vice Dei [Remember that you are a man and remember that you are a god, or God's viceregent]: the one bridleth their power, and the other their will.

注释

〔1〕　Proverbs 25.3.

〔2〕　Nero, d. AD 68, Domitian, d. 96, Commodus, d. 192, and Caracalla, d. 217, were Roman emperors; all notorious for their great cruelties.

〔3〕　Roman emperor, d. 313, said to be the first sovereign to resign his power voluntarily (he abdicated in 305).

〔4〕　German (and Holy Roman) emperor, d. 1558; he abdicated the empire in 1556.

〔5〕　Philostratus, Life of Apollonius, Ⅴ.28.

〔6〕　Not Tacitus, but from Sallust, Jugurthine War, CXIII.1.

〔7〕　See Guicciardini, History of Italy, Ⅰ.

〔8〕　Solyman the Magnificent (or Selymus the First), Sultan of Turkey 1520-66, put his eldest son Mustapha to death at the instigation of his wife, the prince's stepmother, Roxalana. One of her own sons, Bayezid (or Bajazet), rebelled and was executed by Solyman. The Sultan was succeeded by another of her sons, Selymus Ⅱ, who appeared to have none of Solyman's features or character.

〔9〕　Isabella of Anjou, d. 1358.

〔10〕　Constantine the Great, Roman emperor 306-37, executed his son Crispus in 326. At Constantine's death, the empire was divided between his sons: Constantine Ⅱ was killed while attempting to overthrow his brother Constans (whom Bacon calls Constance); Constans himself was murdered in his bed by his own men; and Constantius died in 361 on his way to oppose Julian, who had been proclaimed emperor by his troops.

〔11〕　Demetrius, son of Philip Ⅴ of Macedon, was falsely accused of treason by his brother, the crown-prince Perseus. His father had him put to death in 179 BC. Bacon has confused Philip Ⅴ with Philip Ⅱ, father of Alexander the Great.

〔12〕　Anselm, d. 1109, was twice sent into exile for asserting the rights of the clergy against the secular authority of William Rufus and Henry Ⅰ. Thomas à Becket was murdered in Canterbury Cathedral in 1170 after violent disputes with Henry Ⅱ.

〔13〕　A subdivision of the shire.

〔14〕　Bodyguards to the Turkish sultans.

〔15〕　Bodyguards to the Roman emperors.

Of Cunning

We take cunning for a sinister or crooked wisdom. And certainly there is great difference between a cunning man and a wise man, not only in point of honesty, but in point of ability. There be that can pack the cards, and yet cannot play well; so there are some that are good in canvasses and factions, that are otherwise weak men. Again, it is one thing to understand persons, and another thing to understand matters: for many are perfect in men's humours, that are not greatly capable of the real part of business, which is the constitution of one that hath studied men more than books. Such men are fitter for practice than for counsel, and they are good but in their own alley: turn them to new men, and they have lost their aim; so as the old rule to know a fool from a wise man, Mitte ambos nudos ad ignotos et videbis [Send both of them naked among strangers and then you will see],[〔1〕]doth scarce hold for them. And because these cunning men are like haberdashers of small wares, it is not amiss to set forth their shop.

It is a point of cunning to wait upon him with whom you speak, with your eye, as the Jesuits give it in precept; for there be many wise men that have secret hearts and transparent countenances. Yet this would be done with a demure abasing of your eye sometimes, as the Jesuits also do use.

Another is that when you have anything to obtain of present dispatch, you entertain and amuse the party with whom you deal with some other discourse, that he be not too much awake to make objections. I knew a counsellor and secretary that never came to Queen Elizabeth of England with bills to sign, but he would always first put her into some discourse of estate, that she mought the less mind the bills.

The like surprise may be made by moving things when the party is in haste and cannot stay to consider advisedly of that is moved.

If a man would cross a business that he doubts some other would handsomely and effectually move, let him pretend to wish it well, and move it himself in such sort as may foil it.

The breaking off in the midst of that one was about to say, as if he took himself up, breeds a greater appetite in him with whom you confer, to know more.

And because it works better when anything seemeth to be gotten from you by question than if you offer it of yourself, you may lay a bait for a question by showing another visage and countenance than you are wont; to the end to give occasion for the party to ask what the matter is of the change […]

In things that are tender and unpleasing, it is good to break the ice by some whose words are of less weight, and to reserve the more weighty voice to come in as by chance, so that he may be asked the question upon the other's speech […]

In things that a man would not be seen in himself, it is a point of cunning to borrow the name of the world; as to say, The world says, or, There is a speech abroad.

I knew one that, when he wrote a letter, he would put that which was most material in the postscript, as if it had been a by-matter.

I knew another that, when he came to have speech, he would pass over that that he intended most, and go forth, and come back again and speak of it as of a thing that he had almost forgot.

Some procure themselves to be surprised at such times as it is like the party that they work upon will suddenly come upon them, and to be found with a letter in their hand, or doing somewhat which they are not accustomed; to the end they may be apposed of those things which of themselves they are desirous to utter.

It is a point of cunning to let fall those words in a man's own name, which he would have another man learn and use, and thereupon take advantage. I knew two that were competitors for the secretary's place in Queen Elizabeth's time, and yet kept good quarter between themselves, and would confer one with another upon the business; and the one of them said that to be a secretary in the declination of a monarchy was a ticklish thing, and that he did not affect it. The other straight caught up those words and discoursed with divers of his friends that he had no reason to desire to be secretary in the declination of a monarchy. The first man took hold of it and found means it was told the Queen; who, hearing of a declination of a monarchy, took it so ill as she would never after hear of the other's suit.

There is a cunning, which we in England call The turning of the cat in the pan, which is, when that which a man says to another, he lays it as if another had said it to him. And to say truth, it is not easy, when such a matter passed between two, to make it appear from which of them it first moved and began […]

Some have in readiness so many tales and stories, as there is nothing they would insinuate but they can wrap it into a tale, which serveth both to keep themselves more in guard and to make others carry it with more pleasure.

It is a good point of cunning for a man to shape the answer he would have, in his own words and propositions, for it makes the other party stick the less.

It is strange how long some men will lie in wait to speak somewhat they desire to say, and how far about they will fetch, and how many other matters they will beat over to come near it. It is a thing of great patience, but yet of much use.

A sudden, bold, and unexpected question doth many times surprise a man, and lay him open. Like to him, that having changed his name, and walking in Paul's, another suddenly came behind him and called him by his true name, whereat straightways he looked back.

But these small wares and petty points of cunning are infinite, and it were a good deed to make a list of them, for that nothing doth more hurt in a state than that cunning men pass for wise.

But certainly some there are that know the resorts and falls of business, that cannot sink into the main of it; like a house that hath convenient stairs and entries but never a fair room. Therefore you shall see them find out pretty looses in the conclusion, but are no ways able to examine or debate matters. And yet commonly they take advantage of their inability, and would be thought wits of direction. Some build rather upon the abusing of others, and (as we now say) putting tricks upon them, than upon soundness of their own proceedings. But Solomon saith: Prudens advertit ad gressus suos; stultus divertit ad dolos [The wise man pays attention to the steps he is taking: the fool turns aside to the snares].[〔2〕]

注释

〔1〕　Attributed to Aristippus in Diogenes Laertius, Lives of Eminent Philosophers, Ⅱ.73.

〔2〕　Derived from Proverbs 14.8 and 15.

Of Innovations

As the births of living creatures at first are ill-shapen, so are all innovations, which are the births of time. Yet notwithstanding, as those that first bring honour into their family are commonly more worthy than most that succeed, so the first precedent (if it be good) is seldom attained by imitation. For ill, to man's nature as it stands perverted, hath a natural motion, strongest in continuance; but good, as a forced motion, strongest at first. Surely ever medicine is an innovation, and he that will not apply new remedies must expect new evils. For time is the greatest innovator, and if time of course alter things to the worse, and wisdom and counsel shall not alter them to the better, what shall be the end? It is true that what is settled by custom, though it be not good, yet at least it is fit. And those things which have long gone together are as it were confederate within themselves: whereas new things piece not so well, but though they help by their utility, yet they trouble by their inconformity. Besides, they are like strangers, more admired and less favoured. All this is true, if time stood still, which contrariwise moveth so round that a froward retention of custom is as turbulent a thing as an innovation; and they that reverence too much old times are but a scorn to the new. It were good therefore that men in their innovations would follow the example of time itself, which indeed innovateth greatly, but quietly and by degrees scarce to be perceived. For otherwise, whatsoever is new is unlooked for, and ever it mends some, and pairs other: and he that is holpen takes it for a fortune, and thanks the time; and he that is hurt, for a wrong, and imputeth it to the author. It is good also not to try experiments in states, except the necessity be urgent or the utility evident; and well to beware that it be the reformation that draweth on the change, and not the desire of change that pretendeth the reformation. And lastly, that the novelty, though it be not rejected, yet be held for a suspect, and, as the Scripture saith, that we make a stand upon the ancient way, and then look about us, and discover what is the straight and right way, and so to walk in it.[〔1〕]

注释

〔1〕　Jeremiah 6.16.

Of Regiment of Health

There is a wisdom in this beyond the rules of physic: a man's own observation, what he finds good of, and what he finds hurt of, is the best physic to preserve health. But it is a safer conclusion to say, This agreeth not well with me, therefore I will not continue it, than this, I find no offence of this, therefore I may use it. For strength of nature in youth passeth over many excesses which are owing a man till his age. Discern of the coming on of years, and think not to do the same things still; for age will not be defied. Beware of sudden change in any great point of diet, and if necessity enforce it, fit the rest to it. For it is a secret, both in nature and state, that it is safer to change many things than one. Examine thy customs of diet, sleep, exercise, apparel and the like, and try in anything thou shalt judge hurtful, to discontinue it by little and little; but so as if thou dost find any inconvenience by the change, thou come back to it again: for it is hard to distinguish that which is generally held good and wholesome from that which is good particularly and fit for thine own body. To be free-minded and cheerfully disposed at hours of meat and of sleep and of exercise, is one of the best precepts of long lasting. As for the passions and studies of the mind, avoid envy, anxious fears, anger fretting inwards, subtle and knotty inquisitions, joys and exhilarations in excess, sadness not communicated. Entertain hopes, mirth rather than joy, variety of delights rather than surfeit of them, wonder and admiration (and therefore novelties), studies that fill the mind with splendid and illustrious objects (as histories, fables, and contemplations of nature). If you fly physic in health altogether, it will be too strange for your body when you shall need it. If you make it too familiar, it will work no extraordinary effect when sickness cometh. I commend rather some diet for certain seasons than frequent use of physic, except it be grown into a custom: for those diets alter the body more, and trouble it less. Despise no new accident in your body, but ask opinion of it. In sickness, respect health principally; and in health, action. For those that put their bodies to endure in health may, in most sicknesses which are not very sharp, be cured only with diet and tendering.Celsus could never have spoken it as a physician, had he not been a wise man withal, when he giveth it for one of the great precepts of health and lasting, that a man do vary and interchange contraries, but with an inclination to the more benign extreme: use fasting and full eating, but rather full eating; watching and sleep, but rather sleep; sitting and exercise, but rather exercise; and the like. So shall nature be cherished and yet taught masteries. Physicians are some of them so pleasing and conformable to the humour of the patient, as they press not the true cure of the disease; and some other are so regular in proceeding according to art for the disease, as they respect not sufficiently the condition of the patient. Take one of a middle temper; or, if it may not be found in one man, combine two of either sort; and forget not to call as well the best acquainted with your body, as the best reputed of for his faculty.

Of Discourse

Some in their discourse desire rather commendation of wit, in being able to hold all arguments, than of judge-ment, in discerning what is true; as if it were a praise to know what might be said, and not what should be thought. Some have certain commonplaces and themes wherein they are good, and want variety; which kind of poverty is for the most part tedious, and, when it is once perceived, ridiculous. The honourablest part of talk is to give the occasion, and again to moderate and pass to somewhat else, for then a man leads the dance. It is good, in discourse and speech of conversation, to vary and intermingle speech of the present occasion with arguments, tales with reasons, asking of questions with telling of opinions, and jest with earnest: for it is a dull thing to tire, and, as we say now, to jade anything too far. As for jest, there be certain things which ought to be privileged from it; namely, religion, matters of state, great persons, any man's present business of importance, and any case that deserveth pity. Yet there be some that think their wits have been asleep, except they dart out somewhat that is piquant and to the quick. That is a vein which would be bridled:

Parce, puer, stimulis, et fortius utere loris.

[Spare the whip, boy, and pull harder on the reins][〔1〕]

And generally, men ought to find the difference between saltness and bitterness. Certainly he that hath a satirical vein, as he maketh others afraid of his wit, so he had need be afraid of others' memory. He that questioneth much shall learn much and content much, but especially if he apply his questions to the skill of the persons whom he asketh; for he shall give them occasion to please themselves in speaking, and himself shall continually gather knowledge. But let his questions not be troublesome, for that is fit for a poser. And let him be sure to leave other men their turns to speak. Nay, if there be any that would reign and take up all the time, let him find means to take them off and to bring others on, as musicians use to do with those that dance too long galliards. If you dissemble sometimes your knowledge of that you are thought to know, you shall be thought another time to know that you know not. Speech of a man's self ought to be seldom and well chosen. I knew one was wont to say in scorn, He must needs be a wise man, he speaks so much of himself. And there is but one case wherein a man may commend himself with good grace, and that is in commending virtue in another, especially if it be such a virtue whereunto himself pretendeth. Speech of touch towards others should be sparingly used, for discourse ought to be as a field, without coming home to any man. I knew two noblemen, of the west part of England, whereof the one was given to scoff, but kept ever royal cheer in his house; the other would ask of those that had been at the other's table, Tell truly, was there never a flout or dry blow[〔2〕]given? To which the guest would answer, Such and such a thing passed. The lord would say, I thought he would mar a good dinner. Discretion of speech is more than eloquence, and to speak agreeably to him with whom we deal is more than to speak in good words or in good order. A good continued speech, without a good speech of interlocution, shows slowness; and a good reply or second speech, without a good settled speech, showeth shallowness and weakness. As we see in beasts, that those that are weakest in the course are yet nimblest in the turn, as it is betwixt the greyhound and the hare. To use too many circumstances ere one come to the matter is wearisome; to use none at all is blunt.

注释

〔1〕　Ovid, Metamorphoses, Ⅱ.127.

〔2〕　A jibe or sarcastic comment.

Of Beauty

Virtue is like a rich stone, best plain set: and surely virtue is best in a body that is comely, though not of delicate features, and that hath rather dignity of presence than beauty of aspect. Neither is it almost seen, that very beautiful persons are otherwise of great virtue, as if nature were rather busy not to err, than in labour to produce excellency. And therefore they prove accomplished, but not of great spirit, and study rather behaviour than virtue. But this holds not always; for Augustus Caesar, Titus Vespasianus, Philip le Bel of France, Edward the Fourth of England, Alcibiades of Athens, Ismael the Sophy of Persia, were all high and great spirits, and yet the most beautiful men of their times. In beauty, that of favour is more than that of colour, and that of decent and gracious motion more than that of favour. That is the best part of beauty which a picture cannot express; no, nor the first sight of the life. There is no excellent beauty that hath not some strangeness in the proportion. A man cannot tell whether Apelles[〔1〕]or Albert Dürer were the more trifler; whereof the one would make a personage by geometrical proportions, the other, by taking the best parts out of divers faces to make one excellent. Such personages, I think, would please nobody but the painter that made them. Not but I think a painter may make a better face then ever was, but he must do it by a kind of felicity (as a musician that maketh an excellent air in music), and not by rule. A man shall see faces that, if you examine them part by part, you shall find never a good, and yet all together do well. If it be true that the principal part of beauty is in decent motion, certainly it is no marvel though persons in years seem many times more amiable: pulchrorum autumnus pulcher [the autumn of the beautiful is beautiful];[〔2〕]for no youth can be comely but by pardon, and considering the youth as to make up the comeliness. Beauty is as summer fruits, which are easy to corrupt, and cannot last; and for the most part it makes a dissolute youth, and an age a little out of countenance: but yet certainly again, if it light well, it maketh virtues shine, and vices blush.

注释

〔1〕　Greek painter, fourth century BC.

〔2〕　A saying of Euripides, preserved in Plutarch, Alcibiades, Ⅰ.3.

Of Deformity

Deformed persons are commonly even with nature: for as nature hath done ill by them, so do they by nature, being for the most part (as the Scripture saith) void of natural affection and so they have their revenge of nature. Certainly there is a consent between the body and the mind, and where nature erreth in the one, she ventureth in the other: Ubi peccat in uno, periclitatur in altero [While she errs in the one, she runs a risk in the other]. But because there is in man an election touching the frame of his mind, and a necessity in the frame of his body, the stars of natural inclination are sometimes obscured by the sun of discipline and virtue. Therefore it is good to consider of deformity, not as a sign, which is more deceivable, but as a cause, which seldom faileth of the effect. Whosoever hath anything fixed in his person that doth induce contempt, hath also a perpetual spur in himself to rescue and deliver himself from scorn. Therefore all deformed persons are extreme bold - first, as in their own defence, as being exposed to scorn, but in process of time, by a general habit. Also, it stirreth in them industry, and especially of this kind, to watch and observe the weakness of others, that they may have somewhat to repay. Again, in their superiors, it quencheth jealousy towards them, as persons that they think they may at pleasure despise; and it layeth their competitors and emulators asleep, as never believing they should be in possibility of advancement, till they see them in possession. So that upon the matter, in a great wit deformity is an advantage to rising. Kings in ancient times (and at this present in some countries) were wont to put great trust in eunuchs, because they that are envious towards all are more obnoxious and officious towards one. But yet their trust towards them hath rather been as to good spials and good whisperers than good magistrates and officers. And much like is the reason of deformed persons. Still the ground is, they will, if they be of spirit, seek to free themselves from scorn, which must be either by virtue or malice. And therefore let it not be marvelled if sometimes they prove excellent persons; as was Agesilaus, Zanger the son of Solyman, Aesop, Gasca, President of Peru; and Socrates may go likewise amongst them, with others.

Of Suitors

Many ill matters and projects are undertaken, and private suits do putrefy the public good. Many good matters are undertaken with bad minds; I mean not only corrupt minds, but crafty minds that intend not performance. Some embrace suits which never mean to deal effectually in them, but if they see there may be life in the matter by some other mean, they will be content to win a thank, or take a second reward, or at least to make use in the meantime of the suitor's hopes. Some take hold of suits only for an occasion to cross some other; or to make an information whereof they could not otherwise have apt pretext, without care what become of the suit when that turn is served; or generally to make other men's business a kind of entertainment to bring in their own. Nay, some undertake suits with a full purpose to let them fall, to the end to gratify the adverse party or competitor. Surely there is in some sort a right in every suit; either a right of equity, if it be a suit of controversy, or a right of desert, if it be a suit of petition. If affection lead a man to favour the wrong side in justice, let him rather use his countenance to compound the matter than to carry it. If affection lead a man to favour the less worthy in desert, let him do it without depraving or disabling the better deserver. In suits which a man doth not well understand, it is good to refer them to some friend of trust and judgement, that may report whether he may deal in them with honour; but let him choose well his referendaries, for else he may be led by the nose. Suitors are so distasted with delays and abuses, that plain dealing, in denying to deal in suits at first, and reporting the success barely, and in challenging no more thanks than one hath deserved, is grown not only honourable, but also gracious. In suits of favour, the first coming ought to take little place. So far forth consideration may be had of his trust, that if intelligence of the matter could not otherwise have been had but by him, advantage be not taken of the note but the party left to his other means, and in some sort recompensed for his discovery. To be ignorant of the value of a suit is simplicity; as well as to be ignorant of the right thereof is want of conscience. Secrecy in suits is a great mean of obtaining, for voicing them to be in forwardness may discourage some kind of suitors, but doth quicken and awake others. But timing of the suit is the principal. Timing, I say, not only in respect of the person that should grant it, but in respect of those which are like to cross it. Let a man, in the choice of his mean, rather choose the fittest mean than the greatest mean, and rather them that deal in certain things than those that are general. The reparation of a denial is sometimes equal to the first grant, if a man show himself neither dejected nor discontented. Iniquum petas, ut aequum feras [Ask for more than what is just, so that you may get your due][〔1〕]is a good rule where a man hath strength of favour, but otherwise a man were better rise in his suit, for he that would have ventured at first to have lost the suitor, will not in the conclusion lose both the suitor and his own former favour. Nothing is thought so easy a request to a great person as his letter, and yet if it be not in a good cause it is so much out of his reputation. There are no worse instruments than these general contrivers of suits; for they are but a kind of poison and infection to public proceedings.

注释

〔1〕　Quintilian, The Education of an Orator, Ⅳ.5.16.

Of Studies

Studies serve for delight, for ornament, and for ability. Their chief use for delight, is in privateness and retiring; for ornament, is in discourse; and for ability, is in the judgement and disposition of business. For expert men can execute, and perhaps judge of particulars, one by one; but the general counsels, and the plots and marshalling of affairs come best from those that are learned. To spend too much time in studies is sloth; to use them too much for ornament is affectation; to make judgement wholly by their rules is the humour of a scholar. They perfect nature, and are perfected by experience, for natural abilities are like natural plants that need proyning by study; and studies themselves do give forth directions too much at large, except they be bounded in by experience. Crafty men contemn studies, simple men admire them, and wise men use them; for they teach not their own use; but that is a wisdom without them and above them, won by observation. Read not to contradict and confute; nor to believe and take for granted; nor to find talk and discourse; but to weigh and consider. Some books are to be tasted, others to be swallowed, and some few to be chewed and digested: that is, some books are to be read only in parts; others to be read, but not curiously; and some few to be read wholly and with diligence and attention. Some books also may be read by deputy, and extracts made of them by others, but that would be only in the less important arguments, and the meaner sort of books; else distilled books are like common distilled waters, flashy things. Reading maketh a full man; conference a ready man; and writing an exact man. And therefore, if a man write little, he had need have a great memory; if he confer little, he had need have a present wit; and if he read little, he had need have much cunning, to seem to know that he doth not. Histories make men wise, poets witty, the mathematics subtle, natural philosophy deep, moral grave, logic and rhetoric able to contend. Abeunt studia in mores [Studies go to make up a man's character].[〔1〕]Nay, there is no stond or impediment in the wit but may be wrought out by fit studies, like as diseases of the body may have appropriate exercises. Bowling is good for the stone and reins; shooting for the lungs and breast; gentle walking for the stomach; riding for the head; and the like. So if a man's wit be wandering, let him study the mathematics; for in demonstrations, if his wit be called away never so little, he must begin again. If his wit be not apt to distinguish or find differences, let him study the Schoolmen, for they are cymini sectores [hairsplitters]. If he be not apt to beat over matters, and to call up one thing to prove and illustrate another, let him study the lawyers' cases. So every defect of the mind may have a special receipt.

注释

〔1〕　Ovid, Heroides, XV.83.

Of Vainglory

It was prettily devised of Aesop,[〔1〕]The fly sat upon the axle-tree of the chariot wheel, and said, 'What a dust do I raise!' So are there some vain persons that, whatsoever goeth alone or moveth upon greater means, if they have never so little hand in it, they think it is they that carry it. They that are glorious must needs be factious, for all bravery stands upon comparisons. They must needs be violent to make good their own vaunts. Neither can they be secret, and therefore not effectual, but according to the French proverb, Beaucoup de bruit, peu de fruit: much bruit, little fruit. Yet certainly there is use of this quality in civil affairs. Where there is an opinion and fame to be created, either of virtue or greatness, these men are good trumpeters. Again, as Titus Livius noteth in the case of Antiochus and the Aetolians,[〔2〕]There are sometimes great effects of cross lies, as, if a man that negotiates between two princes to draw them to join in a war against the third, doth extol the forces of either of them above measure, the one to the other: and sometimes he that deals between man and man raiseth his own credit with both by pretending greater interest than he hath in either. And in these and the like kinds, it often falls out that somewhat is produced of nothing, for lies are sufficient to breed opinion, and opinion brings on substance. In militar commanders and soldiers, vainglory is an essential point, for as iron sharpens iron, so by glory one courage sharpeneth another. In cases of great enterprise, upon charge and adventure, a composition of glorious natures doth put life into business, and those that are of solid and sober natures have more of the ballast than of the sail. In fame of learning, the flight will be slow without some feathers of ostentation. Qui de contemnenda gloria libros scribunt, nomen suum inscribunt [Men who write books on the worthlessness of glory take care to put their names on the title-page].[〔3〕]Socrates, Aristotle, Galen, were men full of ostentation. Certainly vainglory helpeth to perpetuate a man's memory, and virtue was never so beholding to human nature, as it received his due at the second hand. Neither had the fame of Cicero, Seneca, Plinius Secundus, borne her age so well, if it had not been joined with some vanity in themselves: like unto varnish, that makes ceilings not only shine but last. But all this while, when I speak of vainglory, I mean not of that property that Tacitus doth attribute to Mucianus, Omnium quae dixerat feceratque arte quadam ostentator [He had a certain skill of displaying to advantage all that he had said or done],[〔4〕]for that proceeds not of vanity, but of natural magnanimity and discretion, and in some persons is not only comely, but gracious. For excusations, cessions, modesty itself well governed, are but arts of ostentation. And amongst those arts there is none better than that which Plinius Secundus speaketh of, which is to be liberal of praise and commendation to others, in that wherein a man's self hath any perfection. For saith Pliny very wittily: In commending another you do yourself right, for he that you commend is either superior to you in that you commend, or inferior. If he be inferior, if he be to be commended, you much more; if he be superior, if he be not to be commended, you much less.[〔5〕]Glorious men are the scorn of wise men, the admiration of fools, the idols of parasites, and the slaves of their own vaunts.

注释

〔1〕　Not Aesop, but Lorenzo Bevilaqua.

〔2〕　Antiochus, King of Syria, allied with the Aetolians against Rome, but was defeated. See Livy, History, XXXV.12 and 17-18.

〔3〕　From Cicero, Tusculan Disputations, Ⅰ.15.

〔4〕　From Histories, Ⅱ.80.

〔5〕　From Letters, Ⅵ.17.4.

Of Anger

To seek to extinguish anger utterly is but a bravery of the Stoics. We have better oracles: Be angry, but sin not. Let not the sun go down upon your anger. Anger must be limited and confined, both in race and in time. We will first speak how the natural inclination and habit to be angry may be attempered and calmed. Secondly, how the particular motions of anger may be repressed, or at least refrained from doing mischief. Thirdly, how to raise anger or appease anger in another.

For the first: there is no other way but to meditate and ruminate well upon the effects of anger, how it troubles man's life. And the best time to do this is to look back upon anger when the fit is throughly over. Seneca saith well that anger is like ruin, which breaks itself upon that it falls.[〔1〕]The Scripture exhorteth us to possess our souls in patience.[〔2〕]Whosoever is out of patience is out of possession of his soul. Men must not turn bees,

animasque in vulnere ponunt.

[and lay down their lives in the wound.][〔3〕]

Anger is certainly a kind of baseness; as it appears well in the weakness of those subjects in whom it reigns: children, women, old folks, sick folks. Only men must beware that they carry their anger rather with scorn than with fear, so that they may seem rather to be above the injury than below it: which is a thing easily done if a man will give law to himself in it.

For the second point: the causes and motives of anger are chiefly three. First, to be too sensible of hurt, for no man is angry that feels not himself hurt; and therefore tender and delicate persons must needs be oft angry, they have so many things to trouble them which more robust natures have little sense of. The next is the apprehension and construction of the injury offered to be, in the circumstances thereof, full of contempt; for contempt is that which putteth an edge upon anger, as much or more than the hurt itself. And therefore, when men are ingenious in picking out circumstances of contempt, they do kindle their anger much. Lastly, opinion of the touch of a man's reputation doth multiply and sharpen anger. Wherein the remedy is, that a man should have, as Consalvo[〔4〕]was wont to say, telam honoris crassiorem [a thicker web of honour]. But in all refrainings of anger, it is the best remedy to win time, and to make a man's self believe that the opportunity of his revenge is not yet come, but that he foresees a time for it; and so to still himself in the meantime and reserve it.

To contain anger from mischief, though it take hold of a man, there be two things whereof you must have special caution. The one, of extreme bitterness of words, especially if they be aculeate and proper; for communia maledicta [general revilings] are nothing so much; and again, that in anger a man reveal no secrets, for that makes him not fit for society. The other, that you do not peremptorily break off in any business in a fit of anger; but howsoever you show bitterness, do not act anything that is not revocable.

For raising and appeasing anger in another: it is done chiefly by choosing of times, when men are frowardest and worst disposed, to incense them. Again, by gathering (as was touched before) all that you can find out to aggravate the contempt. And the two remedies are by the contraries. The former, to take good times, when first to relate to a man an angry business, for the first impression is much. And the other is to sever, as much as may be, the construction of the injury from the point of contempt, imputing it to misunderstanding, fear, passion, or what you will.

注释

〔1〕　On Anger, Ⅰ.1.2.

〔2〕　See Luke 21.19.

〔3〕　Virgil, Georgics, Ⅳ.238.

〔4〕　Gonzalo, Hernandez de Cordova, Spanish general, d. 1515.

导读

西格蒙德·弗洛伊德（Sigmund Freud，1856—1939），奥地利精神病医生、心理学家。弗洛伊德是精神分析学派创始人，他开辟了心理学研究的新领域，他的学说为20世纪西方人文科学提供了重要的理论支柱，影响广泛深远。

《文明与缺憾》出版于1930年，是弗洛伊德晚年的作品。对心理学研究者来说，自己的童年记忆、人生经历，也是重要的研究对象和参照系。本文将以较多的笔墨介绍弗洛伊德本人的生活环境、成长历程及其学术思想的形成与发展，对书中出现的一些关键术语，也将略作说明，以便读者更加顺畅地阅读此书。

弗洛伊德生于奥匈帝国摩拉维亚（今属捷克）的一个犹太家庭。父亲是羊毛商人，母亲是父亲的第三任妻子。弗洛伊德有两个同父异母的哥哥，五个妹妹，一个弟弟。弗洛伊德9岁进入学校学习，比一般同学小一岁。17岁进入维也纳大学学习，25岁获得医学博士学位。26岁订婚，30岁结婚，婚后育有三子三女。弗洛伊德毕业之前做过军医，毕业后做过外科、内科医生，之后转向精神病治疗、研究、教学工作，几年后以神经病医师身份私人开业行医。

1895年，弗洛伊德与布洛伊尔合作写成《歇斯底里症研究》一书，在这本书中，弗洛伊德首次提出“精神分析学”这一概念。父亲去世后，弗洛伊德开始进行自我分析，并长期坚持下来。1900年出版的精神分析学经典著作《梦的解析》，是弗洛伊德的早期代表作。该书出版后，弗洛伊德身边聚集了一批年轻学者，其中有阿德勒、C.G.荣格，他们成立研究小组和协会。之后，精神分析学派渐渐成型，逐步赢得了国际声誉，最终发展成国际精神分析协会。但因理念不合，精神分析学派开始分裂。1911年，阿德勒创立个体心理学。1914年，也就是第一次世界大战爆发的那一年，C.G.荣格辞去国际精神分析协会主席的职务，创立分析心理学。1919年一战结束，弗洛伊德创办出版公司，专门发行精神分析学方面的书刊，直至1938年被纳粹查封。

1933年纳粹执政迫害犹太人，在柏林公开焚烧弗洛伊德的著作。1936年，弗洛伊德加入英国皇家学会。1938年，德国吞并奥地利，纳粹占领维也纳，弗洛伊德的女儿被捕，他被迫去到伦敦，他五个妹妹中有四个在奥地利被纳粹杀害。1939年，第二次世界大战爆发，弗洛伊德在伦敦去世。

在世界大战的酝酿期、爆发期，精神分析学派得到蓬勃发展，是历史的必然。工业文明的发展，使人类成为“戴着假肢的神”，像上帝一样征服自然，然而个体并未因此感到更加幸福（本书第三章）。快速的生活节奏和激烈的生存强竞争加重了人们的心理压力，这是精神病医师和心理学家应该取得成就的时代。

弗洛伊德的职业生涯，从内外科医生到精神病医生再到心理学家，他的学术研究的兴趣，也从早期对个体精神世界的关注，发展到晚年对集体社会心理的思考。弗洛伊德意识到，解决个体幸福或痛苦的问题，靠征服自然、治愈肉体疾患、深入意识底层解决心理问题，还不够，还需要“对文化集体作出病理探究”，他把治愈“社会精神病”的希望寄托在未来（本书第八章）。

1930年，《文明与缺憾》出版的时候，弗洛伊德已经74岁高龄。可以说，《文明与缺憾》是在一战和二战之间的“社会精神病”间歇期，一个心理学领域的思想大师对人类行为的反思。作者对比个体意识与集体意识的共性和差异性，尝试利用经过修正的精神分析学原理，来解释“社会精神病”，探索治疗“社会精神病”的方法。了解这一点，结合书名的指引，读者对本书“无题”式的八章内容，就不至于理不清头绪。

一战期间，弗洛伊德三个儿子全部从军，两个儿子参战。1920年，他年仅26岁的女儿去世了。此时弗洛伊德64岁，人生步入晚年。这些都促使他去思考死亡的问题。这一年，他提出了“死亡本能”概念，完善了他的本能理论。在本书中，弗洛伊德使用了死亡本能、破坏性本能、攻击性本能等提法，用以说明有机体返回无机状态的倾向，它是一种负能量，是破坏和战争的根源，个体通过攻击对象或自身来消除生命中的焦虑和挣扎。与死亡本能相对的是生存本能，生存本能是维持个体生存和群体繁衍发展的本能，可以说是广义的性本能或者广义的力比多（libido），本书中也常用“爱神厄洛斯”来表示生存本能。

在弗洛伊德学术研究的不同阶段，在精神分析学派其他成员的著作中，力比多的概念有不同的表述。力比多也称“性力”，它最初来源于各种身体器官获得快感、回避痛苦的欲望，潜藏在人的潜意识中成为本能力量；力比多是人的心理活动和行为的动力，是创造性的力量。一个人的力比多是有限的，在此方向投入多，则在其他方向的投入会减少。

生存本能和死亡本能都存在于人或群体的潜意识中。潜意识也称无意识，是深层的、原始的、非理性的本能欲望的老巢，对潜意识的研究，是精神分析学的首创。精神分析学将人格分为三个层次，最基本的层次是“本我”，遵循快乐原则，对应精神世界中的潜意识；中间一层是“自我”，遵循现实原则，它从本我中分化出来，充当本我与外部世界的联络者和协调者；最上层是“超我”，它从自我中分化出来，遵循道德原则，承担监管审查、自我批判的角色。

此书善于从不同角度说明问题，分析精到入微，即便不熟悉精神分析学的人，也能理解作者的想法，相信它会给读者带来不错的阅读体验。

余雄杰

文明与缺憾

Ⅰ

人通常会追逐权力、成功与财富，羡慕别人所拥有的这一切，却对生命中真正有价值的事物不予重视，并且依据错误的标准作出判断—人们很容易发出这样的感慨。然而，作出如此笼统的概括，很容易忽略人类物质世界和精神世界的丰富多彩。有一些人受到同时代人的尊崇，然而其伟大品质和功绩却往往与很多人的理想和目标不相符合。人们或许认为这些伟人毕竟只为少数人所欣赏，而大多数人对他们毫无兴趣。然而，由于人们思想和行为方式的差异，个人欲望和追求的不同，事情恐怕不会如此简单。

有这样一位杰出人士，与我有通信往来，并在信中称我为好友。我曾给他写过一封简短的信，称宗教乃是幻想。他回信说，对我的见解表示完全赞成，但他很遗憾我未能理解人们对宗教虔诚的真正根源。这种根源在于一种特别的感觉，他自己就从未摆脱过这种感觉，也在很多人身上得到验证，因此他认为这种感觉亦应该为千万人所共有，他称之为“永生”，一种无边无际的“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉。他继续说，这种感觉纯粹是主观的，不是一种信条，不能确保拥有这种感觉的人们长生不老，但却是宗教力量的源泉，为各个教派和宗教体系所控制，被引到特定的渠道，当然也被它们吸收利用了。只要拥有这种海洋般无边无尽的感觉，人们即可称自己是信奉宗教的，即使他们拒绝相信任何信条、任何幻想。

我那可敬的朋友[1]曾经以诗的形式赞扬了幻想的魔力。他的观点给我造成了不小的困惑。我自身丝毫不能感到这种“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉。要知道科学理性地对待感觉是很不容易的。人们可能会试图描述感觉的生理表现，但这是行不通的，而且恐怕这种“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉是无助于描述的。我们能做的只是研究那些与感觉最为接近的概念性的东西。如果我没有理解错的话，我那朋友指的“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉是一种慰藉，就像一位古怪却又才思新颖的作家给予选择结束自己生命的主角的一种安慰：“我们不会脱离这个世界的。”这是一种与身外世界紧密相连的归属感。对于我来说这属于一种理性的领悟，当然也不乏情感的色彩，尽管在其他类似的思维活动中也不乏情感色彩。凭借我自己的经验，我实在无法让自己信服这种感觉的产生本质。但我无法否认在他人身上这种感觉实实在在地存在着。然而，唯一的问题是，这种感觉是否得到了准确的解释，或者说是否应该被看作是所有宗教需求的源泉。

对于这一问题，我也没有决定性的、建设性的解决建议。但仅仅凭一种直接的感觉，来告知人们与外部世界存在的联系，并用来解释人们需要宗教的原因，这样的想法从一开始听上去就很奇怪，并且与我们的心理结构不相吻合。因此，我们需要找出一种心理分析的方法，对于这种感觉的遗传起源作出合理的解释。以下的思路即论证了这一点。我们通常不会产生比对自我更确定的感觉。人们大多会觉得这种自我是独立的整体，并与一切其他的东西对立。其实不然，心理分析学的研究首次告诉我们这是错误的，事实上自我向内在延伸，延伸至一种我们称之为本我的无意识心理实体，且界限模糊不清；自我就好像是本我的外表。对于自我与本我的关系，心理分析仍有很多方面可向我们揭示。然而至少表面来看，自我的轮廓似乎可以被清晰分明地勾勒出来。只有一种状态—诚然是一种不寻常的状态，但不应被贬为病态的状态—自我不再轮廓分明。在情爱的巅峰状态，自我与对象的界限可能变得模糊。尽管与所有感官认识相悖，恋爱中的人们总会宣称“我”和“你”是一体的，并且随时表现得像一体的。这种自我与外界的界限能够暂时地被生理功能打断，自然也会被疾病干扰。病理学的研究让我们认识到，在很多情况下自我与外部世界的界限会变得模糊不清，或者说根本是被错误地划分了。在有些病例中，人身体的某些部分，甚至是精神生活的某些部分，如观念、思想、感觉，似乎变得很陌生，从自我中分离开来。在另一些情况中，病人把那些明显产生于自我并应该得到自我认识的事情归于外部世界。因此，即使是自身的感觉也会产生混乱，而且自身的界限并不是恒定的。

通过进一步的思考，我们便可知道，成年人对于自己的感觉不可能与刚出生时相同，它必然经过了一个发展的过程。可以理解的是，这样的过程并不能被实际演示出来，但有很大概率可以重构。对于一个新生儿来说，外部世界就是其感觉的由来；一开始，他并未将自我与外部世界分离开来。但在外部各种刺激的作用下，他逐渐学会了将自我与外界区分开来。他会发现，有些刺激源任何时候都可以向其传递感觉，后来他认识到这些刺激源属于自己的器官；而另外一些—包括他最渴望的东西，如母亲的乳房，会暂时挪开，只有通过哭喊才会重回眼前，以上这些区别一定给他留下了深刻的印象。正是以这种方式，自我首次碰到了“客体”，一些在“外面”的东西，只有通过特定的行为，才能促使它出现。将自我从各种感觉中分离出来，进而认识到“外部世界”；更进一步的诱因来自频繁的、各种各样的不可避免的痛苦（或者说幸福缺失），这种痛苦的感觉，只有在快乐原则发挥绝对作用时，才能得以避免和消除。于是这样一种趋势就会产生，即将自我和任何可能产生这样不愉快体验的事物区分开，并将这种不愉快的体验赶走，以便建立与一个陌生、险恶的外部世界相抗衡的纯粹追求快乐的自我。这种以快乐为导向的原始自我必然会受到经验的修正。毕竟，有些给予我们快乐、我们不愿放弃的事物并不属于自我，而属于客体；而另外一些我们想要消除的折磨和痛苦，却证明是来自内部，与自我密不可分。于是，我们掌握了一种方法，通过有目的地控制我们的感觉活动和合适的肌体运动，来区分什么是来自内部的（即属于自我的），什么是来自外部的（即来自外界的）。这就向建立现实世界原则迈出了第一步，对未来发展起着支配作用。这种内部和外部的区分具有现实意义，使人们远离不愉快的经历及其造成的威胁。事实上，自我在驱除源于内部的某些不愉快感觉时，如果采取与驱除来源于外部不愉快事物同样的手段，往往会成为重大心理疾病的起始点。

自我正是通过这种方法使其从外部世界中分离开来。更确切地说，自我在一开始是包括一切的，只是后来从自身中分离出了一个外部的世界。于是，我们现在的自我感觉，只是一种更为广泛、包罗万象的感觉的残留物，这种初始的感觉与自我和周边世界更为密切的联系相一致。如果我们可以作如下假设，即自我的这种原始的感觉或多或少地在人们的精神生活中存续下来，那么它会像一个搭档，与范围更小、界定更严的成熟的自我感觉共存。与之相对应的就是那些与宇宙一体的、无边无际的概念，即我的朋友常用来阐释“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉的概念。但我们是否可以假定，最初存在的事物仍然会存续下去，与后来从中演化而来的事物共同存在呢？

毋庸置疑！这种情况无论发生在精神领域还是其他领域，都不足为奇。以动物世界为例，人们通常认为动物是由低级向高级进化的。然而，如今所有低级形式的生命依然存在。有些大型爬行动物，如大型蜥蜴，已经灭绝而让位于哺乳动物，但大型爬行动物真正的代表—鳄鱼却依然存在。这样的类比或许有点牵强，况且很多存活下来的低级物种也并非现存的高级物种的真正祖先，中间的环节大多已经消失了，我们只能通过重新构建才可以得知，这就削弱了这个类比的可比性。然而，在精神领域，原始的感觉与从中演化出来的感觉是共存的。这样的现象非常普遍，不必举例去证明。这往往是发展中的分叉导致，即一部分（从数量上讲）态度或者本能冲动保持不变，而另一部分却得到进一步发展。

由此，又提出一个精神领域里更为普遍的记忆和保留的问题，这一问题几乎尚未研究过，却充满魅力、意义重大，我们不妨探讨一下，尽管理由尚不够充分。我们曾经认为，我们经常遗忘是因为记忆痕迹的破坏，即记忆痕迹的消亡，但在纠正了这一错误观点之后，我们发现事实恰恰相反。即在精神生活中，一样东西一旦形成就永远都不会消失，一切皆以某种形式得到保存，条件合适时，皆可找回。例如，只要（因催眠或精神疾患）回到从前，即可找回当时的记忆。这样的假设意味着什么，让我们试着用另一领域的类比来揭示。以“永恒的城市”的发展为例，历史学家告诉我们最早期的罗马是一个四方城，是帕拉蒂尼山上用栅栏围起来的居住点。之后是七山城阶段，是由各个分散山丘上的居住点组成的联盟。接着，是塞维安墙围起来的城市。再之后，经过罗马共和国以及帝国时代早期的变迁，就成了奥瑞里安皇帝用城墙围起来的城市。我们不再向前追溯城市所经历的种种变迁了，只是不由自主地会想，如果一个拥有丰富历史学与地形学知识的旅行者去罗马旅游时，他能发现罗马早期各个阶段的哪些遗迹呢？他会发现除了一些缺口，奥瑞里安的城墙并没有多大的变化。他可以不时地看到挖掘出土显露出来的一段段塞维安城墙上的痕迹。凭借足够的考古学知识（至少要比当今考古学家具有更丰富的知识）他能看出整个塞维安城墙的整体布局，透过现代罗马城的规划他能看到罗马四方城的轮廓。至于古城中曾经的建筑物，他是无论如何也无法找到的，因为它们已经不存在了，顶多能找到一些残片而已。关于罗马共和国的丰富知识至多能使他指出罗马古城中的庙宇在当时究竟位于何方，公共建筑究竟曾经建于何处。现在这些地方早已被废墟掩盖—但并非是原来建筑的废墟，而是在这些建筑被焚烧、破坏后又建起来的各种建筑的废墟。无须赘言，古罗马的这些遗迹，已成为碎片，散落在文艺复兴后近代兴建的大都市的混乱之中。诚然，大多旧址依然存在，只是掩埋在现代建筑之下。像罗马这样的历史古城，过去就是这样延续下来的。

现在让我们作这样一个奇妙的假想，即假定罗马并非是一个人们居住的地方，而是一个与罗马一样有着漫长而丰富多彩历史的精神实体。在这个精神实体中，一旦形成的东西就不会消失，并且先前的发展时期与现今是共存的。对罗马而言，就相当于一直到被哥特人围攻时，塞弗尤斯宫殿与恺撒大帝皇宫依然矗立在帕拉蒂尼山上；圣安吉罗堡的城垛上仍然装饰着美丽的塑像。不仅如此，朱庇特神庙会屹立在卡法莱里—克莱门蒂诺宫之上，而没有必要将后者移除，而且，这座神庙不仅具有当时的形态，即罗马帝国时期所见到的形态，还保留着更早期的姿态，依然保留着伊特鲁里亚人的元素，其檐口依然用陶瓦装饰。在如今的圆形大剧场，我们仍然可以欣赏已经消失的尼禄时代金色的房屋。在万神殿广场上，我们不仅可以找到今天由哈德良传给我们的万神殿，同时，还能找到拉格瑞帕人所建的最初的大厦；在同一块土地上，矗立着密涅瓦圣玛丽亚教堂以及该教堂的前身，即古老的神庙。观察者也许只需要改变他的视线或位置就可以看到其中一个或另一个。

显然，再进一步展开这样的想象毫无意义：结果会无法想象，甚至荒诞可笑。我们要在空间上表现历史顺序，唯一的办法就是将空间铺开并列，因为同一空间不能存放两个不同的事物。这样的尝试似乎是一项没有意义的游戏。唯一的正当理由是：它向我们表明，通过形象的描述，我们距离掌握精神生活的特性还有多远。

但是有一个异议我们必须回应。人们或许会问，为什么要把一个城市的过去与我们精神的过去相提并论呢？即便是对于我们的精神而言，一切过去皆被保存下来，这个假定也得满足一个前提，即我们的大脑必须是完整的，其组织结构没有受到创伤或炎症的损害。这些疾病的原因可以比作是破坏性的因素。然而对于一个城市而言，这些破坏性因素是司空见惯的，即便这个城市不像罗马那样动荡不安，即便像伦敦那样几乎没有遭到外敌的蹂躏。哪怕一个城市的发展过程再和平，也少不了拆除和新建一些建筑，基于此，任何城市都无法与精神有机体相比。

我们欣然接受这样的异议，放弃鲜明对比的做法，转而与更为相关的事物相比较，如动物肌体和人类肌体。但这样我们也会发现同样的问题。肌体成长的早期阶段根本没有被保存下来，只是为后期阶段提供材料，并被吸收到后期阶段。成年人的身体中是找不到胚胎的，儿童的胸腺在青春期之后会被结缔组织取代，胸腺的形式不复存在。在成年人的骨骼之中，固然可以找到儿童时代骨骼的大致轮廓，但骨骼在不断加长、增厚并最终定型，在这一生长过程中，儿童的骨骼形态消失了。事实上，早期阶段与最终的形态并存，也许只有在精神领域中才可能发生，我们根本无法拿其他事物与精神相提并论，并试图阐释精神这一现象。

也许我们在这个问题上扯得太远了。或许我们应该满足于这样的结论，即过去在精神生活中可能会得到保存，没有必要被摧毁。情况可能是这样的：即使是在精神领域之中，过去、陈旧的东西也会变得模糊或者被吸收，不管是在事物的正常发展情况之下或者是在其他例外情况下。我们不能利用任何方法使它们恢复到原来的状态，又或许只有在特定的有利条件下我们才可能做到。对于这一点，我们无法得知。我们唯一能做的就是坚信在精神世界中，对过去的保存记忆是一条定律，而非令人惊讶的例外。

因此，如果我们准备承认许多人都有那一种“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉，并欲将其追溯到自我感觉的早期阶段，那么一个新的问题就又出现了：是什么东西使得这种感觉被认作是宗教需要的源泉呢？

我并不觉得这种说法是令人信服的。毕竟一种感觉只有是某种强烈需要的表现时，才能成为力量的源泉。我认为，宗教的需要无疑是从婴儿的无助，和由此引起的对父亲的渴望中衍生出来的，尤其因为这种感觉不仅仅存在于童年时代，而且由于恐惧命运的至上权力，它被永久地保存了下来。我实在无法找出对于儿童来说比父亲的保护更加强烈的需求。因此，那种可能力图恢复无限自恋的“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉，在宗教需要中就不可能发挥主要作用。人们信奉宗教的缘由，可以清晰地追溯到孩子的无助的感觉中。可能这其后还隐藏着什么，但目前我们还不得而知。

我可以想象这种“如海洋般浩渺”的感觉随后与宗教发生了联系。与这种浩渺感觉相连的理智认识是，“自我与宇宙融为一体”，这成为把宗教当作慰藉的初步尝试，即以另一种方式否认自我感觉到的源于外界的危险。我不得不再次承认研究这些无形的概念非常困难。我的另一个朋友怀着对知识的极大渴求，做了一个极其不寻常的实验，最后变得几乎无所不知。他向我保证说，人们在练习瑜伽的过程中，背对外界，将注意力集中到肌体的功能之上，运用特殊的呼吸方式，可以获得全新的、宇宙般的感觉。他把这样的感觉解释成向精神生活被长久掩盖的原始形态的回归。他由此可以说看到了神秘主义智慧的重要生理基础；也找到了与诸如恍惚、极乐这类难解的精神状态的关系。但我还是忍不住用席勒民谣中潜水者的话来说：

……让他欣悦吧，那在玫瑰色的光芒中呼吸的人。

Ⅱ

在《幻想的未来》一书中，我关注的重点不是宗教情感极其深奥的起源，而是普通人所理解的宗教。宗教以其令人称羡的完整教义和应许体系，一方面向人们解释世界之谜，另一方面宽慰着人们，称细心的上帝会照看他们的生活，现世他们所遭受的苦难，在未来世界会得到上帝的补偿。除了至尊高尚的父亲形象，普通人再也想象不出什么来形容这个上帝。只有这样的父亲才能理解他的孩子—人类的需要，才能被他们的请求感动，才能因他们的忏悔欣慰。这整个想法显然太幼稚，与现实相去太远，因此想到大多数人都无法超越这样的人生观，不能不让博爱的心灵感到疼痛。更令人不安的是，尽管今天很多人已经知道这种宗教是站不住脚的，却仍然可悲地企图采取措施一步一步地来捍卫它。人们喜欢混进教徒的行列以便对付某些哲学家，并提醒他们不要触犯十诫之一：“你们不要轻慢地谈论主，亵渎你们的上帝！”因为这些哲学家们认为他们能拯救宗教的上帝，其办法是把他变成一条非人格化的模糊抽象的原则。如果过去的某些伟人们这么做了，我们不能指责他们，因为我们知道他们不得不这么做的原因。

再让我们回到普通人及其宗教的话题上来，即唯一能称之为宗教的宗教。我们首先想到的就是最伟大的诗人和思想家之一歌德的一句有关宗教和艺术、科学关系的著名评论：

拥有科学和艺术的人同时也就拥有了宗教，如果有人两者都不具备，那就让他信奉宗教吧！

这句话一方面将宗教和人类最高的两项成就—科学和艺术作了比较；又从另一方面声明了宗教、科学、艺术在人生中的价值，认为宗教与后两项成就可以互相说明、互相替代。想剥夺一个既不拥有科学又不拥有艺术的普通人信奉宗教的权利，我们显然缺乏像诗人歌德那样的权威。要深刻理解和欣赏歌德的主张，我们须另辟蹊径。生活赋予我们太多难以承受的困难：它带来太多痛苦，太多失望，太多无法解决的问题。要容忍它，我们就不得不采取一些缓和的措施。（正如特奥多尔·冯塔纳告诉我们的：没有帮助，你什么也做不了）此类缓和措施大概有三种：有效地分散注意力，这能使我们轻视所承受的苦难；替代性的满足，这能减弱我们的痛苦；麻醉物质，这能麻痹我们对痛苦的感知。诸如此类的东西是必不可少的。[2]伏尔泰在写作《天真》的结尾时劝解人们去打理一个属于自己的花园，这样就能分散转移自己对苦难的注意力。学术活动也是此类分散转移。作为替代性满足的手段之一，艺术是与现实对照的幻想，但正因为幻想在精神生活中所扮演的重要角色，艺术其实在心理上同样有效。麻醉物质影响我们的肉体并改变了它的化学物质。在这一系列的手段中，界定宗教占有的位置并不容易。我们因此必须看得更远一些。

人生的目的是什么？这个问题已经被提出过无数次，至今没有一个令人满意的回答，或许这个问题根本就没有答案。一些提出这个问题的人补充说，如果人生注定没有目的，那么人生对人们而言也就失去了价值。但这种威胁也改变不了什么。相反，人们似乎有权不去考虑这个问题。这种威胁似乎只是建立在此种人为的假设之上，诸如此类的例子不胜枚举。没有人讨论动物是为了什么而活，除非是为了服务人类的目的。但是这种观点同样站不住脚，因为世上还有很多动物，人类除了对他们进行描述、分类并且研究，其他什么也做不了；许多物种甚至连这种用途都没有，因为早在被人们发现之前，它们就已经灭绝了。

似乎只有宗教才能回答人活着是为了什么这个谜题。因此人生具有目的的观点成立与否就取决于宗教体系，得出这样的推断几乎是不会错的。

于是我们现在将话题转向一个更适中的问题：人类本身的行为揭示出其人生的目标和目的到底是什么？人们对生活有什么预期呢？回答毫无疑问：他们追求快乐幸福，希望得到幸福并一直幸福下去。这种追求有正反两个目标：一方面它旨在消除一切痛苦和不愉快的经历，另一方面旨在获得强烈的快乐感。幸福，从严格意义上讲只与后者有关。与人类追求目的的二分法相一致的是，人类活动，根据其寻求实现的主要目的或唯一目的，也朝着两个方向展开。

正如我们所看到的，正是快乐原则决定了人生的目的。这原则从一开始就支配着我们的精神器官。它的效力是毋庸置疑的。然而它与整个世界—无论是宏观的还是微观的—都是相悖的。整个宇宙的建构都是与快乐相悖的，因此快乐原则无法实现；人们赞同“人类应该获得幸福”并不是“创世”意图的一部分。从最严格的意义上来讲，我们所称的“幸福”产生于压抑的需求突然得到的满足。幸福的本质决定了幸福只能是暂时的。当快乐原则所渴望的某种情况被延长时，只能带来一种微弱的满足感。我们天生就只能从对比中获得强烈的快感，从某一状态本身只能获得很少的快乐。[3]因此，我们幸福的可能性已经被我们的气质所限制。生活中，我们更容易经历不幸。苦难从三个方面威胁着我们：肉体上，我们注定要衰败、腐烂，且从来都是伴随着疼痛、焦虑这些警告信号；外部世界方面，它会向我们施加巨大的、难以平息的、破坏性的压力；最后是人际关系。人际关系可能给我们带来比前两者更大的痛苦。尽管我们倾向于把这种苦难看作是额外附加的，但它或许与源自其他方面的苦难一样，无法避免。

所以，在这些潜在痛苦带来的压力之下，人们习惯于调整自己对幸福的要求，这也不足为奇；正如幸福原则本身也受外部世界的影响而转变，形成一种更适中的“现实准则”，认为如果摆脱苦恼、逃离不幸就是万幸了，避免苦难这一主要任务当前，获得快乐已经变得次要了。思考告诉我们条条道路皆可通向幸福大道，所有这些道路都曾为各派处世哲学所推崇，且前人都已经实践过。无限制地满足我们所有的需要是最具诱惑力的生活方式，但这意味着将警告抛之脑后，眼前只顾享乐，很快就会尝到苦果。其他以避免苦难为首要目的的方法由于它们所关注的痛苦根源不同而有所差异。有些方法很极端，有些方法很中庸，有些很片面，还有些同时从几个角度解决问题。主动避世、与他人保持适当距离都是常见的为避免人际关系带来的痛苦而采取的保护方式。有人认为能通过这种方式获得的快乐来自平静与安宁。面对可怕的外部世界，如果想不借助外力单枪匹马地保护自己，就只能选择逃避。当然还有其他更好的方式：作为人类社会的一分子，你能在应用科学的帮助下对自然发动攻击，使其屈从于人类的意志。那么，这样做你就是与大家一起为了所有人的幸福而努力。避免苦难最有趣的方法是那些试图影响人类自身结构的方法。归根结底，所有的苦难不过是一种感觉，只有当我们感觉到它的时候，它才存在；而我们能感受到它，仅仅是因为身体以某些特定方式调节了状态。

影响我们自身结构的最原始同时也是最有效的方法是化学方法—麻醉法。我想，没有人完全明白化学方法是如何起作用的，但事实就是，有些外因物质一旦出现在血液或人体组织中，就会直接引起快感；这些物质同时还会改变我们感觉能力的决定因子，使我们不再容易感到不快。这两种影响不仅同时出现，而且密切相关。然而，在我们身体的化学结构中，也一定存在着发挥类似作用的物质。因为，我们至少知道一种病症，即狂躁症，在没有使用任何麻醉品的情况下，就出现了类似于麻醉的状态。除此之外，在我们正常的精神生活中，还存在着在比较容易释放的快乐与比较不易释放的快乐这两者之间的摆动，与此相应的是对不舒适的低敏感与高敏感。令人非常遗憾的是，精神麻醉至今还未得到科学的研究。人们认为麻醉物质在追求幸福和驱散苦难的过程中大有裨益，因此，不仅仅个人，就连整个民族在力比多[4]的分配中也赋予了它牢固的地位。多亏了麻醉物质，我们不仅能够直接获得快感，而且满足了我们摆脱外界的强烈渴望。我们知道，通过麻醉法“解忧”，我们随时能够逃避现实的压力，躲在自己的世界里，体会这个世界带来的更好的感觉。众所皆知，正是麻醉物的这种特质使其更具危险性和伤害性。在有些情形下，麻醉物质浪费了本可造福于人类的大量能量。

然而，我们的精神器官结构复杂，也受到很多其他影响。正如欲望的满足会带来幸福感一样，如果外部世界拒绝满足或忽视我们的需求，就会成为巨大苦难的根由。因此人们希望可以通过干预这些本能的冲动来将自己从痛苦中解救出来。这种抵御痛苦的行为不再是对感觉器官施加影响，它旨在控制我们需求的内在根源。在极端的例子中，这种行为是通过扼杀本能欲望实现的，就像东方哲学智慧所说的那样，就像瑜伽所做的那样。如果这种方法成功了，人们就无可否认地同时放弃了其他活动—事实上，牺牲了他的生活—只为沿另一路线抵达幸福的彼岸，这种幸福源自平和与安宁。当我们的目标不那么极端时，我们走的也是这条道路，不过寻求的只是控制自己的本能罢了。在这种情况下，控制是由已经服从现实原则的较高心理机制实施的。与此同时，绝不是说要抛弃满足欲望的目标，而是获得了针对苦难的某种保护机制。因为当欲望冲动得到控制，而不是完全不受节制的时候，欲望得不到满足给人带来的痛苦会相对较轻。但不可否认的是，快乐的可能性也减少了。满足没有受到自我控制的野性本能冲动所产生的快感，相比较于满足受到自我控制的本能所带来的快感，自然是强烈许多。这就简洁地解释了乖戾冲动的不可抗拒性，任何禁忌物所具有的吸引力也可能来源于此。

另一种避免苦难的技巧是利用力比多的转移，这种转移是我们精神器官所允许的，这就使得力比多的作用具有更大的灵活性。现在的任务就是使本能的目标发生转移，不再会受到外部世界的挫折。这里本能的升华扮演了重要的角色。如果人们能充分地增加精神和脑力活动所产生的快乐，我们就能获得最大的收益。这时命运也无法对我们造成多大伤害。这类满足—如艺术家们在创造、塑造他想象的东西的过程中获得的快乐；抑或是科学家们在解决问题和发现真理中获得的快乐—具有一种特性，那就是，总有一天我们能用心理玄学的术语描述它。但现在我们只能象征性地说，它们看上去“更好更高级”。但与原始、初级欲望的满足所获得的效果相比，这类满足的强度还是受到了限制：这类满足不能震撼我们的肉体。这种方法的缺点在于它不能广泛应用，它只适用于一小部分人。它把才能和天赋作为先决条件，这些天赋并非人人皆备，因此不能使这一方法对每个人都有效。并且即使在那一小部分人中，这种方法也不能完全抵御苦难，它并不能提供抵挡命运箭矢的盔甲。当人们自身的躯体成为了苦难的源泉时[5]，它就必然失效了。上述这种方法清楚地表明，其目的是通过从内在的精神活动过程中寻找满足感，从而使人独立于外部世界。这种特征在接下来的方法中体现得更加明显，人与现实的关系更加松散，满足由幻想中获得。人们承认幻想，从中获得的享受并没有因为源于现实的偏差而受到干扰。产生这些幻想的领域就是想象中的生活；当现实感出现时，这个领域显然不受制于真实性检测的要求，一如既往地去满足那些难以实现的欲望。在众多源于想象的满足中，居于首位的要算是对艺术品的欣赏了；借助于艺术家之手，那些本身没有创造力的凡夫俗子也能获得艺术的享受。但受到艺术影响的人不可能把艺术作为快乐源泉和生活慰藉的价值看得过高。艺术产生的微弱的麻醉作用只能使我们暂时摆脱生活的苦难。它的作用并没有强烈到能让我们忘却现实的痛苦。

另一种操作起来更有力、更彻底的方法则将现实视为唯一的敌人和所有苦难的源头；认为人们生活中根本无法忍受现实，要想真正感到幸福，就必须断绝一切与现实的联系。隐士们于是避世不出，拒绝与现实有任何联系。但其实人能做的不止这些：人们可以努力去改造这个世界，重建一个世界，新世界中消除了那些最让人无法容忍的事物，取而代之的是符合人们欲望的事物。一般来说，任何人选择这条道路去追寻幸福，怀着绝望抗争的精神，最终将一无所获。现实对他来说太强大了，他将成为一个狂人，通常找不到人帮助实现他的幻想。然而我们可以这么认为，我们中的每个人都表现得或多或少像个偏执狂，痴心妄想地要去矫正这个世界中无法忍受的部分，并将幻想纳入到现实中。其中具有重要意义的例子是，相当多的人一起试图通过幻想重新塑造现实，来避免痛苦，寻求幸福与庇护。人类的各种宗教应该就是集体幻想的典型例子。当然，没有一个依然持有这种幻想的人会承认这是幻想。

我认为，这并不是一个人们追求幸福、避免痛苦的所有方法的清单。我也清楚这些材料可用不同的方式排列。其实还有一种方法我尚未提及，并不是因为忘记，而是因为这种方法涉及我们以后要讲的内容。在生活艺术中人们怎么会忘掉这一特别的方法呢？其特点是，它将各种特征极其奇特地组合在一起。自然，它也寻求独立于所谓的命运，为达到这一目的，它利用我们前文中所提及的力比多转移法，将满足感转移到内在的精神过程中。但它并不脱离外部世界，相反，它紧紧地抓住了外部世界的对象，并通过建立与外部世界对象的情感联系来获得幸福。它并不满足于避免不愉快的经历—这一目标源于精疲力尽的屈从；事实上，它绕开了这一消极目标，一如既往、激情四溢地去追求积极的幸福目标。或许这一方法比起其他任何方法更加接近目标。当然，我正在谈论的生活方式就是：将爱看作一切事物的中心，并期待从爱与被爱中获得一切满足。这种精神态度是我们自然而然就具备的；爱的一种表现形式—性爱，让我们强烈地体验到一种压倒一切的快感，因此树立了一种寻找幸福的模式。我们应该沿着首次邂逅幸福的道路继续寻找幸福，还有什么比这更自然呢？但这种生活方式的缺点亦显而易见，如果不是这样，也没有人会放弃这种寻找幸福的途径，转而投向其他途径。当我们沉溺于爱的时候，我们对痛苦的防备从未如此薄弱；当失去爱的对象或其对我们的爱时，我们会感到从未有过的凄凉孤独。然而，关于这一特别的生活方式，关于将爱作为获得幸福的一种方式的价值，这并不是最后的断言：关于这一点，我还有很多话要说。

在这里我们可以探讨这样一个有趣的例子：生活中的幸福主要是在对美的享受中获得的，不论美在何处被呈现在我们的感官和判断面前—无论是人体形态和姿态的美，自然物体和风景的美，艺术甚至是科学创造的美。这种生活目标的美学态度并不能在苦难威胁我们的时候提供多大保护，但是它能补偿很多东西。美的享受有一种让人微醉的独特作用。美并没有什么很明显的用途，人们也不易看出美对于人类文明为什么不可或缺，然而，缺乏美的文明是不可想象的。美学探讨的是在什么情况下美会被理解，但美学还无法弄明白美的本质和根源；通常缺乏实质内容时，就会用空泛、冗长的辞藻来掩饰。遗憾的是，精神分析学也几乎没有谈论到美。唯一可以肯定的是，美源自性感觉领域；对美的热爱，可以理想地解释为那种目标抑制的冲动。“美”和“吸引”最初都是性对象的特质。值得注意的是，虽然看到生殖器会让人兴奋，但人们并不认为生殖器本身是美的；相反，美的性质似乎与性的某些次要特征相关。

尽管我的论述尚不完整，尚处于开始阶段，但我想斗胆作出如下论述，来结束目前探讨的问题。我们那由快乐原则主宰的追寻幸福的使命并不能完全实现，但我们不能、事实上也不可以放弃努力，去更加接近幸福。为了达到这个目的，我们也许会踏上不同的道路，并在积极地寻求快乐与消极地避免不幸这两大目标中优先选择一个。但不论我们选择了哪条道路，都不可能完全获得所渴望的一切。幸福（较弱意义上的幸福还是可能实现的）就是关于个人力比多分配的问题。没有哪条建议适用于所有人，每个人都得自己探索救赎之道。其间，各种不同因素都发挥着作用，影响着个人的选择，问题在于他能从外部世界中得到多少真正的满足，在于他能在多大程度上独立于外部世界，以及最后，在于他感到自己有多大的力量来按照自己的意愿改造世界。除外部世界外，这里起决定性作用的还包括个人的心理特性。性欲强烈的人会尤其看重与他人的情感关系；自恋的人，相对而言则更加自足，更倾向于在自我精神进程中寻找最为重要的满足；行动派不会放弃与外部世界的接触，因为他能以此衡量自己的力量。对于第二种人来说，他的天赋以及他的本能所能升华的程度决定着他的兴趣所在。任何极端的选择都将受到惩罚，因为如果一个人选择了一种生活方式，排除其他一切生活方式，那么他将会处于危险的境地中。就像审慎的商人不会把所有资本投在一项事业中一样，处世哲学也许会告诫我们不要指望某一种尝试就能让我们获得所有满足。成功从来都是不可预测的，它取决于很多因素的机缘巧合，又或许仅仅取决于心理适应环境，以及利用环境创造快乐的能力。如果一个人的本能素质天生就不好，又没有真正经历过对他日后成功必不可少的力比多成分的改变和重组过程，他会感到很难从外部世界中获得幸福，尤其在面对极其困难的任务时。最后一种生活方式是（至少能保证让他获得一些替代性的满足），他可以逃入精神病的状态以寻求解脱；这种情况通常会在一个人年轻时发生。如果一个人晚年追求幸福受挫，他仍可以通过长期依赖麻醉物所产生的快乐获得慰藉，或者，进行绝望的抗争，最后精神变态。[6]

这种选择和适应的过程遭到了宗教的干涉，宗教将其获得幸福、避免苦难的方式不加区别地强加到每一个人身上。宗教的方法就是贬低生命的价值，通过幻想扭曲真实世界面貌，以智力上的恐吓为先决条件。强制人们处于心理上的幼稚状态，并诱使人们进入集体妄想的状态，以此为代价，宗教成功地让人免于患上精神病。但除此之外，宗教再也没什么别的作用了。正如我们已经提到过的，在人类的能力范围内还有很多通往幸福的途径，但是没有哪一条能保证一定成功。就连宗教也不能作出这样的保证。如果信徒们最终不得不谈论上帝的“深不可测的旨意”，他等于就是在承认，要想在苦难中最终获得安慰和快乐，他别无选择，只能无条件地服从。如果他准备接受这一点，那么或许他本可以避开走过的弯路。

Ⅲ

到目前为止，我们对幸福的研究仍没有提出多少新颖的内容。即使我们继续追问，为什么人获得幸福那么困难，获得开创性见解的可能性仍然并不乐观。关于这个问题我们已经作出回答，指出了痛苦的三个来源：自然力量的强大优势，我们肉体的脆弱，用来调节家庭、国家、社会的人际关系制度的不足。对于前两个来源，我们不必犹豫、很快就能作出判断：我们不得不承认这两种痛苦来源的存在，并且屈服于这不可避免的折磨。我们永远无法完全地掌控自然；我们的肉体仅是自然的一部分，永远是一个短暂的构造物，其适应能力和取得成功的能力有限。认识到这一点，并不会让我们悲观绝望，相反它指引了我们活动的方向。即使我们不能够消除所有痛苦，至少我们可以消除或减轻其中的一部分，几千年的经验已经证实了这一点。我们对第三个痛苦的根源—社会来源，态度则截然不同。我们根本不会承认它，我们不明白为什么自己建立的制度却不能保护、造福我们所有人。然而，想想我们在避免来源于社会的痛苦这一方面收效甚微，我们难免怀疑这儿是否也存在着不可征服的本性因素—这次是我们的精神自我。

当开始思考是否存在这种可能性时，我们遇到了一个令人震惊的观点，对此我们必须花点时间仔细研究。这种观点认为，我们称之为文明的东西是我们不幸的主要根源；如果我们放弃文明，退回到原始状态，就会更加幸福。我说这种观点令人震惊，是因为无论我们如何定义文明的概念，我们试图使用的一切保护自己免受痛苦威胁的方法都确确实实属于这个文明本身。

如此众多的人对文明充满敌意，他们如何形成了这样奇特的观点呢？我相信，长期以来，人们对文明深深不满，而特定历史事件使得不满的土壤里滋生出对文明的强烈谴责。我才疏学浅，尚不能沿着人类历史一直追溯下去，找出完整的因果链。但我想我可以找出最近的两个历史起因。这种对文明的敌意，一定早在基督教战胜异教时就已经存在了。毕竟，这种敌意与贬低尘世生命的基督教思想有着密切联系。前一历史起因在于，航海发现让我们接触到了原始居民和种族。由于观察不充分，加上对其礼仪风俗的错误认识，欧洲人感到他们过着简朴幸福的生活，几乎没有什么需求，认为这种生活是他们这些拥有优越文明的到访者们无法获得的。后来的经验证明了其中一些论断是错误的。这些原始民族生活比较安逸，被错误地认为是因为他们没有复杂的文化需要，而事实是，由于大自然的恩赐，这些人的主要需求能够轻而易举地得到满足。后一历史起因我们尤其熟悉。这一起因发生在人们认识到精神病的机制之后。文明社会中的人享有的幸福本来就少得可怜，而这点幸福还要受到精神病的威胁。人们发现，社会为了其文化理想，迫使人们备尝艰辛，当人们无法忍受时，便变成精神病。由此可以推论，暂停或者减少这些文化理想的要求，幸福的可能性即有可能恢复。

此外还有一个对文明失望的因素。过去几代人中，人类在自然科学及其技术应用方面取得了显著进步，其控制自然的程度，前人几乎难以想象。这些科技进步的细节，众所皆知，此处不用赘言。人们为这些成果感到自豪，确实也是应该的。然而，人们发现，几千年来的渴望的实现—新近获得的对时空的控制、对自然的征服，并没有增加他们想从生活中得到的快乐，并没有让他们感到更加幸福。根据这一事实，我们不能由此断言技术在我们的幸福体系中毫无价值；而应该推断出的结论是，正如控制自然不是文化事业所要达到的唯一目标，也不是人类幸福的唯一前提条件。人们也许要反问：如果我能够随时听到住在几百英里以外我的孩子的声音，如果我的朋友经过艰辛的海上长途航行最终登岸，并在最短的时间内向我通报他的情况，难道我没有真正获得快乐吗？我的幸福感没有增加吗？医学的进步大幅度地降低了婴儿死亡率和妇女生产时受感染的可能性，而且还延长了文明人的平均寿命，难道说这些都毫无意义吗？我们还可以举出许多发生在这个受到鄙薄的时代中科技进步产生裨益的例子。与此同时，悲观主义的批判声也响起，提醒我们上述大部分的满足属于某类笑话所推崇的“廉价快乐”的模式。例如，在寒冷的冬夜，把大腿裸露在被子外面然后再抽进来而得到的那种享受。如果没有铁路征服了距离，我的孩子就永远不会离开家乡，我也就无须打电话听他的声音；如果不能坐船航行，我的朋友就不会踏上海上征途，那么我也就不需要电报来减少我对他的担忧。如果婴儿死亡率下降迫使我们采取极端的节育措施，结果我们却没有比卫生条件得到重视之前生养更多的孩子，我们婚姻中的性生活受到节制，甚至与自然选择规律相悖，如此看来降低婴儿死亡率又有何用？最后，如果生活充满艰辛、困苦、缺少乐趣，只有死才是一种解脱，我们拍手欢迎还来不及，那么长寿对我们又有何益呢？

在当今文明中，我们似乎确实并不感到舒适，但是，我们很难知道早期人类是否幸福，他们幸福的程度，以及他们的文化条件在幸福问题上发挥的作用。我们总想要客观地考虑人们的疾苦，也就是说，把我们自身，连同我们自己所有的需要和感受，置于他们的情形中，然后再决定我们会从中发现他们哪些幸福或不幸的情景。这种探索事物的方法似乎很客观，因为它不考虑主观感觉的差异。但它却是最主观的方法，因为我们对他人的精神状态一无所知，只是把自身的精神状态强加到他们身上。但是，幸福完全是一种主观状态。不论我们对某些情况多么望而生畏，例如，古代的苦工、十七世纪欧洲三十年战争时期的农民、宗教法庭的牺牲者、将被屠杀的犹太人，我们也根本不可能与他们感同身受，不可能去猜测人们对快乐和不快乐感觉的接受能力究竟发生了什么变化—敏感性的逐渐减少，希望的丧失。另外，更加原始或者更加高级的麻醉方法已经改变人们对于愉快或不愉快感觉的接受能力。在极端痛苦的情形下，身体会启动一些特殊的精神保护机制。我感觉继续探讨问题的这个方面没有多大益处。

现在，我们应该把注意力转到文明的本质上来，因为人们怀疑文明对获得幸福是否具有价值。在通过研究获得某些发现之前，我们不应该指望用一个公式三言两语地概括出文明的本质。因此，我们将满足于重复地说：“文明”是指使我们的生活不同于我们的动物祖先的所有成就和制度的总和，这些成就和制度服务于两个目的，即保护人类抵御自然危害与调节人际关系。为了加深对文明的理解，我们将人类社会各个文明表现出的独立特征汇集在一起。在这样做时，我们毫不迟疑地将语言用法或者一些人所称的“语感”作为指导，并且坚信这样我们能公正地评判内在感知，因为内在感知很难用抽象术语进行表述。

文明的起始阶段很容易辨认。一切使地球为人类效劳、保护人类不受凶猛自然力量的侵害等等的活动和价值都属于文明的范畴。文明这一方面的构成几乎是无可置疑的。如果我们追溯到久远的过去，我们发现最初的文明活动是工具的使用、火的利用和房屋的建造。在这些成就中，对火的利用尤为突出，这是一项非同凡响、前所未有的成就[7]；人类还开创了很多其他成就，并从此一路走下去，其中的动力显而易见。人类利用各种工具改善了他的运动器官或感觉器官，或者说消除了发挥这些器官功能的障碍。引擎能让巨大的力量为人们所用，人们可以在任何地方像指挥自己的肌肉一样使用它，有了船和飞机，无论是水还是天空都不能阻碍人的运动。通过眼镜，人纠正了眼球晶状体的缺陷；有了望远镜，人能看到很远的地方；有了显微镜，人克服了视网膜结构造成的视力限制。通过照相机，人创造了可以捕获转瞬即逝的视觉印象的仪器，而留声机则保存了同样转瞬即逝的听觉印象，这两者从本质上说都是人类天生记忆力的物化。借助电话就可以听到远方的人说话，这即使在童话故事中也被认为是不可能的，文字起源于不在场的人的声音的记录，而房子则是母亲子宫的替代物。子宫是人的第一处居所，人类很有可能还留恋着它，在那里人感到安全舒适。

人类借助科学技术，在这个世界上创造了这么多成就！而人最初来到这个世界上只是个孱弱的动物有机体，人类的每一个个体一开始都是无助的婴儿—“噢，大自然中尘埃一般”—人类取得这些成就听上去不仅像童话一般，而且事实上实现了所有—不，大多数—童话般的愿望。所有这些成就人类可以称之为文化成果。很久以前，人类就形成了全能和全知的理想概念，并在神的身上得以体现，人类把自己不能实现的或者被禁止的欲望都寄托在众神身上。因此，我们可以说这些神就是文化理想。今天，人类几乎实现了所有这些理想，他自己几乎就变成了神。但无可否认的是，这些理想只是以惯常的方式得到实现，且只是基于人类的常识判断之上，即它们并非完全得到实现，在某些方面根本没有实现，在其他方面则是部分得到实现。可以说人类已经变成神，带着假肢的神。当他带上所有的辅助器官时，他确实让人印象深刻，尽管这些器官尚未成为他身体的一部分，不时地还会带给他不少麻烦。然而，人类有资格用这样的事实安慰自己，即文明的发展不会在1930年就停滞不前。未来的岁月里，文明这个领域将会有崭新的、也许是不可思议的发展，人类将变得更加像上帝。但是，为了有助于研究，我们不要忘记现代人对于他上帝般的特性并没有感到幸福。

既而我们承认，如果一个国家中有助于人类利用土地或者抵御自然力量的一切事物—总之，对人类有用的一切事物—都受到了照看并且井然有序，那么这个国家的文明确实达到了很高的水平。在这些国家中，可能淹没土地的河流得到治理，河水被引到干旱的地区；土地经过精耕细作种上了适宜的植物；地下矿产资源经过艰辛的劳动开采出来，制成必需的工具；交通工具方便、快捷、可靠；危险的野生动物因被捕杀而灭绝，家畜饲养繁荣发展。但除此之外，我们对文明还有很多别的要求，尤其是，我们希望这些要求在上述这类国家中得到满足。当人们把注意力转向没有任何实用价值的东西—或者任何看似没用的东西，例如在供人玩耍消遣、储蓄新鲜空气的城市公园的场地建造花坛，或者用花盆装饰住宅的窗户，我们也非常赞同，把这也视为文明的象征，就好像我们要否定对文明提出的最初要求似的。我们很快认识到，我们希望文明重视的这种无用的东西就是美；我们要求文明人热爱自然中所遇到的美，并且如果有能力，用双手创造美。然而，我们对文明的要求远没有穷尽，除了美之外，我们还要看到清洁和秩序。当我们读到位于斯特拉特福德的莎士比亚父亲家门前有很大一个粪堆的描述时，就会认为莎士比亚时期英国乡镇的文明水平还比较低。当我们看到维也纳郊区林间小路上乱扔的废纸时，便义愤填膺地称之为“野蛮”—文明的对立。我们觉得一切污秽都与文明相悖，我们也把清洁的要求扩展到人身上。当从书中读到太阳王路易十四身上有股难闻的气味时，我们不禁感到吃惊。在贝拉岛（又叫美丽岛）上，当看到拿破仑早晨洗漱用的小脸盆时，我们不禁摇头。事实上，即使有人把使用肥皂视为文明的一个标准，我们也不会感到吃惊。秩序同样如此，它和清洁一样与人类行为密切相关。但在自然中我们找不到清洁的模式。相反，秩序是从自然界模仿来的。人类所观察到的天体的匀称与整齐，不仅给人类提供了将秩序引进生活中的样式，而且还提供了如何保持秩序的线索。秩序是一种强迫性的重复，一个模式一旦确定下来，秩序就决定了一件事何时、何地以及如何去做，这样一来，再遇到相同的情况，人们就不必犹豫不决了。秩序的好处无可争议。它使人们能够充分利用时间和空间，同时还节省脑力。人们或许有理由指望秩序一开始就不费吹灰之力地在人类活动中得到确立，但可能会惊讶于事实并非如此—恰恰相反，人类天性草率、无序、靠不住，因此必须通过艰苦的训练，才能学会模仿天体模式。

显然，美、清洁和秩序在我们对文明的要求中占有特殊的地位。谁都不会认为它们在生活中与我们对自然力的控制和我们即将认识到的其他因素同等重要。但是，也没有人会认为它们微不足道，希望抛弃它们。文明并不仅仅关注功用，这一点已经在人们热爱美，并坚持把美包括进文明这一例子中得到证实。秩序的用处显而易见。至于清洁，我们必须记住它也是卫生学对我们的要求。我们可以推断，甚至在有科学预防法之前，人类也并未完全忽视卫生和清洁之间的关系。然而，功用性并不能完全解释人们对清洁的追求；除此之外，一定还涉及其他的因素。

然而，没有什么比高层次精神活动（包括智力、科学和艺术等方面的成就）的欣赏和培养，以及思想在人类生活中被赋予的主导作用更能体现文明的特征。这些思想中首推宗教体系，关于其复杂性，我在别处已经论及；其次是哲学思考；最后是所谓的人类理想，即人类所形成的关于个人、国家和整个人类所能达到的完美境界的主张，以及基于这些理想所提出的要求。事实上，这些精神活动产生的思想和成就并不是孤立的，而是密切相连的，这不仅增加了描述它们的困难，而且还使追溯它们的心理起源变得复杂。如果我们假定，通常人类一切活动的动力都是源于追求功用和快乐这两个相互融合的目标，我们必须承认我们在这里谈论的一切文明体现皆是如此，尽管这在科学和艺术活动中显而易见。但是，毫无疑问其他活动也满足了人类的强烈需要，虽然也许只是满足少部分人的需要。同时，我们也不要被这样或那样的宗教、哲学体系或者理想等价值判断引入歧途。无论是我们通过思考，在这些宗教、哲学或理想中找到人类精神的最高成就，抑或是将其认定为歪理邪说并加以谴责，我们都不得不承认，它们的存在及优势地位都是高度文明的象征。

作为文明最后但也极为重要的一个特性，我们要考虑如何调节人与人之间的关系，即影响人们扮演邻居、员工、性对象、家庭成员以及国家公民等角色的各种社会关系。这里，要避开文明特定理想要求的影响，抓住一般意义上的文明属性尤其困难。也许，当人类首次尝试调节这些社会关系时，我们就可以宣布文明的因素已经出现。因为如果没有这样的尝试，人们就不得不屈服于个人武断意志的支配。也就是说，体格比较强壮的人将根据他自己的利益和本能冲动来独断专行。如果这个体格较强壮的人遇到了比他还强的人，后者同样也会这样做。只有当大部分人聚集到一起时，才会比任何个体强大得多，才能形成针对个人的统一阵线。只有在这时，集体社会生活才成为可能。集体的力量被冠以“正义”的名义，与被谴责为“蛮力”的个人力量相抗衡。个体的力量被集体的力量所取代是人类向文明迈进的决定性一步。其本质在于：作为社会集体的成员会在自己满意的一定范围内节制自己的欲望，而作为个人则毫无节制。因此，接下来对文明的要求便是公正，也就是，法律秩序一旦制定，就不能徇私枉法，偏向某一个人。这一点并不要求对法律体系的道德伦理作出价值判断。文明的进一步发展似乎旨在达到法律不再表达少数人意志的一种境界—即不是某一个种姓、某一社会阶层或者某一部族意志的表达，因为这些小团体相对于其他更广泛的团体而言，就像是暴戾的个人。最终结果应该是，所有人或至少是合格的社会集体成员，通过放弃部分本能的满足，建立起一个法律体系，使得这些合格的社会成员不会沦为个人蛮力的牺牲品。

个体自由并不是文明的恩赐。在文明产生以前，自由的程度最大，尽管那时自由也并没有多少实际意义，因为个体几乎不能捍卫他的自由。文明的发展限制了自由，法律公正要求每个人都必须受到限制，无一例外。人类集体中所表现出的任何对自由的渴望都可能演变为对现存不公正的反抗，因而有助于文明的进一步发展，与文明并不排斥。但是，这种对自由的渴望也可能产生于人类原始性格的遗留部分，这种遗留部分尚未被文明驯服，因此会成为敌视文明的基础。因此，对自由的渴望会转而反对文明的某种特定形式和要求，或者彻底反对文明。似乎任何影响都不能够诱使个人将其本性改变成白蚁一般的本性。人们或许永远要反对集体意志，维护个体自由的权利。人类的斗争大部分围绕着一个任务，即寻找个人要求与文明集体要求之间合适的或者两全其美的和解。涉及人类命运的一个问题是，这种融合是否可以通过某一特定的文明模式达到，或者冲突是否根本就是无法调和的。

人类的共同感觉告诉我们人类生活中的哪些特点可以称之为文明，我们因此对文明有了一个清晰印象，勾勒出了文明的整体轮廓，尽管我们尚未学到任何不为人所熟知的东西。与此同时，我们应尽量避免限于偏见，认为文明就是走向完善，就是人类通往至善至美的必经之路。但我们现在提出的这个观点，可能会把我们引向别处。文明的进程，在我们看来似乎是人类经历的一个独特过程，其中某些内容为我们所熟知。根据其所引起的人类本能的众所皆知的性情的变化，我们即可对文明特性进行描述，对于本能的满足是我们有效利用生命的终极任务。这些本能中的一些成分被消耗掉了，取而代之的是针对个体而言的性格特征。这一过程最奇怪的例子要算是幼儿的肛门欲。在幼儿的成长过程中，他们对肛门的排泄作用、排泄器官和排泄物的最初兴趣转变为一组特征，即我们所熟悉的节俭、秩序感和清洁感。虽然这些特性本身大有益处、备受推崇，但可能被强化，直至占据绝对主导地位，形成所谓的肛门性格。这种情况是如何发生的，我们不得而知，但是，这种观点无疑是正确的。我们已经看到秩序和清洁是文明的基本要求，尽管它们是否至关重要，是否是快乐的源泉，并不非常明显。从这点上说，我们不禁想到文明紧承与个体力比多发展的相似性。肛门欲之外的其他本能，则被诱使改变其获得满足的条件，转而寻找其他的途径。大多情形下，这个过程与我们所熟知的升华过程（本能目的的升华）是相一致的。但在某些情况下，也可能不一致。本能的升华是文化发展最显著的特征；由于它的存在，科学、艺术、思想意识等较高层次的精神活动才在文明生活中发挥着至关重要的作用。乍看起来，人们会倾向认为文明将升华作用强加于本能身上。但对这一问题进一步思考，可能会有更好的认识。第三个因素似乎最重要，即文明在多大程度上要通过消除本能才能得到确立；多大程度上要利用克制、压抑或其他手段使得强烈的本能得不到满足为前提条件，这一点不容忽视。这种“文化挫折”支配着人类广泛的社会关系领域。我们早已知道，这种挫折造成对文明的敌意，一切文明都须与这一敌意抗争。它也对我们的精神分析科学提出了严肃的要求，分析科学对此尚需作出很多解释。如何才能剥夺对本能的满足，要想解决这一问题并非易事。剥夺本能的满足，而不冒任何风险是不可能的。若没有有效补偿，严重的混乱肯定会接踵而来。

但是，关于文明发展这一特殊过程与个体的正常成熟过程具有可比性这一观点，如果想要知道它具有什么意义，显然还须解决另一问题，我们必须追问文明发展究竟源于什么样的影响，它究竟是如何开始的，其进程中又有什么决定因素。

Ⅳ

这一任务十分艰巨，人们望而却步是自然的。下面是我曾作过的一些猜测。

一个原始人在发现通过劳动就能改善他在地球上的命运后，主动权实际上掌握在他自己手中，其他人与他齐心协力还是作对，对他来说就不再无关紧要了。对他而言，这个其他人也就具有了作为一个共同劳动伙伴的价值，如果他们生活在一起，将会大有裨益。甚至早在类人猿的史前时期，人类就有了组织家庭的习惯，家庭成员大概就是他最初的帮手。或许家庭的建立是基于以下事实，即生殖满足的需要不再像一个客人，某一天突然出现，然后离去，很久都不回来，而是像一个长期的房客住了下来。从此以后，男性就有了一种把女性—说得更概括一些—把他的性对象留在身边的动机；而女性则不愿离开她弱小的孩子，为了孩子和强壮的男性继续生活在一起。[8]这样的原始家庭，仍然缺乏文明的一项基本特征：父亲作为家庭首脑，拥有绝对的独裁权力。在《图腾与禁忌》一书中，我曾试图揭示原始家庭怎样发展到下一阶段以兄弟关系为纽带的群居生活。在制服父亲的过程中，儿子们发现联合起来要比一个人的力量大得多。图腾文化就是建立在种种限制之上的，儿子们之间必须互相迫使对方遵守这些限制，才能保持上述的群居生活。遵守禁忌的习俗形成了最初的“法律”体系。因此，两种原因导致人类选择群居生活：一是艰难的外部环境迫使人们共同参与劳动；二是爱的力量，爱一方面使得男人不愿意放弃自己的性对象，另一方面使得女人不愿意被夺去自己的亲骨肉—孩子。厄洛斯爱神和定数女神阿南刻（爱和必要性）也就成为人类文明的始祖。文明的第一个结果是，数目相当可观的一部分人能够共同生活在一个集体中。由于这两个巨大的力量在集体中共同发挥作用，人们因此可以期望文明进一步得到发展，顺利地朝着更好地支配外部世界，吸收更多人群加入这个集体的方向前进。然而，这样的文明为什么绝对不会是文明社会成员们的幸福源泉，就很难理解了。

在我们接着探讨对文明的敌意产生于什么地方之前，就上述视爱为文明基础之一的观点，请允许我们在此说一点题外话，借以弥补我们在前面论述的不足。前面我们探讨过人类发现性（生殖的）爱能给予他最强烈的满足体验，而且实际上为他提供了所有幸福的典范，那么这一发现一定向他表明，他应该在生活中继续沿着性关系的途径去寻找幸福，并且使生殖器的性欲成为其生活的中心。我们接着又讲过，在这一过程中，他使自己以一种危险的方式依赖于一部分外部世界，即他选择的爱的对象，如果他被所爱的对象抛弃，或是由于不忠或死亡而失去所爱的对象，他就会感受到极度的痛苦。正因为此，每个时代的智者贤人都严厉地警告我们要抵制这种生活方式，尽管如此，这种生活方式仍对许多人有着巨大的吸引力。

有一小部分人，由于自身的特质，不顾一切地试图通过爱去寻找幸福，尽管爱的作用在精神方面必然要经过修正。这些人把重心从被爱转移到主动去爱，从而使自己独立于所爱对象的意愿；为了避免自己失去所爱的对象，他们不是把自己的爱仅仅给予某一个对象，而是一视同仁地给予每个人；为了避免由性爱带来的不确定和失望，他们背离性的目标，并把这种本能转化成一种目标抑制冲动。这样他们就在内心产生了一种均衡、坚定的爱的情感，这种爱，尽管源自性爱，却与波涛汹涌般的性爱不再有任何外在上的相似之处。也许圣方济亚西西是利用这种爱去追求内在幸福感做得最极致的一个。再有，我们承认的实现人类快乐原则的手段之一往往与宗教有关。这种与宗教的联系也许存在于遥远的感觉领域，那里自我与对象的区别，或是对象与对象的区别被忽略了。有一种伦理观点—其深层动机我们马上就会认识到—认为这种对人类和世界的博爱是人类能够达到的最高境界。尽管刚刚开始讨论这一问题，我还是要提出两点主要的保留意见：首先，在我们看来，不加区分的爱，是对所爱对象的不公正，导致一部分爱的内在价值丧失；其次并非所有的人都值得爱。

作为家庭建立的基础的那种爱，不论是不放弃其直接性满足的原始形式，还是经过目标抑制修正过的形式，在文明中依然发挥着作用。不管以何种方式，爱继续发挥着将相当多的人聚集在一起的作用，这一作用比共同的劳动利益产生的凝聚效果更为强烈。语言随意地用“爱”这个词是有历史根由的。这个词不仅表示男人与女人之间的关系，男女之间的生殖需要促使他们建立起家庭，家庭中父母与孩子之间、兄弟姐妹之间积极的情感也称之为“爱”，尽管我们须把这种情感描述成“目标抑制的爱”。事实上，目标抑制的爱原本是一种纯粹的肉体上的爱，在人们的潜意识中还是如此。纯粹的肉体之爱和目标抑制的爱二者都可从家庭延伸出去，使原本陌生的人之间产生了一种新的联系。性爱导致了新的家庭的建立；“目标抑制”的爱则产生了“友谊”。友谊对于文明而言非常重要，因为它克服了性爱的某些局限，比如说排他性。但爱与文明的关系，发展下去，变得模糊起来，一方面，爱与文明的利益产生冲突，另一方面，文明以众多的限制威胁着爱。

爱与文明的裂痕似乎是不可避免的。然而人们并不能立刻辨出个中原因。它首先表现为家庭与个人所属的较大集体之间的冲突。我们已经看到，文明的主要使命之一就是把人们聚集在更大的集体之中。但是家庭不愿意放弃它的成员。一个家庭团结得越是紧密，其成员往往就越要脱离其他人，也就越难进入一个更广阔的生活圈子。从种系遗传学的角度来看，比较古老的共同生活方式，现在只在童年期存在，它拒绝被后来所形成的文明方式取代。因此脱离家庭成为每一个年轻人面临的任务，并且社会常常通过成年仪式和社交入会仪式来帮助他们完成这个任务。这给人的印象是，这些困难是所有的心理发展—事实上是所有的有机体发展—的固有困难。

此外，女人很快站到了文明潮流的对立面，显露出阻碍和抑制文明发展的影响—尽管最初正是女人对爱的要求奠定了文明的基础。女人所代表的是家庭和性生活的利益；而创造文明日益成为男人的工作，给他们布置了更为艰巨的任务，迫使男人不得不实行本能的升华，而女人则没有这样的倾向。由于一个男人没有无限的心理能量可供使用，所以他必须临时分配自己的力比多以完成自己的使命。他在文化目标上消耗的精力，很大程度上就不能再用在女人身上了。他与男性的频繁交往，以及对这种交往的依赖，更加让他无法尽一个丈夫和父亲的义务。因此女人会发现，正是由于文明的要求，她们才被置于次要的地位，所以她们就产生了对文明的敌对情绪。

文明对性生活的限制倾向，与它扩大文化阵地的其他倾向一样明显。在文明的起始阶段，即图腾阶段，就有反对性对象选择中乱伦行为的禁律，也许这是从古到今人类性生活所经历的最强烈的打击。禁忌、法律和风俗习惯进一步限制了性自由。这些限制不仅影响到男人，也影响到了女人。但在这一点上，并非所有的文明都采取同样手段与力度；人们享有的性自由程度受到社会经济结构的影响。我们早已知道这一方面的文明需要服从效益，因为文明消耗的心理能量正是所剥夺的性行为所需要的能量。在这一方面，文明对于性欲的做法就像一个部族或是一个阶层的人一样，在征服另一部族或阶层后便开始剥削他们。由于害怕被压迫方起来反抗，压迫一方就采取了严格的预防措施。在这样的发展过程中，我们西欧的文明已达到了很高的水平。从心理的角度来看，从一开始就禁止各种形式的儿童性生活的做法是站得住脚的。因为如果在儿童时代没有为约束性欲打好基础的话，在成年时期就没有希望来约束性欲了。然而一个文明社会毫无理由去做得更过分，甚至否认这些显而易见和令人震惊的事实。对于性成熟的个人来说，对象的选择只能局限于异性，并且大多数超出生殖器以外的性满足会被认为是变态行为而遭到禁止。一切清规戒律要求所有人去过同样的性生活，而毫不考虑人类在性素质方面所存在的先天或后天的差异；因而剥夺了相当一部分人的性乐趣，这成为严重的不公平的根源。这些约束的结果是，那些自身素质未受限制的正常人，其所有性趣就能通过那些依旧敞开的渠道，完全地排泄出去。但这种被视为合法的异性性行为仍然受到法律和一夫一妻制的限制。当今文明清楚地表明，它只承认一男一女在一个不能撤销的唯一契约基础上的性关系；它不赞成性行为成为快乐本身的源泉，只能容忍性行为作为繁衍后代的手段，因为到目前为止，还没有什么手段能代替性行为来繁衍后代。

以上当然是一种极端的观点。大家都知道它根本行不通，即使短期内也行不通。只有弱者才屈服于这样一种对他们性自由的公然侵犯。而强者只有在得到补偿的条件下才会忍受这种侵犯。这些我们在后面还要提到。文明社会自知它不得不对一些根据其法令本该惩罚的犯罪行为睁一只眼闭一只眼。但是我们不应因此犯相反的错误，认为文明既然没有去实施它既定的所有目标，那么上述文化态度就无伤大雅。文明人的性生活还是大大地被削弱了；我们常常会产生这样的印象：性的功能会衰退，就像我们的牙齿和头发作为人体器官会衰老一样。人们有理由认为性作为快乐的源泉、作为实现人生目的的手段已经明显减弱了。有时候，人们似乎发现不仅是文明的压力，而是性功能本身固有的某种东西，使我们不能得到完全的满足，迫使我们选择别的途径追求幸福。这一说法或许是错误的，但很难下定论。[9]

Ⅴ

精神分析法告诉我们，那些被我们称为精神病的人所不能忍受的正是这些性生活的挫折。精神病患者在他的症状中为自己创造了一些替代性的满足，然而这些满足不是本身造成他的痛苦，就是成为他痛苦的来源，因为它们使他与周围环境和社会相处困难。后一现象很容易理解，但前者又给我们提出了一个新的难题。文明除了要求人类牺牲性满足外，还要求人类作出其他方面的牺牲。

我们将文明发展的困难看作是发展的普遍困难所在，将这一困难追溯到力比多的惰性上，归结为力比多拒绝新的角色、不愿放弃旧有的角色。性爱是两个人之间的一种关系，任何第三者只能是多余或者碍事的，但文明所依靠的却是众人之间的关系；我们由此可以推论出文明与性行为之间的对立，这与文明发展的困难问题是一回事。当恋爱关系发展到高潮时，恋人们对外界就毫无兴趣了，对于一对恋人来说，有他们自己就已足够，甚至不需要共同的孩子来促使自己幸福。爱神厄洛斯通过让两个人相恋来进行繁衍后代的行为，但达到这一众所皆知的目的后，就拒绝再有所作为了，爱神存在的核心价值的体现，在这件事上再明显不过了。

到现在为止，我们完全可以想象这样一个文化集体，其成员成双成对，力比多在他们自身中即获得满足，但共同的工作和利益还是将这些成对的人们联系在一起。如果真是这样的话，文明就不必再汲取性行为的能量了。但是这种理想的情形并不存在，也从来没有发生过。现实告诉我们，文明并不满足于人类现有的纽带关系，文明还要寻求通过力比多把集体成员相互连接起来，并且为达到这一目的不惜一切手段，支持一切可以使集体成员建立起强烈认同感的途径，最大程度上唤起目标抑制的力比多以借助友谊的纽带增强集体的关联。为了实现这些目标，节制性生活就变得不可避免。然而我们还是无法理解是什么迫使文明走上这样的发展道路，是什么引发了文明对性行为的对抗，其必要性何在。一定存在某种扰乱文明的因素，只是我们尚未发现。

在我们说的文明社会的理想要求中，有一条或许能指引我们作出正确理解。这一要求是：“你须爱邻居如同爱自己”。这一要求举世皆知，并且无疑比基督教还要悠久。基督教把它作为最值得骄傲的主张加以推崇。然而它确实并不古老，在各个历史时期，它对人们来讲仍然陌生。让我们以一种天真的态度来对待这一问题，就像第一次听到这句话一样，这样我们就不禁会产生一种惊奇和困惑的感觉。我们为什么要这样做呢？这样做对我们有什么好处呢？但是首先，我们如何才能做到这一点呢？它怎么可能呢？我的爱对我来说是某种宝贵的东西，我不应当不负责任地将它抛出。这种爱使我承担着某些义务，为了履行这些义务，我必须准备作出牺牲。如果我爱某一个人，他在某些方面就必须值得我去爱（我在这里不考虑他可能对我有什么用，也不考虑他作为性对象对我有什么样的重要性，因为这两种关系对于爱我的邻居这一训诫都没有关系）。如果他在某些重要方面很像我，以至于我在爱他时能够爱我自己，那么他就值得我爱；如果他是一个比我完美得多的人，从而我在爱他的同时可以爱自己的理想形象，那么他也值得我爱；再者，如果他是朋友的儿子，我也必须去爱他，如果他遇到什么灾难的话，我的朋友所感到的痛苦也就是我的痛苦—我应当去分担这一痛苦。但是，如果他对我来说是一个陌生人，并且如果他自身没有什么吸引我的优点，或者在我的感情生活中无足轻重，他就不能够吸引我，那么让我去爱他将会很难。事实上，去爱陌生人是错误的，因为我的亲人或朋友珍视我的爱，并将我的爱视为一种我对他们偏爱的表示，如果我把一个陌生人和他们同等对待，这对他们来说是不公平的。但是如果我去爱他（用那种博爱方式）—只是因为他也是地球上的生物，就像昆虫、蚯蚓或草蛇一样，恐怕他只能分享我的爱的一小部分—我的理性判断会把大部分爱留给自己。如果一个训诫实施起来并不能让人感觉合理，这样的训诫又有何用呢？

再进一步观察，我发现了更多的困难。这样一个陌生人不仅不值得我爱，而且老实地讲，他更多是引起我的敌意，甚至憎恨。他似乎对我也没有一丝爱的意思，且没有对我表现出丝毫的关心与体谅。如果对他有利，他会毫不犹豫地伤害我，他也绝不会自问因此所得的利益是否和我遭受的伤害相当。实际上，他甚至不需要去获得什么利益，只要可以满足他的某种欲望，他就会毫无顾忌地嘲笑我、侮辱我、诽谤我，让我成为他的配角以显出他的优势。他越感到安全，我就越感到无助，也越肯定他会以这样的方式对待我。如果他的表现完全不同，对我这个陌生人，他表示出关心，表现出宽容，那么任何情形下我也愿意以同样的方式对待他，而不需任何训诫的指示。的确，如果这条庄严的训诫这样说的话：“爱你的邻居就像他爱你一样”，那么我就毫无异议了。还有第二条训诫，它似乎更让我无法理解，并且引起我内心更强烈的反感。这就是：“爱你的敌人”。然而，经过仔细考虑之后，我觉得把它视为一个更加过分的要求是错误的；说到底，它与第一条训诫是一回事。[10]

我似乎听到一个威严高贵的声音告诫着我：“恰恰是由于你的邻居不值得你爱，甚至是你的敌人，你才必须要爱他像爱你自己一样。”于是我明白了这条训诫不过是又一个“因为荒谬故我信”的例子而已。

现在，当我的邻居被告诫说要爱我像爱他自己一样时，他完全可能作出和我一样的反应，并且因为同样的原因而拒绝爱我。我希望他不会给出和我完全一样的客观理由，但他却有和我同样的想法。尽管如此，人类行为还是存在着差异，伦理学不顾这些差异的条件制约，将其划分为“善”和“恶”两类。只要这些不可否认的差异依然存在，去践行高级伦理要求的内容对文明的目标就会造成损害，因为这会提倡恶有善报。在这一点上，人们不禁会想起法国国民议会厅曾经的一幕，人们在争论着是否废除死刑。一个议员强烈地要求废除死刑，他的演讲得到持久的雷鸣般的掌声，直至大厅中传来一个声音：“让杀人犯先迈出第一步不去杀人吧！”

隐藏在这一切背后的，也是许多人不愿意承认的真相是：人类不是需要爱的温和生物，顶多是受到攻击后会采取防卫措施而已；相反，人类在其本能的禀性中蕴藏着强大的攻击性。因此，他们的邻居不仅仅是潜在的助手或性对象，而且是诱发他们对其发动攻击的对象，他们会毫无补偿地剥削他的劳动力，未经他的许可便强行与他发生性关系，霸占他的财产，羞辱他，折磨他，让他痛苦，并且杀死他。“人对人如同狼对狼一样”。面对历史上和生活中的经验，谁还有勇气对这个结论提出质疑呢？一般来说，这种残酷的攻击性或者等待着某种挑衅，或者服务于某种通过比较温和的手段即能达到的目标。当条件适宜，平时控制着人类的精神上的制衡力量失去效力时，他们的攻击性即自发显现，暴露出兽性，连同类也不能免于受害。但凡想想种族大迁徙的恐怖情形，想想匈奴人或者又称之为成吉思汗和帖木儿统治下的蒙古人的侵略，想想虔诚的十字军占领耶路撒冷的时候，抑或是第一次世界大战的恐怖情形，人们都将不得不承认这一事实。

我们在自己身上觉察到了这种攻击性倾向，也有理由假定别人身上也具有这样的倾向，这种倾向破坏了我们与邻居的关系，也迫使文明之路更为迂回曲折。由于人类之间充满原始的敌意，文明社会永远存在着崩溃的危险。劳动中的共同利益尚不足以将人类团结在一起，因为源自本能的感情远比理智的利益强大得多。文明必须尽其最大的努力来限制人类的攻击性本能，并且运用心理反应形成机制来控制它们的显现。从此就有了一些方法的运用，旨在促进人们情感上彼此认同、进入目标抑制的性关系中，就有了对性生活的限制，就有了爱邻居如同爱自己的理想训诫，这一训诫的合理性在于：没有什么比它更能与人的攻击性本性相抗衡了。尽管作了种种尝试，文明的这些努力目前仍收效甚微。文明希望通过使用暴力打击罪犯的权利，来防止最赤裸裸的野蛮暴行，但是法律对于人类攻击性表现的微妙形式却无能为力。如今我们每个人须丢弃年轻时寄托在他人身上的期望，这种期望只能是幻想；须学会认识到他人的恶意让我们的生活变得如此艰难和痛苦。同时，指责文明试图从人类活动中消除争斗和竞争也是不公平的。争斗与竞争自然必不可少。但是对立未必就是敌对，对立只是完全被误用成敌对的一种情形而已。

共产主义者认为他们已经找到了将人类从罪恶中解脱出来的途径。根据他们的观点，人无疑本来是好的，对邻居也友善，但私有制度腐化了其天性。私有财产的拥有权赋予个人以权力并诱使他运用这种权力去虐待他的邻人；而那些被剥夺财产的人就必定会对压迫者充满敌意，必定会反抗其压迫。如果废除了私有制，实行财产公有，即人人享有财产，那么恶意和敌对就会在人类中消失。由于每个人的需要都将得到满足，任何人都没有理由把另一个人当作他的敌人；所有人都将乐意承担起任何必要的工作。我并不关心对共产主义制度在经济体制方面的批评，私有财产的废除究竟是否合适、有益，我也无从得知。[11]但我能确认的是，这种废除私有财产做法背后的心理学假设毫无依据，只是幻想而已。废除私有财产后，人类对攻击的喜好仅仅是被剥夺了其众多手段中的一个，虽然无疑这是一个强大的手段，但绝不是最强的手段。人在权力和影响上的差异、攻击性的本性都没有任何改变，攻击性为达到目的利用的正是这种权力和影响上的差异。攻击性并不是由财产造成的；财产匮乏的原始社会弥漫的几乎是毫无节制的攻击性。在幼儿期，人的攻击性即显露出来了，那时所谓的财产尚未脱离原始的肛门期形式，它构成了人们之间各种感情和爱的关系的基础（也许只有一个例外，就是母亲和儿子的关系）。即使我们废除了物质财富的私人所有权，性关系领域的特权仍然存在，人或许在其他方面完全平等，但这一特权必定引起人们极度的不满和强烈的憎恨。如果我们也消除这一特权，允许性生活完全自由，并且进而废除家庭这一文明的胚胎细胞，我们诚然无法预知文明进程可能会走上怎样的新道路；但有一点我们可以确定：无论文明之路通向何方，人类本性中的攻击性坚不可摧，将会如影随形地跟从文明。

显而易见，让人们放弃攻击性倾向并非易事。没有这一需求的满足，他们就会感到不适。人们不应轻视相当小的一个文化圈子所享有的优越性，这一优越性以一种对圈外人的敌意形式给攻击性本能提供了一种发泄渠道。人类总是可以通过爱将相当一部分人团结在一起，只要圈外人成为其攻击对象。我曾经讨论过这样一种现象，即恰恰是疆土毗连，并且本应关系密切的群体，常常沉溺于相互斗争、相互讥笑嘲弄之中—比如西班牙人和葡萄牙人，北德人和南德人，英格兰人和苏格兰人，等等。我将这种现象称之为“细微差异上的自恋”，这一名称当然并不足以解释这一现象。但它可以视为某一群体满足攻击性倾向、增强集体凝聚力的一个便利而又无伤大雅的方法。散居各地的犹太人对其定居地所在的东道国文化作出了宝贵的贡献；然而不幸的是，中世纪对犹太人的大屠杀并未使基督教徒们因此感到那个时代更加安全、和平。在圣·保罗将博爱奠定为基督徒社团的基础之后，其不可避免的后果是，基督徒对那些处于这一集体之外的人们极度地不能容忍。对罗马人而言，其帝国并不是建立在爱的基础之上，因此，宗教的不相容对他们来说是陌生的，尽管宗教是国家大事，并且在全国传播。日耳曼人主宰世界的梦想要以反犹太主义来作补充也不是不可能理解的偶然现象。在俄国建立一个共产主义的新文明的努力会以迫害资产阶级作为心理支柱，也就变得可以理解了。只是人们未免有点担忧地感到疑惑：布尔什维克在彻底清除了他们的资产阶级后又将做什么呢？

如果文明把如此大的牺牲不仅强加于人类的性行为，而且还强加于人类的攻击性行为的话，我们就能更好地理解为什么在这样一种文明里人们极难使自己感到幸福了。其实原始人由于不被限制其本能，境况反而更好一些。然而原始人无法确定能长长久久地享受这样的好运，这一点让我们稍感平衡。文明人则是用他可能获得的一部分幸福换取了一部分安全。然而，我们还应考虑到，在原始家庭中，只有它的首领才能充分享受这种本能的自由；其他人则生活在奴隶般的压迫之中。所以在文明的原始时期，享受文明的好处的少数人和被剥夺了这些好处的多数人之间，形成了极其鲜明的对比。至于今天仍存在的原始民族，更仔细的调查已表明：我们毫无理由因其享受的自由而妒忌他们的本能生活。他们要受到一种不同类型的约束，这种约束或许比强加在文明人身上的约束更为严苛。

当我们理直气壮地挑剔文明的现状，指责它没有充分理睬我们对幸福生活形式的要求，指责它容许如此多的或许完全可以避免的苦难存在时；当我们毫不吝惜批评，试图发掘出它不完美的根源时—我们是在行使自己的正当权利，并不是在表明我们就是文明的敌人。我们希望在文明社会中逐渐施行一些改变，使其更好地满足我们的要求，免于以上批评。但我们或许也应该熟悉这样的观点，即有些难题存在于文明的本性之中，无论通过何种改革都无法克服。我们除了面临限制本能的任务（这一任务我们已经做好准备）外，还面临着一个危险的境况，这一境况我们称之为“集体心理痛苦”。当一个社会的纽带主要依靠成员之间的认同感，而发挥领导才干的个人，在集体形成中却又未能获得应有的名望时，这一危险就最具威胁性。美国文明的现状给我们提供了一个绝好的机会，来研究人们应该惧怕的文化伤害。但是我将抵住对美国文明进行批判的诱惑；我不想给人留下这样的印象，即我自身也想使用美国式批判方法。

Ⅵ

在过去的写作过程中，我从未像现在一样如此强烈地感到，我所描述的东西不过是些众所周知的事情，而我还在浪费着纸张笔墨，在一定的时候还要浪费排字工人和印刷工人的劳动，来论述一些实际上是不言而喻的东西。基于此，如果承认一个特殊、独立的攻击本能的存在，似乎意味着必须对精神分析理论关于本能方面的内容作出修改，我将会非常乐意地去修改。

然而我们将会看到，事情并非如此，很久以前，精神分析论就存在这样的一个方向改变，现在只不过是更加热切地关注这一方向，并沿着这一方向追踪下去，探寻后果罢了。在分析理论缓慢发展出的所有要素中，关于本能原理的摸索是最费劲的一个。但本能原理对于精神分析的整个结构必不可少，因此必须充实这一理论。在最初我感到完全迷失的时候，诗人哲学家席勒的一句话给我提供了最初的线索，其大意是“食欲与性欲”构成了这个世界的机制。食欲可以用来代表那些旨在保存个体的本能；而性欲则寻求对象，其主要功能，因自然各方面的恩赐，是保存人类这一物种。所以，最初自我本能和对象本能相互对立。我采用“力比多”这一术语表示后者，而且仅仅表示后一种本能的能量。因而这一对立就是自我本能和指向对象的爱（从最广的意义上讲）—力比多本能之间的对立。诚然，这些对象本能中的一种，即性虐狂本能，和其他对象本能完全不同；因为它完全缺乏爱。再者，从某些方面来说，它明显地依附于自我本能；它无法掩盖其与旨在控制的本能之间的紧密联系，而与力比多目的无关。然而，这样的矛盾还是可以克服的：毕竟，性虐狂显然是性生活中的一部分；只不过，在这种性生活中，温柔为残忍所取代。精神病似乎就是自我保存的利益和力比多需要之间斗争的结果，在这一斗争中，自我胜出，但却付出了痛苦和牺牲的惨重代价。

每一个分析家都会承认，即使在今天，这个观点听起来仍是正确的，而不是早就被摒弃的一个错误。不过，当我们的研究从探讨被抑制的本能发展到探讨压抑性的原动力时，从对象本能发展到自我，对精神分析论作出修改也就成为必然。这里关键性的一步是自恋概念的引进—也就是说，认识到自我本身也被力比多占领，事实上自我是力比多的原始老巢，并且某种程度上仍是力比多的指挥部。这种自恋的力比多转向对象，于是就成为对象力比多；而对象力比多可能再次转换为自恋力比多。自恋这一概念使我们有可能对创伤性精神病，对许多与精神病密切相关的状况，以及精神病本身加以理解和分析。我们没有必要放弃移情性精神病是由自我实行阻止性欲的尝试导致的这一观点；但是力比多的概念却受到了威胁。由于自我本能也是属于力比多的，所以我们暂时似乎必须使力比多等同于一般意义上的本能能量，正如C.G.荣格之前提出的那样。不过仍然可以肯定的是，本能不可能都属于同一类型，尽管目前对此我还无法解释。当强迫性重复和本能的守旧性（或倒退性）引起我的注意时，我在《超越快乐原则》（1920）一书中迈出了下一步。从对生命开端和对具有可比性的生物的思考，我得出以下结论：除了保存生物体本身并使它加入更大的单位的本能外，[12]一定还存在着另外一个相反的本能，这一本能试图分解这些单位，并且把它们送回到原始、无机的状态。这就是说，不仅存在着爱神厄洛斯，还存在着死亡本能。生命现象正可以从这两种本能的相互作用、相互抗衡中得到解释。然而，要具体说明这一假定的死亡本能的活动并非易事。厄洛斯的表现形式是清晰可见、可闻的；人们或许可以设想死亡本能在有机体趋向死亡解体的过程中悄悄地发挥着作用，但这当然还不能成为证据。一个更富有成效的设想是，一部分死亡本能转向外部世界，以攻击性本能和破坏性本能的面貌出现。通过这一途径死亡本能本身被迫转而为厄洛斯服务，因为有机体会破坏其他有生命或无生命的事物，而不是破坏其自身。相反，任何阻止攻击性向外发展的行为都必定助长有机体的自我破坏，自我破坏无论如何总会继续进行。同时，人们根据下面的例子可能得出这样的猜想：这两种本能极少或可能从不单独出现，它们总是以极为多样化的不同比例融合在一起，因而我们难以判断、辨认。在性虐狂中，它早就被视为性的部分冲动，人们可以看到爱的本能与破坏的本能极其强烈的融合形式。而它的对应物—性受虐狂—则是指向内部的破坏和性欲的结合，这一结合使得本无法觉察的抗衡变得显而易见、可以觉察。

关于死亡本能或破坏本能存在的假想甚至在精神分析界也遭到了反对；我很清楚人们常常有这样一种倾向，就是把一切对爱不利和敌对的东西都归咎于爱的本质中的原始双极性。我在这里阐述的观点最初只是试验性地提出，但是随着时间的推移，这些观点在我头脑中变得根深蒂固，以致我再也不能从其他角度思考了。我认为，从理论的角度来看，它们比任何其他人可能会想到的理论都更有用；它们能够提供一个既不忽视、也不歪曲事实的答案，而这正是科学工作所力求达到的境地。我承认，在性虐狂和受虐狂身上，我们总能看到（向外或向内的）破坏本能与性欲牢牢地结合在一起；但是我再也无法理解我们怎能忽视非性欲攻击性和破坏性的普遍存在，并且怎能在对生活的解释中不给它以合适的地位呢（破坏的欲望转向内部时，我们多半感受不到；当然，除非它带着性欲的色彩）。我记得破坏本能的思想在精神分析的著述中刚出现时，最初我自己也抗拒，并且很长时间之后才接受了这一思想。所以，当其他人抵制这一思想，并且现在仍然抵制时，我并不感到吃惊。当人们谈论到人类天生具有“邪恶”、攻击性和破坏性以及残酷性时，“儿童是不喜欢这种谈论的”。上帝根据他自己的完美形象创造了人类；谁都知道邪恶（尽管基督教科学派一贯否认，邪恶还是不可避免地存在着）与上帝的全能和至善是多么地难以调和。这时，魔鬼即成为上帝最好的借口，就像犹太人在雅利安人的理想世界中所发挥的辩解作用一样。尽管如此，人们仍可以认为上帝应对魔鬼的存在以及魔鬼所代表的邪恶负责。鉴于这些困难，我建议每个人在适当的时候都应该向人类的道德深层本性深鞠一躬，这会帮助我们受到普遍欢迎，并使我们免除许多烦恼。[13]

“力比多”一词可以再次被用来表示厄洛斯能量的具体表现，这样做为的是把它们和死亡本能的能量加以区别。[14]必须承认，死亡本能更加难以掌握，某种程度上只能被辨认为厄洛斯留下的残余，只有与厄洛斯相融合才会显现，否则难以让人捕捉。在性虐狂中，死亡本能在充分满足性欲的同时，为了自己的目的扭曲了性欲的目的。正是从性虐狂问题上，我们获得了死亡本能及其与厄洛斯的关系最为清楚的认识。然而，即便死亡本能出现时没有任何目的性，在其极其麻木狂热的破坏中，这种本能的满足是伴随着高度的自恋享受的，因为这一本能的满足展示了自我无所不能的愿望如何得以实现。当破坏本能受到节制、驯服时，就像目标抑制转向对象时一样，它会帮助自我满足其生存需要、去控制自然。由于对这一本能存在的假设主要建立在理论基础上，所以我们应当承认它不是反对对立理论的充分证据。但在我们目前的知识结构下，事情在我们看来就是如此，将来的研究和思考无疑会决定性地澄清这一问题。

在接下来的论述中，我的观点是，攻击性倾向是人的一种原始的、自发的气质，这又回到了之前的论点上，即这一倾向构成了文明的最大障碍。之前的研究中我们也认识到文明是人类所经历的一个特殊过程，我们现在仍然受着这一思想的影响。现在需再补充一点，那就是文明是为厄洛斯服务的一个过程，它的目的是把个人，然后是家庭，最后是种族、民族和国家结合在一个大的统一体中，即人类社会。为什么必须如此，我们无从得知：纯粹是厄洛斯在发挥作用。这众多的人类必须通过力比多互相联结起来；单靠必要性即一起劳动的优势是无法把他们聚拢在一起的。然而，文明的进程遭到了人类的自然攻击性本能的对抗，这种攻击性体现为个体对群体的敌意和群体对个体的不友善。这种攻击性本能是死亡本能衍生的主要代表。我们是在死亡本能与厄洛斯同时出现时发现的，它与厄洛斯一起统治着这个世界。现在，我想文明进程的含义对我们不再是什么晦涩的东西了。文明的进程一定体现出爱神和死神、生存本能和破坏本能的较量，正如在人类身上所体现的一样。这一斗争是所有生命最基本的内容，因此文明的进程可以简单地描述成人类为了生存的斗争。[15]这场巨人间的争斗，正是我们的保姆用天国的摇篮曲所试图缓和的争斗。

Ⅶ

为什么我们的动物亲戚们没有表现出这样的文化斗争呢？我们无从得知。但很可能有一些动物，比如说蜜蜂、蚂蚁和白蚁，它们斗争了几千年，然后形成了其国家制度、分工和对个体的约束机制，让我们羡慕不已。我们现状的特点是，我们认为，在上述任何一个动物的王国里或者扮演其中任何一种所分配的角色，我们都不会感觉幸福。至于其他动物，环境影响和它们内心冲突的本能之间很可能已达到暂时的平衡，因而发展也就停了下来。在原始人中，新一轮力比多的爆发也许会触发抵抗破坏性本能的新活动。这里尚有许多问题需要追问，许多问题尚未得到回答。

另一问题与我们的关系更为密切。这一问题是文明用什么方法来抑制与自己对抗的攻击性，使其失去危害，并且可能的话消除它呢？我们已经认识到了其中几种方法，但尚未发现最重要的方法。对此我们可以在个人发展的例子上加以研究。个人身上究竟发生了什么事，让他把攻击性变得无害呢？一定发生了什么奇怪的事情，这一点显而易见，我们不会怀疑。他的攻击性转而向内投射、被内化，实际上也就是被遣回到其发源地—换言之，指向他的自我。在那里它被一部分自我所接管，这部分自我成为超我，与自我的其他部分相对立，并且以“良知”的形式，对本想指向其他个体的自我施加同等严厉的攻击性，来管束自我。严厉的超我和受制于它的自我之间的紧张关系被我们叫作“内疚感”，表现为一种对惩罚的需要。这样，就像在一座已被占领的城市中派兵驻防一样，文明通过削弱个体、剥夺他的武器、建立了一个内在的权威来监视他，从而克服了个人危险的攻击性。

关于内疚感的起源，精神分析家和其他心理学家持不同看法；但即使是分析家也发现要解释这一问题并不容易。首先，如果我们问一个人怎么会有了内疚感时，会得到一个不容怀疑的答案：当一个人做了某种他知道是“坏的”事情时，他就会感到内疚（虔诚的人们会说是“有罪的”事情）。但是我们看到这一答案并未讲出任何实质性内容。稍稍犹豫后，我们会补充说，即使一个人没有真正去做坏事，而只是意识到自己有干坏事的意图，他也可能会感到内疚；于是有人会提出这样的问题：为什么会把做坏事的意图和做坏事的行为等同起来呢？然而，两种情况都存在着一个前提条件，即我们认为邪恶是应遭到谴责的，是不应付诸实施的。这一判断我们又是如何作出的呢？我们或许会否定存在着一种原始、天生的辨别是非的能力。邪恶对于自我来说，常常并不是什么有害或危险的东西，恰恰相反，可能是自我所欢迎和享受的东西。因此，这里有一个外部的影响在起作用，恰恰是这一影响决定了什么是好事，什么是坏事。由于一个人自身的情感并不会把他引向这条途径，所以他必须有一个服从这一外部影响的动机。在一个人孤立无援的情况下和对别人的依靠中，我们可以轻易地发现这一动机，并恰当地把这一动机称为对丧失爱的惧怕。如果他失去了他所依靠的人的爱，他就失去了保护，面临着种种危险。首先，他会面临被惩罚的危险，较强大的人会用惩罚的形式来显示其优势。所以在最初，邪恶会让人面临丧失爱的危险，人因此必须避免邪恶的行为和念头。因此一个人是否已经干了坏事或者仅仅有这样的打算两者没有多大差别。无论哪一种情况，只要被监视的权威发现，丧失爱的危险就会降临，并且任何一种情况下，权威的做法都是一样。

这种精神状态叫作“问心有愧”，但实际上它名不副实，因为在这个阶段，内疚感显然仅仅是一种对失去爱的恐惧，一种“社会性的”焦虑。在小孩子中间，内疚感仅是如此，绝不会是任何其他东西；但对许多成年人而言，唯一的改变是，曾经是父亲或者父母亲所占据的位置现在被一个更大的人类社会所取代。因此，只要确信权威不会知晓他们所干的坏事，或不会因此责怪他们，他们就常常允许自己去干种种可能给予他们乐趣的坏事；他们所害怕的只是被发现。这是今天的社会需要应付的普遍状况。

在这一权威实现内化，建立起超我之前，事情并没有太大变化。建立超我后，良知的现象才达到了一个新的高度，只有这时候，人们才可以正确地讨论良知和内疚感。[16]这时，担心被发现的问题不复存在了，而且做坏事和做坏事的念头之间的区别也全然消失了，因为一切东西、即便是人自己的想法都瞒不过超我。自然，事情的现实危险已经过去，因为据我们所知的一切，超我这一新的权威没有理由去虐待自我，因为它与自我密切相连；但形成超我的方式依然在起作用，使得已被克服的过去的东西继续存续下来，以致事情实质上与一开始没有差别。超我以同样的焦虑折磨着邪恶的自我，并伺机寻找机会让自我接受外部世界的惩罚。

在良知发展的第二个阶段，它呈现出一种特性，这种特性在第一阶段是没有的，并且不再那么容易解释。一个人越是道德高尚，其良知对自我就越严厉、越不信任，所以最终恰恰是这些最圣洁的人指责自己罪恶最为深重。这意味着美德剥夺了其一部分应得的奖赏；顺从和节制的自我并没有获得它的指导者的信任，似乎只是徒劳地去努力获取超我的信任。我相信很快就会有人提出异议，说这些困难是人为的，并且有人会说一个更加严格的、警惕性更高的良知正是道德本性的特征。此外，道德高尚的人称他们自己为罪人时，并不是没有道理，鉴于那些满足本能的诱惑，尤其是他们所受到的那些强烈诱惑—众所周知，诱惑只是在频频受挫后才会增强，而对它们偶尔满足却会使它们至少是暂时地被削弱。在疑问丛生的道德学领域还有一个事实是：恶运—换言之，外部挫折—大大增强了超我的良知力量。当一个人一切都顺利时，他的良知是宽容的，并且放任自我做各种事情；但是当恶运降临到他头上时，他就检查自己的灵魂，承认自己的罪过，提高良知的要求，强制自己禁欲并且用苦行来惩罚自己。[17]整个人类都这样做过，而且还在这样做。然而，这一点很容易用原始的、婴幼儿期的良知来解释。正如我们看到的，在良知进入超我阶段后，这一早期的良知并没有被放弃，而是始终站在超我的身旁和身后。命运被认为是父母权威的替代者。如果一个人不走运，那就意味着他不再为这一至高无上的力量所青睐；并且由于受到这种失去爱的威胁，他就会再一次服从于超我这一虚拟的父母权威—而在他走运时，则乐于忽略这一权威。如果人们持一种严格宗教意义上的观点，把命运仅仅视为神的意志的体现的话，上述情况就更显而易见了。以色列人曾经相信他们是上帝的宠儿，当伟大的天父将一个接一个的不幸降临到他们头上时，他们从来没有怀疑过他们与上帝的关系，或者质疑过其权力和公正。相反，他们产生出先知，让先知斥责他们所犯的罪行，并从内疚中创造出具有极其严格训诫的犹太教体系。奇怪的是，原始人的表现则完全不同。如果他遇到了不幸，他不是责备自己，而是责备他的崇拜对象，责备它显然没有尽到责任，并且他不会自罚而是鞭打他的崇拜对象。

因而，我们了解到了内疚感的两个来源：一个源自对于某个权威的恐惧，另一个源自对后来出现的超我的恐惧。对权威的恐惧迫使我们抑制本能的满足；对超我的恐惧在此基础上，还坚持惩罚我们自己，因为被禁止的欲望的存在是瞒不过超我的。我们也了解到该如何去理解超我的严厉性，即良知的要求。严厉的超我纯粹地保持了外部权威的严厉，它接替并部分地取代了外部权威。现在我们可以看到，对本能的克制是如何与内疚感联系起来的。最初，对本能的克制是由于惧怕外部权威；一个人为了不丧失爱便放弃了某些本能的满足。如果一个人实现了这样的克制，他就可以说是服从于外部权威了，并且也不再有内疚感了。但是对于超我的恐惧，情形就不同了。在这里，对本能的克制是不够的，因为本能的欲念依然存在并且不能瞒过超我。因此，尽管克制了欲望，内疚感还会发生，这就在超我的建立过程中，或者说是良知的形成中，造成了一个很费事的条件。对本能的克制再也不会让人感到完全轻松自由；虔诚的节欲也不再保证会得到爱的奖赏。外部不幸的威胁—爱的丧失和外部权威的惩罚—已经转换成了内心永久的不幸，转换成了内疚感所产生的焦虑。

这些相互关系极其复杂但又极其重要，因此，我不怕重复，将从另一个角度再来探讨这一问题。这些关系发生的先后顺序如下所述：首先，由于恐惧外部权威的攻击而产生了对本能的克制（这当然就是对失去爱的恐惧造成的结果，因为爱可以使人们免除这种惩罚性的攻击）。然后是内部权威的建立，由于对它的恐惧，即对良知的恐惧，产生了对本能的抑制。在第二种情况下，做坏事的企图和做坏事的行为是相当的，因此就有了内疚感和对惩罚的需要。良知的攻击性接替了外部权威的攻击性。到目前为止，事情无疑已经弄清楚了；但是不幸（从外部迫使本能的抑制，从而进一步增强良知）施加的影响又有什么样的地位呢？以及在最善良、最易于管教的人们身上，良知那惊人的严厉性又发挥着怎样的作用？我们对良心的这两种特性已作过解释，但是我们大概仍然觉得这些解释并未触及问题的实质，仍然还有一些问题尚未得到解释。最后，这里出现了一种观念，它完全属于精神分析领域，与人们的一般思维方式不同。这种观念可以使我们明白为什么我们研究的对象好像总是混乱和模糊不清的。它告诉我们首先是良知（说得更准确些，是恐惧—后来变成了良知）促使我们对本能进行克制，但是后来这种因果关系就颠倒了。每一种对本能的抑制现在都成为良知的一个动态源泉，并且每一种新的抑制都增强了后者的严厉和苛刻。如果我们能把这一说法与已知的关于良知的起因较好地统一起来，我们就不由得要赞成以下似非而是的论述，即良知是克制本能的结果，或者说这种（从外部强加我们的）对本能的抑制产生了良知，然后良知又要求进一步抑制本能。

这一论述和以前关于良心起因的说法之间的矛盾实际上并不太大，而且之后我们会发现有办法让矛盾变得更少。为了便于阐述，我们把攻击本能作为例子，并且假设这里所谈的抑制总是指对攻击性的抑制（这当然只是暂时的假想）。于是，抑制本能对良知所产生的作用便是：我们抑制的攻击性都被超我接管，超我进而加强了（对自我）的攻击性。这一观点与良知最初的攻击性是外部权威的严厉性的延续因而与抑制无关的观点存在分歧。但是，如果我们为超我攻击性的最初部分假设一个不同的来源，这种分歧就不复存在了。比如，不管外部权威剥夺的是儿童哪一种本能的满足，它都使儿童不能满足其最初的、但也是最重要的各种本能，所以在儿童身上一定会对外部权威形成相当程度的攻击性。但是，他必须抑制这种报复性的攻击本能的满足，于是，借助大家所熟悉的种种机制，他找到了摆脱这一困境的途径。通过身份认同，他把这个无法攻击的权威融进自身。权威现已变成了他的超我，并接管了作为孩子原本要反抗的所有攻击性。儿童的自我必须满足于扮演倒霉的权威即父亲的角色，这样一来，父亲的地位就降低了。在这里，事情的真实情形常常是颠倒的：“如果我是父亲，你是孩子，我将会对你更坏。”超我和自我之间的关系是尚未分化的自我和外在对象间真实关系的回归，只不过这种关系因为主体的欲望而遭到扭曲。这种情况具有典型性。但是根本区别则是超我最初的严厉性不代表或者说不完全代表一个人从父亲那里所体验到的或者归之于父亲的严厉性；它毋宁说是代表一个人自身对外部对象的攻击性。如果这个说法是正确的，我们就可以接前文观点断言，良知一开始是通过对攻击性冲动的压抑产生的，后来由于进一步的类似压抑而得到加强。

这两种观点哪一种是对的呢？先提出的那种观点从种系进化模式的角度看似乎是无懈可击的；而新提出的这种观点则以上述令人满意的方式使这一理论得到圆满的阐述。很显然，二者都说得通，直接观察的事实也证明了这一点。它们相互并不矛盾，甚至在某一点上它们是一致的，因为儿童的报复攻击性一部分是由他所预料的父亲的惩罚攻击性程度所决定的。然而经验表明，儿童所形成的超我的严厉性和他所受到的待遇的严厉性绝不是对应的。前者的严厉性似乎独立于后者的严厉性。一个在宽容的环境中长大的孩子可能会有非常严厉的良知。但是，夸大这种独立性也是错误的；我们不难相信，严厉的教养也会对孩子超我的形成产生巨大影响。这就等于说，在超我的形成和良知的出现过程中，天生的气质因素和来自现实环境的影响是一起发挥作用的。这根本谈不上令人吃惊；相反，它是所有这些过程的一个普遍的病原性条件。[18]

可以断言，当一个孩子用极其强烈的攻击性和相应严厉的超我来对他最初的本能挫折作出反应时，这还是符合种系进化模式的，超出了今天能被理解的行为，这个原始社会的父亲无疑极其残忍暴戾。因此，如果我们从个体的发展转移到种系的进化，关于良知起源的两种理论间的差异就进一步缩小了。另一方面，我们就会注意到在这两个发展过程中存在一个重要的新的差异。我们无法摆脱这样一个设想，即人类的内疚感是从俄狄浦斯情结中萌生的，这种情况在兄弟联合起来杀死父亲的时候就存在了，在这种情况下，攻击性的行为不是被压抑而是被付诸实施—而对父亲的这种攻击性行为进行压抑，也被认为是儿童内疚感的原因。这时候，气愤填膺的读者如果作出如下抗议，我绝不会感到惊奇。“那么一个人是否杀死自己的父亲就无关紧要了—他在两种情况下都会产生内疚感。我们在这儿可以提出几点疑问，或者内疚感并非产生于对攻击性的压抑；或者杀父的故事是杜撰的，原始人的孩子与今天的孩子一样，并不经常杀父。此外，如果这个故事不是杜撰的，而是一段可信的历史，那么人们也会认为发生这样的事情是可能的—一个人感到内疚是因为他确实干了不该干的事情。而这样的例子，每天都有发生，精神分析却没作任何解释。”

读者的批评颇有道理，我们应弥补这一遗漏。这个问题并没有什么神秘之处。当一个人因做错一件事而内疚，这种情感应该称作悔恨更为合适。它只是与已经做过的行为有关，尽管它的前提良知—感到内疚的准备状态—在这一行为发生之前就已经存在了。因此，这种悔恨永远不会帮助我们发现良知和一般的内疚感的起源。日常情形通常是：本能的需要占了上风，战胜了相对无力的良知，获得了满足；一旦得到满足后，本能需要就自然减弱，于是又恢复了之前与良知相对平衡的状态。因而，在现在的探讨中，精神分析法有理由把由悔恨产生内疚感的情况排除在外，不管这种情况出现得多么频繁，也不管它们实际上的重要性有多大。

但是，如果把人类的内疚感追溯到杀死原始社会的父亲，那也只不过是“悔恨”的一个例子。因此，我们是否该假设良知和内疚感在杀父之前尚不存在呢？那么在这种情况下，悔恨是从哪里产生的呢？毫无疑问，这个例子将会为我们拨开内疚感的迷雾，并且结束我们目前的尴尬局面。我相信这是能够做到的。这种悔恨是人对于父亲原生的矛盾情感的结果。他的儿子们恨他，但也爱他。在儿子们通过攻击行为满足了他们的憎恨之后，他们的爱就会在对这种行为的悔恨中体现出来。通过模仿父亲的自居作用，这种爱建立起超我，并赋予它父亲的权力，就好像是要惩罚他们对父亲的攻击性行为，它制定了旨在避免重现这种行为的种种限制。由于反对父亲的攻击性倾向在以后的世世代代中会反复出现，内疚感也就一直存在，每一次攻击性被压抑后，转到超我上，内疚感就会进而增强。现在，我想你们对于两件事可以说是完全清楚了：在良知的起源中，爱所发挥的作用，以及内疚感产生的不可避免性。一个人不论是否杀死了自己的父亲并不真正具有决定性的作用。不管在哪种情况下，一个人都必定会感到内疚，因为内疚感是矛盾心理斗争的表现。是爱神厄洛斯和破坏或死亡本能间的无止境斗争的表现。当人们面临共同生活的任务时，这一冲突就被煽动起来。只要家庭还是集体生活的唯一形式，这一冲突注定表现为俄狄浦斯情结，从而建立起良知并且产生最初的内疚感。当文明试图从家庭集体延伸到社会集体时，过去所决定的冲突形式，延续了下去，并且被强化，导致了内疚感的进一步加剧。由于文明所遵从的是内在性欲冲动，这种冲动要求把人类组成为一个密切联结的群体，所以它只能通过内疚感的不断增强而达到其目的。起初与父亲有关的事情，在与群体的关系中得以实现。如果说文明是从家庭向整个人类社会发展的必要过程，那么，由于来自矛盾心理的先天的冲突，以及爱和死亡意愿之间无休止的斗争，文明将必然与日益增长的内疚感难分难解地联系在一起，而且这种内疚感也许会达到一个令人难以忍受的程度。人们不禁会想到伟大诗人对“天神们”尖锐的指控：

“你们把我们带到人世间，你让可怜的人儿感到内疚，然后让他遭受惩罚，因为在世间一切罪过终遭报应。”

当我们认识到只有少数人才能毫不费力地从他们自己混乱的感情中产生最深刻的认识，而其余的人必须历经痛苦、不确定的摸索，才能最终找到通往真理的道路，我们或许可以舒一口气。

Ⅷ

本书写到接近尾声时，作者必须请求读者原谅，原谅作者不是一个老练的向导，因此让读者走了一些乏味、单调的岔路和绕道。毫无疑问，作者本可以做得更好一些。在此，我设法作些改善，虽然似乎有点晚了。

首先，我猜想读者会认为我们对内疚感的讨论破坏了本书的框架：这些讨论占据了太多篇幅，而其他与这些关系不是很密切的论题就被挤到了一边。这可能扰乱了本项研究的结构；但它与本项研究的意图却是一致的，即呈现出内疚感是文明发展所面临的最重要的问题，并且表明我们为了文明所付出的失去幸福的代价正是由于内疚感的加强而造成的。[19]

这一命题，即我们研究的最终结论，似乎仍然有些奇怪，其原因大概可追溯到内疚感和我们的意识这一奇特的关系上，这种关系我们仍然不太理解。在我们视为正常的悔恨的一般情况下，内疚感可以很清晰地为意识所觉察到。实际上，我们习惯于说“内疚意识”，而不是说“内疚感”。对精神病的研究为我们提供了认识正常状况的最有价值的线索，但它也使我们遇到了一些矛盾。精神病中有一种名为强迫观念性精神病，表现为病人的内疚感强加于意识；支配着该病的临床症状以及病人的生活，几乎不容其他任何东西出现在它旁边。但是在精神病的大多数情况中，内疚感则完全是无意识的，然而却并没有因此而减少其重要影响。当我们告诉病人他们有“无意识内疚感”时，他们不相信。为了让他们或多或少理解我们的说法，我们给他们说起对惩罚的无意识需要，内疚感就是通过这种需要表现的。但是内疚感与某种形式的精神病的关联不应被过分强调，因为即使在强迫观念性精神病中，某些类型的病人如果被阻止作出某些行为，他们也意识不到自己的内疚感，或只能把它感受为一种令人痛苦的不安，或是一种焦虑而已。终有一天，这些情况我们会弄清楚，但目前还不行。在这里，指出下述这一点或许有益：从根本上讲，内疚感只不过是焦虑的一种局部形式；在其后来发展阶段，它完全与对超我的恐惧融合在一起。同样，焦虑相对于意识，我们也发现了同样特别的变化形式。焦虑总是以某种形式掩藏在所有症状的后面，尽管有时候会控制着整个意识，而在别的时候，它则完全把自己隐藏起来—因为焦虑首先只是一种感觉，如果我们想要保持心理上的问心无愧—我们不得不谈论无意识焦虑，或者存在焦虑的可能性。因此，完全可以设想，文明所产生的内疚感本身也未被觉察到，它在很大程度上仍是无意识的，或者只是表现为一种不适，一种不满足感，人们因此转而寻找其他动机。至少宗教从来没有忽略过内疚感在文明中所发挥的作用，此外还有一点—这我之前并没有意识到—它们声称要把人类从这种内疚感（他们称之为原罪）中救赎出来。在基督教中，耶稣一个人的牺牲，承担起所有人的原罪，其他人因此得到救赎。从这种救赎方式我们可以推断原始内疚产生的时机，这一时机也标志着文明的开端。

以下对几个术语的解释尽管不是特别重要，但也未必完全多余，如“超我”“良知”“内疚感”“对惩罚的需要”和“悔恨”，因为这些词我们也许常常用得不太准确并且经常混淆。它们都适用于同一关系，只是指代这一关系的不同方面。超我是我们假定的一个权威，良知是我们归于这个权威的一个功能—这一功能包括监管和评价自我的行为和意图，执行一种审查制度。内疚感即超我的严厉性，因此与良知的严厉性是等同的。它是自我对于这样被监视的一种感觉，是对自我的抗争与超我的要求之间的紧张状况的评估。对超我这一挑剔的权威的恐惧—存在于整个超我自我关系之下的恐惧，相当于对惩罚的需要—是自我这一方面的本能表现，自我在残酷的超我的影响下形成受虐倾向。它将其内在固有的破坏性本能的一部分用于与超我建立起爱的纽带。直到可以证明超我的存在时，我们才应当谈论到良知。至于说内疚感，我们必须说它是先于超我而存在的，因此也就先于良知而存在。在早期阶段，它是恐惧外部权威的直接表现，是对自我和外部权威之间的紧张状态的承认。它是对外部爱的需要和本能满足的欲望—对这种欲望的抑制产生了攻击性—之间冲突的直接产物。内疚感的这两个层次—一个来自对外部权威的恐惧，一个来自对内部权威的恐惧—的重叠在若干方面妨碍了我们对良知的认识。悔恨是在涉及内疚感的情形下自我的反应的一个总称。它包含了内疚感背后发挥作用的焦虑的原始感觉的材料形式；它本身是一种惩罚，而且可能包括对惩罚的需要。所以，悔恨也可能比良知产生得更早。

在此再回顾一下探讨过程中令我们一时困惑不解的矛盾同样有益无害。我们一度称内疚感是因未被实施攻击性行为而产生的，而另一时候又称内疚感是因为实施了攻击行为的结果—发生在历史之初的杀父行为之后的结果。我们设法找到解决这一矛盾的方法。因为内部权威超我的建立，这一情况发生了根本变化。在这之前，内疚感等同于悔恨，而“悔恨”这一名称应当用来指真正实施了攻击性行为之后产生的反应。在这之后，由于超我的无所不知，攻击企图和攻击行为之间的区别失去了意义。从此以后，内疚感不仅可以因为暴力行为的实施而产生（这一点众所周知），而且可以仅仅因为存在暴力行为的意图而产生（正如精神分析所发现的）。尽管有这一新的心理情况出现，但两种主要原始本能之间矛盾心理的冲突，仍然会产生同样的效果。显然在这里我们极其想通过内疚感与意识之间的不同关系去解决这里所提出的问题。我们可能会认为对于某种邪恶行为的悔恨而产生的内疚感应当总是有意识的，而对某种邪恶冲动的感觉的内疚感却可能是无意识的。但事实并不那么简单：强迫观念性精神病强有力地反驳了这一观点。第二个矛盾关系到超我的攻击能量。一种观点认为这种攻击能量仅仅是外部权威的惩罚能量的延续，并使这种能量保存于心灵中；而另一种观点认为，它是由用来反对施加抑制的外部权威的、自身尚未使用的攻击能量所组成的。第一种观点似乎更适用于内疚感的历史，第二种观点则更适用于内疚感的理论。进一步的思考则可以圆满解决这一表面看来似乎不可调和的矛盾；两种观点共同的必要因素都涉及内化了的攻击性。再者，临床的观察实际上允许我们把归于超我的攻击性来源区分为两个；在特定情况下，其中一个发挥较强的作用，但通常他们都是共同发挥作用。

我认为，此处郑重地提出以下观点是个合适的时机，而早些时候我曾建议暂时接受这一观点。即任何一种挫折—本能满足的受阻—都会或可能导致内疚感的增强。最新的分析学著作均表现出对这种观点的偏好。如果我们认为这一观点仅适用于攻击性本能，那么我认为我们的理论就能大为简化，并且我们也很难找到与这一假想相矛盾的东西。那么我们该如何灵活、经济地解释当性爱要求未被满足时，内疚感增强这一现象呢？只要采用迂回的方法，还是可以解释的—假如我们设想性爱满足的受阻会引起对干涉这一满足的那个人的某种攻击性，并且这种攻击性本身接着不得不受到抑制。但如果是这样的话，那么由于被压抑并且转交给超我而转变成内疚感的，归根到底只是攻击性。我相信，如果精神分析关于内疚感的起源方面的发现仅限于攻击性本能的话，那么我们对许多过程就可以作出更为简单和清晰的解释。对临床材料的考察在这里没有给予我们任何明确的答复：因为正如我们的假设所讲，这两种本能几乎从来不以纯粹的、相互分离的形式出现。但是对极端病例的研究也许会指向我所期望的方向。通过将这一局限性的观点应用于压抑过程，从而从中推论出它的基本优点，还是很具诱惑力的。正如我们所知，精神病的症状从其本质上看是对于未实现的性愿望的替代性满足。在我们的精神分析工作过程中，我们惊奇地发现，可能每一种精神病都隐蔽着一定量的无意识的内疚感，它反过来又利用精神病症状，作为一种惩罚，从而增强了这些症状。现在明确地阐述出下列主张似乎不无道理，即当一种本能受到压抑时，它的力比多因素就会转化为症状，它的攻击性因素就会转化为内疚感。即使这一论点只是接近于事实，但它还是值得我们去关注。

此外，本书的某些读者可能会有这样的感觉，就是关于厄洛斯和死亡本能之间的斗争规则讲得过多了些。这一规则旨在表示人类所经历的文明历程以及个体所经历的发展历程的特点。此外，据说它还揭示了一般有机生命体的秘密。如此一来，探究三种过程的相互关系似乎就很有必要。如果我们考虑到人类文明的进程和个人的发展过程都是重要的历程，因此一定带有最普遍意义上的生命本质，那么我们就有充分理由反复讨论上述斗争规则了。另一方面，斗争规则的普遍特性意味着仅仅证明其存在，对于区分这些过程毫无帮助，除非通过特定的条件来限制缩小它的范围。因此，我们只能满足于这样的断言，即文明的历程是生命历程的一种特殊修正形式，而生命历程是生命在面临由厄洛斯所确定、阿南刻（现实的迫切性）所设定的任务下经历的过程，这个任务就是通过力比多纽带将离散的个体凝聚到集体之中。然而，当我们集中关注人类文明与个体发展或成长过程之间的关系时，我们可以毫不迟疑地作出如下结论，即二者在本质上即便不是同一过程，也是极其相似的，因为二者涉及两个不同的对象。当然，人类文明与个体发展相比，属于较高等级的抽象，因此也就比较难以用具体的术语来描述，我们也不要过分追求二者之间的类比；但是考虑到这两个过程的目的的相似性—一个是创造一个由许多个体组成的群体，另一个是把个体融合到这样的群体中—我们对于二者使用的方法和导致的结果都如此相似，也就不会感到吃惊了。但是，这两个过程之间有一个特别重要的区别，在此不得不提。在个人的发展过程中，旨在获得幸福的快乐原则仍是至高无上的。个体适应或融入集体，则似乎是达到幸福目的的一个几乎不可回避的前提条件。如果这一目的能够脱离那个条件而实现，也许会更好一些。换句话说，个人的发展过程似乎是两种趋势相互影响的结果：一种是对幸福的追求，我们通常称之为“利己的”，另一种是对集体中的伙伴关系的追求，我们称之为“利他的”。这两个术语都没有深入到问题的本质。如同我们所说的，在个人发展的过程中，重点在于利己的对幸福的追求；而另一种追求可以说带有“文化的”性质，则通常只满足于发挥限制的作用。在文明的发展过程中，情形就不同了。在这里，首要目标是让人类个体形成一个统一体。诚然，幸福的目的依然存在，但被推到了一个次要的位置上。甚至如果不必关注个人幸福的话，一个巨大的人类社会集体的创造将会变得极其成功。因而，个人的发展过程可能具有其独特的方面，这些方面为人类文明的发展所不容。只有当个人的发展把与集体的融合作为它的目的时，它才与人类文明的发展存在一致性。

正像行星在围绕恒星公转的同时，也围绕自己的轴自转一样，个体在参加人类发展过程的同时，也在走着自己的生活道路。但隐约看来，天体中各种力量的相互作用似乎凝固成一种永恒不变的秩序；而在有机生命领域里，我们却能看到各种力量是如何互相竞争、冲突，如何产生千变万化的结果的。同样地，个人幸福与人类同伴关系这两种追求在每个人身上不得不相互斗争；因此个人发展和文化发展这两个过程也必定相互抵触，彼此争夺地盘。但是，个人和社会间的斗争并不是厄洛斯与死亡这两个主要本能间也许是不可调和的矛盾的衍生物。它是力比多的充分利用问题上的争执，可以比之为自我与对象在力比多分配上的争夺。不论目前的文明如何压抑着个人生活，我们希望未来的文明中，这种自我与对象在力比多分配上的矛盾能够最终在个体身上得到调和。

文明的发展和个人的发展之间的类比可以作出进一步的有意义的延伸。我们完全有理由宣称，人类集体同样逐渐形成了超我，在这个超我的影响下，文明的发展得以产生。任何一个熟知不同文明的人一定忍不住去详细探索这一意义上的类比。我在此仅提出几个突出的观点。一个时代文明的超我与个人的超我有着类似的起源。它建立在伟大领袖人物的人格所留下的影响基础之上—这些领袖天生具有强大的精神和智慧，或者说在他们身上表现出某种最强烈、最纯粹、往往也是最片面的人类追求的形式。在许多实例中，这一类比甚至进一步延伸下去：这些领袖人物，在其有生之年，经常（即便不总是）受到别人的嘲弄和虐待，甚至被残忍地处死—实际上，原始社会的那个父亲的命运就是如此：他直到被暴力处死之后很久才获得了尊敬。领袖人物的这种注定的命运，在基督耶稣身上体现得最为淋漓尽致—如果他不是一个虚构的人物，不是从原始事件的模糊记忆中创造出来的话。文化超我和个人超我的另一个相同点就是两者都建立起了严厉的理想要求；未达到这些要求将会遭到“良知的恐惧”的惩罚。于是，这里我们遇到了一个奇怪的现象，即我们在群体中所看到的相关精神过程比起在个体中看到的更为我们所熟悉，更加容易被意识到。在个人身上，超我的攻击性，只在紧张状态出现时，以谴责的形式清晰地呈现出来；而真正的要求本身却仍然保持在无意识的背景中。这些要求，如果带到意识中，我们就会发现它们与现行文化的超我的戒律是一致的。至此，群体的文化发展和个体的个人发展这两个过程呈现出规则的一致性。这样一来，超我的一些表现和特征在文化集体的行为中要比在个人行为中更容易被发现。

文化超我在形成它的理想后，就会树立起各种要求。在这些要求中，处理人们之间相互关系的则集体被冠以伦理学之名。人们总是赋予伦理学很高的价值，似乎希望伦理学发挥极其重要的作用。事实上，伦理学关注的是文明中最令人痛苦的处境。因而伦理学也被看作一种治疗的尝试—通过超我的训诫，取得迄今为止其他文化活动都无法取得的成效。正如我们所知，摆在我们面前的问题是，如何摆脱文明的最大障碍—人类具有互相攻击的气质上的倾向；正因为这个缘故，我们才尤其关心可能是文化超我的最新要求，即“爱邻居犹如爱自己”的训诫。对精神病的研究和治疗引起我们对个人超我提出两种非议：在它严厉的戒律和禁令中，它很少考虑自我的幸福，因为它首先没有充分地估计本我在反对服从这些要求和戒律方面的本能的力量；其次，没有充分地估计现实的外部环境所造成的困难。因此，为了达到治疗的目的，我们常常必须反对病人的超我，并且试图降低它的要求。同样地，我们也可以反对文化超我的伦理要求。它也没有充分地考虑到人类的精神构造的实际情况。它发布了命令，却不询问人们是否能够服从它。相反，它设想一个人的自我从心理角度上能够完成任何被要求做到的事情，自我能绝对控制住本我。这种设想是错误的。即使在正常人身上，他的本我也只能在一定范围内得到控制。如果对一个人要求过多，在他身上就会产生一种反抗心理，或者引起精神病，或者使他不愉快。“爱邻居犹如爱自己”这一训诫是对人类攻击性最强有力的防备，并且是文化超我以非心理学方式行事的一个出色例子。这一训诫是不可能实现的；如此夸张的爱只能降低爱的价值，而不能摆脱人类相互攻击的困境。文明对此置若罔闻；它只是提醒着我们，一个训诫越是难以遵从，它就越值得去遵从。然而在今天的文明中，遵循这个训诫的人与漠视这个训诫的人相比，只能使自己处于不利的地位。如果对攻击性的防备可能引起像攻击性本身所引起的那么多的不愉快，那么攻击性对文明来说是怎样一个强大的障碍啊！这种情形下，我们所谓的“自然”伦理学，除了让人们获得一种认为自己比别人强的自恋的满足之外，一无是处。正是这时候，基于宗教的伦理学登场了，向人们承诺一个更美好的来世。我个人认为，只要美德在现世得不到酬报，伦理学的说教将是徒劳的。同时，真正改变人们与财产的关系，肯定要比任何伦理学要求更为有效；但是社会主义者对这一事实的认识，又因为对人类本性的一种理想主义的新的误读，而变得模糊不清、不切实际。

在我看来，试图在文化发展的现象中探索超我作用这种方法，还会有进一步的发现。我必须加紧结束本书的探索，可是还有一个问题是我几乎不能回避的。如果说文明的发展与个人的发展以同样的方式进行，且进程如此相似，那么难道我们没有理由作出如下的诊断吗—在文化要求的影响之下，某些文明或者文明的某些阶段，可能整个人类文明，都变成了“精神病”？对于这些精神病的分析性的解剖很可能带来治疗性的建议，这些建议将会具有重大意义。我不认为把精神分析转用于文化集体这种尝试是荒谬的，或者断定它是徒劳的。但是，我们应当非常谨慎，并且不要忘记我们只是进行类比而已，无论是概念的类比还是与人类的类比，把它们从其所产生和演化的出发点强行拽出来都是危险的。再者，对集体的精神病诊断面临着一个特殊困难：在个人精神病例中，我们首先只需要把病人与假定的正常环境相比照，就能得到一点线索。而对于一个集体来说，因所有成员都患有同样的精神症状，因此不存在像个人精神病的可比照的背景环境，而必须从别处去寻找这样的背景。至于说把所获得的知识运用于治疗，由于谁也没有权力将这样一种治疗强加于集体，所以对社会精神病的最贴切的分析又有什么用呢？尽管存在这一切困难，我们仍然相信有一天会有人敢于对文化集体作出病理探究。

出于种种原因，我根本无意对人类文明作出任何评价。我一直小心避免受到如下狂热偏见的影响，即认为我们的文明是我们所拥有的或者可能获得的最宝贵的事物，并且认为文明之路将把我们带领到我们迄今难以想象到的完美高度。我至少可以心平气和地倾听批评家的这样一种观点，他认为，考虑到文明努力的目标及其使用的方式，人们一定会得出这样的结论，即整个文明的努力不值得这样劳心费力，其结果只会导致个人注定无法忍受的状态。我在这些方面知识匮乏，因此更易做到不偏不倚。我能确定的只有一件事，即人类的价值判断无疑会受到他的幸福愿望的引导，因此这些价值判断相当于努力用一些论据来支撑其幸福的幻想。如果有人指出人类文明具有必然性，并声称限制性生活、宣扬博爱的理想须以自然选择为代价，这是一种趋势，无法避免、无法偏离，我们最好是屈服这一趋势，就好像它是必然规律一样，那么我想我完全可以理解。另一方面，我也知道反对的观点是什么，即在人类的历史进程中，像这些我们认为难以实现的理想追求，常常被抛到一边，而被其他追求所取代。因而，我不敢以先知的身份在我的同胞面前自居，我甘愿接受他们指责我不能给予他们任何慰藉：因为说到底，无论是最狂热的革命者还是最虔诚的信徒都一样，他们的根本需要都是安慰。

对我来说，人类的重大问题在于，其文明发展能否并在多大程度上控制住他们的攻击性和自我破坏本能对集体生活的干扰。从这方面看来，也许现在这个时代应该受到特别的注意。人类已经在很大程度上取得了对自然力量的控制，以致他们可以借助于自然的力量，毫不困难地自相残杀，直到只剩最后一个人。他们明白这一点，目前的不安、痛苦和焦虑的心情大部分就是由此产生的。现在我们期待着两个“天神”之一—永生的爱神厄洛斯，在与同样永生的对手死神的斗争中，能够坚持自己的立场。但谁又能预见结果又将如何呢？

[1]罗曼·罗兰。

[2]在《虔诚的海伦》一书中，威廉·布施在一个较低的层次上同样谈论到这一问题：“忧愁的人有白兰地相伴。”

[3]歌德提醒世人说：“世上一切皆可忍受，唯有长期的艳阳天。”然而或许这只是一种夸张的说法。

[4]力比多（libido）指人的一种本能需要，被认为是产生欲望的源泉，尤其是性欲。

[5]伏尔泰曾明智地提出：一个人除非具有特殊的气质为他指引生活中的兴趣所在，否则他所承担的普通工作就可以发挥这一作用。限于篇幅我无法充分说明工作在力比多的分配中所扮演的重要角色。没有什么其他生活方式比强调工作的重要性更能将个体和现实世界紧密相连了，个体的工作至少在现实世界和人类社会的一隅为他提供了稳妥的一席之地。使得大量自恋的、具有攻击性的，甚至情色的力比多成分可以转移到专业工作和与之相关的人际关系上，与工作在维护和辩解个人存在对社会所发挥的不可或缺的作用相比，这一作用的价值并不逊色。如果我们可以自由选择职业活动，也就是说，如果通过升华，可以将现有的爱好、持续不断或生来固有的本能冲动运用到工作中，就会在职业活动中获得特殊的满足。然而，人们很少会把工作视为通向幸福的途径，他们不像努力追求其他满足欲望的可能性途径那样去努力工作。大部分人工作只是因为迫不得已；人们对工作的厌恶成了最棘手的社会问题的根源。

[6]我感到我有必要指出前面论述中至少存在一个漏洞。讨论人类幸福的种种可能性时，不应该不考虑自恋与对象力比多的关系。我们需要知道一个人本质上独立自主对于有效利用力比多有着怎样的意义。

[7]精神分析的材料尽管不全面，不能对此作出肯定的解释，但关于人类这一伟大成就的起源至少可以作一个异想天开的猜测。原始人在接触到火时，他好像有一种用尿灭火以满足婴儿欲望的习惯。原始人把向上喷出的火舌视为男性生殖器的象征，现有传说毫无疑问地体现出这一点。排尿灭火—这个行为仍被后来的巨人如小人国中的格列佛、拉伯雷笔下的高康大所重复—因此是一种男性之间的性行为，是同性恋竞争中对男性性能力的享受。第一个放弃这种享受将火留下的人，将它随身带走，使它为己所用。通过灭掉自己性兴奋的欲火，他制服了自然力量之火。因此，这个伟大的文化征服是对他放弃满足本能欲望的奖赏。而且，似乎是男人指派女人看护好被俘虏在炉膛中的火，因为女人的身体构造使她不可能屈服于这种灭火欲望的诱惑。而且值得注意的是，心理分析的经验时常证明了野心、火和尿道性冲动之间的关系。

[8]性行为的生理周期保存了下来，但生理周期对性兴奋的心理作用却倒退了。这一变化很可能与嗅觉刺激的减弱有关，最初正是通过嗅觉刺激，女性月经周期会在男性身上产生一种心理效果。嗅觉刺激后来遭到视觉兴奋的压抑，其作用也被视觉兴奋取代。与间断性的嗅觉刺激不同，视觉兴奋则总是保持有效。月经期的禁忌就是来自这种“有机体性压抑”，这是一种对已被取代的人类发展前一阶段的防御，而所有其他的动机大概都处于次要地位。（参看戴利的著作，《土著神话与阉割情节》第十三章，1927）当上一文化阶段的神灵变成下一文化阶段的恶魔时，上述过程就在不同程度上重复着。嗅觉刺激的减弱本身似乎是人类直立行走的结果。直立行走使得以前被隐藏起来的人类生殖器暴露出来，因而需要保护，也唤起了人类的羞耻感。因此，可以说文明的这一关键性过程是由于人类有了直立行走的姿势而开始的。从此，事情发展的顺序是：从嗅觉刺激的衰退和月经期间的性禁忌，到视觉刺激的优势和生殖器官的显露，然后就发展到持续的性兴奋，家庭的建立，从此人类就跨入了文明的大门。这只是一个理论上的推测，但它很重要，值得我们在那些与人类关系密切的动物身上去加以验证。
在人类对清洁的文明追求中，同样存在着一个明白无误的社会因素，尽管清洁后来被卫生学证明是正确的，但早在这一点被证实之前，人类就已经追求清洁了。对清洁的迫切要求来自人们清除排泄物的需要，排泄物当时就已经为人们的感官难以容忍。我们知道在保育院里，情形就大不相同了，排泄物并不会引起孩子们的恶心。粪便作为从他们体内排出的身体的一部分，对他们来说似乎颇有价值。这里的教养尤其强调促进儿童发展的下一阶段早日到来，在下一阶段，排泄物粪便就会被认为是无用、恶心、可恶、可憎的。体内排泄物如果不是那么臭气熏天的话，它的价值是不会这样被否定，以致遭到人直立行走后嗅觉刺激被压抑的同样命运。所以，肛门欲首先屈服于走向文明的“有机体性压抑”。对肛门欲的进一步转化负有责任的社会因素的存在，在这样的事实中得到证明：在人类进化过程中，每个人都很少觉得自己的排泄物恶心，他只是觉得别人的粪便恶心。所以说，一个人如果不讲卫生—不把自己的粪便隐藏起来的话，他就会触怒别人；他就没有体谅别人。这一情形在我们最强烈、最常听的咒骂声中体现出来。如果不是由于下述两个特点招致人们的蔑视，人类用他在动物界最忠实的朋友—狗来咒骂就让人费解了：一是，狗最重要的感官就是嗅觉，并且它对排泄物并不反感；二是，狗对性活动并不感到羞耻。

[9]上面阐述的观点有以下几方面的依据。人也是一种动物，与动物一样，具有明显的两性气质。个体的人相当于两个对称的一半的融合，根据某些研究者的看法，其中一半纯粹是男性的，另一半纯粹是女性的，而每一半原先也同样可能是两性的。性别是一个生物学的事实，在人的精神生活中扮演着极其重要的角色，却很难从心理的角度去把握它。我们习惯说每个人都表现出男性和女性的本能的冲动、需要和特征；尽管解剖学确实能够区分男性和女性的特征，心理学却不能。对于心理学来说，两性之间的差别消失了，变成了主动性和被动性之间的区别；我们也毫不犹豫地把男性与主动性，女性与被动性等同起来，然而这一观点在动物界绝没有得到普遍的证实，关于两性共存的理论仍然还有许多晦涩难解的问题，与本能理论尚未联系起来，这在我们看来，不能不算是精神分析的严重缺陷。尽管如此，如果我们假设每个人都试图在其性生活中寻求男性欲望与女性欲望的满足，也不排除这些欲望不能通过同一对象得到满足，且如果两种欲望不分开，不引入到合适的渠道的话，两者会彼此干涉。但另一问题又产生了，就是与性爱关系相联系的除了性本能自身的虐待狂部分以外，常常还有一种明显的攻击性倾向。面对这一复杂性，爱的对象往往不能理解和容忍，而农妇则对此表现出某种程度的理解和忍耐；她会抱怨说她的丈夫不再爱她了，因为他一个星期没打她了。然而，最深层的推测是前面在注解中所谈及的内容（第四章，46页）。大意是讲，由于人类采用了直立的姿势，并且嗅觉功能减弱，结果不仅他的肛门欲，而且他的整个性欲，都存在着沦为有机体压抑的牺牲品的危险，由于这一原因，一种让人难以理解的反感总是伴随着性功能，这种厌恶感妨碍了性的充分满足，迫使其远离性目标，进入力比多的升华和转化境界。我知道布洛勒（“性阻力”，《心理分析与心理病态研究年鉴》第五卷，1913）曾经指出存在着这样一种对性生活的原始反感。一切精神病患者，还有许多其他人，反对“我们是在尿与粪便之间出生的”这一事实。生殖器难闻的气味，许多人无法忍受，他们的性交兴致因而遭到破坏。因此我们可能发现，伴随文明发展的性压抑的最深的根源，是有机体为了保护人直立行走后所形成的新的生活方式而对其早期动物式的生存进行的防御。奇怪的是，这一研究的结果正好与对性的陈腐世俗偏见相吻合。然而，研究结果也好，偏见也好，目前还只是一些可能性而已，尚缺乏科学确证。我们不要忘记，尽管嗅觉刺激作用的价值降低不容置疑，但有一些人，甚至在欧洲，认为对我们难以忍受的生殖器气味，是备受推崇的性刺激物，并拒绝清除它们[参看伊万·布劳克从调查中收集到的一些关于性生活中嗅觉的民间传说，它们发表于弗里德里希·克劳斯的《人类学》各卷中]。

[10]一位富有想象力的伟大作家，至少可以用开玩笑的方式说出那些会遭到谴责的真心话。例如，海涅承认：“我的性情最为平和。我的愿望是：有一间茅草屋顶的陋舍，但有舒适的床、精美的食品、最新鲜的牛奶和奶油，窗前有鲜花，门前有绿树，并且如果仁慈的上帝想让我完全幸福的话，他应允许我享受这样的快乐，看到六七个我的敌人吊在这些树上。在他们临死之前，由于内心的感动，我将饶恕他们生前对我做的一切坏事。的确，一个人应当饶恕他的敌人—但是在他被吊起之前绝不可能。”

[11]任何一个人，如果他年轻时曾饱尝贫困的痛苦，并且感受过富人们的蔑视和傲慢，毋庸置疑，他对于目前反抗财富不均及其一切后果的努力，绝对不会不理解或没有任何好感。当然，如果这样的反抗打着公正的名义，呼吁人人平等这一抽象要求，那么，其异议就太明显了：大自然赋予每个人不同的身体素质和心理能力，这样的不公正根本无法革除。

[12]厄洛斯永无休止的扩张性趋势与本能的守旧性之间对立明显，这一对立可以成为对下一步问题进行研究的出发点。

[13]歌德的《浮士德》一书中摩菲斯特这一人物，让我们看到了把罪恶根源与破坏本能画上等号的一个相当具有说服力的例子：“一切产生的事物/都应当被破坏/……/因此，你所称的一切罪行，/破坏—简而言之—邪恶/那才是我真正的本性。”这个魔鬼自认为他的敌人并不是至善，而是大自然生育和繁衍的力量，即厄洛斯：“从水中、土中（接上页）和空气中显露出来，/成千的胚芽破土而出，蓬勃生长/在干燥、潮湿、温暖和寒冷之中/如果我不是真的蕴藏着热情的火焰的话，/那我就没有什么特别的东西可以展示了。”

[14]我们现在的观点大致可以表述如下：每种本能的表现都有力比多的参与，但并非所有的表现都是力比多。

[15]或许为了更精确起见，我们应该加上一句：经过某一事件后，文明必将呈现的某种形式，仍然是一种猜测而已。

[16]任何一个反应敏锐的人都会理解并考虑到这样一个事实：这不仅仅是一个超我存在的问题，而且是其相对力量和影响范围的问题，并且这是一个逐渐过渡的过程，这些问题在上面的概括性陈述中都得到了明确的区分。到目前为止，对良知和内疚的所有论述都是众所周知、毋庸置疑的。

[17]恶运在提升道德水准中发挥着作用，这一主题在马克·吐温的一篇有趣的短篇小说《我偷的第一个瓜》中得到揭示。这第一个瓜碰巧尚未成熟，我听到马克·吐温自己读着这个故事，读出标题后，他停顿下来，然后自问：“是第一个吗？”这就说明了一切：第一个，而不是唯一一个。

[18]在《对总体人格的精神分析》（1927）一书中，弗兰兹·亚历山大准确地评价了两种主要的导致儿童患病的养育方法—过度严厉和过度娇宠，并与艾卡豪恩对少年犯罪的研究联系起来。“过度宽容和溺爱的父亲”是孩子形成过分严厉的超我的原因。因为在爱的影响下，他们没有发泄其攻击性的方法，只有把它转入内部。少年犯在缺乏爱的环境下长大，他们缺乏自我和超我之间的紧张状态，所以整个攻击性都能指向外部。所以如果不考虑假定存在的气质方面的因素，我们可以说严厉的良知起源于两个因素的相互作用：本能的挫折和被爱的体验，前者释放出攻击性；后者使攻击性转向内部并且把它交给超我。

[19]“因而良知确实使我们每个人都变成了懦夫……”今天年轻人所受的教育向他们掩盖了性欲将会在他们生活中所起的作用，但这并不是我们对这种教育的唯一谴责。这种教育的过错还在于，它没有使年轻人对他们注定会成为攻击性的对象有所准备。当教育用这样一种错误的心理导向把年轻人送入生活中时，就好像是给即将踏上极地考察征程的人们配备了一套夏装和一张意大利北部的湖泊地图。在这里很显然存在着对伦理道德要求的滥用。如果教育者们如此讲：这是人们为了自己和他人的幸福应该做的，但我们也应预计到人们可能不去这么做，那么这些道德要求的严厉性就不会那么有害了。但是相反，教育却使年轻人相信其他每个人都遵循这些道德戒律—每个人都具有德行。这也是为什么年轻人也应当具有德行的原因。

1

It is impossible to resist the impression that people commonly apply false standards, seeking power, success and wealth for themselves and admiring them in others, while underrating what is truly valuable in life. Yet in passing such a general judgement one is in danger of forgetting the rich variety of the human world and its mental life. There are some individuals who are venerated by their contemporaries, but whose greatness rests on qualities and achievements that are quite foreign to the aims and ideals of the many. One may be inclined to suppose that these great men are appreciated after all only by a minority, while the great majority have no interest in them. However, it is probably not as simple as that, owing to the discrepancies between people's thoughts and actions and the diversity of their desires.

One of these outstanding men corresponds with me and in his letters calls himself my friend. I sent him a little piece of mine that treats religion as an illusion, and in his reply he said that he wholly agreed with my view of religion, but regretted that I had failed to appreciate the real source of religiosity. This was a particular feeling of which he himself was never free, which he had found confirmed by many others and which he assumed was shared by millions, a feeling that he was inclined to call a sense of 'eternity', a feeling of something limitless, unbounded–as it were 'oceanic'. This feeling was a purely subjective fact, not an article of faith; no assurance of personal immortality attached to it, but it was the source of the religious energy that was seized upon by the various churches and religious systems, directed into particular channels and certainly consumed by them. On the basis of this oceanic feeling alone one was entitled to call oneself religious, even if one rejected every belief and every illusion.

This opinion of my esteemed friend,* who himself once celebrated the magic of illusion in poetic form, caused me no small difficulty. I can discover no trace of this 'oceanic' feeling in myself. It is not easy to treat feelings scientifically. One may try to describe their physiological symptoms. Where this is not feasible–and I fear that the oceanic feeling will not lend itself to such a description–there is nothing left to do but to concentrate on the ideational content most readily associated with the feeling. If I have understood my friend correctly, what he has in mind is the same as the consolation that an original and rather eccentric writer offers his hero before his freely chosen death: 'We cannot fall out of this world.' It is a feeling, then, of being indissolubly bound up with and belonging to the whole of the world outside oneself. I would say that for me this is more in the nature of an intellectual insight, not of course without an emotional overtone, though this will not be wanting in other acts of thought that are similar in scope. Relying on my personal experience, I should not be able to convince myself of the primary nature of such a feeling. But this does not entitle me to dispute its actual occurrence in others. The only question is whether it is correctly interpreted and whether it should be acknowledged as the fans et origo of all religious needs.

I have nothing to suggest that would decisively con tribute to the solution of this problem. The idea that a person should be informed of his connection with the world around him through an immediate feeling that is used for this purpose from the beginning sounds so bizarre, and fits so badly into the fabric of our psychology, that we are justified in looking for a psychoanalytic–that is to say a genetic–derivation of such a feeling. The following train of thought then suggests itself. Normally we are sure of nothing so much as a sense of self, of our own ego. This ego appears to us autonomous, uniform and deafly set off against everything else. It was psychoanalytic research that first taught us that this was a delusion, that in fact the ego extends inwards, with no clear boundary, into an unconscious psychical entity that we call the id, and for which it serves, so to speak, as a façade. And psychoanalysis still has much to tell us about the relation of the ego to the id. Yet externally at least the ego seems to be clearly and sharply delineated. There is only one condition–admittedly an unusual one, though it cannot be dismissed as pathological–in which this is no longer so. At the height of erotic passion the borderline between ego and object is in danger of becoming blurred. Against all the evidence of the senses, the person in love asserts that 'T' and 'you' are one and is ready to behave as if this were so. What can be temporarily interrupted by a physiological function must of course be capable of being disturbed by morbid processes also. Pathology acquaints us with a great many conditions in which the boundary between the ego and the external world becomes uncertain or the borderlines are actually wrongly drawn. There are cases in which parts of a person's own body, indeed parts of his mental life–perceptions, thoughts, feelings–seem alien, divorced from the ego, and others in which he attributes to the external world what has deafly arisen in the ego and ought to be recognized by it. Hence, even the sense of self is subject to disturbances, and the limits of the self are not constant.

A further consideration tells us that the adult's sense of self cannot have been the same from the beginning. It must have undergone a process of development, which understandably cannot be demonstrated, though it can be reconstructed with a fair degree of probability. The new-born child does not at first separate his ego from an outside world that is the source of the feelings flowing towards him. He gradually learns to do this, prompted by various stimuli. It must make the strongest impression on him that some sources of stimulation, which he will later recognize as his own physical organs, can convey sensations to him at any time, while other things–including what he most craves, his mother's breast–are temporarily removed from him and can be summoned back only by a cry for help. In this way the ego is for the first time confronted with an 'object', something that exists 'out there' and can be forced to manifest itself only through a particular action. A further incentive to detach the ego from the mass of sensations, and so to recognize a 'world outside', is provided by the frequent, multifarious and unavoidable feelings of pain (or absence of pleasure), whose termination and avoidance is required by the absolute pleasure principle. A tendency arises to detach from the ego anything that may give rise to such un pleasurable experience, to expel it and so create an ego that is oriented solely towards pleasure and confronts an alien and menacing world outside. The limits of this primitive pleasure-oriented ego are inevitably corrected by experience. After all, some of the things that give us pleasure and that we are loath to forgo belong not to the ego, but to the object, and some of the torments that we wish to expel prove to be of internal origin and inseparable from the ego. We learn how to distinguish between the internal, which belongs to the ego, and the external, which comes from the world outside, through deliberate control of our sensory activity and appropriate muscular action. This is the first step towards establishing the reality principle, which will govern subsequent developments. The distinction between the internal and the external naturally serves a practical purpose, in that it provides protection against unpleasurable experiences and the threat of them. The fact that the ego employs exactly the same methods to expel certain unpleasurable sensations from within as it does to repel others from without becomes the starting point for significant pathological disorders.

In this way, then, the ego detaches itself from the external world. Or, to put it more correctly, the ego is originally all-inclusive, but later it separates off an external world from itself. Our present sense of self is thus only a shrunken residue of a far more comprehensive, indeed all-embracing feeling, which corresponded to a more intimate bond between the ego and the world around it. If we may assume that this primary sense of self has survived, to a greater or lesser extent, in the mental life of many people, it would coexist, as a kind of counterpart, with the narrower, more sharply defined sense of self belonging to the years of maturity, and the ideational content appropriate to it would be precisely those notions of limitlessness and oneness with the universe–the very notions used by my friend to elucidate the 'oceanic' feeling. But have we any right to assume that what was originally present has survived beside what later evolved from it?

Undoubtedly! There is nothing surprising about such an occurrence, either in the mental sphere or in other spheres. Regarding the animal world, we adhere to the hypothesis that the most highly developed species have evolved from the lowest. Yet we find all the simple forms of life still existing today. The race of the great saurians has become extinct and made way for the mammals, but a genuine representative of this race, the crocodile, is still with us. The analogy may be too remote, and it is weakened by the fact that as a rule the lower species that survive are not the true ancestors of the more highly developed species of today. The intermediate stages have mostly died out and are known to us only through reconstructions. In the realm of the mind, however, the retention of the primitive beside what has evolved from it is so common that there is no need to cite examples to prove it. When this happens it is mostly the result of divergent developments. One portion (in quantitative terms) of an attitude, of an instinctual impulse, has remained unchanged, while another has developed further.

This brings us up against the more general problem of retention in the psychical sphere, which has so far hardly been studied, but is so fascinating and significant that we may perhaps be permitted, though not for any adequate reason, to dwell on it for a while. Having overcome the error of thinking that our frequent forgetfulness amounts to the destruction of the trace left by memory and therefore to an act of annihilation, we now tend towards the opposite presumption–that, in mental life, nothing that has once taken shape can be lost, that everything is somehow preserved and can be retrieved under the right circumstances–for instance, through a sufficiently long regression. Let us try to understand, with the help of an analogy from another field, what this presumption implies. As an example let us take the development of the Eternal City. Historians tell us that in the earliest times Rome was Roma quadrata, an enclosed settlement on the Palatine Hill. The next phase was the Septimontium, a union of the settlements on the separate hills. After this it was the city bounded by the Servian Wall, and still later, after all the vicissitudes of the republican and the early imperial age, the city that the emperor Aurelian enclosed within his walls. We will not pursue the further transformations undergone by the city, but we cannot help wondering what traces of these early stages can still be found by a modern visitor to Rome–whom we will credit with the best historical and topographical knowledge. He will see Aureliah's wall virtually unchanged, save for a few gaps. Here and there he will find stretches of the Servian wall that have been revealed by excavations. Because he commands enough knowledge–more than today's archaeologists–to be able to trace the whole course of this wall and enter the outlines of Roma quadrata in a modem city plan. Of the buildings that once occupied this ancient framework he will find nothing, or only scant remains, for they no longer exist. An extensive knowledge of the Roman republic might at most enable him to say where the temples and public buildings of that period once stood. Their sites are now occupied by ruins–not of the original buildings, but of various buildings that replaced them after they burnt down or were destroyed. One need hardly add that all these remnants of ancient Rome appear as scattered fragments in the jumble of the great city that has grown up in recent centuries, since the Renaissance. True, much of the old is still there, but buried under modem buildings. This is how the past survives in historic places like Rome.

Now, let us make the fantastic assumption that Rome is not a place where people live, but a psychical entity with a similarly long, rich past, in which nothing that ever took shape has passed away, and in which all previous phases of development exist beside the most recent. For Rome this would mean that on the Palatine hill the imperial palaces and the Septizonium of Septimius Severus still rose to their original height, that the castle of San Angelo still bore on its battlements the fine statues that adorned it until the Gothic siege. Moreover, the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus would once more stand on the site of the Palazzo Caffarelli, without there being any need to dismantle the latter structure, and indeed the temple would be seen not only in its later form, which it assumed during the imperial age, but also in its earliest, when it still had Etruscan elements and was decorated with terracotta antefixes. And where the Coliseo now stands we could admire the vanished Domus Aurea of Nero; on the Piazza of the Pantheon we should find not only the present Pantheon, be queathed by Hadrian, but the original structure of M. Agrippa; indeed, occupying the same ground would be the church of Maria sopra Minerva and the ancient temple over which it is built. And the observer would perhaps need only to shift his gaze or his position in order to see the one or the other.

It is clearly pointless to spin out this fantasy any further: the result would be unimaginable, indeed absurd. If we wish to represent a historical sequence in spatial terms, we can do so only by juxtaposition in space, for the same space cannot accommodate two different things. Our attempt to do otherwise seems like an idle game; its sole justification is to show how far we are from being able to illustrate the peculiarities of mental life by visual means.

There is one objection that we must try to answer. Why did we choose to compare the past of a city with the psychical past? Even where the life of the psyche is concerned, the assumption that everything past survives is valid only if the mind has remained intact and its fabric has not suffered from trauma or inflammation. However, destructive factors that might be compared with such causes of disease, are not absent from the history of any city, even if it has had a less turbulent past than Rome or, like London, hardly ever been ravaged by an enemy. Even the most peaceful urban development entails the demolition and replacement of buildings, and so for this reason no city can properly be compared with a psychical organism.

We readily yield to this objection and, forgoing any striking contrast, turn to a more closely related object of comparison, the animal or human body. But here too we find the same phenomena. The earlier phases of development are not preserved at all, having been absorbed into the later ones, for which they supplied the material. The embryo cannot be discovered in the adult; the thymus gland of the child is replaced after puberty by connective tissue, but no longer exists as such; in the adults marrow-bone I can admittedly trace the outline of the child's bone, but this has disappeared through stretching and thickening before taking on its final form. The fact remains that the retention of all previous stages, together with the final shape, is possible only in the mind, and that we are not in a position to illustrate this phenomenon by means of any parallel.

Perhaps we go too far in making this assumption. Perhaps we should be content to say that the past may be retained in the life of the psyche and need not be destroyed. It may be that even in the psychical sphere some things that are old are so obscured or consumed in the normal way of things, or in exceptional circumstances–that there is no longer any way of restoring and reviving them, or that their retention is linked to certain favourable conditions. This may be so, but we have no way of knowing. All we can do is hold on to the fact that in mental life the retention of the past is the rule, rather than a surprising exception.

Hence, if we are prepared to acknowledge that an 'oceanic' feeling exists in many human beings and inclined to trace it back to an early phase of the sense of self, a further question arises: what claim has this feeling to be regarded as the source of religious needs?

I do not find such a claim compelling. After all, a feeling can be a source of energy only if it is itself the expression of a strong need. To me the derivation of religious needs from the helplessness of the child and a longing for its father seems irrefutable, especially as this feeling is not only prolonged from the days of childhood, but constantly sustained by a fear of the superior power of fate. I cannot cite any childish need that is as strong as the need for paternal protection. The role of the oceanic feeling, which might seek to restore unlimited narcissism, is thus pushed out of the foreground. The origin of the religious temperament can be traced in clear outline to the child's feeling of helplessness. Some thing else may be concealed behind it, but for the time being this remains obscure.

I can imagine that the oceanic feeling subsequently became connected with religion. Being at one with the universe, which is the intellectual content associated with this feeling, strikes us as an initial attempt at religious consolation, as another way of denying the danger that the ego perceives as a threat from the outside world. I must confess yet again that I find it very hard to work with these almost intangible concepts. Another of my friends, whose insatiable thirst for knowledge has driven him to conduct the most extraordinary experiments and finally made him virtually omniscient, has assured me that in practising yoga one can actually arouse new sensations and universal feelings in oneself by turning away from the outside world, by fixing one's attention on bodily functions, and by breathing in special ways. Such sensations and feelings he would interpret as regressions to ancient conditions in the life of the psyche that have long been overlaid. He sees in them a physiological justification, so to speak, for much of the wisdom of mysticism. This would suggest connections with many obscure psychical states such as trance and ecstasy. Yet I cannot help exclaiming, with the diver in Schiller's ballad:

Es freue sich, wer da atmet im rosigen Licht.

[Let him rejoice, whoever draws breath in the roseate light!]

————————————————————

* Romain Rolland.

2

In my piece entitled 'The Future of an Illusion' I was much less concerned with the most profound sources of religious sentiment than with what the common man understands by his religion, the system of teachings and promises that on the one hand explains to him, with enviable thoroughness, the riddles of this world, and on the other assures him that a careful providence will watch over his life and compensate him in a future existence for any privations he suffers in this. The common man cannot imagine this providence otherwise than as an immensely exalted father. Only such a being can know the needs of the children of men, be softened by their pleas and propitiated by signs of their remorse. All this is so patently infantile, so remote from reality, that it pains a philanthropic temperament to think that the great majority of mortals will never be able to rise above such a view of life. It is still more embarrassing to learn how many of those living today, who cannot help seeing that this religion is untenable, nevertheless seek to defend it, bit by bit, in pathetic rearguard actions. One would like to mingle with the believers, in order to confront those philosophers who think they can rescue the God of religion by replacing him with an impersonal, shadowy, abstract principle, and to remind them of the commandment: 'Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain.' If some of the greatest spirits of the past did the same, we cannot appeal to their example here, for we know why they had to.

Let us return to the common man and his religion, the only one that deserves the name. The first thing that occurs to us is the well-known remark by one of our great poets and thinkers, which describes how religion relates to art and science:

Wet Wissenschafi und Kunst besitzt,

hat auch Religion;

Wer jene belden nicht besitzt,

der babe Religion!

[Whoever possesses science and art also has religion; whoever possesses neither of these, let him have religion!]

On the one hand these lines contrast religion with man's two highest achievements; on the other they state that, when it comes to the value they have in our lives, they can represent or stand in for one another. Even if we wish to deny the common man's claim to religion, we clearly lack the authority of the poet. We will try to get closer to an appreciation of his proposition by adopting a special approach. The life imposed on us is too hard for us to bear: it brings too much pain, too many disappointments, too many insoluble problems. If we are to endure it, we cannot do without palliative measures. (As Theodor Fontane told us, it is impossible without additional help.) Of such measures there are perhaps three kinds: powerful distractions, which cause us to make light of our misery, substitutive satisfactions, which diminish it, and intoxicants, which anaesthetize us to it. Something of this sort is indispensable.* Voltaire has distractions in mind when he ends his Candide with the advice that one should cultivate one's garden; another such distraction is scholarly activity. Substitutive satisfactions, such as art affords, are illusions that contrast with reality, but they are not, for this reason, any less effective psychically, thanks to the role that the imagination has assumed in mental life. Intoxicants affect our physical constitution and alter its chemistry. It is not easy to define the position that religion occupies in this series. We shall have to approach the matter from a greater distance.

The question of the purpose of human life has been posed innumerable times; it has not yet received a satisfactory answer and perhaps does not admit of one. Some of those who have posed it have added that if life should turn out to have no purpose, it would lose my value it had for them. Yet this threat alters nothing. Rather, it seems that one is entitled to dismiss the question. The threat appears to rest upon the very human presumption of which we have so many other instances. No one talks about the purpose of the life of animals, unless it is that they are meant to serve human beings. Yet this too is untenable, for there are many animals that man can do nothing with–except describe, classify and study them–and countless animal species have escaped even this use by living and dying out before man set eyes on them.

Again, only religion has an answer to the question of the purpose of life. It can hardly be wrong to conclude that the notion that life has a purpose stands or falls with the religious system.

We will therefore turn now to the more modest question of what human beings themselves reveal, through their behaviour, about the aim and purpose of their lives, what they demand of life and wish to achieve in it. The answer can scarcely be in doubt: they strive for happiness, they want to become happy and remain so. This striving has two goals, one negative and one positive: on the one hand it aims at an absence of pain and unpleasurable experiences, on the other at strong feelings of pleasure. 'Happiness', in the strict sense of the word, relates only to the latter. In conformity with this dichotomy in its aims, human activity develops in two directions, according to whether it seeks to realize–mainly or even exclusively–the one or the other of these aims.

As we see, it is simply the programme of the pleasure principle that determines the purpose of life. This principle governs the functioning of our mental apparatus from the start; there can be no doubt about its efficacy, and yet its programme is at odds with the whole world–with the macrocosm as much as with the microcosm. It is quite incapable of being realized; all the institutions of the universe are opposed to it; one is inclined to say that the intention that man should be 'happy' has no part in the plan of 'creation'. What we call happiness, in the strictest sense of the word, arises from the fairly sudden satisfaction of pent-up needs. By its very nature it can be no more than an episodic phenomenon. Any prolongation of a situation desired by the pleasure principle produces only a feeling of lukewarm comfort; we are so constituted that we can gain intense pleasure only from the contrast, and only very little from the condition itself.* Hence, our prospects of happiness are already restricted by our constitution. Unhappiness is much less difficult to experience. Suffering threatens us from three sides: from our own body, which, being doomed to decay and dissolution, cannot dispense with pain and anxiety as warning signals; from the external world, which can unleash overwhelming, implacable, destructive forces against us; and finally from our relations with others. The suffering that arises from this last source perhaps causes us more pain than any other; we are inclined to regard it as a somewhat superfluous extra, though it is probably no less ineluctable than suffering that originates elsewhere.

It is no wonder that, under the pressure of these possibilities of suffering, people are used to tempering their claim to happiness, just as the pleasure principle itself has been transformed, under the influence of the external world, into the more modest 'reality principle'; that one counts oneself lucky to have escaped unhappiness and survived suffering; and that in general the task of avoiding suffering pushes that of obtaining pleasure into the background. Reflection teaches us that we can try to perform this task by following very different paths; all these paths have been recommended by various schools of worldly wisdom and trodden by human beings. Unrestricted satisfaction of all our needs presents itself as the most enticing way to conduct one's life, but it means putting enjoyment before caution, and that soon brings its own punishment. The other methods, which aim chiefly at the avoidance of unpleasurable experience, differ according to which source of such experience is accorded most attention. Some of them are extreme and others moderate; some are one-sided, and some tackle the problem at several points simultaneously. Deliberate isolation, keeping others at arm's length, affords the most obvious protection against any suffering arising from interpersonal relations. One sees that the happiness that can be attained in this way is the happiness that comes from peace and quiet. Against the dreaded external world one can defend oneself only by somehow turning away from it, if one wants to solve the problem unaided. There is of course another, better path: as a member of the human community one can go on the attack against nature with the help of applied science, and subject her to the human will. One is then working with everyone for the happiness of all. The most interesting methods of preventing suffering are those that seek to influence one's own constitution. Ultimately, all suffering is merely feeling; it exists only in so far as we feel it, and we feel it only because our constitution is regulated in certain ways.

The crudest, but also the most effective method of influencing our constitution is the chemical one–intoxication. No one, I think, fully understands how it works, but it is a fact that there are exogenous substances whose presence in the blood and tissues causes us direct feelings of pleasure, but also alters the determinants of our sensibility in such a way that we are no longer susceptible to unpleasurable sensations. Both effects not only occur simultaneously: they also seem closely linked. However, there must also be substances in the chemistry of our bodies that act in a similar way, for we know of at least one morbid condition–mania–in which a condition similar to intoxication occurs, without the introduction of any intoxicant. Moreover, in our normal mental life there are oscillations between fairly easy releases of pleasure and others that are harder to come by, and these run parallel to a lesser or a greater susceptibility to unpleasurabte feelings. It is much to be regretted that this toxic aspect of mental processes has so far escaped scientific investigation. The effect of intoxicants in the struggle for happiness and in keeping misery at a distance is seen as so great a boon that not only individuals, but whole nations, have accorded them a firm place in the economy of the libido. We owe to them not only a direct yield of pleasure, but a fervently desired degree of independence from the external world. We know, after all, that by 'drowning our sorrows' we can escape at any time from the pressure of reality and find refuge in a world of our own that affords us better conditions for our sensibility. It is well known that precisely this property of intoxicants makes them dangerous and harmful. In some circumstances they are responsible for the futile loss of large amounts of energy that might have been used to improve the lot of mankind.

The complicated structure of our mental apparatus, however, admits of a good many other influences too. Just as the satisfaction of the drives spells happiness, so it is a cause of great suffering if the external world forces us to go without and refuses to satisfy our needs. One can therefore hope to free oneself of part of one's suffering by influencing these instinctual impulses. This kind of defence against suffering is no longer brought to bear upon the sensory apparatus; it seeks to control the inner sources of our needs. In extreme cases this is done by stifling the drives in the manner prescribed by the wisdom of the east and put into effect in the practice of yoga. If it succeeds, one has admittedly given up all other activity too–indeed, sacrificed one's life–only to arrive, by a different route, at the happiness that comes from peace and quiet. We follow the same route when our aims are less extreme and we seek merely to control our drives. Control is then exercised by the higher psychical authorities, which have subjected themselves to the reality principle. At the same time the aim of satisfaction is by no means abandoned; a certain protection against suffering is obtained, in that failure to satisfy the drives causes less pain if they are kept in thrall than if they are wholly uninhibited. All the same, the possibilities of pleasure are undeniably diminished. The feeling of happiness resulting from the satisfaction of a wild instinctual impulse that has not been tamed by the ego is incomparably more intense than that occasioned by the sating of one that has been tamed. Here we have an economic explanation for the irresistibility of perverse impulses, perhaps for the attraction of whatever is forbidden.

Another technique for avoiding suffering makes use of the displacements of the libido that are permitted by our psychical apparatus and lend its functioning so much flexibility. Here the task is to displace the aims of the drives in such a way that they cannot be frustrated by the external world. Sublimation of the drives plays a part in this. We achieve most if we can sufficiently heighten the pleasure derived from mental and intellectual work. Fate can then do little to harm us. This kind of satisfaction–the artist's joy in creating, in fashioning forth the products of his imagination, or the scientist's in solving problems and discovering truths–has a special quality that it will undoubtedly be possible, one day, to describe in metapsychological terms. At present we can only say, figuratively, that they seem to us 'finer and higher', but their intensity is restrained when compared with that which results from the sating of crude, primary drives: they do not convulse our physical constitution. The weakness of this method, however, lies in the fact that it cannot be employed universally, as it is accessible only to the few. It presupposes special aptitudes and gifts that are not exactly common, not common enough to be effective. And even to the few it cannot afford complete protection against suffering; it does not supply them with an armour that is proof against the slings and arrows of fortune, and it habitually fails when one's own body becomes the source of the suffering.*

It is already clear, in the case of this last method, that the purpose is to make oneself independent of the external world by seeking satisfaction in internal, psychical processes, but in the next one the same features are brought out even more strongly. Here the link with reality is loosened still further; satisfaction is derived from illusions, which one recognizes as such without letting their deviation from reality interfere with one's enjoyment. The sphere in which these illusions originate is the life of the imagination, which at one time, when the sense of reality developed, was expressly exempted from the requirements of the reality test and remained destined to fulfil desires that were hard to realize. Fore most among the satisfactions we owe to the imagination is the enjoyment of works of art; this is made accessible, even to those who are not themselves creative, through the mediation of the artist. It is impossible for anyone who is receptive to the influence of art to rate it too highly as a source of pleasure and consolation in life. Yet the mild narcosis that art induces in us can free us only temporarily from the hardships of life; it is not strong enough to make us forget real misery.

Another method, which operates more energetically and more thoroughly, sees reality as the sole enemy, the source of all suffering, something one cannot live with, and with which one must therefore sever all links if one wants to be happy, in any sense of the word. The hermit turns his back on the world and refuses to have anything to do with it. But one can do more than this: one can try to recreate the world, to build another in its place, one in which the most intolerable features are eliminated and replaced by others that accord with one's desires. As a rule anyone who takes this path to happiness, in a spirit of desperate rebellion, will achieve nothing. Reality is too strong for him. He will become a madman and will usually find nobody to help him realize his delusion. It is asserted, however, that in some way each of us behaves rather like a paranoiac, employing wishful thinking to correct some unendurable aspect of the world and introducing this delusion into reality. Of special importance is the case in which substantial numbers of people, acting in concert, try to assure themselves of happiness and protection against suffering through a delusional reshaping of reality. The religions of mankind too must be described as examples of mass delusion. Of course, no one who still shares a delusion will ever recognize it as such.

This is not, I think, a complete list of the methods that human beings employ in trying to gain happiness and keep suffering at bay, and I am aware that the material can be arranged differently. There is one method that I have not yet mentioned–not because I have forgotten it, but because it will concern us later in another context. How could one possibly forget this particular technique in the art of living? It is distinguished by the most curious mixture of characteristics. Naturally it seeks independence from what may best be called fate, and to this end it transfers satisfaction to internal mental processes and makes use of the facility for libidinal displacement that has already been mentioned. But it does not turn away from the external world: on the contrary, it clings to the things of this world and obtains happiness through an emotional attachment to them. Nor is it content with the avoidance of unpleasurable experience, a goal that derives, as it were, from tired resignation; indeed, it bypasses this goal, pays no attention to it, and adheres to the original, passionate striving for the positive achievement of happiness. Perhaps it actually gets closer to this goal than any other method. I am referring of course to the way of life that places love at the centre of everything and expects all satisfaction to come from loving and being loved. This kind of mental attitude comes naturally enough to us all; one manifestation of love, sexual love, has afforded us the most potent experience of overwhelming pleasure and thereby set a pattern for our quest for happiness. What is more natural than that we should go on seeking happiness on the path where we first encountered it? The weakness of this technique of living is obvious; if it were not, nobody would have thought of abandoning this route to happiness in favour of another. We never have so little protection against suffering as when we are in love; we are never so desolate as when we have lost the object of our love or its love for us. But this is not the last word on this particular technique of living, which is based on the value of love as a means of happiness: there is much more to be said about it.

Here one can bring in the interesting case in which happiness in life is sought mainly in the enjoyment of beauty, wherever it presents itself to our senses and our judgement–the beauty of human forms and gestures, of natural objects and landscapes, of artistic and even scientific creations. This aesthetic approach to the purpose of life affords little protection against the sufferings that threaten us, but it can make up for much. The enjoyment of beauty has a special quality of feeling that is mildly intoxicating. Beauty has no obvious use, nor is it easy to see why it is necessary to civilization; yet civilization would be unthinkable without it. The science of aesthetics investigates the conditions under which the beautiful is apprehended; it has not been able to clarify the nature and origin of beauty; as commonly happens, the absence of results is shrouded in a wealth of high sounding, empty verbiage. Unfortunately psychoanalysis too has scarcely anything to say about beauty. All that seems certain is its origin in the sphere of sexual feeling; it would be an ideal example of an aim-inhibited impulse. 'Beauty' and 'attractiveness' are originally properties of the sexual object. It is notable that the genitals themselves, the sight of which is always exciting, are hardly ever judged beautiful; on the other hand, the quality of beauty seems to attach to certain secondary sexual characteristics.

Despite the incompleteness of my presentation, I venture to offer, even at this early stage, a few remarks to round off our present enquiry. The programme for attaining happiness, imposed on us by the pleasure principle, cannot be fully realized, but we must not–indeed cannot–abandon our efforts to bring its realization somehow closer. To reach this goal we may take very different routes and give priority to one or the other of two aims: the positive aim of gaining pleasure or the negative one of avoiding its opposite. On neither route can we attain all we desire. Happiness, in the reduced sense in which it is acknowledged to be possible, is a problem concerning the economy of the individual libido. There is no advice that would be beneficial to all; everyone must discover for himself how he can achieve salvation. The most varied factors will come into play and direct his choice. It is a question of how much real satisfaction he can expect from the external world, how far he is led to make himself independent of it, and, finally, how much strength he feels he has to change it in accordance with his wishes. Apart from the external conditions, what will be decisive here is the individuals mental constitution. The predominantly erotic person will give priority to his emotional relations with others; the narcissistic person, being more self-sufficient, will seek the most important satisfactions in his own internal mental processes; the man of action will not give up contact with the external world, on which he can test his strength. For the second of these types the nature of his gifts and the extent to which he is able to sublimate his drives will determine where he should lodge his interests. Any extreme decision will be penalized, in that it will expose the individual to the dangers that arise if he has chosen one technique of living to the exclusion of others. Just as the prudent merchant avoids tying up all his capital in one place, so worldly wisdom will perhaps advise us not to expect all our satisfaction to come from one endeavour. Success is never certain; it depends on the coincidence of many factors, and perhaps on none more than the capacity of our psychical constitution to adapt its functioning to the environment and to exploit the latter for the attainment of pleasure. Any one who has been born with a particularly unfavourable instinctual constitution and who has not properly under gone the transformation and reordering of the components of his libido–a process that is indispensable for later achievements–will find it hard to derive happiness from his external situation, especially if he is faced with fairly difficult tasks. As a last technique for living, which at least promises him substitutive satisfactions, he may take refuge in neurotic illness; this usually happens early in life. Anyone who sees his quest for happiness frustrated in later years can still find consolation in the pleasure gained from chronic intoxication, or make a desperate attempt at rebellion and become psychotic.*

Religion interferes with this play of selection and adaptation by forcing on everyone indiscriminately its own path to the attainment of happiness and protection from suffering. Its technique consists in reducing the value of life and distorting the picture of the real world by means of delusion; and this presupposes the intimidation of the intelligence. At this price, by forcibly fixing human beings in a state of psychical infantilism and drawing them into a mass delusion, religion succeeds in saving many of them from individual neurosis. But it hardly does any more; there are, as we have said, many paths that can lead to such happiness as is within the reach of human beings, but none that is certain to do so. Not even religion can keep its promise. If the believer is finally obliged to speak of God's 'inscrutable decrees', he is admitting that all he has left to him, as the ultimate consolation and source of pleasure in the midst of suffering, is unconditional submission. And if he is ready to accept this he could probably have spared himself the detour.

————————————————————

* On a more basic level Wilhelm Busch says the same in Die Fromme Helene: 'Whoever has cares has liquor too.'

* Goethe even reminds us: 'Everything in the world can be endured, except a succession of fine days.' However, this may be an exaggeration.

* Unless a special aptitude dictates the direction that a person's interest in life is to take, the ordinary professional work available to everyone can occupy the place assigned to it by Voltaire's wise advice. Within the scope of a short survey it is not possible to pay sufficient attention to the vital role of work in the economy of the libido. No other technique for the conduct of life binds the individual so firmly to reality as an emphasis on work, which at least gives him a secure place in one area of reality, the human community. The possibility of shifting a large number of libidinal components–narcissistic, aggressive, even erotic – towards professional work and the human relations connected with it lends it a value that is in no way inferior to the indispensable part it plays in asserting and justifying a person's existence in society. Special satisfaction comes from professional activity when this is freely chosen and therefore makes possible the use, through sublimation, of existing inclinations, of continued or constitutionally reinforced instinctual impulses. And yet people show scant regard for work as a path to happiness. They do not strive after it as they do after other possibilities of satisfaction. The great majority work only because they have to, and this aversion to work is the source of the most difficult social problems.

* I feel impelled to point out at least one of the gaps that have remained in the presentation given above. No consideration of the possibilities of human happiness should fail to take into account the relation between narcissism and object libido. We need to know what being essentially reliant on our own resources means for the economy of the libido.

3

Our study of happiness has so far taught us little that is not generally known. Even if we go on to ask why it is so difficult for people to be happy, the prospect of learning something new seems little better. We have already answered this question by pointing to the three sources of our suffering: the superior power of nature, the frailty of our bodies, and the inadequacy of the institutions that regulate people's relations with one another in the family, the state and society. Regarding the first two, our judgement cannot vacillate for long: it obliges us to acknowledge these sources of suffering and submit to the inevitable. We shall never wholly control nature; our constitution, itself part of this nature, will always remain a transient structure, with a limited capacity for adaptation and achievement. Recognition of this fact does not have a paralysing effect on us; on the contrary, it gives direction to our activity. Even if we cannot put an end to all suffering, we can remove or alleviate some of it; the experience of thousands of years has convinced us of this. Our attitude to the third source of suffering, the social source, is different. We refuse to recognize it at all; we cannot see why institutions that we ourselves have created should not protect and benefit us all. However, when we consider how unsuccessful we have been at preventing suffering in this very sphere, the suspicion arises that here too an element of unconquerable nature may be at work in the background–this time our own psyche.

When considering this possibility, we come up against a contention which is so astonishing that we will dwell on it for a while. It is contended that much of the blame for our misery lies with what we call our civilization, and that we should be far happier if we were to abandon it and revert to primitive conditions. I say this is astonishing because, however one defines the concept of civilization, it is certain that all the means we use in our attempts to protect ourselves against the threat of suffering belong to this very civilization.

By what route have so many people arrived at this strange attitude of hostility to civilization? I think a deep, long-standing dissatisfaction with the state of civilization at any given time prepared the ground on which a condemnation of it grew up owing to particular historical causes. I think I can identify the last two of these; I am not sufficiently erudite to trace the causal chain back far enough into the history of the human race. Some such hostility to civilization must have been involved already in the victory of Christianity over paganism. After all, this hostility was very close to the devaluation of earthly life that came about through Christian teaching. The penultimate cause arose when voyages of discovery brought us into contact with primitive peoples and tribes. Owing to inadequate observation and the misinterpretation of their manners and customs, they appeared to the Europeans to lead a simple, happy life, involving few needs, which was beyond the reach of their culturally superior visitors. Subsequent experience has corrected several such judgements; the fact that these peoples found life so much easier was mistakenly ascribed to the absence of complicated cultural requirements, when in fact it was due to nature's bounty and the ease with which their major needs could be satisfied. The final cause is particularly familiar to us; it arose when we became acquainted with the mechanism of the neuroses that threaten to undermine the modicum of happiness enjoyed by civilized man. It was discovered that people became neurotic because they could not endure the degree of privation that society imposed on them in the service of its cultural ideals, and it was inferred that a suspension or a substantial reduction of its demands would mean a return to possibilities of happiness.

There is an added factor of disappointment. In recent generations the human race has made extraordinary advances in the natural sciences and their technical application, and it has increased its control over nature in a way that would previously have been unimaginable. The details of these advances are generally known and need not be enumerated. Human beings are proud of these achievements, and rightly so. Yet they believe they have observed that this newly won mastery over space and time, this subjugation of the forces of nature–the fulfilment of an age-old longing–has not increased the amount of pleasure they can expect from life or made them feel any happier. We ought to be content to infer from this observation that power over nature is not the sole condition of human happiness, just as it is not the sole aim of cultural endeavours, rather than to conclude that technical progress is of no value in the economy of our happiness. By way of objection it might be asked whether it is not a positive addition to my pleasure, an unequivocal increment of my happiness, if I can hear, as often as I wish, the voice of the child who lives hundreds of miles away, or if a friend can inform me, shortly after reaching land, that he has survived his long and arduous voyage. Is it of no importance that medicine has succeeded in significantly reducing infant mortality and the risk of infection to women in childbirth, and in adding a good many years to the average life-span of civilized man? We can cite many such benefits that we owe to the much-despised era of scientific and technical advances. At this point, however, the voice of pessimistic criticism makes itself heard, reminding us that most of these satisfactions follow the pattern of the 'cheap pleasure' recommended in a certain joke, a pleasure that one can enjoy by sticking a bare leg out from under the covers on a cold winter's night, then pulling it back in. If there were no railway to overcome distances, my child would never have left his home town, and I should not need the telephone in order to hear his voice. If there were no sea travel, my friend would not have embarked on his voyage, and I should not need the telegraph service in order to allay my anxiety about him. What is the good of the reduction of infant mortality if it forces us to practise extreme restraint in the procreation of children, with the result that on the whole we rear no more children than we did before hygiene became all important, but have imposed restraints on sexual life within marriage and probably worked against the benefits of natural selection? And finally, what good is a long life to us if it is hard, joyless and so full of suffering that we can only welcome death as a deliverer?

It seems certain that we do not feel comfortable in our present civilization, but it is very hard to form a judgement as to whether and to what extent people of an earlier age felt happier, and what part their cultural conditions played in the matter. We shall always tend to view misery objectively, that is to project ourselves, with all our demands and susceptibilities, into their conditions, and then try to determine what occasions for happiness or unhappiness we should find in them. This way of looking at things, which appears objective because it ignores the variations in subjective sensitivity, is of course the most subjective there can be, in that it substitutes our own mental state for all others, of which we know nothing. Happiness, however, is something altogether subjective. However much we recoil in horror when considering certain situations–that of the galley slave in ancient times, of the peasant in the Thirty Years War, of the victim of the Holy Inquisition, of the Jew waiting for the pogrom–it is none the less impossible for us to empathize with these people, to divine what changes the original insensitivity, the gradual diminution of sensitivity, the cessation of expectations, and cruder or more refined methods of narcotization have wrought in man's receptivity to pleasurable and unpleasurable feelings. In cases where there is a possibility of extreme suffering, certain protective psychical mechanisms are activated. It seems to me fruitless to pursue this aspect of the problem any further.

It is time to consider the essence of the civilization whose value for our happiness has been called into question. We will refrain from demanding a formula that captures this essence in a few words before we have learnt anything from our investigation. We will content our selves with repeating that the word 'civilization' designates the sum total of those achievements and institutions that distinguish our life from that of our animal ancestors and serve the dual purpose of protecting human beings against nature and regulating their mutual relations. In order to understand more, we will bring together the individual features of civilization as they manifest themselves in human communities. In doing so we have no hesitation in letting ourselves be guided by linguistic usage or, as some would say, a 'feeling for language', trusting that in this way we shall do justice to inner perceptions that still refuse to be expressed in abstract terms.

The first stage is easy: we recognize as belonging to civilization all activities and values that are useful to human beings, by making the earth serviceable to them, by protecting them against violent natural forces, and so forth. About this aspect of civilization there can be scarcely any doubt. If we go back far enough, we find that the first civilized activities were the use of tools, the taming of fire, and the building of dwellings. Among these, the taming of fire stands out as a quite extraordinary and unprecedented achievement;* with the others man struck out on paths that he has continued to follow ever since, the stimulus to which is not hard to guess. With all his tools man improves on his own organs, both motor and sensory, or clears away the barriers to their functioning. Engines place gigantic forces at his disposal, which he can direct, like his muscles, wherever he chooses; the ship and the aeroplane ensure that neither water nor air can hinder his movements. By means of spectacles he can correct the defects of his ocular lens; with the telescope he can see far into the distance; and with the microscope he can overcome the limits of visibility imposed by the structure of the retina. In the camera he has created an instrument that captures evanescent visual impressions, while the gramophone record does the same for equally fleeting auditory impressions; both are essentially materializations of his innate faculty of recall, of his memory With the help of the telephone he can hear sounds from distances that even the fairy tale would respect as inaccessible. Writing is in origin the language of the absent, the house a substitute for the womb–one's first dwelling place, probably still longed for, where one was safe and felt so comfortable.

What man, through his science and technology, has produced in this world, where he first appeared as a frail animal organism and where every individual of his species must still make his entry as a helpless babe–'oh inch of nature!'–all this not only sounds like a fairy tale, but actually fulfils all–no, most–fairytale wishes. All these assets he can claim as cultural acquisitions. Long ago he formed an ideal conception of omnipotence and omniscience, which he embodied in his gods, attributing to them whatever seemed beyond the reach of his desires–or was forbidden him. We may say, then, that these gods were cultural ideals. Man has now come close to reaching these ideals and almost become a god himself. Admittedly only in the way ideals are usually reached, according to the general judgement of humanity–not completely, in some respects not at all, in others only partly. Man has become, so to speak, a god with artificial limbs. He is quite impressive when he dons all his auxiliary organs, but they have not become part of him and still give him a good deal of trouble on occasion. However, he is entitled to console himself with the fact that this development will not have come to an end in AD 1930. Distant ages will bring new and probably unimaginable advances in this field of civilization and so enhance his god-like nature. But in the interest of our investigation let us also remember that modem man does not feel happy with his god-like nature.

We acknowledge, then, that a country has a high level of civilization if we find that in it everything that can assist man in his exploitation of the land and protect him against the forces of nature–everything, in short, that is of use to him–is attended to and properly ordered. In such countries, rivers that threaten to flood the land must have their courses regulated and their waters channelled to areas of drought. The soil must be carefully tilled and planted with crops that it is suited to support; the mineral wealth below ground must be diligently brought to the surface and used to make the necessary tools and implements. Means of transport must be frequent, fast and reliable. Dangerous wild beasts must be exterminated, and the breeding of domestic animals must flourish. But we have other demands to make on civilization and, remarkably, we hope to find them realized in the very same countries. As though we wished to repudiate our first demand, we also welcome it as a sign of civilization if people devote care to things that have no practical value whatever, that indeed appear useless–for instance, when the urban parks that are needed as playgrounds and reservoirs of fresh air also contain flowerbeds, or when the windows of the houses are adorned with pots of flowers. We soon realize that what we know to be useless, but expect civilization to value, is beauty; we demand that civilized man should revere beauty where he comes across it in nature and create it, if he can, through the work of his hands. Yet our claims on civilization are far from exhausted. We also demand evidence of cleanliness and order. We do not think highly of the civilization of an English country town in Shakespeare's day when we read that there was a large dunghill in front of the door of his father's house at Stratford. We are indignant and call it 'barbarous'–which is the opposite of 'civilized'–when we find the paths in the Vienna woods littered with discarded papers. Squalor of any kind seems to us incompatible with civilization, and we extend the demand for cleanliness to the human body too. We are amazed to read what a foul smell emanated from the person of the Roi Soleil, and we shake our heads when, on visiting Isola Bella, we are shown the tiny wash-basin that Napoleon used for his morning toilet. Indeed, we are not surprised if someone actually proposes the use of soap as a criterion of civilization. Much the same is true of order, which, like cleanliness, relates wholly to the work of man. But while we cannot expect cleanliness in nature, order is in fact copied from her; observation of the great astronomical regularities gave man not only the model for the introduction of order into his own life, but the first clues about how to do it. Order is a kind of compulsion to repeat, which, once a pattern is established, determines when, where and how something is to be done, so that there is no hesitation or vacillation in identical cases. The benefits of order are undeniable; it enables people to make the best use of space and time, while sparing their mental forces. One would be entitled to expect that it had established itself in human activities from the start and without any difficulty; and one may well be surprised that this is not so–that people show a natural tendency to be careless, irregular and unreliable in their work and must first be laboriously trained to imitate the celestial models.

Beauty, cleanliness and order plainly have a special place among the requirements of civilization. No one will maintain that they are as vitally important as control over the forces of nature and other factors that we shall become acquainted with later on, but neither will anyone wish to dismiss them as matters of minor importance. The fact that civilization is not concerned solely with utility is demonstrated by the example of beauty, which we insist on including among the interests of civilization. The usefulness of order is quite patent; as for cleanliness, we must bear in mind that it is also required by hygiene, and we may presume that people were not entirely unaware of this connection even before the age of scientific prophylaxis. Yet utility does not wholly explain the striving for cleanliness: something else must be involved too.

No feature, however, seems to us to characterize civilization better than the appreciation and cultivation of the higher mental activities, of intellectual, scientific and artistic achievements, and the leading role accorded to ideas in human life. Foremost among these ideas are the systems of religion, on whose complex structure I have tried to throw some light elsewhere; next come philosophical speculations, and finally what may be called human ideals, the notions, formed by human beings, of the possible perfection of the individual person, the nation and humanity as a whole, together with the demands they set up on the basis of such notions. The fact that these inventions are not independent of one another, but closely interwoven, increases the difficulty not only of describing them, but of establishing their psychological derivation. If we assume, quite generally, that the mainspring of all human activities is the striving for the two confluent goals of utility and the attainment of pleasure, we have to agree that this applies also to the manifestations of civilization that we have mentioned here, though it is easy to see only in the case of scientific and artistic activity. There can be no doubt, however, that the others also answer to powerful human needs, perhaps to needs that have developed only in a minority of people. Moreover, one must not allow oneself to be misled by value judgements regarding one or other of these religions, philosophical systems and ideals; one may think to find in them the highest achievement of the human spirit or deplore them as aberrations, but one has to acknowledge that their very existence, and especially their predominance, signifies a high level of civilization.

As the last and certainly not the least important characteristic of a civilization we have to consider how the mutual relations of human beings are regulated, the social relations that affect a person as a neighbour, employee or sexual object of another, as a member of a family or as a citizen of a state. Here it becomes particularly difficult to keep oneself free from certain ideal requirements and to grasp what pertains to civilization in general. Perhaps one may begin by declaring that the element of civilization is present as soon as the first attempt is made to regulate these social relations. If no such attempt were made, they would be subject to the arbitrary will of the individual; that is to say, whoever was physically stronger would dictate them in accordance with his interests and instinctual impulses. Nor would anything be changed if this strong individual came up against another who was even stronger. Communal life becomes possible only when a majority comes together that is stronger than any individual and presents a united front against every individual. The power of the community then pits itself, in the name of 'right', against the power of the individual, which is condemned as 'brute force'. The replacement of the power of the individual by that of the community is the decisive step towards civilization. Its essence lies in the fact that the members of the community restrict themselves in their scope for satisfaction; whereas the individual knew no such restriction. Hence, the next requirement of civilization is justice, that is the assurance that the legal order, once established, shall not be violated again in favour of an individual. This entails no judgement regarding the ethical value of such a system of law. The subsequent development of civilization seems to aim at a situation in which the law should no longer express the will of a small community–a caste, a social stratum or a tribe–that in its turn relates like a violent individual to other groups, which may be more comprehensive. The ultimate outcome should be a system of law to which all–or at least all those who qualify as members of the community–have contributed by partly forgoing the satisfaction of their drives, and which allows no one–again subject to the same qualification–to become a victim of brute force.

Individual liberty is not an asset of civilization. It was greatest before there was any civilization, though admittedly even then it was largely worthless, because the individual was hardly in a position to defend it. With the development of civilization it underwent restrictions, and justice requires that no one shall be spared these restrictions. Whatever makes itself felt in a human community as an urge for freedom may amount to a revolt against an existing injustice, thus favouring a further advance of civilization and remaining compatible with it. But it may spring from what remains of the original personality, still untamed by civilization, and so become a basis for hostility to civilization. The urge for freedom is thus directed against particular forms and claims of civilization, or against civilization as a whole. It does not seem as though any influence can induce human beings to change their nature and become like termites; they will probably always defend their claim to individual freedom against the will of the mass. Much of mankind's struggle is taken up with the task of finding a suitable, that is to say a happy accommodation, between the claims of the individual and the mass claims of civilization. One of the problems affecting the fate of mankind is whether such an accommodation can be achieved through a particular moulding of civilization or whether the conflict is irreconcilable.

By allowing common feeling to tell us what features of human life may count as civilized, we have gained a distinct impression or overall picture of civilization, though at first without learning anything that is not generally known. At the same time we have taken care not to concur with the prejudice that civilization is synonymous with a trend towards perfection, a path to perfection that is pre-ordained for mankind. Yet now we are faced with a view that perhaps leads somewhere else. The development of civilization appears to us as a peculiar process that humanity undergoes and in which some things strike us as familiar. We may characterize this process by citing the changes it brings about in well-known dispositions of the human drives, whose satisfaction is, after all, the economic task of our lives. Some of these drives are used up in such a way that in their place something appears that in an individual we describe as a character trait. The most curious example of this process is found in the anal eroticism of young human beings. Their original interest in the excretory function, in the organs and the products involved in it, is transformed as they grow older into a group of traits that we know as thrift, a sense of order and cleanliness, which, while valuable and welcome in themselves, may intensify and become predominant, thus producing what is called the anal character. How this happens we do not know, but there is no doubt that this view is correct. We have now found that order and cleanliness are essential requirements of civilization, though it is not altogether obvious that they are vitally necessary, any more than it is obvious that they are sources of pleasure. At this point we could not fail to be struck at first by the similarity between the process of civilization and the libidinal development of the individual. Other drives are induced to shift the conditions for their satisfaction, to direct them on to other paths; in most cases this coincides with sublimation (of the aims of the drives), with which we are familiar, but in some the two may still be kept apart. Sublimation of the drives is a particularly striking feature of cultural development, which makes it possible for the higher mental activities–scientific, artistic and ideological–to play such a significant role in civilized life. Yielding to a first impression, one is tempted to say that sublimation is a fate that civilization imposes on the drives. But one would do better to reflect on the matter a little longer. Thirdly–and this seems the most important point–it is impossible to overlook the extent to which civilization is built up on renunciation, how much it presupposes the non-satisfaction of powerful drives–by suppression, repression or some other means. Such 'cultural frustration' dominates the large sphere of inter personal relations; as we already know, it is the cause of the hostility that all civilizations have to contend with. It will also make serious demands on our scientific work; in this connection we have much to explain. It is not easy to understand how it is possible to deprive a drive of satisfaction. It cannot be done without risk; if there is no economic compensation, one can expect serious disturbances.

However, if we want to know what value can be claimed by our conception of the development of civilization as a particular process, comparable with the normal maturation of the individual, we clearly have to address another problem and ask ourselves to what influences the development of civilization owes its origin, how it emerged and what has determined its course.

————————————————————

* Psychoanalytic material, while incomplete and impossible to interpret with any certainty, at least allows a surmise–a fantastic-sounding one–about the origin of this great human achievement. It is as though primitive man was in the habit, when confronted with fire, of using it to satisfy an infantile desire by urinating on it and so putting it out. Extant legends leave us in no doubt about the original phallic interpretation of the tongues of flame stretching upwards. Extinguishing a fire by urinating on it–an activity still resorted to by the latter-day giants Gulliver in Lilliput and Rabelais' Gargantua–was therefore like a sexual act performed with a man, an enjoyment of male potency in homosexual rivalry. Whoever first renounced this pleasure and spared the fire was able to take it away with him and make it serve his purposes. By damping down the fire of his own sexual excitement he had subdued the natural force of fire. This great cultural conquest would thus be the reward for forgoing the satisfaction of a drive. Moreover, it is as though the man had charged the woman with guarding the fire, now held prisoner on the domestic hearth, because her anatomy made it impossible for her to yield to such a temptation. It is remarkable too how regularly analytic findings testify to the link between ambition, fire and urinal eroticism.

4

The task seems immense, and one may freely admit to being daunted by it. Here are the few conjectures I have been able to arrive at.

When primitive man had discovered that he had it in his own hands–quite literally–to improve his earthly lot by working, it could no longer be a matter of indifference to him whether someone else was working with him or against him. This other person now acquired for him the value of a fellow-worker, and it was useful to him if they both lived together. Even earlier, in his ape-like prehistory, man had taken to forming families, and members of the family were probably his first helpers. Presumably the founding of the family was linked with the fact that the need for genital satisfaction no longer made its appearance like a guest who turns up suddenly one day, then leaves and is not heard of again for a long time, but moved in as a permanent lodger. Hence, the male acquired a motive for keeping the female or–to put it more generally–his sexual objects around him, while the females, not wanting to be separated from their helpless young, had for their sake to remain with the stronger male.* In this primitive family we note the absence of one essential feature of civilization: the arbitrary power of the father, the head of the family, was absolute. In Totem and Taboo I tried to trace the route that led from this family to the next stage of communal living, which took the form of bands of brothers. On overpowering their father, the sons found that the group could be stronger than the individual. Totemic culture rests upon the restrictions they had to impose on one another in order to sustain this new state of affairs. Taboo observances constituted the first system of 'law'. There were thus two reasons why human beings should live together: one was the compulsion to work, which was created by external hardship; the other was the power of love, which made the man loath to dispense with his sexual object, the woman, and the woman loath to surrender her child, which had once been part of her. Eros and Ananke (Love and Necessity) thus become the progenitors of human civilization too. The first consequence of civilization was that even fairly large numbers of people could now stay together in a community. And because these two powerful forces worked in concert, future developments could be expected to proceed smoothly towards better and better control of the external world and the extension of the community to take in more and more people. Moreover, it is not easy to see how this civilization could be anything but a source of happiness to its participants.

Before we go on to consider where a disturbance might arise, let us allow ourselves to be deflected by the recognition of love as a foundation for civilization; in this way we can ill a gap in our earlier discussion. We said that, since sexual (genital) love had afforded man the most potent experiences of satisfaction and had actually supplied him with the model for all happiness, this should have told him that he would do well to go on seeking his happiness in the sphere of sexual relations and place genital eroticism at the centre of his life. We went on to say that by doing this one made oneself dangerously dependent on part of the external world, the chosen love-object, that one was exposed to extreme suffering if one was spurned by it or lost it through infidelity or death. For this reason sages in every age have emphatically advised against this way of conducting one's life, but it has not yet lost its attraction for much of humankind.

A small minority of people are enabled by their constitution, in spite of everything, to find happiness through love, though this necessitates great psychical modifications of its function. These people make themselves independent of the concurrence of the object of their love by shifting the main emphasis from being loved to their own loving; they protect themselves against the loss of the love object by directing their love not to individuals, but to everyone in equal measure, and they avoid the uncertainties and disappointments of genital love by deviating from its sexual aim and transforming the drive into an aim-inhibited impulse. What they thereby create in themselves–a state of balanced, unwavering, affectionate feeling–no longer bears much outward resemblance to the turbulent genital love-life from which it none the less derives. Perhaps St Francis of Assisi went furthest in exploiting love in this way to gain a feeling of inner happiness; moreover, what we recognize as one of the techniques for fulfilling the pleasure principle has frequently been associated with religion, with which it may be connected in those remote regions where the differentiation of the ego from the objects or the objects from one another is neglected. One ethical view, whose deeper motivation will presently become obvious, sees this readiness to love mankind and the world in general as the highest attitude to which human beings can attain. Even at this early stage we will not withhold our two main reservations: first, an undiscriminating love seems to us to forfeit some of its intrinsic value by doing its object an injustice, and, secondly, not all human beings are worthy of love.

The love that founded the family remains effective in civilization, both in its original form, in which direct sexual satisfaction is not renounced, and in its modified form as aim-inhibited affection. In both it continues to perform the function of binding together fairly large numbers of people, and it does so more intensively than would be possible on the basis of a common interest in work. The careless way in which the language uses the word 'love' can be justified historically. The word denotes not only the relation between a man and a woman, whose genital needs have led them to found a family, but also the positive feelings that exist within the family between parents and children, and between siblings, though we are bound to describe the latter relation as aim-inhibited love or affection. This aim inhibited love was in fact once a fully sensual love, and it still is in the individual's unconscious. Both fully sensual and aim-inhibited love extend outside the family and create new bonds with people who were previously strangers. Genital love leads to the formation of new families, and aim-inhibited love to 'friendships', which become important for civilization because they avoid some of the restrictions of genital love, such as its exclusivity. But as it develops, the relation of love to civilization ceases to be unequivocal. On the one hand, love comes into conflict with the interests of civilization; on the other, civilization threatens love with substantial restrictions.

This rift seems unavoidable, but its cause is not at once discernible. It first manifests itself as a conflict between the family and the wider community to which the individual belongs. We have already noted that one of civilization's chief endeavours is to bring people together in large units. However, the family will not give up the individual. The closer the solidarity of the family, the more often its members tend to cut themselves of from other people and the harder it is for them to enter into the wider circle of life. The phylogenetically older mode of living together–the only one that exists in childhood–resists being superseded by the civilized one that was acquired later. Detaching oneself from the family is a task that faces every young person, and society often supports him in performing it with puberty and initiation rites. One has the impression that such difficulties attach to any psychical development, indeed to any organic development.

Moreover, women soon come into conflict with the cultural trend and exercise a retarding, restraining influence on it, even though it was they who first laid the foundations of civilization with the claims of their love. Women stand for the interests of the family and sexual life, whereas the work of civilization has become more and more the business of the menfolk, setting them increasingly difficult tasks and obliging them to sublimate their drives–a task for which women have little aptitude. No person has unlimited quantities of psychical energy at his disposal, and so he has to accomplish his tasks through an expedient distribution of the libido. Whatever energy he expends on cultural aims is largely denied to the opposite sex: his constant association with men and his dependency on this association even estrange him from his duties as a husband and father. The woman therefore sees herself forced into the back ground by the claims of civilization and adopts a hostile attitude to it.

Civilization's tendency to restrict sexual life is no less clear than its other tendency–to extend the cultural circle. The first phase of civilization, the totemic phase, already involves the prohibition of incest in the choice of one's sexual object; this is perhaps the most drastic mutilation that man's erotic life has experienced through out the ages. Taboo, law and custom create further restrictions, affecting both men and women. Not all civilizations go to the same lengths; and the economic structure of society influences the degree of sexual freedom that remains. We already know that in this respect civilization follows the dictates of economic necessity, because it deprives sexuality of much of the mental energy that it consumes. Civilization thus behaves towards sexuality like a tribe or a section of the population that has subjected another and started exploiting it. Fear that the victims may rebel necessitates strict precautionary measures. A high point in such a development can be seen in our western European civilization. It is psycho logically quite justified to begin by prohibiting expressions of infantile sexuality, for there is no prospect of curbing the sexual appetities of adults unless preparatory measures have been taken in childhood. Yet civilized society cannot in any way be justified in going further and actually denying these phenomena, which are easily demonstrable, indeed striking. The sexually mature individual finds that his choice of object is restricted to the opposite sex, and that most extra-genital gratifications are forbidden as perversions. The demand for a uniform sexual life for all, which is proclaimed in all these prohibitions, disregards all the disparities, innate and acquired, in the sexual constitution of human beings, thereby depriving fairly large numbers of sexual enjoyment and becoming a source of grave injustice. The result of such restrictions might be that in normal persons–those who are not constitutionally inhibited–all sexual interest would low, with no loss, into the channels still let open to it. But what is not outlawed–heterosexual genital love–is still limited by legitimacy and monogamy. Present-day civilization makes it clear that it will permit sexual relations only on the basis of a unique and indissoluble bond between a man and a woman, that it disapproves of sexuality as a source of pleasure in its own right and will tolerate it only as the device–for which a substitute has still to be found–for the increase of mankind.

This is of course an extreme view, and it is known to have proved impracticable, even for quite short periods. Only the weaklings have acquiesced in such a gross invasion of their sexual freedom; stronger spirits have insisted on a compensatory condition, which can be mentioned later. Civilized society has found itself obliged to turn a blind eye to many transgressions that by its own lights it should have punished. Yet one must not err in the opposite direction and assume that such a cultural attitude is altogether innocuous because it does not do all it sets out to do. After all, the sexual life of civilized man has been seriously damaged; at times one has the impression that as a function it is subject to a process of involution, such as our teeth and our hair seem to be undergoing as organs. One is probably entitled to suppose that its importance as a source of happiness–and therefore as a means to fulfil our purpose in life–has perceptibly diminished. Now and then one seems to realize that this is not just the pressure of civilization, but that something inherent in the function itself denies us total satisfaction and forces us on to other paths. This may be wrong–it is hard to decide.*

Sigmund Freud

————————————————————

* The organic periodicity of the sexual process had been retained, but its influence on psychical sexual excitation was reversed. This change was most probably connected with the decline of the olfactory stimuli by which the menstrual process affected the mate psyche. Their role was taken over by visual excitations, which differed from the intermittent olfactory stimuli in that they could remain permanently effective. The taboo on menstruation stems from this 'organic repression', as a defence against a phase of development that has been surmounted; all other motivations are probably of a secondary nature. (Cf. C. D. Daly, 'Hindumythologie und Kastrationskomplex', Imago XIII, 1927.) This process is replicated at a different level when the gods of a past cultural period become the demons of the next. However, the decline of the olfactory stimuli itself seems to have resulted from man's decision to adopt an upright gait, which meant that the genitals, previously hidden, became visible and in need of protection, thus giving rise to a sense of shame. The beginning of the fateful process of civilization, then, would have been marked by man's adopting of an erect posture. From then on the chain of events proceeded, by way of the devaluation of the olfactory stimuli and the isolation of the menstrual period, to the preponderance of the visual stimuli and the visibility of the genitals, then to the continuity of sexual excitation and the founding of the family, and so to the threshold of human civilization. This is merely theoretical speculation, but it is sufficiently important to deserve to be precisely tested against the conditions of life obtaining among those animals that are closely related to man.

There is an unmistakable social factor in the cultural striving for cleanliness too, which was later justified on grounds of hygiene, but manifested itself before this connection was appreciated. The urge for cleanliness arises from the wish to get rid of excrement, which has become repugnant to the senses. In the nursery, as we know, things are different. Excrement does not arouse any disgust in the child; it seems valuable to him as a part of his body that has become detached. Upbringing here insists on accelerating the future course of development, which will make excrement worthless, disgusting, revolting and abominable. Such a reversal of values would be scarcely possible if this material excreted by the body were not condemned by its strong smell to share the fate that overtook the olfactory stimuli after man adopted an erect posture. Hence, anal eroticism first yields to the 'organic repression' that paved the way for civilization. Evidence of the social factor, leading to the further transformation of anal eroticism, is found in the fact that, all evolutionary progress notwithstanding, human beings hardly find the smell of their own excrement offensive–only that of others. A person who lacks cleanliness–who does not hide his excrement–thereby offends others and shows them no consideration, and this is reflected in our strongest and commonest terms of abuse. It would also be incomprehensible that man should use the name of his most faithful friend in the animal world as a term of abuse, were it not for the fact that the dog incurs his contempt through two of its characteristics: as an animal that relies on smell it does not shun excrement, and it is not ashamed of its sexual functions.

* The following observations are offered in support of the supposition made above. Man too is an animal with an unequivocally bisexual disposition. The individual represents a fusion of two symmetrical halves; one of these, in the opinion of some investigators, is purely male, the other female. It is equally possible that each half was originally hermaphrodite. Sexuality is a biological fact that is immensely important in our psychical life, but it is hard to compre hend psychologically. We are in the habit of saying that every human being exhibits both male and female impulses, needs and properties, but while anatomy can distinguish between male and female, psy chology cannot. In the latter discipline the contrast between 'male' and 'female' pales into one between 'active' and 'passive'. We do not hesitate to equate 'active' with 'male' and 'passive' with 'female', but these equations are by no means universally confirmed by the study of animals. The theory of bisexuality is still shrouded in obscurity, and the fact that it has not been connected with that of the drives is bound to strike us as a serious flaw in psychoanalysis. Be that as it may, if we take it to be a fact that every individual seeks to satisfy both male and female desires in his or her sexual life, we are prepared for the possibility that these are not fulfilled by the same object and that they interfere with one another unless they can be kept apart and each impulse can be guided into the proper channel. A further difficulty arises because erotic relations are so often associated with a degree of direct aggression, quite apart from the sadistic component that properly belongs to them. Faced with such complications, the love-object will not always be as understanding and tolerant as the farmer's wife who complained that her husband no longer loved her because he had not beaten her for a week.

The surmise that goes deepest, however, is one that arises from my remarks in the footnote [section IV, p. 46], to the effect that, with man's adoption of an upright posture and the devaluation of his sense of smell, the whole of his sexuality–not just his anal eroticism–was in danger of becoming subject to organic repression, so that the sexual function has since been accompanied by an unaccountable repugnance, which prevents total gratification and deflects it from the sexual aim towards sublimations and displacements of the libido. I know that some time ago Bleuler ('Der Sexualwiderstand', Jahrbuch für psychoanalytische und psy-chopathologische Forschungen V [1913]) pointed to the existence of an original aversion to sexual life. All neurotics, and many others, object to the fact that inter urinas et faeces nascimur ('we are born between urine and faeces'). The genitals give off strong smells that are intolerable to many and spoil their enjoyment of sexual intercourse. Hence, the ultimate root of the sexual repression that accompanies cultural progress would seem to be the organic defence of the new way of life, ushered in by man's adoption of an upright gait, against his earlier animal existence. This result of scientific research coincides in a curious way with a banal prejudice that is often voiced. However, these are at present merely unconfirmed possibilities that lack any scientific corroboration. And let us not forget that, in spite of the undoubted devaluation of olfactory stimuli, there are certain peoples, even in Europe, for whom the pungent genital odours we find offensive are valuable sexual stimuli, which they would be loath to forgo. (See the folkdoric findings of Iwan Bloch's questionnaire on 'the sense of smell in sexual life', published in various issues of the Anthropophyteia of Friedrich S. Krauss.)

5

Psychoanalytic work has taught us that it is precisely these frustrations of sexual life that those whom we call neurotics cannot endure. Neurotics create substitutive satisfactions for themselves in their symptoms, but these either create suffering in themselves or become sources of suffering by causing the subjects difficulties in their relations with their surroundings and society. The latter fact is easy to understand, but the former poses a fresh puzzle. However, civilization demands other sacrifices apart from that of sexual satisfaction.

We have viewed the difficulty of cultural development as a general difficulty of development by tracing it back to the inertia of the libido, to the latter's unwillingness to give up an old position for a new one. We are saying much the same thing when we derive the opposition between civilization and sexuality from the fact that sexual love is a relationship between two people, in which a third party can only be superfluous or trouble some, whereas civilization rests on relations between quite large numbers of people. When a love relationship is at its height, the lovers no longer have any interest in the world around them; they are self-sufficient as a pair, and in order to be happy they do not even need the child they have in common. In no other case does Eros so deafly reveal what is at the core of his being, the aim of making one out of more than one; however, having achieved this proverbial goal by making two people fall in love, he refuses to go any further.

Up to now we can well imagine a cultural community consisting of such double individuals, libidinally sated in themselves, but linked by the bonds of shared work and interests. If this were so it would not be necessary for civilization to rob sexuality of any of its energy. But this desirable state of affairs does not exist, and never has. Reality shows us that civilization is not satisfied with the bonds that have so far been conceded to it; it seeks also to bind the members of the community libidinally to one another, employing every available means to this end, favouring any path that leads to strong identifications among them, and summoning up the largest possible measure of aim-inhibited libido in order to reinforce the communal bonds with ties of friendship. For the fulfilment of these objectives the restriction of sexual life becomes inevitable. Yet we lack any understanding of the necessity that forces civilization along this path and can account for its opposition to sexuality. There must be a disturbing factor that we have not yet discovered.

One of what have been called the ideal demands of civilized society may put us on the fight track. It runs: 'Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself'. It is famous the world over, and certainly older than Christianity, which puts it forward as its proudest claim, but assuredly not very old, for in historical times it still struck people as strange. We will approach it naively, as if we were heating it for the first time. We shall then be unable to suppress a sense of surprise and bewilderment. Why should we behave in this way? What good will it do us? But above all, how shall we manage to act like this? How will it be possible? My love is something I value and must not throw away irresponsibly. It imposes duties on me, and in performing these duties I must be prepared to make sacrifices. If I love another person, he must in some way deserve it. (I will disregard whatever use he may be to me, and whatever importance he may have for me as a sexual object: these two kinds of relationship have no relevance to the injunction to love my neighbour.) He deserves it if, in certain important respects, he so much resembles me that in him I can love myself. He deserves it if he is so much more perfect than myself that I can love in him an ideal image of myself. I must love him if he is my friend's son, for the pain my friend would feel if any harm befell him would be my pain too; I should have to share it. But if he is a stranger to me and cannot attract me by any merit of his own or by any importance he has acquired in my emotional life, it becomes hard for me to love him. Indeed, it would be wrong of me to do so, for my love is prized by my family and friends as a sign of my preference for them; to put a stranger on a par with them would be to do them an injustice. Yet if I am to love him, with this universal love-just because he is a creature of this earth, like an insect, an earthworm or a grass-snake–then I fear that only a modicum of love will fall to his share, and certainly not as much as the judgement of my reason entitles me to reserve for myself. What is the point of such a portentous precept if its fulfilment cannot commend itself as reasonable?

On closer inspection I find still more difficulties. This stranger is not only altogether unlovable: I must honestly confess that he has a greater claim to my enmity, even to my hatred. He appears to have not the least love for me and shows me not the slightest consideration. If it is to his advantage, he has no hesitation in harming me, nor does he ask himself whether the magnitude of his advantage is commensurate with the harm he does me. Indeed, it need not bring him any advantage at all: if he can merely satisfy some desire by acting in this way, he will think nothing of mocking, insulting or slandering me, or using me as a foil to show off his power. The more secure he feels and the more helpless I am, the surer I can be of his behaving towards me like this. If he acts differently towards me, a stranger, and treats me with consideration and forbearance, I am in any case ready to repay him in like coin, without any injunction to do so. Indeed, if this grandiose commandment were to read: 'Love thy neighbour as thy neighbour loves thee', I should have no quarrel with it. There is another commandment that I find even more unintelligible and that causes me to rebel even more fiercely. It runs: 'Love thine enemies.' But on reflection I see that I am wrong to reject it as a still greater presumption. Essentially it is no different.*

But now I seem to hear a dignified voice admonishing me: 'It is precisely because your neighbour is not lovable, but on the contrary your enemy, that you must love him as yourself.' I then understand this to be another instance of Credo quia absurdum ('I believe it because it is absurd').

Now, it is quite likely that my neighbour, if enjoined to love me as himself, will react exactly as I do and reject me for the very same reasons. I hope he will not have the same objective justification, but he will be of the same mind. However, there are differences in human behaviour that ethics classify as 'good' and 'evil', disregarding the fact that such differences are conditioned. While these undeniable differences remain, the fulfilment of these high ethical demands is detrimental to the purposes of civilization in that it proposes direct rewards for wrongful conduct. In this connection one cannot help recalling an incident that occurred in the French Chamber when capital punishment was being debated. One speaker pleaded passionately for its abolition and received tumultuous applause, until a voice called out from the body of the hall: 'Que messieurs les assassins commencent!' ['Let the murderers make the first move!']

The reality behind all this, which many would deny, is that human beings are not gentle creatures in need of love, at most able to defend themselves if attacked; on the contrary, they can count a powerful share of aggression among their instinctual endowments. Hence, their neighbour is not only a potential helper or sexual object, but also someone who tempts them to take out their aggression on him, to exploit his labour without recompense, to use him sexually without his consent, to take possession of his goods, to humiliate him and cause him pain, to torture and kill him. Homo homini lupus [Man is a wolf to man]. Who, after all that he has learnt from life and history, would be so bold as to dispute this proposition? As a rule, this cruel aggression waits for some provocation or puts itself at the service of a different aim, which could be attained by milder means. If the circumstances favour it, if the psychical counter-forces that would otherwise inhibit it have ceased to operate, it manifests itself spontaneously and reveals man as a savage beast that has no thought of sparing its own kind. Whoever calls to mind the horrors of the migrations of the peoples, the incursions of the Huns, or of the people known as the Mongols under Genghiz Khan and Tamefiane, the conquest of Jerusalem by the pious Crusaders, or indeed the horrors of the Great War, will be obliged to acknowledge this as a fact.

It is the existence of this tendency to aggression, which we detect in ourselves and rightly presume in others, that vitiates our relations with our neighbour and obliges civilization to go to such lengths. Given this fundamental hostility of human beings to one another, civilized society is constantly threatened with disintegration. A common interest in work would not hold it together: passions that derive from the drives are stronger than reasonable interests. Civilization has to make every effort to limit man's aggressive drives and hold down their manifestations through the formation of psychical reactions. This leads to the use of methods that are meant to encourage people to identify themselves with others and enter into aim-inhibited erotic relationships, to the restriction of sexual life, and also to the ideal commandment to love one's neighbour as oneself, which is actually justified by the fact that nothing else runs so much counter to basic human nature. For all the effort invested in it, this cultural endeavour has so far not achieved very much. It hopes to prevent the crudest excesses of brutal violence by assuming the right to use violence against criminals, but the law cannot deal with the subtler manifestations of human aggression. There comes a point at which each of us abandons, as illusions, the expectations he pinned to his fellow men when he was young and can appreciate how difficult and painful his life is made by their ill will. At the same time it would be unjust to reproach civilization with wanting to exclude contention and competition from human activity. These are certainly indispensable, but opposition is not necessarily enmity: it is merely misused as an occasion for the latter.

The communists think they have found the way to redeem mankind from evil. Man is unequivocally good and well disposed to his neighbour, but his nature has been corrupted by the institution of private property. Ownership of property gives the individual the power, and so the temptation, to mistreat his neighbour; who ever is excluded from ownership is bound to be hostile to the oppressor and rebel against him. When private property is abolished, when goods are held in common and enjoyed by all, ill will and enmity among human beings will cease. Because all needs will be satisfied, no one will have any reason to see another person as his enemy; everyone will be glad to undertake whatever work is necessary. I am not concerned with economic criticisms of the communist system; I have no way of knowing whether the abolition of private property is expedient and beneficial.* But I can recognize the psychological presumption behind it as a baseless illusion. With the abolition of private property the human love of aggression is robbed of one of its tools, a strong one no doubt, but certainly not the strongest. No change has been made in the disparities of power and influence that aggression exploits in pursuit of its ends, or in its nature. Aggression was not created by property; it prevailed with almost no restriction in primitive times, when property was very scanty. It already manifests itself in the nursery, where property has hardly given up its original anal form. It forms the basis of all affectionate and loving relations among human beings, with perhaps the one exception of the relation between the mother and her male child. Even if we do away with the personal right to own material goods, the prerogative that resides in sexual relations still remains, and this is bound to become the source of the greatest animosity and the fiercest enmity among human beings who are equal in all other respects. If we remove this inequality too and allow total sexual freedom–thus doing away with the family, the germ-cell of civilization–it will admittedly be impossible to foresee on what new paths the development of civilization may strike out. But of one thing we can be certain: this indestructible feature of human nature will follow it wherever it leads.

It is clearly not easy for people to forgo the satisfaction of their tendency to aggression. To do so makes them feel uneasy. One should not belittle the advantage that is enjoyed by a fairly small cultural circle, which is that it allows the aggressive drive an outlet in the form of hostility to outsiders. It is always possible to bind quite large numbers of people together in love, provided that others are left out as targets for aggression. I once discussed this phenomenon, the fact that it is precisely those communities that occupy contiguous territories and are otherwise closely related to each other–like the Spaniards and the Portuguese, the North Germans and the South Germans, the English and the Scots, etc.–that indulge in feuding and mutual mockery. I called this phenomenon 'the narcissism of small differences'–not that the name does much to explain it. It can be seen as a convenient and relatively innocuous way of satisfying the tendency to aggression and facilitating solidarity within the community. The Jews of the diaspora have made valuable contributions to the cultures of the countries in which they have settled, but unfortunately all the massacres of Jews that took place in the Middle Ages failed to make the age safer and more peaceful for the Christians. After St Paul had made universal brotherly love the foundation of his Christian community, the extreme intolerance of Christianity towards those let outside it was an inevitable consequence. To the Romans, whose state was not founded on love, religious intolerance had been quite foreign, though religion was a state concern and the state was steeped in religion. Nor was it quite fortuitous and incomprehensible that the Germanic dream of world-dominion should invoke anti-semitism as its complement. And it is under standable that the attempt to establish a new, communist culture in Russia should find psychological support in the persecution of the bourgeois. One only wonders, with some anxiety, what the Soviets will turn to when they have exterminated their bourgeoisie.

If civilization imposes such great sacrifices not only on man's sexuality, but also on his aggressivity, we are in a better position to understand why it is so hard for him to feel happy in it. Primitive man was actually better off, because his drives were not restricted. Yet this was counterbalanced by the fact that he had little certainty of enjoying this good fortune for long. Civilized man has traded in a portion of his chances of happiness for a certain measure of security. But let us not forget that in the primeval family only its head could give full rein to his drives; its other members lived in slavish suppression. In that primordial era of civilization there was therefore an extreme contrast between a minority who enjoyed its benefits and the majority to whom they were denied. As for today's primitive peoples, more careful study has shown that we have no reason whatever to envy them their instinctual life by reason of the freedom attaching to it; it is subject to restrictions of a different kind, which are perhaps even more severe than those imposed on modem civilized man.

When we rightly reproach the present state of our civilization with its inadequate response to our demand for a form of life that will make us happy, and with allowing so much suffering, which could probably be avoided–and when we strive, with unsparing criticism, to expose the roots of this inadequacy–we are exercising a legitimate right and certainly not revealing ourselves as enemies of civilization. We may hope gradually to carry out such modifications in our civilization as will better satisfy our needs and escape this criticism. But perhaps we shall also become familiar with the idea that there are some difficulties that are inherent in the nature of civilization and will defy any attempt at reform. In addition to the tasks involved in restricting the drives–for which we are prepared–we are faced with the danger of a condition that we may call 'the psychological misery of the mass'. This danger is most threatening where social bonding is produced mainly by the participants' identification with one another, while individuals of leadership calibre do not acquire the importance that should be accorded to them in the formation of the mass. The present state of American civilization would provide a good opportunity to study the cultural damage that is to be feared. But I shall avoid the temptation to engage in a critique of American civilization; I do not wish to give the impression of wanting to employ American methods myself.

————————————————————

* A great writer can allow himself, at least in jest, to express psychologi cal truths that incur severe disapproval. Heine, for instance, confesses: 'I have the most peaceable disposition. My wishes are: a modest cottage with a thatched roof, but a good bed, good food, milk and butter, very fresh, flowers in front of the window, a few beautiful trees in front of the door; and if the good Lord wants to make me completely happy, he will grant me the pleasure of seeing six or seven of my enemies hanged from these trees. My heart will be moved, and before they die I will forgive them all the wrongs they did me in their lifetime. Yes, one must forgive one's enemies, but not before they are hanged.'

* Anyone who has tasted the misery of poverty in his youth and experienced the indifference and arrogance of propertied people, should be safe from the suspicion that he has no sympathy with current efforts to combat inequalities of wealth and all that flows from them. Of course, if this struggle seeks to appeal to the abstract demand, made in the name of justice, for equality among all men, the objection is all too obvious: nature, by her highly unequal endowment of individuals with physical attributes and mental abilities, has introduced injustices that cannot be remedied.

6

With none of my writings have I had such a strong feeling as I have now that what I am describing is common knowledge, that I am using pen and paper, and shall soon be using the services of the compositor and the printer, to say things that are in fact self-evident. For this reason I shall be glad to take the matter up if it appears that the recognition of a special, independent aggressive drive entails a modification of psychoanalytic theory regarding the drives.

It will be seen that this is not so, that it is merely a matter of focusing more sharply on a change of direction that took place long ago, and of following up its consequences. Of all the elements of analytic theory that have taken so long to develop, the doctrine of the drives is the one that has edged its way forward most laboriously. And yet it was so indispensable to the whole that some thing had to be put in its place. After I had at first been totally at a loss, my first clue came from a proposition by the poet-philosopher Schiller, to the effect that the mechanism of the world was held together by 'hunger and love'. Hunger could be taken to represent those drives that seek to preserve the individual creature, whereas love strives after objects, and its chief function, favoured in every way by nature, is to preserve the species. Thus at first ego-drives and object-drives con fronted one another. To denote the energy of the latter–and them alone–I introduced the term 'libido'; there was thus a contrast between the ego-drives and the libidinal drives of love, in the widest sense of the word, which were directed towards an object. One of these latter, the sadistic drive, admittedly stood out from the rest because its aim was so utterly devoid of love. More over, in some respects it was obviously attached to the ego-drives; it could not conceal its close affinity to the drives that aim at domination and have no libidinal purpose. However, it proved possible to get over this discrepancy: after all, sadism was clearly part of sexual life, in which cruelty could replace tendemess. Neurosis appeared to be the result of a struggle between the interest of self-preservation and the demands of the libido, a struggle in which the ego had triumphed, but at the price of grave suffering and sacrifice.

Every analyst will admit that even today this does not sound like a long-discarded error. Yet a modification became indispensable when our research proceeded from what was repressed to the agent of repression, from the object-drives to the ego. The decisive step here was the introduction of the concept of narcissism–that is to say the recognition that the ego itself is occupied by libido, that it is in fact the libido's original home and remains to some extent its headquarters. This narcissistic libido turns towards objects, thus becoming object libido, and can change back again into narcissistic libido. The concept of narcissism made it possible to understand and analyse traumatic neurosis, together with many other conditions that are closely related to the psychoses, as well as the psychoses themselves. There was no need to abandon the interpretation of transference neuroses as attempts by the ego to fend of sexuality, but the concept of libido was endangered. Since the ego-drives too were libidinal, it seemed for a time inevitable that the libido should be allowed to merge with the energy of the drives generally, as C. G. Jung had earlier advocated. Yet there remained something like a certainty, as yet unexplained, that the drives could not all be of the same kind. My next step was taken in Beyond the Pleasure Principle (1920), when I was first struck by the compulsion to repeat and the conservative nature of the drives. Starting from speculations about the beginning of life and from biological parallels, I reached the conclusion that, in addition to the drive to preserve the living substance and bring it together in ever larger units,* there must be another, opposed to it, which sought to break down these units and restore them to their primordial inorganic state. Beside Eros, then, there was a death drive, and the inter action and counteraction of these two could explain the phenomena of life. Now, it was not easy to demonstrate the activity of this supposed death drive. The manifestations of Eros were plain enough to see and hear; one might presume that the death drive operated silently inside the living being, working towards its dissolution, but this of course did not amount to a proof. A more fruitful idea was that a portion of the drive was directed against the external world and then appeared as a drive that aimed at aggression and destruction. In this way the drive was itself pressed into the service of Eros, inasmuch as the organism destroyed other things, both animate and inanimate, instead of itself. Conversely, any restriction of this outward-directed aggression would be bound to increase the degree of self-destruction, which in any case continued. At the same time one could surmise, on the basis of this example, that the two kinds of drive seldom–perhaps never–appeared in isolation, but alloyed with one another in different and highly varying proportions and so became unrecognizable to our judgement. In sadism, which has long been recognized as a partial drive of sexuality, one would be faced with a particularly strong alloy of the striving for love and the drive for destruction, just as its counterpart, masochism, would be a combination of inward-directed destruction and sexuality, through which the otherwise imperceptible striving became conspicuous and palpable.

The assumption of a death drive or a drive for destruction has met with resistance even in analytic circles; I am aware that there is a widespread tendency to ascribe anything that is thought to be dangerous or hostile about love to an original bipolarity in its own nature. The views I have developed here were at first put forward only tentatively, but in the course of time they have taken such a hold on me that I can no longer think in any other way. In my view they are theoretically far more serviceable than any others one might entertain; they produce what we strive for in scientific work–a simple answer that neither neglects nor does violence to the facts. I recognize that we have always seen sadism and masochism as manifestations of the destructive drive, directed outwards or inwards and strongly alloyed with eroticism, but I can no longer understand how we could have ignored the ubiquity of non-erotic aggression and destruction and failed to accord it its due place in the interpretation of life. (The inward-directed craving for destruction mostly eludes our perception, of course, unless it is tinged with eroticism.) I can remember how I myself resisted the idea ora destructive drive when it first appeared in psychoanalytic literature, and how long it took me to become receptive to it. That others rejected it too, and still do, I find less surprising. 'For the little children do not like it' when there is talk of man's inborn tendency to 'wickedness', to aggression and destruction, and there fore to cruelty. For God created them in his own perfect image; one does not wish to be reminded of how hard it is to reconcile the existence of evil, which cannot be denied–despite the protestations of Christian Science–with His infinite power and goodness. The Devil would be the best excuse for God; he would take on the same exculpatory role in this context as the Jew in the world of the Aryan ideal. But even so, one can still demand that God be held responsible for the existence of the Devil and the evil he embodies. In view of these difficulties, it is advisable for each of us, at an appropriate point, to make a profound obeisance to man's deeply moral nature; this will help to make us generally popular, and much will be forgiven us.*

The name 'libido' can once more be applied to manifestations of the power of Eros, in order to distinguish them from the energy of the death drive.† It has to be admitted that the latter is much harder to grasp and can to some extent be discerned only as a residue left behind by Eros, and that it escapes our notice unless it is revealed through being alloyed with Eros. It is in sadism, where it perverts the erotic aim for its own purposes while fully satisfying the sexual striving, that we have the clearest insight into its nature and its relation to Eros. Yet even where it appears without any sexual purpose, in the blindest destructive fury, there is no mistaking the fact that its satisfaction is linked with an extraordinarily high degree of narcissistic enjoyment, in that this satisfaction shows the ego how its old wish for omnipotence can be fulfilled. Moderated and tamed–aim-inhibited, as it were–the destructive drive, when directed towards objects, must provide the ego with the satisfaction of its vital needs and with control over nature. As its existence is posited essentially on theoretical grounds, one must also admit that it is not wholly proof against theoretical objections. But this is how things appear to us now, in the present state of our knowledge; future research and reflection will undoubtedly bring the decisive clarification.

For the rest, I take the view that the tendency to aggression is an original, autonomous disposition in man, and I return to my earlier contention that it represents the greatest obstacle to civilization. At one point in this investigation we were faced with the realization that civilization was a special process undergone by humanity, and we are still under the spell of this idea. We will now add that it is a process in the service of Eros, whose purpose is to gather together individuals, then families and finally tribes, peoples and nations in one great unit–humanity. Why this has to happen we do not know: it is simply the work of Eros. These multitudes of human beings are to be libidinally bound to one another; necessity alone, the advantages of shared work, will not hold them together. However, this programme of civilization is opposed by man's natural aggressive drive, the hostility of each against all and all against each. This aggressive drive is the descendant and principal representative of the death drive, which we have found beside Eros and which rules the world jointly with him. And now, I think, the meaning of the development of civilization is no longer obscure to us. This development must show us the struggle between Eros and death, between the life drive and the drive for destruction, as it is played out in the human race. This struggle is the essential content of all life; hence, the development of civilization may be described simply as humanity's struggle for existence.* And this battle of the giants is what our nurse-maids seek to mitigate with their lullaby about heaven.

————————————————————

* The contrast that emerges here between the restless expansive tendency of Eros and the generally conservative nature of the drives is striking and could become the starting point for the study of further problems.

* Especially convincing is the equation of the principle of evil with the destructive drive in the person of Goethe's Mephistopheles: 'For everything that comes into being /Is worthy of destruction /…/ So, then, everything you call sin, / Destruction–in short, evil- / Is my true element.'

As his adversary, the devil himself names not the holy and the good, but nature's power to procreate, to multiply life–in other words, Eros: 'From air, water and earth/A thousand germs break forth, / In dry, wet, warm and cold!/Had I not reserved the flame for myself, / I should have nothing to call my own.'

† Our present view can be roughly expressed in the proposition that libido is involved in the manifestation of every drive, but not everything in this manifestation is libido.

* Probably we should add, to be more precise: 'in the shape it was bound to take on after a certain event that is still a matter for conjecture'.

7

Why do our relatives, the animals, show no sign of such a cultural struggle? We have no way of knowing. It is very likely that some of them–the bees, the ants, the termites–struggled for thousands of centuries until they evolved the state institutions, the distribution of functions, the restrictions on individuals, for which we admire them today. It is characteristic of our present condition that we feel we should not be happy in any of these animal states or the roles assigned in them to individuals. In the case of other animal species it may be that a temporary compromise was reached between the influences of their surroundings and the conflicting drives within them, so that any development was brought to a halt. It may be that in primitive man a fresh access of libido fanned fresh resistance on the part of the destructive drive. There are many questions to be asked, and as yet no answers.

Another question is closer to home. What means does civilization employ in order to inhibit the aggression it faces, to render it harmless and possibly eliminate it? We have already become acquainted with some of the methods, but not with the one that seems most important. We can study this in the development of the individual. What happens to him to render his aggressivity harmless? Something very curious, which we would not have suspected, but which is plain to see. The aggression is introjected, internalized, actually sent back to where it came from; in other words, it is directed against the individual's own ego. There it is taken over by a portion of the ego that sets itself up as the super-ego, in opposition to the rest, and is now prepared, as 'conscience', to exercise the same severe aggression against the ego that the latter would have liked to direct towards other individuals. The tension between the stem super-ego and the ego that is subject to it is what we call a 'sense of guilt'; this manifests itself as a need for punishment. In this way civilization overcomes the dangerous aggressivity of the individual, by weakening him, disarming him and setting up an internal authority to watch over him, like a garrison in a conquered town.

Regarding the origin of the sense of guilt, the analyst's view differs from that of other psychologists, and he too finds it difficult to account for. In the first place, if we ask how a person comes to have a sense of guilt, the answer we receive cannot be gainsaid: one feels guilty (pious people would say 'sinful') if one has done something one recognizes as 'evil'. Ten we realize how little this tells us. After some hesitation we may add that even a person who has done no wrong, but merely recognizes in himself an intention to do wrong, may consider him self guilty–which raises the question of why in this case the intention is equated with the deed. Both cases presuppose that we have already recognized evil as reprehensible, as something that should not be carried out. How do we arrive at this judgement? We may reject the notion of an original–as it were, natural–capacity to distinguish between good and evil. Evil is often far from harmful or dangerous to the ego; it may even be some thing it welcomes and takes pleasure in. Here, then, is a pointer to an outside influence, which determines what is to be called good or evil. As a person's own feelings would not have led him in this direction, he must have a motive for submitting to this outside influence. This is easily dicovered in his helplessness and dependency on others; it can best be described as a fear of loss of love. If he loses the love of a person he depends on, he is no longer protected against various dangers; above all, he is exposed to the risk that this more powerful person will demonstrate his superiority by punishing him. At first, then, evil is something for which one is threatened with loss of love; it must therefore be avoided. Hence, it hardly matters whether one has already done some thing wrong or merely intends to; in either case the danger arises only if the supervising authority finds out, and in either case the authority would behave in the same way.

This state of mind we call a 'bad conscience', but it really does not merit the name, for at this stage consciousness of guilt is clearly no more than a fear of loss of love, a 'social' anxiety. In a small child it can never be anything else, but for many adults too the only change is that the place once occupied by the father, or by both parents, has been taken over by the wider human community. Hence, adults regularly allow themselves to commit wrongful acts that hold out the promise of enjoyment, so long as they are sure that the authority will not learn of it or cannot hold it against them; their only fear is of being found out. This is the state of affairs that today's society generally has to reckon with.

Nothing much changes until the authority is internalized through the establishment of the super-ego. The phenomena of conscience are thereby raised to a new level; only now can one properly speak of conscience and a sense of guilt.* The fear of discovery is no longer an issue, nor is the difference between wrong-doing and the intention to do wrong, for nothing, not even one's thoughts, can be hidden from the super-ego. Of course, the real gravity of the situation has passed, for to the best of our belief the new authority, the superego, has no reason to ill-treat the ego, with which it is intimately linked. But the way it came into existence is still influential in ensuring the survival of what is past and has been surmounted, so that things remain essentially as they were at the beginning. The superego torments the sinful ego with the same anxieties and is on the look-out for opportunities to expose it to punishment by the external world.

At this second stage of development, the conscience exhibits a peculiarity that was absent at the first and is not easy to explain. The more virtuous a person is, the sterner and more distrustful is his conscience, so that the very people who have attained the highest degree of saintliness are in the end the ones who accuse themselves of being most sinful. Virtue thus forfeits part of its promised reward; the compliant and abstinent ego does not enjoy the trust of its mentor and seemingly strives in vain to earn it. Now, it will at once be objected that these are artifically contrived difficulties, that a stricter and more vigilant conscience is the hallmark of a moral nature, and that if saints call themselves sinners, this is not without justification, in view of the temptations they are under to satisfy their drives, temptations to which they are particularly exposed, as it is well known that temptations are only increased by constant frustration, but diminished, at least for a time, by the occasional satisfaction. Another fact in the highly problematic field of ethics is that ill luck–that is to say, external frustration–greatly enhances the force of conscience in the super-ego. So long as things go well for a person, his conscience is lenient and indulges the ego in all kinds of ways. When a misfortune has befallen him he searches his soul, recognizes his sinfulness, pitches the demands of his conscience higher, imposes privations on himself, and punishes himself by acts of penance.* Whole peoples have behaved like this and still do. However, this is easily explained by reference to the original infantile phase of the conscience, which is not abandoned after the introjection into the super-ego, but persists beside and behind it. Fate is seen as replacing parental authority; if one suffers misfortune, this is because one is no longer loved by this supreme power, and under the threat of such loss of love, one again bows to the virtual parental authority of the super-ego, which one was happy to ignore while one's luck held. This becomes especially clear if one takes a strictly religious view and sees fate only as the expression of the divine will. The people of Israel had thought of itself as God's favourite child, and when the great Father let one misfortune after another rain down upon His people, it never doubted this relationship with God or questioned His power and justice, but brought forth the prophets, who reproached it for its sinfulness, and created, from its consciousness of guilt, the exceedingly stem precepts of its priestly religion. It is curious how differently primitive man behaves. Having met with misfortune, he puts the blame not on himself, but on the fetish, which has clearly not done its duty, and whips it instead of punishing himself.

We thus know of two origins of the sense of guilt: one is fear of authority; the other, which came later, is fear of the super-ego. The former forces us to forgo the satisfaction of our drives; in addition to this, the latter insists on punishment, for the continuance of our for bidden desires cannot be hidden from the super-ego. We have also learnt how the severity of the super-ego–the requirements of conscience–can be understood. This severity simply perpetuates that of the external authority, which it supersedes and partly replaces. We now see how renunciation of the drives relates to consciousness of guilt. Initially this renunciation results from fear of the external authority; one renounces certain satisfactions in order to avoid losing its love. After renouncing them, one is, as it were, quits with the authority, and no sense of guilt should remain. Tings are different, however, when it comes to fear of the super-ego. To renounce the drives is no longer enough, for the desire persists and cannot be concealed from the super-ego. Despite one's renunciation, then, a sense of guilt will arise, and this is a great economic disadvantage in the institution of the super-ego, or, one might say, in the formation of conscience. Renunciation of the drives no longer has a fully liberating effect; virtuous abstention is no longer rewarded by the assurance of love; the threat of extemal unhappiness–loss of love, and punishment at the hands of the external authority–has been exchanged for an enduring inner unhappiness, the tension generated by the consciousness of guilt.

These interrelations are at once so complicated and so important that, at the risk of repeating myself, I should like to tackle them from a different angle. The chronological sequence, then, would be as follows: first, renunciation of the drives, resulting from fear of aggression from the external authority (for this is what fear of the loss of love amounts to, love being a protection against this punitive aggression), then the setting up of the internal authority and the renunciation of the drives, resulting from fear of this authority, fear of conscience. In this second situation an evil deed is on a par with an evil intention; hence the consciousness of guilt and the need for punishment. The aggression of the conscience continues the aggression of the external authority. This much is probably already clear, but what room is let for the influence of misfortune–renunciation imposed from without–which reinforces the conscience, for the extraordinary severity of conscience that is found in the best and most tractable persons? We have already explained both these peculiarities of conscience, but we probably still have the impression that our explanations fail to go to the heart of the matter and leave some things unexplained. And here at last an idea comes in that belongs entirely to psychoanalysis and is foreign to our ordinary way of thinking. This idea is such as to enable us to understand why the subject was bound to strike us as so confused and lacking in transparency. For it tells us that although it is at first the conscience (or, rather, the fear that later becomes the conscience) that causes us to renounce the drives, this causal relation is later reversed. Every renunciation of the drives now becomes a dynamic source of conscience; every fresh renunciation reinforces its severity and intolerance; and if we could only bring it more into harmony with what we know about the emergence of conscience, we should be tempted to endorse the paradoxical statement that conscience results from the renunciation of the drives, or that this renunciation (imposed on us from without) creates the conscience, which then demands further renunciation.

The contradiction between this statement and what we have said about the genesis of the conscience is not so very great, and we can see a way of reducing it further. For greater ease of presentation let us take the example of the aggressive drive, and let us assume that we are dealing in every case with the renunciation of aggression. This is naturally to be taken only as a provisional assumption. The effect that the renunciation of the drives has on the conscience is such that any aggression whose satisfaction we forgo is taken over by the super-ego and increases the latter's aggression (towards the ego). This is not consistent with the view that the original aggression of the conscience continues the severity of the external authority and has therefore nothing to do with renunciation. The inconsistency is removed, however, if we assume a different origin for the super-ego's initial stock of aggression. A considerable measure of aggressivity must have developed in the child against the authority that deprives him of his first (and most significant) satisfactions, no matter what kind of deprivations were required. The child is obliged to forgo the satisfaction of this vengeful aggression. He helps himself out of this difficult economic situation by recourse to familiar mechanisms. By means of identification he incorporates this unassailable authority into himself; it now becomes the super-ego and takes over all the aggression that, as a child, one would have liked to exercise against it. The child's ego has to content itself with the sad role of the authority–the father–which has been so degraded. As so often happens, the original situation is reversed. 'If I were the father and you the child, I should treat you badly.' The relation between the super-ego and the ego amounts to the return, distorted by the subject's desire, of the real relations between the once undivided ego and an external object. This is typical too. The essential difference, however, is that the original severity of the super-ego is not–or not to such a great extent–the severity that one has experienced from him [the father] or attributes to him; it represents rather one's own aggression towards him. If this is correct, one can actually maintain that conscience initially arose through the suppression of an aggressive impulse and continues to be reinforced by similar suppressions.

Which of these two views is correct–the earlier one, which we found genetically incontestable, or the newer one, which rounds of the theory in such a welcome fashion? Clearly both are justified, as is shown by the evidence of direct observation. They do not contradict each other; they even coincide at one point, for the vengeful aggression of the child will be determined partly by the amount of punitive aggression he expects from his father. Experience teaches us, however, that the severity of the super-ego that is developed by a child in no way replicates the severity of the treatment he has himself experienced. It appears to be independent of this: even with a very lenient upbringing, a child may develop a very stern conscience. Yet it would also be wrong to exaggerate this independence; it is not difficult to convince oneself that a strict upbringing also has a strong influence on the formation of the child's super-ego. This amounts to saying that, in the formation of the super-ego and the emergence of conscience, innate constitutional factors act in concert with influences from the real environment. This is not at all surprising; indeed, it is the universal aetiological condition for all such processes.*

One can also say that if a child reacts to the first great frustrations of the drives with excessive aggression and a corresponding severity of the super-ego, it is following a phylogenetic model and going beyond the reaction that would be justified today; for the primeval father was certainly terrible and could be credited with the utmost aggression. The differences between the two views of the genesis of conscience are thus reduced still further if one shits one's attention from individual to phylogenetic development. On the other hand, we become aware of a new and significant difference between these two developmental processes. We cannot get away from the assumption that the sense of guilt stems from the Oedipus complex and was acquired when the brothers banded together and killed the father. On that occasion aggression was not suppressed, but acted out–the same aggression whose suppression in the child is supposed to be the source of his sense of guilt. At this point I should not be surprised if the exasperated reader were to exclaim, 'so it's immaterial whether one kills one's father or not–one acquires a sense of guilt in any case! Here one may take leave to voice a few doubts. Either it is not true that the sense of guilt derives from suppressed aggression, or else the whole story of the killing of the father is a fiction, and primeval children did not kill their fathers any more often than children do today. Besides, if it is not a fiction, but a plausible piece of history, it would be a case of something happening that everybody expects to happen–of someone feeling guilty because he really has done something that cannot be justified. And for such cases, which after all occur every day, psychoanalysis still owes us an explanation.'

This is true, and the matter must be remedied. Nor is there any great mystery about it. If one has a sense of guilt after committing a misdeed, and because one has committed it, this feeling ought rather to be called remorse. It relates only to a deed, although of course it presupposes that before the deed there was already a conscience, a readiness to feel guilty. Such remorse can therefore never help us to discover the origin of conscience and of the sense of guilt generally. What usually happens in these everyday cases is that a need generated by a drive acquires sufficient strength to prevail over a relatively weak conscience and achieve satisfaction; once satisfied, the need is naturally reduced, and the previous balance of forces is restored. Psychoanalysis is therefore right to exclude from the present discussion the case of a sense of guilt that stems from remorse, however common it is and however great its practical importance.

But if man's sense of guilt goes back to the killing of the primeval father, this too was a case of 'remorse'. So should we suppose that conscience and a sense of guilt did not exist before the deed was done? Where did the remorse come from in this case? Undoubtedly this case should clear up the mystery of the sense of guilt and put an end to our embarrassments. And I believe it does. This remorse was the result of the primordial emotional ambivalence towards the father: his sons hated him, but they also loved him. Once their hate was satisfied by this act of aggression, their love manifested itself in the remorse they felt for the deed. Through identification with the father, this love established the super-ego, endowed it with the power of the father–as though to punish the act of aggression committed against him–and invented restrictions that would prevent its repetition. And since aggressivity towards the father recurred in succeeding generations, the sense of guilt remained too, and was reinforced whenever aggression was suppressed and transferred to the super-ego. Now, I think, we can at last grasp two things quite clearly: the part played by love in the emergence of conscience and the fateful inevitability of the sense of guilt. Whether one has killed one's father or refrained from doing so is not really decisive; in either case one is bound to feel guilty, for the sense of guilt is the expression of the conflict of ambivalence, the unending struggle between Eros and the destructive drive, the death drive. This conflict is fanned as soon as people are faced with the task of living together. So long as the family is the only form of communal life, the conflict is bound to express itself in the Oedipus complex, to establish the conscience and to create the primordial sense of guilt. When an attempt is made to extend the community, the conflict is continued in forms that depend on the past; it is reinforced, and leads to an increased sense of guilt. Because civilization obeys an internal erotic impulse that requires it to unite human beings in a tightly knit mass, it can achieve this goal only by constantly reinforcing the sense of guilt. What began in relation to the father is brought to fruition in relation to the mass. If civilization is the necessary trend of development that leads from the family to humanity as a whole, it follows that the intensification of the sense of guilt, perhaps to a degree that the individual finds hard to endure, is indissolubly linked with it, as a consequence of the innate conflict of ambivalence, of the perpetual contention between love and the death-wish. One is reminded of the poet's poignant indictment of the 'heavenly powers':

Ihr führt ins Leben uns hinein,

Ihr lasst den Armen schuldig werden,

Dann überlasst iht ihn der Pein,

Denn jede Schuld rächt sich auf Erden.

[You lead us into life, you let the poor man become guilty, then you deliver him to punishment, for all guilt is avenged on earth.]

And one may well breathe a sigh of relief when one recognizes that it is nevertheless given to a few human beings to produce the most profound insights, more or less effortlessly, from the maelstrom of their own feelings, while we others constantly have to grope our way forward through agonizing insecurity.

————————————————————

* Any perceptive person will understand and take into account the fact that the present synopsis makes sharp distinctions where the real transitions are more gradual, that it is not just a question of the existence of the super-ego, but of its relative strength and its sphere of influence. After all, what has so far been said about conscience and guilt is generally known and hardly disputed.

* The part played by misfortune in the promotion of morality is the subject of a delightful short story by Mark Twain, The first melon I ever stole. This first melon chanced to be unripe. I heard Mark Twain read the story himself. After reading out the title he stopped and asked himself: 'Was it the first?' That said it all: the first was not the only one.

* In Psychoanalyse der Gesamtpers8nlichkeit (1927) Franz Alexander has accurately assessed the two main types of pathogenic methods of upbringing, over-strictness and over-indulgence, in connection with Aichhorn's study of delinquency. The 'excessively soft and indulgent' father will cause a child to form an excessively severe super-ego, because the child, influenced by the love it receives, has no other way of dealing with its aggression than by turning it inwards. In the delinquent who has been brought up without love there is no tension between the ego and the super-ego: all his aggression can be directed outwards. Hence, if one disregards any constitutional factor that may be presumed to exist, one can say that a strict conscience arises from the interplay of two influences on a person's life: the frustration of the drives, which unleashes aggression, and the experience of being loved, which turns this aggression inwards and transfers it to the super-ego.

8

Having reached the end of a road like the present one, the author must beg his readers' forgiveness for not being a more skilful guide and for not sparing them a number of dreary stretches and tiresome detours. It can undoubtedly be done better. I will now try, rather late in the day, to make some amends.

In the first place, I suspect, the readers will have the impression that the discussions of the sense of guilt distort the framework of this essay, in that they take up too much space and push the rest of the content, with which they are not always closely related, to one side. This may have disturbed the structure of the study, but accords entirely with its intention, which is to present the sense of guilt as the most important problem in the development of civilization and to show how the price we pay for cultural progress is a loss of happiness, arising from a heightened sense of guilt.*

Whatever still seems strange about this proposition, the final conclusion of our study, can probably be traced back to the quite peculiar relationship, which still is far from understood, between the sense of guilt and our consciousness. In the common instances of remorse that we regard as normal, the sense of guilt makes itself clearly perceptible to the consciousness; indeed, we often speak of a 'consciousness of guilt' instead of a 'sense of guilt'. From the study of neuroses, to which, after all, we owe the most valuable pointers to an understanding of what is normal, a number of contradictions emerge. In one of these disorders, obsessional neurosis, the sense of guilt forces itself stridently on the consciousness, dominating both the clinical picture and the patient's life, and allowing hardly anything else to appear beside it. In most other forms of neurosis, however, it remains quite unconscious, though the effects it produces are not for that reason any less important. Patients do not believe us when we tell them they have an 'unconscious sense of guilt', and so, to make ourselves to some extent intelligible, we speak of an unconscious need for punishment, in which the sense of guilt expresses itself. How ever, its connection with one form of neurosis should not be overstated, for even in cases of obsessional neurosis there are some types of patient who are unaware of their sense of guilt, or who experience it only as a tormenting malaise, a kind of anxiety, when they are prevented from carrying out certain actions. One day we should be able to understand these things, but at present we cannot. At this point it might be useful to remark that the sense of guilt is fundamentally nothing other than a topical variety of anxiety; in its later phases it merges completely with fear of the super-ego. In the case of anxiety too we find the same extraordinary variations in its relation to consciousness. It is present in some way behind all the symptoms, though sometimes it seizes control of the whole of the consciousness, while at other times it is completely hidden, so that we have to speak of an unconscious anxiety or–if we wish to retain a clear psychological conscience, anxiety being initially only a feeling–of 'possibilities of anxiety'. Hence, it is quite conceivable that even the sense of guilt engendered by civilization is not recognized as such, but remains for the most part unconscious, or manifests itself as an unease, a discontent, for which other motivations are sought. The religions, at least, have never ignored the part that a sense of guilt plays in civilization. Moreover–a point I failed to appreciate earlier–they claim to redeem humanity from this sense of guilt, which they call sin. From the way in which this redemption is achieved in Christianity–through the sacrificial death of one man, who thereby takes upon himself the guilt shared by all–we drew an inference as to what may have been the original occasion for our acquiring this primordial guilt, which also marked the beginning of civilization.

It cannot be very important, though it may not be entirely superfluous, to elucidate the meanings of a few terms such as 'super-ego' , 'conscience' , 'sense of guilt' , 'need for punishment' and 'remorse' , which may often have been used too loosely and interchangeably. They all apply to the same relationship, while denoting different aspects of it. The super-ego is an authority that we postulate, and conscience a function that we ascribe to it, along with others–this function being to supervise and assess the actions and intentions of the ego, to exercise a kind of censorship. The sense of guilt, the harshness of the super-ego, is thus identical with the severity of the conscience; it is the ego's perception of being supervised in this way, its assessment of the tension between its own strivings and the claims of the super-ego. Fear of this critical authority–a fear that underlies the whole relationship and amounts to a need for punishment–is the manifestation of a drive on the part of the ego, which has become masochistic under the influence of the sadistic super-ego and devotes a portion of its inherent drive for internal destruction to establishing an erotic bond with the super-ego. One should not speak of conscience until the super-ego can be shown to exist. As for the sense of guilt, one has to admit that it predates the superego, and therefore the conscience. At this early stage it is a direct manifestation of the fear of external authority, an acknowledgement of the tension between the ego and this authority, a direct derivative of the conflict between the need for its love and the urge for the satisfaction of the drives, the inhibiting of which generates aggressivity. The superimposition of the two layers of the sense of guilt–the one due to fear of the external authority, the other to fear of the intemal authority–has greatly hampered our understanding of the relations that the conscience enters into. Remorse is a general term for the reaction of the ego in cases that involve a sense of guilt; it contains, in largely unaltered form, the emotional material of the anxiety that is at work behind the sense of guilt. It is itself a punishment and may involve the need for punishment. Thus it too may pre-date conscience.

Nor can there be any harm in reviewing the contradictions that have temporarily confused us in the course of our investigation. At one point it was said that the sense of guilt resulted from an act of aggression that had not been carried out, while at another–and precisely at its historical inception, the killing of the father–it was said to derive from one that had been. We managed to find a way out of this difficulty. With the institution of the internal authority, the super-ego, the situation changed radically. Before this, the sense of guilt had been identical with remorse, a term that should properly be reserved for the reaction that follows the acting out of aggression. After this, thanks to the omniscient super-ego, the distinction between intended and fulfilled aggression lost its force. A sense of guilt might now result not only from a violent deed that was actually performed–as everyone knows–but also from one that was merely intended–as psychoanalysis has discovered. Despite the new psychological situation, the conflict of ambivalence between the two primal drives still produces the same effect. There is an obvious temptation to seek here the solution of the problem posed by the varying relation of the sense of guilt to consciousness. A sense of guilt that arises from remorse for an evil deed should always be conscious, whereas one that is prompted by the perception of an evil impulse might remain unconscious. Yet it is not as simple as that: obsessional neurosis emphatically contradicts this view. The second contradiction was that, according to one view, the aggressive energy that we ascribe to the super-ego merely perpetuates the punitive energy of the external authority and preserves it in the mind, whereas according to another view it is one's own unused aggression, directed against this inhibiting authority. The former view seems to accord more with the history, the latter more with the theory of the sense of guilt. Detailed consideration has succeeded almost too well in resolving this apparently irreconcilable contradiction; what remains as the essential common factor is that both involve internalized aggression. Again, clinical observation actually allows us to distinguish between the two sources of aggression that we ascribe to the super-ego, but in any given case either the one or the other may produce the stronger effect, though as a rule they act in concert.

This is, I think, an appropriate place at which to enter a serious plea for a view whose provisional acceptance we recommended a short while back. In the latest analytic literature we find a predilection for the view that the sense of guilt is, or may be, intensified by any kind of frustration–if satisfaction of any drive is thwarted. I think we gain a substantial theoretical simplification if we take this to apply only to the aggressive drives. Little will be found to conflict with this assumption. For how are we to explain, dynamically and economically, a heightening of the sense of guilt that appears when there is an unsatisfied erotic demand? This seems possible, after all, only if we presume a circuitous route–if the prevention of erotic satisfaction provokes aggressivity towards whoever interferes with it, and if this aggressivity then has to be suppressed. But then only the aggression is converted into a sense of guilt by being suppressed and transferred to the super-ego. I am convinced that we shall be able to represent many processes more simply and transparently if the findings of psychoanalysis relating to the origin of the sense of guilt are restricted to the aggressive drives. In this case, examination of the clinical material does not yield an unambiguous answer: in accordance with our hypothesis, the two kinds of drive almost never appear in their pure form, mutually isolated. However, a study of extreme cases will no doubt point in the direction I anticipate. It is tempting to derive an initial advantage from this more restricted view by applying it to the process of repression. As we have discovered, the symptoms of neuroses are essentially substitutive satisfactions for unfulfilled sexual desires. In our analytic work we have been surprised to find that perhaps every neurosis conceals a certain measure of unconscious guilt, and this in turn intensifies the symptoms by using them as a punishment. It now seems plausible to formulate the following proposition: when a drive is repressed, its libidinal elements are converted into symptoms and its aggressive components into a sense of guilt. Even if this thesis only approximates to the truth, it still merits our interest.

Some readers may feel that they have heard the formula of the struggle between Eros and the death drive too often. It was meant to characterize both the cultural process undergone by humanity and the development undergone by the individual; moreover, it was said to have revealed the secret of organic life in general. It seems imperative to investigate how these three processes relate to one another. Now, the recurrence of the formula is justified as soon as one considers that the development of human civilization and the development of the individual are both vital processes and must there fore partake of the nature of life in the most general sense. On the other hand, the very universality of this feature means that proof of its presence is of no help in differentiating these processes, unless it is narrowed down by particular conditions. Hence, we can be content only with the statement that the process of civilization is a special modification of the life process that is under gone by the latter under the influence of a task that is set by Eros at the instigation of Ananke (the exigency of reality)–the task of uniting discrete individuals in a community bound together by libidinal ties. However, if we focus our attention on the relation between the civilization of mankind and the development or upbringing of the individual, we shall conclude, without much hesitation, that the two processes are very similar in kind, if not indeed one and the same process, as it affects different kinds of object. Human civilization naturally belongs to a higher order of abstraction than the development of the individual; it is therefore harder to apprehend in concrete terms, and the search for analogies should not be compulsively pursued to excess. Yet in view of the similarity of the aims–the one being to create a unified mass consisting of many individuals, the other to integrate the individual into such a mass–the similarity of the means used in the two processes and the similarity of the resultant phenomena will come as no surprise. There is one distinction between the two processes that is of such extraordinary significance that it must not remain unmentioned any longer. In the development of the individual, the programme of the pleasure principle, aimed at the attainment of happiness, remains paramount. Integration into a community, or adaptation to it, seems a scarcely avoidable condition; it has to be met if the goal of happiness is to be reached. Perhaps it would be better if this were possible without such a condition. In other words, the development of the individual seems to be a product of the interaction of two trends–the striving for happiness, which we commonly call 'egoistic', and the striving for fellowship within the community, which we call 'altruistic'. Neither term goes much below the surface. In the development of the individual, as we have said, the emphasis falls mostly on the egoistic striving for happiness, while the other process, which we may call 'cultural', is usually content with a restrictive role. In the process of civilization things are different: the aim of forming a unified whole out of individual human beings is all-important. True, the aim of happiness is still present, but it is pushed into the background; it is almost as though the creation of a great human community would be most successful if there were no need for concern with individual happiness. There may thus be particular features in the development of the individual that are not matched in the process of civilization; the former need coincide with the latter only in so far as its aim is to incorporate the individual into the community.

Just as the planet still circles round its sun, yet at the same time rotates on its own axis, so the individual partakes in the development of humanity while making his own way through life. To our dull gaze, however, the play of forces in the heavens seems frozen in a changeless order, while in the field of organic life we can still see how the forces contend with one another, and how the conflict yields ever-changing results. In the same way the two strivings–for individual happiness and for human fellowship–have to contend with each other in every individual; so too the processes of individual and cultural development are bound to come into conflict and dispute each other's territory. But this struggle between the individual and society does not derive from the no doubt irreconcilable antagonism of the primal drives, Eros and death; it indicates a conflict in the economy of the libido, which may be compared with the conflict regarding the distribution of the libido between the ego and its objects. It admits of an eventual accommodation within the individual, such as we may hope for in the future of civilization, however oppressive it may be at present in the life of the individual.

The analogy between the development of civilization and that of the individual can be significantly extended. One can justifiably maintain that the community too evolves a super-ego and that the development of civilization takes place under its influence. Anyone who is conversant with different civilizations may find it tempting to pursue this equation in detail. I will confine myself to drawing attention to a few striking points. The super-ego of a cultural epoch has an origin not unlike that of the individual; it rests upon the impression let behind by the personalities of great leaders, people who were endowed with immense spiritual or intellectual power or in whom some human striving found its strongest and purest, and hence often most one-sided, expression. In many cases the analogy goes even further, in that in their lifetime these figures were quite often, though not always, mocked and abused by others, or even cruelly done to death–just as indeed the primeval father did not attain divinity until long after he was done to death. The most poignant example of this fateful link is the figure of Jesus Christ–unless this figure is mythological and was called into being on the basis of an obscure memory of that primeval event. A further point of agreement is that both the cultural and the individual super-ego make stern ideal demands, and that failure to meet these demands is punished by 'fear of conscience'. Here, indeed, we encounter a curious phenomenon: the relevant mental processes, when seen in the mass, are more familiar, more accessible to our consciousness than they can ever be in the individual. In the individual only the aggression of the super-ego makes itself clearly heard, when tension arises, in the form of reproaches, while the demands themselves often remain unconscious in the background. When brought fully into consciousness, they are seen to coincide with the precepts of the current cultural super-ego. At this point there seems to be a regular cohesion, as it were, between the cultural development of the mass and the personal development of the individual. Some manifestations and properties of the super-ego can thus be recognized more easily by its behaviour in the cultural community than by its behaviour in the individual.

After developing its ideals, the cultural super-ego sets up its demands. Among these, the demands concerned with the mutual relations of human beings are collectively known as ethics. A high value has always been placed on ethics, as though it were expected to perform exceptionally important services. And indeed it does address itself to the subject that is easily recognized as the sorest point in any civilization. Ethics is thus to be viewed as an attempt at therapy, an endeavour to achieve, through a precept of the super-ego, what has not so far been achievable through other cultural activities. As we know, the problem is how to remove the greatest obstacle to civilization, the constitutional propensity of human beings to mutual aggression, and for this very reason we have a special interest in what is probably the most recent commandment of the cultural super-ego: 'Love thy neighbour as thyself'. The study and treatment of neuroses lead us to level two reproaches against the individual super-ego: in the severity of its precepts and prohibitions it shows too little concern for the happiness of the ego, in that it fails to take sufficient account of the forces that oppose compliance with them, the instinctual strength of the id, and the difficulties that prevail in the real environment. For therapeutic purposes we are therefore often obliged to oppose the super-ego and attempt to lower its demands. We can make quite similar objections to the ethical demands of the cultural super-ego. This too is insufficiently concerned with the facts of man's psychical constitution; it issues a commandment without asking whether it can be obeyed. It assumes that it is psychologically possible for the human ego to do whatever is required of it, that the ego has absolute control over the id. This is an error. Even in people who are called normal, control of the id cannot be increased beyond certain limits. To demand more is to provoke the individual to rebellion or neurosis, or to make him unhappy. The commandment 'Love thy neighbour as thyself' is the strongest defence against human aggression and an excellent example of the unpsychological manner in which the cultural super-ego proceeds. It is impossible to keep this commandment; such a huge inflation of love can only lower its value, not remove the problem. Civilization neglects all this; it reminds us only that the harder it is to comply with a precept, the more merit there is in compliance. Yet in today's civilization, whoever adheres to such a precept puts himself at a disadvantage in relation to all who lout it. How potent an obstacle to civilization aggression must be if the defence against it can cause as much unhappiness as the aggression itself! In this situation, what we call natural ethics has nothing to offer but the narcissistic satisfaction of being able to think one is better than others. This is where ethics based on religion enters the scene with its promises of a better life hereafter. I am inclined to think that, for as long as virtue goes unrewarded here below, ethics will preach in vain. I have no doubt, too, that a real change in people's relations to property will be of more help here than any ethical commandment; yet the recognition of this fact among socialists has been obscured and made impracticable by a new idealistic misreading of human nature.

An approach that tries to trace the role of a super-ego in the phenomena of cultural development seems to me to promise further discoveries. I must hasten to a close, but there is still one question I can hardly avoid. If the development of civilization so much resembles that of the individual and operates with the same means, is one not entitled to proffer the diagnosis that some civilizations or cultural epochs–possibly the whole of humanity–have become 'neurotic' under the influence of cultural strivings? The analytic dissection of these neuroses might be followed up by suggestions for therapy that would merit great interest. I could not say that such an attempt to apply psychoanalysis to the cultural community would be absurd or doomed to futility. But one would have to be very cautious, remembering that one was dealing only with analogies, and that with concepts, as with human beings, it is dangerous to wrench them out of the sphere in which they originated and have evolved. Moreover, the diagnosis of communal neuroses comes up against a special difficulty: in the individual neurosis the first clue we have is the contrast between the patient and his supposedly normal environment. When it comes to a mass of individuals, all affected by the same condition, no such background is present; it would have to be borrowed from elsewhere. And as for the therapeutic application of the knowledge one obtained, of what use would even the most apposite analysis orasocial neurosis be, if no one had the authority to force the mass to undergo treatment? Yet despite all these difficulties we may be fairly sure that one day somebody will venture upon such a pathological study of cultural communities.

For a variety of reasons I have no wish whatever to offer an evaluation of human civilization. I have been careful to refrain from the enthusiastic prejudice that sees our civilization as the most precious thing we possess or can acquire, and believes that its path will necessarily lead us to heights of perfection hitherto undreamt of. I can at least listen, without bridling, to the critic who thinks that, considering the goals of cultural endeavour and the means it employs, one is bound to conclude that the whole effort is not worth the trouble and can only result in a state of affairs that the individual is bound to find intolerable. My impartiality is facilitated by my scant knowledge of such matters. There is only one thing that I know for certain: the value judgements of human beings are undoubtedly guided by their desire for happiness and thus amount to an attempt to back up their illusions with arguments. I should understand perfectly if someone were to stress the inevitability of human civilization and maintain, for instance, that the tendency to restrict sexual life, or to promote the humanitarian ideal at the expense of natural selection, were trends that could not be averted or deflected and that it was best to yield to them as if they were naturally ordained. On the other hand, I am familiar with the objection that in the course of human history such strivings, which we consider insurmountable, have often been cast aside and replaced by others. I therefore dare not set myself up as a prophet vis-à-vis my fellow men, and I plead guilty to the reproach that I cannot bring them any consolation, which is fundamentally what they all demand, the wildest revolutionaries no less passionately than the most well-behaved and pious believers.

The fateful question for the human race seems to be whether, and to what extent, the development of its civilization will manage to overcome the disturbance of communal life caused by the human drive for aggression and self-destruction. Perhaps in this context the present age is worthy of special interest. Human beings have made such strides in controlling the forces of nature that, with the help of these forces, they will have no difficulty in exterminating one another, down to the last man. They know this, and it is this knowledge that accounts for much of their present disquiet, unhappiness and anxiety. And now it is to be expected that the other of the two 'heavenly powers', immortal Eros, will try to assert himself in the struggle with his equally immortal adversary. But who can foresee the outcome?

————————————————————

* 'Thus conscience doth make cowards of us all…' That a modem upbringing conceals from the young person the role that sexuality will play in his life is not the only criticism that must be levelled against it. Another of its sins is that it does not prepare him for the aggression of which he is destined to be the object. To send the young out into life with such a false psychological orientation is like equipping people who are setting out on a polar expedition with summer clothes and maps of the North Italian lakes. This reveals a certain misuse of ethical demands. The severity of these would do little harm if the educators said, 'This is how people ought to be if they are to be happy and make others happy, but one must reckon with their not being like this.' Instead, the young person is led to believe that everyone else complies with these ethical precepts and is therefore virtuous. This is the basis of the requirement that he too should become virtuous.

译者导读

勒内·笛卡尔（René Descartes，1596—1650），生于法国安德尔-卢瓦尔省的图赖讷拉海（现名为笛卡尔，因笛卡尔得名），是法国著名的哲学家、数学家、物理学家。他对现代数学的发展作出了重要的贡献，因将几何坐标体系公式化而被认为是解析几何之父。他还是西方现代哲学思想的奠基人，是近代唯物论的开拓者且提出了“普遍怀疑”的主张。他的哲学思想深深影响了之后的几代欧洲人，开拓了所谓“欧陆理性主义”哲学。

笛卡尔的著名作品之一是《沉思录》。笛卡尔把《方法导论》中所描述的哲学再加以发挥，撰写成《第一哲学沉思》（Meditationes des primapilosophia）。为了慎重起见，他将手稿的样本分寄给当时著名的神学家和哲学家，以征求他们的意见。该书的对象是学术界的人士，用拉丁文写成，全名为《形而上学沉思，证明天主实有及灵魂的不死不减》（Meditationes de prima philosophia in quibus Deiexistentia et animae humanoe immertalitas demonstrantur）。笛卡尔将学者的疑难和自己的答辩一并附在书中于1641年出版，被后人称为《沉思录》。该书是笛卡尔的成熟之作，成为研究他的哲学思想的主要资料。

《沉思录》分为两部分，第一部分是笛卡尔对怀疑、人类的精神、上帝的存在、真理和错误、物质性东西以及灵魂和肉体的区别等六个问题的沉思。

第二部分是笛卡尔自己收集起来的反驳和他对这些反驳的答辩，字里行间展示了笛卡尔哲学的有趣之处。他十分留心被普遍接受的大量错误的概念，决定要达到恢复真理的目的，就需从零开始做起。因此开始怀疑老师教给他的一切，包括所有最崇高的信仰，所有的常识观念，甚至外部世界的存在，连同自己的存在。

第一组反驳是由荷兰神学家卡特鲁斯提出的，他把自己的回答送给麦尔塞纳，希望他收集其他人的意见。结果，以麦尔塞纳为首的一批神学家向他提出了第二组反驳。第三组反驳是由英国哲学家霍布斯提出的。第四组反驳是杨森主义者阿尔诺提出的。第五组反驳是原子论者伽森狄提出的一长篇反驳，并且后来对笛卡尔的回答也作了反驳。第六组反驳是由麦尔塞纳集合起来的一批哲学家、几何学家和神学家们提出的。这些反驳之音和笛卡尔本人的答辩实际上是欧洲近代第一次公开的、直接的哲学论战。它们对于了解笛卡尔的哲学思想有着十分重要的意义。

前言

我在《谈引导理性和探求真理的方法》（以下简称《谈方法》）一书中曾简单探讨过有关上帝和人的头脑的问题。该书是于1637年用法文出版的。当时我无意深入探讨这两个问题，只是简单地介绍了一番，为的是从读者的反应中了解该如何展开进一步的探讨。我一向认为这两个问题非常重要，应该不止一次地去探讨；而在解释这两个问题上，我采取的方式又很新奇，不同于往常，因此我认为在一本法文书里详细探讨这两个问题，也没什么帮助，因为大家都能看懂，以免天赋不如我的人会以为他们应该效仿这一做法。

在《谈方法》里，我曾请凡是在我的书里看出什么值得反驳之处的人，费心把这些地方告诉我，但是，关于我书中谈到的问题，只有两点异议值得一提。我想在确切地解释这两点异议以前，简短地介绍下异议的内容。

第一个异议是：人类大脑反思自身，把自身看作思维之物，但不能由此推断大脑的本性或实质仅仅在于它是思维之物，“仅仅”这一词就把其他凡是有可能说得上也是属于灵魂的东西都排除掉了。我对这个异议的回答是：在那种情况下，我并不想按照问题的实质（因为那时我还没有谈到问题的实质），而仅仅是按照我自己的思路，把它们排除了。所以，我的意思是：我除了只知道我是一个在思维之物，或者说我是一个具有思维能力的东西之外，我那时还没发现有什么东西是属于我的本质的。不过接下来，我将指出我是怎么从我不知道别的什么东西属于我的本质这个事实，推断出事实上并没有什么别的东西是属于我的本质的。

第二个异议是：从我心里有一个比我完满的东西的观念这个事实不能得出结论说这个观念比我完满，更不能说这个观念所代表的东西存在。我的回答是：“观念”这个词在这里的意思是模棱两可的。它一方面可以被理解为实质性的，它本身是我的理智的一种活动，在这个意义上，不能说观念比我完满。或者，它可以被理解成意向性的，是观念所代表的事物，即使不能认定这个事物存在于我的理智之外，但就它的本质而言，它却可以比我完满。然而如何仅仅从我心里有比我完满的一个东西的观念这件事，就推断出这个事物的真实存在，接下来我将具体说明。

除了这两个异议以外，我还看到两篇长篇大论的文章。这两篇文章用无神论者的共同论点攻击我的结论，而不是攻击我所作的推理。由于这一类论据对于能正确理解我的观点的人不能产生什么影响，同时也由于很多人的判断违背常理，愚昧不堪，他们宁愿相信对事物先入为主的看法，不管这种看法有多么不正确、多么不合道理，也不愿相信后来才了解到的反驳，尽管反驳很准确而且真实可靠。在这里我不想对这些异议进行答辩，以免成为第一个解答这些异议的人。我想简要地说，所有由无神论者提出的反对上帝存在的东西，或者是因为错误地把人类的感情归因于上帝，或者就是自以为掌握了强大的能力和高妙的智慧，这样我们就能决定和了解上帝能做什么或者应该做什么了。因此，只要我们知道我们人类的头脑被认为是有限的，而上帝却被认为是无限的，不能被掌握的，他们的观点就不会给我们带来任何困难了。

现在，在理解了大家的意见之后，我再重新回到关于上帝和人的头脑的问题，同时也回到整个第一哲学的开端，但我既不希求普遍的认可，也不希求大量的读者。事实上，除非人们愿意并且能够和我一起进行严肃认真的沉思并且能够使思维脱离感官和偏见，我绝不劝人们读我的书，同时我也知道这样的读者为数不多。至于那些不屑于考虑我的论据的逻辑和内在联系并经常断章取义的人，他们读了我的书也不会从中获益。尽管他们也许会找到机会对很多地方吹毛求疵，但他们也不可能轻易就提出意义重大，值得回应的反驳观点来。

然而，我甚至不能保证使这些剩下的读者们在初次阅读我的书时，能在方方面面都满意，我也不会自大地认为我能够预见到读者们所面临的所有问题。因而，我将在《沉思录》里首先阐明，正是按照这种想法，我终于认识了一些显明的真理，以便试试看我是否也能通过同样的理由让别人相信这个真理。在此之后，我再对那些博学多才的人提出的异议进行答辩。《沉思录》在出版前就寄给他们作评论了。他们提出了那么多各种各样的异议，我敢说别的人很难再提出什么更重要、没有涉及的反驳了。因此，我想重申，请读者们在费心看过所有那些异议和我对那些异议所作的答辩之后，再对《沉思录》这本书作出判断。

六个沉思之总结

第一个沉思指出，我们有理由怀疑一切，特别是物质性的东西，因为除了在科学里现有的那些根据之外，还找不出别的根据。虽然这种普遍怀疑的益处在初期阶段还不很明显，不过，它可以让我们摆脱各种各样的成见，给我们提供一条让灵魂脱离感官影响的捷径，并且最终让我们对后来发现的真实事物绝不可能再有什么怀疑，这对我们来说是非常重要的。

在第二个沉思里，只要对事物的存在有一点点怀疑，头脑就可以自由地假定它们都不存在，不过绝不能认为它自身在那段时间是不存在的。这也是很有益的，因为头脑用这个办法很容易把属于它自身的东西，也就是属于理智性的东西，与属于物质性的东西区分开来。

但是，既然有些读者可能会希望在这部分找到我对灵魂不灭的论证，我应该立刻警告他们，凡是我不能严格论证的东西，我是决不会写进书中的。所以，我不得不采用几何学家所使用的方法：先提出求证的命题的全部根据，然后再下结论。那么，在认识灵魂不灭之前，首要之务是形成关于灵魂的清晰的概念，这个概念要完全有别于有关物体的一切概念，这一点在《沉思录》中已经做到了。除此以外，还要求知道我们清楚、分明领会的一切东西本来就是按照我们所领会的那样都是真实的。这在第四个沉思以前还没有能够论证。另外，物质性质还必须有一个清楚的概念，这个概念一部分见于第二个沉思里，一部分见于第五个和第六个沉思里。应该从这一切里得出一个结论：凡是被清楚、分明地领会为不同实体性的东西，就如领会头脑和身体那样，实际上都是互相有别的：我在第六个沉思中作出了这个结论。在这个沉思中还证实了一点：我们把一切身体都领会为是可分割的，相比而言，头脑只能被领会为是不可分割的。我们不能领会半个头脑的概念，而我们却能够领会哪怕是最小的身体部分。所以头脑和身体在性质上不仅不同，甚至在某种意义上是相反的。

不过我没有在这本书里更进一步谈这个问题，一方面因为这些阐述足以说明灵魂不会随着肉体的腐烂而灭亡，因此也足够给人们第二次生命的希望；同时也因为我们可以由之而推论出灵魂不灭首先取决于整个物理学界的解释。首先要知道的是，一切实体，也就是说，事物要想生存，必须被上帝创造，从本性来说，无一例外，它们是不可毁灭的，除非是创造它们的上帝终止存续，要把它们消灭掉，否则它们就永远存在。其次，我们要了解的是，从一般的意义来说，物体是一种实体，因此它也是永远不灭的；但是人的肉体，就其有别于其他物体这一点来说，它不过是由一些肢体和其他类似的一些多变的特点组合成的；而人的大脑不是像这样由多变的特点组合而成，它是一种单纯的实体，即使多变的特点发生变化，它也能领会不同的东西，希求不同的东西，感觉不同的东西，等等，因此，精神是不变的；而人的肉体，仅仅由于它的某些部分的形状改变，它就不再是同一肉体了。由此可见人的肉体可能确实很容易死灭，但是精神，从它的本性来说，是不灭的。

在第三个沉思里，我认为我相当详尽地解释了我的主要论点以证明上帝的存在。不过为了尽量地让读者的精神从感官摆脱出来，我不想用物质性的东西进行比较，因而也许还留有很多模糊不清的地方，对于这些模糊不清的地方，之后，我会在对反驳所作的答辩中将其澄清。比如在众多反驳中有这样一个反驳，在我们心里的一个至上完满的存在体的观念怎么会包含那么多的意图上的实在性，以致它必然应当来自一个至上完满的原因，这是相当难以理解的。在答辩里，我用了一个完美的机器作为类比来说明，这个机器的观念存在于某一个设计者的心里。这个观念的精巧必然有某个原因，那就是设计者的学识，或者从别人身上学的知识，因此同样道理，在我们心里上帝的观念的形成也是有一定原因的，而这个原因就是上帝自己。

在第四个沉思里，凡是我们领会得非常清楚、分明的东西，都被证明是真的；同时我也解释了错误的本质；为了证实以前的观点，也为了更好地理解以后的，以上两点是我们必须知晓的。（同时需要指出的是：我在这里讨论的不是罪恶，换言之，就是在追求善恶之间所犯的错误，我在这里仅仅论述在分辨真假时所产生的错误；我也不打算涉及宗教信仰，或是日常行为方面的东西，而是只涉及理论上的真理，这些真理只有借助于自然之光才能为我们所认识。）

除了解释一般意义上的物质性，第五个沉思运用了新论断来论证上帝的存在，这里可能也会产生一些困难，但是这些困难我将在对异议所作的答辩里去解决。最后，在某种意义上，几何学论证的正确性本身取决于对上帝的认识这一观点是正确的。

最后，在第六个沉思中，我把理性和想象加以区分；并解释了这种区分的标准；证实了人的灵魂确实有别于肉体，却又和肉体紧密结合，形成一个整体；评估了由感官产生的一些错误；提出了避免错误的办法；最后介绍了可能推理出物质存在的各种理由。我认为这些论据对于证明它们已经证明的东西没有什么用，也就是说，确实有一个世界，人有肉体以及诸如此类的事情，这些都是任何一个正常人从来没有怀疑过的。然而，通过思考这些论据，对于上帝和我们的灵魂的认识问题，它们显然就没有那么清晰和有说服力了。因而，我们在精神上对上帝和我们的灵魂的认识理由是最可靠、最明显的理由。我在这六个沉思中唯一的目的就是证明这一点。因此，我在这里不再回顾其他很多问题，关于那些问题，我在《沉思录》里也讨论过了。

第一哲学沉思录

论上帝的存在和人的灵魂与

肉体之间的区别

第一个沉思

论可以怀疑的事物

几年前，我注意到，在幼年时期，我就把一大堆错误的事物当作真相了，并且根据这些错误的事物所建立起来的东西是多么不可靠。因此我曾一度认为，如果我想要在科学领域建立起某种坚定可靠、经久不变的东西，我就得把我历来信以为真的一切东西全部颠覆，再从最基本的东西重新开始。可是这个任务对我来说好像太大了，我也一直等待我能够到达一个成熟的年纪，在那个再合适不过的年纪完成这个任务。因此，我已经等得太久，从现在起，如果再不把我的余生用来展开工程，光是考虑来考虑去的话，那我就该受到责备。所以现在，我恰当地将思绪从一切顾虑中解放出来，安排一段时间使自己免于干扰，我要独自在尽可能长的时间里认真地、自由地来对我的旧见解进行一次总的清算。

可是，为了达到这个目的，没有必要去证明我的旧见解都是错误的——这可能是我永远完不成的工作。不过，理性使我们相信对于那些不是完全确定无疑的东西，我们不应该轻易相信，就像不要相信那些显然是错误的东西一样，如果我找到可以怀疑我的观念的理由，那就足以使我把它们全盘否定。然而，不需要把它们拿来一个个地检查了，因为那将会是一件没完没了的工作。只要根基被破坏，在此基础上建立的东西就自然而然地随之而倒塌，所以我要首先质疑全部旧见解依靠的首要原则。

直到现在，凡是我当作最真实的东西，都是我从感官或通过感官得来的。不过，我有时觉得这些感官欺骗了我；为了小心谨慎起见，对于骗过我们的东西，哪怕就只有一次，也决不加以信任。

可是，虽然感官有时在细微的或遥远的东西上骗过我们，但是也许有很多别的东西，我们绝对不能怀疑，即使它们是来自感官；比如，我在这里，坐在炉火旁边，穿着室内长袍，两只手上拿着这张纸，以及诸如此类的事情。说真的，我怎么能否认这两只手和这个身体是属于我的呢，除非我认为自己和那些让坏脾气冲昏头脑的疯子有些相似？他们穷得叮当响，却以为自己是国王；他们一丝不挂，却以为自己身披黄袍；或者他们的脑袋是陶器做的、是空罐子，或者他们就是用玻璃做的。但是这些人是一群疯子，如果我也和他们做一样的事儿，我就和他们一样疯癫了。

很好。但是我不是一个习惯于晚上睡觉并在梦中做跟疯子一样的事的人，有时，甚至比疯子醒着时做出的事更荒唐。有多少次夜晚的平静使我相信熟悉的事物，比如，我夜里梦见我在这个地方，穿着衣服，在炉火旁边，虽然我是一丝不挂地躺在我的被窝里睡觉！但是，我现在确实用我瞪大的眼睛看到这张纸，我摇晃着的脑袋也并没有发昏，我故意小心地伸出这只手，感受这只手，睡梦中的人是不会感受到如此清晰的事物的。我在其他场合睡觉时也被类似的思想欺骗过。想到这里，我就明显地看到没有什么相当可靠的迹象使人能够分辨出清醒和睡梦来，这不禁使我大吃一惊，吃惊到几乎能够让我相信我现在是在睡觉。

那么让我们就假定我们是睡着了，假定所有这些情况，比如我睁开眼睛，摇晃脑袋，伸出手来等等，都是不真实的；让我们设想我们甚至没有这样的手以及整个身体。但是我们必须承认，出现在我们梦里的那些东西就像某些熟悉的影像，它们只有模仿某种真实的东西才能被描绘。因此，至少那些一般的东西，比如眼睛、脑袋、手，以及整个身体，并不是想象出来的东西，而是真的、存在的东西。即使当画家们努力想象出最奇特的人鱼和人羊，他们也不能给它们加上完全新奇的性质，他们不过是把不同动物的肢体掺和拼凑起来。就算他们偶然想出什么新奇的东西，新奇到我们连类似的东西都没有看见过，从而让他们的作品表现出一种虚构的和错误的东西来，然而，至少他们绘画所用的颜色总应该是真实的吧。同样道理，就算这些一般的东西，例如眼睛、脑袋、手，以及诸如此类的东西都是幻想出来的，可是总得承认，至少一些其他的东西是真实的，它们更简单、更一般，由于这些东西的掺杂，不多不少正像某些真实的颜色掺和起来一样，就形成了存在于我们思维中的东西的一切形象，不管这些东西是真实的，还是虚构的。一般的物理性质和它的广延，以及具有广延性东西的形状、量或大小和数目都属于这一类东西；还有这些东西所处的地点、所占的时间，以及诸如此类的东西。

因此，我们从以上所说的这些将作出这样的结论也许是不会错的：物理学、天文学、医学，以及研究各种复合事物的其他一切科学都是可疑的；而算术、几何学，以及类似的其他科学，由于它们所对待的都不过是一些非常简单、非常一般的东西，不大考虑这些东西是否存在于自然界中，因而反而都含有某种确定无疑的东西。因为，不管我醒着还是睡着，二和三加在一起总是得五，正方形总不会有四个以上的边；像这样明显的一些真理，是不会让人怀疑的。

虽然如此，很久以来我心里就有一种想法：有一个上帝，他是全能的，就是由他把我现在自己喜欢的这个样子创造出来的。虽然上帝绝对没有创造天、地，没有创造带有广延性的物体，没有创造形状、大小和地点，可是，我怎么知道他仍然让人感觉这些东西似乎将按照现在的样子存在着。还有，就像别人甚至在他们以为知道得最准确的事情上弄错一样，也可能是上帝有意让我每次在二加三上，或者在数一个正方形的边上，或者在判断什么更容易的东西（如果人们可以想出来比这更容易的东西的话）上弄错。但是，也许上帝不允许我被如此欺骗，因为他被人说成是至善的。尽管如此，如果说把我做成这样，让我总是弄错，这是和他的善良性相抵触的话，那么允许我有时弄错好像也是和他的善良相异的，但是我不能这样断言。

这里也许有人宁愿否认一个如此强大的上帝的存在而不去相信其他一切事物都是不确定的。不过我们目前还不要去反对他们，让我们假定上面所说的凡是关于一个上帝的话都是无稽之谈。假定我现在的境况要归于某种命运或宿命，或者归之于偶然，或者连续的事件抑或其他希望的方式。既然失误和弄错是一种不完满，那么肯定的是，他们给我的来源所指定的作者越是无能，我就越可能是不完满，以致我总是弄错。对于这样的一些论证，我无可答辩；但是最后我不得不承认，凡是我早先的信仰，没有一个是我现在不能怀疑的，这绝不是由于考虑不周或轻率，而是由于强有力的、经过深思熟虑的理由。因此，假如我想要找到确然可信的东西的话，我今后就不应该赞同这些信仰，就像对待那些明显错误的东西一样。

但是，仅仅知道这些还不够，我还必须把它们记住；因为这些旧的、平常的见解经常回到我的思维中来，它们跟我长时期相处的亲密习惯给了它们权利，让它们不由我的意愿而占据了我的心，差不多成了支配我的信念的主人。只要我把它们按照它们的实际情况那样来加以考虑，即像我刚才指出的那样，它们在某种方式上是可疑的，然而却是十分可能的，因而人们有更多的理由去相信它们而不去否认它们，那么我就永远不能把承认和信任它们的习惯破除。就是因为这个缘故，我想，如果我反过来千方百计地来骗我自己，假装所有这些见解都是错误的、幻想出来的，直到在把我的这些成见反复加以衡量之后，使它们不致让我的主义偏向这一边或那一边，使我的判断今后不致为坏习惯所左右，不致舍弃可以导向认识真理的正路反而误入歧途，那我就做得更加慎重了。因为我知道这既不能产生危险，也不能造成错误，并且我不能夸大我的谨慎，因为现在的问题不在于行动，而仅仅在于认识。

因此，我要假定有某一个妖怪，而不是一个真正的上帝（他是真理的源泉），这个妖怪强大而狡猾，他用尽了力量来骗我。我要认为天、空气、地、颜色、形状、声音以及我们所看到的一切外界事物都不过是邪恶的精灵用来骗取我轻信的一些假象。我要把我自己看成是本来就没有手，没有眼睛，没有肉，没有血，什么感官都没有，但是，好像我对这些东西的信念都是错误的。我要坚决地保持这种想法；如果用这个办法我还认识不了什么真理，那么至少我将做我能做的。也就是说，我要小心翼翼，不去相信任何错误的东西，不让骗子强加给我任何东西，不管他多么强大，多么狡诈。可是，这个打算是非常艰苦吃力的，而且某一种惰性使我不知不觉地又回到我日常的生活方式中来。我就像一个囚犯，在睡梦中享受一种虚构的自由，而且随后开始怀疑他是真的睡了而害怕醒来时，他就和这些愉快的幻象串通起来。与此同时，我自己也不知不觉地重新掉进原先的信念中去，我害怕从这种迷迷糊糊的状态中清醒过来，害怕在这个休息的恬静之后随之而来的是辛勤工作，我生活的未来没有光明，反而在刚刚讨论过的无法摆脱这些难题的黑暗中。

第二个沉思

论人的精神的本性以及

精神比物体更容易认识

昨天的沉思给我带来了如此严峻的困难，以至于我今后再也不能把它们忘掉。可是我却看不出能用什么办法来解决它们；我就好像一下子掉进非常深的漩涡里似的，惊慌失措得既不能让脚在水底站稳，也不能游上来让自己浮在水面。虽然如此，我将努力沿着我昨天已经走上的道路继续前进，再次检验同一个策略，躲开我能够想象出有一点点可疑的什么东西，就好像我知道它是绝对错误的一样。我还要在这条路上一直走下去，直到我碰到什么可靠的东西，或者，至少直到我确实知道在世界上就没有什么可靠的东西时为止。为了移动地球，阿基米德要寻找一个固定的支点。同样的，如果我有幸找到一件确切无疑的小事物，那么我就可以心怀更大的希望了。

因此我假定凡是我看见的东西都是假的。我相信，虚假记忆所代表的东西从来都没有存在过。我认为我没有感官，物体、形状、广延、运动和地点都是不真实的。除了世界上根本就没有什么可靠的东西外，也许再也没有别的了。

可是我怎么知道除了我刚才断定为不可靠的那些东西外，没有我们不能丝毫怀疑的什么别的东西呢？难道就没有上帝，或者什么别的力量，把这些想法放在我心里吗？当我自己也许就能够产生这些想法时？我为什么要这样想？那么至少我，难道我不是什么东西吗？可是我已经否认了我有感官和身体。尽管如此，我犹豫了，因为从这方面会得出什么结论来呢？难道我就是非依靠身体和感官不可，没有它们就不能生存吗？可是我曾说服我自己相信世界上什么都没有，没有天，没有地，没有精神，也没有物体；难道连我也不存在吗？然而，我确实存在，如果我曾说服我自己相信什么东西。可是有一个我不知道是什么的非常强大、狡猾的骗子，他总是用尽一切伎俩来骗我。因此，如果他骗我，那么毫无疑问我是存在的；而且他想怎么骗我就怎么骗我，只要我想到我是一个什么东西，他就总不会使我成为什么都不是。所以，在对每件事很好地加以思考后，最后必须作出这样的结论，而且必须把它当成确定无疑的，即“有我，我存在”这个命题，每次当我说出它来，或者在心里想到它的时候，这个命题必然是真的。

可是我还不大清楚，这个确实存在的我到底是什么，所以今后我必须小心，不要冒冒失失地把别的什么东西当成我，同时也不要在我认为比我以前所有的一切认识都更可靠、更明显的这个认识上弄错了。就是为了这个缘故，所以在我有上述这些想法之前，先要重新考虑我从前认为我是什么；并且要把凡是可以被我刚才讲的那些理由所削弱的东西，全部从我的旧见解中铲除出去，让剩下来的东西恰好是完全确定和不可动摇的。

那么我以前认为我是什么呢？毫无疑问，我是一个人。可是人是什么呢？我想说是一个有理性的动物吗？当然不；因为在这以后，下面的问题就会随之产生：什么是动物，什么是有理性的？这样一来我就将要从仅仅一个问题上不知不觉地陷入两个更困难的问题中去了，而我没有太多的闲暇浪费在像这样的一些细节上。可是，无论什么时候我思考我是什么，我都会思考从前在我心里自然生发出来的那些思想，我过去常常首先想到的是我有脸、手、胳臂，以及肢体组合成的这么一架整套机器，就像从一具尸体上看到的那样，这架机器，我曾称之为身体。我还曾想到我吃饭、走路、感觉、思维，并且我把我所有这些行动都归到灵魂上去；但是我还没有细想这个灵魂到底是什么；或者说，我把它想成未知的东西，它是那么微妙，好像一阵风，一股火焰，或者一股气，这个东西钻进我身体可以看见的部分里。至于物体，我决不怀疑它；我曾以为我把它的性质认识得非常清楚了，并且如果我试着描述我是如何构思它的，我就会这样解释它：物体，我是指一切能为某种形状所限定的东西；它能限制在某个地方，能充满一个空间，在那里，其他任何物体都被排挤出去；它能由触觉、视觉、听觉、味觉，或者嗅觉而被感觉到；它能以若干方式被移动，不过不是靠它自己移动，而是被接触它的东西所推动。因为我认为靠自己移动，无论如何都不属于物体的本性，像本身有自动、感觉和思维等能力的这样一些优越性，事实上，看到像这样一些功能出现在某些物体之中，我倒是非常奇怪的。

可是，现在我假定有某一个极其强大，并且如果可以这样说的话，极其恶毒、狡诈的人，他用尽他的力量和机智来骗我，那么我到底是什么呢？我能够说我具有一点点我刚才归之于物质的本质的那些东西吗？我在这上面进一步细想，在心里把这些东西想来想去，我没有找到其中任何一个是我可以说存在于心里的。重复这个过程而且像以前一样不能取得成功让人感觉很累。就拿灵魂的那些属性来说吧，首先两个是吃饭和走路。既然我真是没有身体，我也就真是既不能走路，也不能吃饭；另外一个是感觉，可是没有身体就不能感觉，除非是我以为以前我在梦中感觉到了很多东西，可是醒来之后我认出实际上并没有感觉。另外是思维。对，就是思维，现在我觉得思维是唯一不能跟我分开的。有我，我存在这是靠得住的，可是，多长时间？我思维多长时间，就存在多长时间。因为假如我停止思维，也许很可能我就同时停止了存在。我现在对不是必然真实的东西一概不接受，因此，严格来说，我只是一个在思维的东西，也就是说，一个精神，一个灵魂，一个理智，或者一个理性，这些名称的意义是我以前不知道的。那么我是一个真实的东西，真正存在着。可是，是一个什么样的东西呢？我说过：是一个在思维的东西。

还是什么呢？我想象，我不是由肢体拼凑起来的被称之为人体的那种东西；我不是一种稀薄、渗透到所有这些肢体里的空气；我不是风，不是火，不是水汽或呼气，也不是我所能想象出来的任何东西，因为我假定过这些都是不存在的。即使这个假定站得住脚，我仍然是一个东西。可是，能不能是这样的：由于我不认识而假定不存在的那些东西，同我所认识的我并没有什么不同？我一点也不知道。关于这一点我现在不去讨论，我只能对我认识的那些东西作判断：我已经认识到我存在着，现在我追问，我已经认识的这个我究竟是谁？可是关于我自己的认识，严格来说既不取决于我还不知道其存在的那些东西，也不取决于任何一个用想象虚构出来的东西，这一点我是非常确定的。“虚构”这个词让我警醒我的错误。因为，如果我把我想象成一个什么东西，那么实际上我就是在虚构了，因为想象只是去深思一个物质性东西的形状或影像。然而，我已经确实知道了我存在着，同时也确实知道了所有那些影像，一般说来，凡是人们归之于物质本质的东西都很可能不过是梦罢了。其次，我意识到，如果我说我要发动想象力以便更清楚地认识我是谁，这和我说我现在是醒着，我看到某种实在和真实的东西，但是由于我看得还不够明白，我要故意睡着，好让我的梦给我把它更真实、更明显地提供出来一样，是同样不合道理的。这样一来，我认识到，凡是我能用想象的办法来理解的东西，都和我对自己的认识无关；认识到，要让精神把它的性质认识得十分清楚，那么就要让精神远离这些东西。

那么我究竟是什么呢？是一个在思维的东西。什么是一个在思维的东西呢？那就是说，一个在怀疑、在领会、在肯定、在否定、在愿意、在不愿意，也在想象、在感觉的东西。当然，如果所有这些东西都适用于我，那就不算少了。可是，为什么这些东西不属于我的本性呢？难道我不是几乎什么都怀疑，然而却了解某些东西，确认和肯定只有这些东西是真实的，否认一切别的东西，希望认识得更多一些，不愿意受骗，想象除自身之外的很多东西，并且注意到很多东西，好像这些东西来自感官。难道所有这一切就没有一件是和我一样，确实存在、同样真实的，尽管我总是睡觉，尽管使我存在的那个人用尽他所有的力量来骗我？这些东西里哪些是同我的思维有分别的，或者可以说是同我自己分得开的呢？因为事情本来是如此明显，是我在怀疑，在了解，在希望，没有什么比这更明显。事实上，我有能力去想象；因为即使可能出现这种情况（就像我以前曾经假定的那样），即我所想象的那些东西不是真的，可是这种想象的能力本身真实存在着，并且是我思维的一部分。因此，我就是那个在感觉事物，或者说，好像是通过感觉器官注意事物的东西；比如说，我已经看见了光，听到了声音，感到了热。这些现象是假的，因为我是在睡觉。可是，我确实似乎看见了，听见了，热了，这总是千真万确的吧；严格地说，这就是我心里叫作在感觉的东西，而在确切的意义上，这就是在思维。

从这里我就开始更清楚地认识了我是什么。可是，我似乎对于其影像是在我的思维中形成的、落于感官的那些有物质性的东西，比不落于想象的未知的自我认识得更清楚，虽然我认为可疑的、未知的、我以外的一些东西倒被我认识得比那些真实的、已知的、属于我自己本性的东西更明白、更容易，这实际上是一件非常奇怪的事情。不过我看出了这是怎么回事：我的精神喜欢漫游，还不能把自己限制在真理的界限之内。就让它这样吧，允许它再一次完全不受约束，这样一来，不久以后，当再一次对它强加限制时，我们就能够更容易地驾驭它了。

让我们考虑一下那些被普遍认为是我们了解得最清楚的东西，也就是我们摸到、看见的物体吧。我不是指一般意义上的物体——因为这种一般概念通常是比较模糊的，而是考虑一下一个特殊物体。以一块刚从蜂房里取出来的蜡为例：它还没有失去蜜的甜味，还保存着一点它从花里采来的香气；它的颜色、形状、大小是明显的；它是硬的、凉的、容易摸的，如果你敲它一下，它就发出一点声音。总之，凡是能够使人清楚地认识一个物体的东西，在这里边都有。可是，正如我说的，有人把它拿到火旁边：剩下的味道发散了，香气消失了，它的颜色变了，它的形状和原来不一样了，它的体积增大了，它变成液体了，变热了，摸不得了。尽管敲它，它再也发不出声音了。在发生了这个变化之后，原来的蜡就不存在了吗？必须承认它还继续存在；而且对这一点，任何人不能否认，没有人会往其他方面想。

那么以前在这块蜡上认识得那么清楚的是什么呢？当然不可能是通过感官所感到的什么东西，因为凡是落于味觉、嗅觉、视觉、触觉、听觉的东西都改变了，不过本来的蜡还继续存在。也许是我现在所想的这个东西，也就是蜡本身，并不是蜜的甜味，不是这种花的香味，不是这种白的颜色，也不是这种形状，不是这种声音，而仅仅是一个刚才在那些形式之下表现而现在又在另外一些形式之下表现的物体。可是，确切说来，我想象的这个东西是什么呢？让我们集中注意力，把凡是不属于蜡的东西都去掉，看一看还剩些什么。当然剩下的只有延伸的、有伸缩性的、可以变动的东西。那么“有伸缩性的”“可以变动的”是指什么的？是不是我想象这块圆的蜡可以变成方的，可以从方的变成三角形的？不是这样。因为我理解它为可能接受无数像这样的改变，即使我不能用我的想象来一个个地认识无数的改变，因此这种理解不是来自于想象的能力。那么这个“广延”是什么意思呢？它不也是未知的吗？因为在蜡融化的时候它就开始增大，在蜡完全融化的时候它就变大了，而当热度再增加时它就变得更大了。如果我没有想到蜡能够在延伸中呈现更多的花样，多到出乎我的想象，我就不能正确地判断什么是蜡了。所以我必须承认我甚至连用想象都不能领会这块蜡是什么，只有我的理智才能够领会它。我说的是这块特别的蜡，至于一般的蜡，那就更明显了。那么只有精神才能领会的这个蜡是什么呢？它就是我看见的、摸到的、想象的那块蜡，就是我一开始认识的那块蜡。可是，要注意的是，感知，不是看，不是摸，也不是想象，从来不是，虽然它从前好像是这样，但是它仅仅是用精神去察看，这种察看可以是片面的、模糊的，像它以前那样，或者是清楚的、分明的，像它现在这样，这取决于我对组成它的那些东西注意的多少。

与此同时，我的精神是多么趋向于错误，我自己也觉得非常奇怪。因为即使我不言不语地在自己心里考虑这一切，我仍局限于这些语言上，几乎被普通言语所欺骗；因为如果人们把原来的蜡拿给我们，我们说我们看见蜡，而不是从颜色和形状上就判断这就是那块蜡。从这里，假如不是我从窗口看街上过路的人，并且说我看见了一些人，就如同说我看见蜡一样，那么我几乎就要断定说：人们认识蜡是用眼睛看，而不是光用精神去观察。可是我从窗口看见了什么呢？无非是一些帽子和大衣，而帽子和大衣遮盖下的可能是一些机器人。不过我判断这是一些真实的人，这样，单凭我心里的判断能力就了解了我以为是我眼睛看见的东西。

一个人要想对事物有更好的超出一般水平的认识，就应该把怀疑一般人说话的形式这件事当成可耻的事。让我们继续去考虑：我最初看到的，用外感官，或至少像他们说的那样，用常识，也就是说用想象力的办法来领会的蜡是什么，是否比我现在对它的领会更清楚、更完善呢？还是在经过认真调查它是什么及怎样认识它后，更好地认识它了呢？当然，连这个都怀疑起来，那是可笑的。因为在这初步的知觉里有什么是清楚、明显的，它包括什么不能明显落于最差的动物的感官里的东西吗？可是，当我把蜡从它的外表分离出来，把它看作似乎是赤裸裸的，没穿衣服的那样，当然，尽管我的判断里还可能存在某些错误，但，如果没有人的精神，我就不能正确理解蜡这个事物。

可是，关于这个精神，也就是说关于我自己，因为直到现在除了我是一个精神之外，我什么都不承认，我将要作何解释呢？我想说的是，关于好像那么清楚分明地领会了这块蜡的这个我，我将要说什么呢？我对我自己认识得难道不是更加真实、确切而且更加清楚、分明吗？因为，如果由于我看见蜡而断定蜡存在，那么由于我看见蜡因此有我存在这件事当然也就越发明显，因为，有可能我所看见的实际上并不是蜡；也有可能我连看东西的眼睛都没有；可是，当我看见或者当我想是看见（这是我不再加以区别的）的时候，这个在思维着的我倒不是个什么东西，这是不可能的。同样，如果由于我摸到了蜡而断定它存在，由此也可以推断我存在着；如果由我的想象或其他理由使我相信而断定它存在，我也总是得出同样的结论。我在这里所注意到的关于蜡的东西也适用于外在于我、在我以外的其他一切东西上。而且，如果说蜡在不仅经过视觉或触觉，同时也经过很多别的原因而被发现了之后，我对它的概念和认识好像是更加清楚、更加分明了，那么，我不是应该越发分明地认识我自己了吗？因为一切用以认识和领会蜡或别的物体的理由都更好地构建了我的精神的本性。但是，精神上也有许多别的东西，借助这些东西可以更分明地理解精神。别的东西如此之多，以至于不值得去考虑由身体到精神所散发的那些东西。

可是，我终于无助地回到了我原来想要回到的地方；现在我知道，我们只是通过精神，而不是通过感官或想象能力来领会物体，而且我们不是由于看见了它，或者摸到了它才认识它，而只是由于我们用思维领会它，那么显然我认识了对我来说没有什么比我的精神更容易认识的东西了。可是，因为几乎不可能这么快就破除一个旧见解；因此，我最好在这里暂时打住，以便经过这么长的沉思之后，把这一个新的认识深深地印到我的记忆中去。

第三个沉思

论上帝的存在

现在我要闭上眼睛，堵上耳朵，关闭我的一切感官，我甚至要把一切物质性的东西的影像都从思维里排除出去，但因为这么做是不可能的，所以或者至少我要把它们看作是无关紧要的，是假的和无意义的，这样一来，我就可以只和自己交流，更深入地理解我的内心世界。我要试着进一步了解、认识我自己。我是一个在思维的东西，这就是说，这个东西在怀疑、在肯定、在否定，知道的东西很少、不知道的很多，在愿意、在不愿意，也在想象、在感觉。就像我刚才说过的那样，即使我所感觉和想象的东西也许并不存在，我确实知道我称之为感觉和想象的这种思维方式，就其仅仅是思维方式来说，一定是存在和出现在我心里的。虽然只是寥寥数语，可是我认为已经把我真正知道的东西，或至少是直到现在觉得我知道了的东西，全部都说出来了。

现在我要更仔细地考虑一下在我心里是否也许还有我没有意识到的其他的东西。我确信我是一个思维着的东西，但是我不是因此也就知道了我需要具备什么，才能使我确实知道什么事情吗？在这个初步的认识里，只有我说的这个清楚、明了的认识。老实说，假如我用这种方法认识得如此清楚、分明的东西竟是假的，那么这个认识就不足以使我确实知道某些东西。从而，似乎我可以把“凡是我们领会得十分清楚、十分分明的东西都是真实的”这一条定为总则。

虽然如此，我以前认为非常清楚、分明而接受的东西，后来我又都认为是可疑的。那些东西是什么呢？是地、天、星辰，以及那些通过我的感官所感到的其他东西。可是，我在这些东西里边曾领会得清楚、明白的是什么呢？当然不是别的，正是那些东西在我心里的观念或思维。并且现在我还不否认这些观念是在我心里。可是还有另外一件事情是我知道的，我甚至认为我之所以清楚地感知它是因为我相信它，然而，事实上，我并没有看出它，即有些东西在我以外，这些观念就是从那里发生的，并且和那些东西一模一样。我就是在这件事情上弄错了，或者，假如说我判断正确，那也绝不是由于我的感知能力。

可是，当我考虑数学和几何学中某种十分简单、十分容易的东西，比如“三加二等于五”诸如此类的其他事情的时候，我不至少也是把它们领会得清清楚楚，确定它们是真的吗？当然，假如从那以后，我认为可以对这些东西产生怀疑的话，那一定不是由于别的理由，而只是因我心里产生这样一种想法，即也许是某位上帝，他给了我这样的本性，让我甚至在我觉得通过亲眼看得最清楚的一些东西上弄错。但是每当这个上帝至高无上的能力的想法出现在我脑海里时，我都不得不承认，如果他愿意，他就很容易使我甚至在我认为自己认识得非常清楚的东西上弄错。从另一个方面来说，每当我回到自以为已经认识得十分清楚的东西上时，我对这些东西又是深信不疑，使我自己不由自主地说：让我被任何能欺骗我的人欺骗吧，但是，只要我认为我是什么东西，我就不会什么都不是；或者既然现在我存在这件事是真的，那么我没有存在过这种事就不可能是真的；他也绝不能使三加二之和多于五或少于五，或者诸如此类的事情，我都看作是自相矛盾的。既然我没有任何理由相信上帝是骗子，事实上，我不知道上帝是否存在，那么仅仅依赖于这个见解之上的怀疑理由当然是非常轻率的，并且，我要说，是形而上学的。可是，为了尽快排除这个理由，我应该检查一下上帝是否存在；如果他存在，我也应检查一下他是否是骗子。只要这是未知的，我就看不出我能够把任何一件事情当作是可靠的。

现在，我必须在这里把我的全部思维分为几类，必须考虑哪些包含真理，哪些包含错误。有的思维就像事物的影像，“观念”这个词只适用于这类东西：比如我想起什么人、怪物、天空、天使，或者上帝本身。然而，另外一些思维有另外的形式，比如当我希望、我害怕、我肯定、我否定时，我总是把某种东西领会为我精神的主体，但是我把某些东西加到我的观念上，不仅仅是考虑中的东西的那些类似物。属于这一类思维的有些叫作意志或情感，另外一些叫作判断。

至于观念，如果只就其本身而不把它们牵涉到别的东西上去，严格说来，它们不能是假的；因为不管我想象一只山羊或一个怪物，在我想象上同样都是真实的。同样，也无须害怕在情感或意志里边会有虚假的东西；因为，即使我可以选择一些坏事情，或者甚至一些不存在的事情，但是不能因此就说我选择它们这件事就是假的。这样一来，就只需要判断了，而在判断这个阶段我应该小心谨慎以免弄错。在判断里可能出现的重要错误在于我认为我心里的观念判断和在我以外的一些东西一样或相似；因为，如果我把观念仅仅看成是我的思维的某些方式，并且不把它们牵涉到别的什么东西上去，这样我也不能弄错了。

在这些观念里，我认为有些观念是与生俱来的，有些是习得的，有些是由我自己捏造的。我这种能理解一个东西，一个真理，或一种思想的能力似乎是仅仅出自我的本性；但是，直到现在我认为，如果我现在听见了什么声音，看见了太阳，感觉到了热，这些感觉都是来自我以外的什么东西；最后，我觉得人鱼、马鹫以及诸如此类的其他一切怪物都是由我捏造出来的。可是也许我可以相信所有这些观念都是外来的，或者是天生的，或者它们都是由我捏造的；因为我还没有清楚地发现它们的真正来源。

我现在要问的主要问题是有关我认为来自于我以外的对象的观念，也就是说，有哪些理由使我相信这些观念和考虑中的东西是一样的。一方面我觉得这是自然告诉我的；而另一方面是我自己体会到这些观念是不以我的意志为转移的，因此，也不依赖我，因为它们时常违背我的意志出现。比如现在，不管我愿意也罢，不愿意也罢，我感觉到了热，而由于这个原因我认为热这种感觉或这种观念是由于一种不同于我的东西，即由于我旁边的火炉的热。除了判断这个外来东西不是把什么别的，而是把它的影像送出来印到我心里以外，我看不出有什么我认为更合理的了。

现在我必须看一看这些理由是否真的令人信服。当我说我觉得这是自然告诉我的，自然这一词所指的仅仅是某种即兴冲动使我相信这个事情，而不是某种自然理性使我认识这个事情是真的。这二者之间的区别很大，因为对于自然理性使我看到的事，我是一点都不用怀疑，就像从我怀疑这件事，就能够推论出我存在，以及类似的事情。因为没有另一种能力让我信任就像信任理性之光一样，并且能够告诉我结论是不真实的。对照而言，过去我经常认为，在善恶之间进行选择时，冲动使我走错方向，我不认为，在其他情况下，我应该更信任这种冲动。

然而，即使这些观念不以我的意志为转移，也不能证明它们必然是从别处来的。因为我刚才所说的那些冲动是在我心里，尽管它们不总是和我的意志一致，同样，也许是我心里有什么其他能力我还没有充分意识到，并且这些能力是观念的来源，直到现在，对我来说好像当我睡觉的时候，这些观念也在我心里形成而不依靠于它们所表现的对象。

最后，即使它们是由我之外的东西引起的，也不能因此就说它们一定应该和那些我之外的对象一样。事实上，在很多事例上我经常看到它们之间有很大的不同。比如对于太阳，我觉得我心里有两种截然不同的观念：一种是来源于感官的，应该放在我前面所说的来自外面的那一类里；根据这个观念，我觉得它非常小。另外一个源自天文学推理，也就是说，从我与生俱来的某些概念里得出来的，或者是由我自己无论用什么方法制造出来的，根据这个观念，我觉得太阳比整个地球大很多倍。我对太阳所领会的这两个观念当然不能都和存在于我之外的太阳一样，理性使我相信直接来自它的外表的那个观念是和它最不一样的。

所有这些足以使我认识，我曾经相信有些在我之外的东西通过我的感官，或者用随便什么别的方法，把它们的观念或影像传送给我，这都不是可靠的判断，而仅仅是从一种盲目的冲动得出来的。

然而还有另外一种途径可以用来考虑一下，是否我心里的观点有一部分是在我之外存在的，比如，如果把这些观念看作只不过是思维的某些方式，那么我就认不出在它们之间有什么不同，都好像是以同样的方式由我产生的。可是，如果把一种观念看作是代表一个东西，其他观念又是代表其他的东西，那么显然它们彼此之间是非常不同的。因为的确，对我来说，代表实体的那些观念，无疑比仅仅代表样式或非本质的那些观念更多一点什么东西，并且本身包含着更多刻意的实在性。再者，我由之而体会到一个至高无上的、永恒的、无限的、不变的、全知的、全能的、他自己以外的一切事物的普遍创造者的上帝的那个观念，无疑在他本身里包含比代表有限的实体的那些观念更多的客观实在性。

现在，从自然理性的角度出发可以明显地得出，在充分的总的原因里一定至少在它的结果里有更多的实在性：因为结果如果不从它的原因里，那么能从哪里取得它的实在性呢？这个原因如果本身没有实在性，怎么能够把它传给它的结果呢？由此可见，不仅无中不能生有，同样地，也不能生出比较完满的东西，换句话说，本身包含更多实在性的东西，也不能是由比较不完满的东西制成的。这个真理无论是在现实的或形式的那种实在性的结果里，或者是在具有客观实在性的观念里，都是清楚、明显的。例如：从来都没有存在过的石头，如果它不是由一个东西所产生，那个东西本身形式地或深入地具有进入石头的组织中的一切，那么石头现在就不能开始存在；同样地，热如果不是由在等级上、程度上，或者种类上至少是和它一样完满的一个东西产生，就不能在一个以前没有热的物体中产生。其他的东西也是这样。此外，热的观念或者石头的观念如果不是由于一个本身包含至少和我在热或者石头里所领会的同样多的实在性的什么原因把它放在我的心里，它也就不可能在我心里。虽然那个原因不能把它们现实的或形式的实在性的任何东西传授到我的观念里，但是不应该因此就想象那个原因不那么实在；因为观念的真实性是这样的，所以它的本性使它除了它从思维或精神所借过来的那种形式的实在性以外，自然不要求别的形式的实在性，而观念只是思维或精神的一个样态。一个观念之所以包含这样一个而不包含那样一个客观实在性，这无疑是来自什么原因，在这个原因里的形式实在性至少同这个观念所包含的客观实在性一样多。因为如果我们设想在观念里有它的原因里所没有的东西，那么这个东西就一定是从无中来的。然而一种东西，用它的观念而存在于理智之中的这种存在方式，不管它是多么不完满，总不能说它不存在，因而也不能说这个观念来源于虚无。

虽然我在我的观念里所考虑的实在性仅仅是客观的，我也不应该怀疑实在性会必然形式地存在于产生我的观念的原因里，也不应该认为这种实在性客观地存在于观念的原因里就够了；因为，正和这种存在方式是由于观念的本性而客观地属于观念一样，存在方式也由于观念的本性而形式地属于这些观念的原因，至少是属于观念的最原始、主要的原因。而且即使一个观念有可能产生另一个观念，可是这种现象也不可能是无穷无尽的，它最终必须达到一个第一观念，这个第一观念的原因就像一个样本或原型一样，在它里面包含着只存在于观念中的形式上的事实。这样，自然理性使我明显地看出，观念在我心里就像一些绘画或者图像一样，它们可能很容易减少衍生出它们的那些东西的完满性，却不能包含比自身更完满的东西。

越是深入地、仔细地考察所有这些事物，我就越是清楚、明白地看出它们是真的。不过最后我从这里得出什么结论来呢？这就是：如果我的某一个观念的客观实在性使我清楚地认识到它既不是形式地，也不是卓越地存在于我，从而我自己不可能是它的原因，那么结果必然是在世界上并不是只有我一个人，而是还有别的什么东西存在，它就是这个观念的原因；另外，如果这样的观念不存在于我，我就没有任何论据能够使我确实知道除了自己以外就没有任何别的东西存在；因为，我曾经仔细地寻找过，可是直到现在也没有找到任何别的论据。

在所有这些观念之中，除了代表我自己的那个观念在这里不可能有任何问题以外，还有一个代表上帝的观念，另外的一些代表物质性的、无生命的东西的观念，以及其他一些代表动物，最后，还有一些观念代表着和我一样的人。

至于代表其他的人，动物，或者天使的那些观念，我容易理解到它们是可以由我关于自己和物质性的东西，以及上帝所具有的其他一些观念混合而成的，尽管除了我以外，世界上根本就没有其他的人，没有动物，没有天使。

至于物质性的东西的观念，我并不认为在它们里边有什么大得不得了的东西使我觉得它们不是由我自己产生的。因为，如果我再仔细地考虑它们并且一个一个地检查它们，就像昨天考察蜡的观念那样，我注意到在那里只有很少的东西是我领会得清清楚楚的，比如大小或者长、宽、厚的广延；用这种广延的这几个词和界限形成的形状；不同形状形成的各个物体之间所保持的地位，以及这种地位的运动或变化；还可以加上实体、时间和数目。至于别的东西，像光、颜色、声音、气味、味道、热、冷，以及落于触觉的其他一些性质，它们在我的思维里边是那么模糊不清，我简直不知道它们到底是真的还是假的，也就是说，不知道我对于性质所领会的观念到底是不是什么实在东西的观念。

虽然我以前提出过，严格意义上的虚假或真正的虚假，只能出现在判断中，即当观念把什么都不是的东西表象为是什么东西的时候就会有物质上的虚假。比如，我对于冷的观念和热的观念很不清楚，也不太明白，以致按照它们的办法我不能分辨出到底是冷缺少热呢，还是热缺少冷，或者二者都是实在的性质，或者都不是；既然没有任何一个观念似乎不给我们展示什么东西，如果说冷实际上不过是缺少热，那么当作实在的、肯定的什么东西代表的观念就不应该不恰当地被叫作假的，其他类似的观念也一样；我当然没有必要把它们归之于别人而不归之于我自己。因为，如果它们确实是假的，就是说，它们并不代表的东西，那么自然的光明使我看出它们产生于无，也就是说它们之所以在我心里只是由于我的本性缺少什么东西，因为它并不是非常完满的。即使这些观念是真的，但它们所代表的实在性少到我甚至不能清楚地把它从虚无中分辨出来，那么我也看不出有什么理由使它们不能由我自己产生的。

至于我脑子里有关物质性的东西的一些清晰的观念，有些似乎是我能够从我自己的观念中得出来的，比如说，和我具有的实体的观念、时间的观念、数目的观念，以及诸如此类的其他东西的观念都是那样得来的。因为，我想到石头是一个实体，也就是说，一个本身有能力存在的东西，想到我是一个实体，虽然我领会得很清楚我是一个在思维着的而不能延展的东西，相反石头是一个可以延展而不能思维的东西，这样，在这两个概念之间有着明显的不同，可是，无论如何它们在表象实体这一点上似乎是一致的。同样，我想到我现在存在，并且除此之外我记得我从前也存在，我领会许多不同的思想，认识到这些思想的数目，在这时候我就在我心里得到时间和数目的观念，从此我就可以把这两种观念随心所欲地传给其他一切东西。至于物质性的东西的观念由之而形成的其他一些性质，即广延、形状、地位、变动等，它们固然不是形式地存在于我心里，因为我不过只是一个在思维的东西；然而，由于这仅仅是实体的某些样态，而且我自己也是一个实体，因此，它们似乎是能够真正地包含在我心里。

因而只剩下上帝的观念了，在这个观念里边，必须考虑一下是否有什么东西是能够来源于我自己的。用上帝这个名称，我是指一个无限的实体，它是不依存于别的东西的、至上明智的、无所不能的，依靠它我自己和其他一切存在之物（如果其他一切之物存在的话）得以被创造。这些观点我越认真考虑，就越不相信它们能够单独地来源于我。因此，从上面所说的一切中，必然得出上帝存在这一结论；虽然实体的观念在我心里就是由于我是一个实体，不过我是一个有限的东西，因而我不能有一个无限的实体的观念，除非这个观念来自于一个真正无限的实体。

我不应该想象我不是通过一个真正的观念，而仅仅是通过有限的东西的否定来领会无限的，就像我通过动和光明的否定来理解静和黑暗那样；因为相反，我明显地看到在无限的实体里边比在一个有限的实体里边具有更多的实在性，因此在我心里以某种方式首先有的是无限的概念而不是有限的概念，也就是说，首先有的是上帝的概念而不是我自己的概念。因为，假如在我心里我不是有一个比我的存在更完满的存在的观念，不是由于同那个存在体作了比较我才会看出我的本性的缺陷的话，我怎么可能认识到我怀疑和我希望，也就是说，我认识到我缺少什么东西，我不是完满无缺的呢？

不能说这个上帝的观念也许实质上是假的，因此可能是从无中得出它来的，就像我以前观察关于热和冷的观念以及诸如此类的其他东西的观念时所说的那样；相反，因为这个观念是非常清楚、非常明白的，它本身比任何别的观念都含有更多的客观实在性，所以自然没有一个观念比它更真实，能够更少被人怀疑为错的和假的了。我说，这个无上完满的、无限的存在体的观念是完全真实的。因为，虽然也许可以设想这样的一个存在体是不存在的，可是不能设想它的观念不给我表象任何实在的东西，就像我之前关于冷的讨论那样。这个观念也是非常清楚、非常明白的，因为凡是我的精神清楚明白地领会为实在和真实的，并且本身含有什么完满性的东西，都完全包含在这个观念里边了。虽然我不理解无限，或者虽然在上帝里边有我所不能理解的、也许用思维绝对不能达到的无数事物，这都无碍于上面所说的这个事实是真的；因为我的本性是有限的，不能理解无限，这是由于无限的本性的缘故；只要我很好地领会这个道理，把凡是我领会得清清楚楚的东西，其中我知道有什么完满性，也许还有无数的其他完满性是我不知道的，都断定为形式地或卓越地存在于上帝里边，使我对上帝所具有的观念在我心里的一切观念中是最真实、最清楚、最明白的就够了。

可是也许我自身是比我自己所理解的更伟大一些，也许我身上归之于上帝本性的完满性是以某种方式潜在于我心中，虽然它们还没有出现，还没有以行动表现出来。事实上，我已经体验到我的认识逐渐增长，我看不出有什么能够阻止它越来越向无限方面增长。还有，既然我的知识获得增长，我看不出有什么阻止我按照这个办法获得上帝本性的其他一切完满性。最后，我也看不出这些完满性的能力（如果我已经具有的话）不足以产生相应的观念。

但是，这都是不可能的。因为，首先，即使我的认识真是每天都取得一些进步，我的本性里真是有很多潜在的东西还没有实现，可是所有这些优点绝对不属于，也不接近我具有的上帝的观念，因为在上帝的观念里，没有仅仅是潜在的东西，全部是现实存在的、实在的东西。甚至这一特征（逐渐增加）是对不完善的一个非常肯定的论述。而且，即使我的认识总是逐渐增加，但是我仍然认为它不可能达到无穷无尽，因为它永远不能达到一个不能再有所增加的那样高度的完满性。可是我把上帝看作是无限的，以至于在他所具有的至高无上的完满性上再也不能有所增加。最后，我清清楚楚地理解了这件事情：一个观念的客观的存在体不能由一个仅仅是潜在的存在而产生——这样的存在真正来说是没有的，它只能由一个形式的或现实的存在体产生。

对于愿意用理性思维仔细思考我上面所说的话的人，没有什么东西不是显而易见的；可是，当我把注意力稍一放松，我的精神的眼睛就被感性东西的影像遮蔽起来，我就不容易记得我对于比我的存在体更完满的一个存在体所具有的观念为什么应该必然地被一个实际上更完满的存在体放在我的心里。这就是为什么我现在放下别的，只考虑具有上帝的这个观念的我自己，如果在没有上帝的情况下，我能不能存在。

我想要问：我是何时从谁那里得到我的存在呢？也许从我自己，或者从我的父母，或者从不如上帝完满的事物中得到我自己的存在；因为不能想象有比上帝更完满，或者和上帝一样完满的东西。

但是，如果是我自己创造了我的存在，我一定就会无惧无求，我也一定不缺少任何东西；因为，凡是在我心里有什么观念的东西，我自己都会给我，这样一来我就是上帝了。我不应该想象我缺少的东西也许比我已经有的东西更难取得；相反，也就认为我，也就是说，一个在思维的东西或实体，是从无中生出来的，这无疑地要比我去认识那些我不知道的、只不过是这个实体的一些偶性的很多东西要难得多。而这样一来，毫无疑问，如果我自己给了我的比我刚才说的更多，即如果我自己创造了我的产生和存在，那么我至少不会缺少比较容易取得的东西，即至少不会缺少我领会上帝的观念中所含有的任何东西，因为那些东西里边没有一件是我觉得更难取得的；如果有一种更难取得的东西，它一定会向我表现出来（假定我自己是我所具有的其他一切东西的来源的话），因为我会体验到我的能力只是停留于此。

我可以假定我过去也许一直是像我现在这样存在，我不会否认这个推理的效力，这样一来我就会接着假定没有必要探究到底是什么创造了我的存在。因为我的全部生存时间可以分为无数部分，而每一部分都绝对不依靠其余部分，这样，从不久以前我曾经存在过这件事上并不能得出我现在一定存在这一结论来，假如不是在这个时候有什么原因重新产生我，创造我，也就是说保存我。事实上，这对于凡是要仔细考虑时间的性质的人都是非常清楚的：即一个实体，为了在它延续的一切时刻里被保存下来，需要同一的能力和同一的行动，这种行动是为了重新产生它和创造它所必要的，如果它还没有存在的话。因此，通过理性之光，我清楚地认识到，保存和创造只是从我们的思想方法上来看才显得不同，而从事实上来看两者并没有什么区别。

所以，我现在应该问我自己，我是否具有什么能力使现在存在的我将来还存在，因为，既然我无非是一个在思维的东西（或者至少既然一直到现在严格说来问题还只在于我自己的这一部分），如果我有这样的一种力量，我一定会毋庸置疑地意识到它。可是，我没有体会到任何这样的力量，因此我明显地认识到我依存于一个和我不同的什么存在体。

然而，也许我所依存的这个存在体并不是上帝，也许我是由我的父母，或者由不如上帝完满的什么其他原因产生的。不，不可能是这样。正如我以前已经说过的，显然在原因里一定至少和在它的结果里有一样多的实在性。因此，既然我是一个在思维的、心里怀有上帝的东西，不管最后归之于我的本性的原因是什么，必须承认它一定同样地是一个在思维的东西，本身具有我归之于上帝本性的一切完满性的观念。然后人们可以重新追问这个原因，它的存在是由于它本身呢，还是由于别的什么东西？如果是由于它本身，那么根据我以前说过的，其结果一定是上帝自己，因为它有了通过本身而存在的能力，那么它无疑地也一定有能力现实地具有它所领会的观念的一切完满性，也就是说，我所领会的是上帝里边的一切完满性。如果它的存在是由于它本身以外的什么原因，那么可以根据同样的道理重新再问：这第二个原因是由于它本身而存在的呢，还是由于别的什么东西而存在的？这样一步一步地，最终问到一个最后原因，这最后原因就是上帝。很明显，在这上面再无穷无尽地追问下去是没有用的，因为问题在这里不在于从前产生我的原因上，而在于现在保存我的原因上。

当然，也不能假定也许我的产生是由于很多原因共同的作用，我从这一个原因接受了我归之于上帝的那些完满性之一的观念，从另外一个原因接受了另外什么的观念，那样一来，所有这些完满性即使真的都存在于宇宙的什么地方，可是不能都结合在一起存在于一个唯一的地方，即上帝之中。相反的，上帝里边的一切东西的统一性，或单纯性，或不可分性，是我对上帝所领会的主要完满性之一；而上帝的一切完满性的各种统一和集合的观念一定不可能是由任何一个原因（由于这个原因，我同时也接受了其他一切完满性的观念）放在我心里的。因为，如果这个原因不让我同时知道它们是什么，它就不能让我把它们理解为联结在一起的、不可分的。

至于我的父母，关于他们，即使我过去所相信的都是真的，可是这并不等于是他们保存了我，也不等于他们把我做成是一个在思维的东西，因为他们不过是把某些部件放在这个物质里，而我在这个物质里发现了现在的我，也就是说，我的精神，我现在只把精神当作了我自己；所以关于他们，在这里是毫无问题的；可是必然得出这样的结论，即我存在和我心里有一个至上完满的存在体的观念，也就是说上帝也存在着这个事实，是非常明显的。

我只剩下去检查一下我是用什么方法获得了这个观念的。因为我不是通过感官把它接受过来的，而且它也从来不像可感知东西的观念那样，因为在可感知东西侵犯或者似乎侵犯我的外部器官。它也不是纯粹由我虚构出来的，因为很明显，我没有能力在上面加减任何东西。因此，可以说它和我自己的观念一样，是从我被创造那时起我与生俱来的。

如果上帝在创造我的时候把这个观念放在我心里，就如同工匠把标记刻印在他的作品上一样；这个标记也不必一定和这个作品有所不同。可是，只就上帝创造我这一点来说，非常可信的是，他是有些按照他的形象产生的我，对这个形象（里面包含有上帝的观念），我是用我领会自己的那个功能去领会的，换句话说，当我对自己进行反省的时候，我不仅认识到我是一个不完满、依存于别人的东西，这个东西不停地希望比我更好、更伟大的东西，而且我同时也认识到我所依存的那个别人，在他本身里边具有我所希求的、在我心里有其观念的一切伟大的东西，不是不确定地、仅仅潜在地，而是实际地、现实地、无限地具有这些东西，而这样一来，他就是上帝。我在这里用来证明上帝存在的论据，它的全部效果就在于我认识到，假如上帝真不存在，我的本性就不可能是这个样子，也就是说，我不可能在我心里有一个上帝的观念；我再说一遍，恰恰是这个上帝，我在我的心里有其观念，也就是说，他具有所有这些高尚的完满性，对于这些完满性我们心里尽管有什么轻微的观念，却不能全部理解。他不可能有任何缺点；凡是标志着什么不完满性的东西，他都没有。这就足以明显地说明他不能是骗子，因为理智的自然之光告诉我们，欺骗必然是由于什么缺点而来的。

不过，在我把这件事更仔细地进行检查并对人们能够从其中取得的其他真理进行考虑之前，我认为最好是停下来一些时间专去深思这个完满无缺的上帝，思考一下他的属性，至少尽我的可以说是为之神眩目夺的、精神的全部能力去深思、赞美、崇爱这个灿烂的光辉之无与伦比的美。因为，信仰告诉我们，来世的至高无上的幸福就在于对上帝的这种深思之中，这样，我们从现在起就体验出，像这样的一个沉思，尽管它在完满程度上差得太远，却使我们感受到我们在此世所能感受到的最大满足。

第四个沉思

论真理和错误

这几天我已经慢慢习惯于把我的精神从感官里独立出来，同时我也认识到对于物质性的东西的认识有很少是准确的，我们所认识的更多的东西是关于人的精神和关于上帝本身的，这样，我现在就毫无困难地把我的思维从考虑可感觉或可想象的东西上转到考虑完全脱离物质、纯粹精神的东西上去。关于人的精神，我对它有一个非常清晰的概念，既然它是一个在思维的东西，一个没有长、宽、厚的延展性，不着一点物质性的东西，我的这个观念当然比任何物质性的东西的观念都要清楚。而且当我考虑到我怀疑，也就是说我是一个不完全的、依存于别人的东西的时候，在我心里就十分清楚明白地出现了一个完全的、不依存于别人的存在体的观念，也就是上帝的观念。单从这个观念存在于我心里，或者具有这个观念的我是存在的这件事来看，我可以清楚地得出上帝是存在的，而且我所存在的每时每刻都依赖于上帝的存在，这个结论是如此得清晰明了，所以我认为不能有什么能比这件事更明确、更可靠地为人们所认识的了。因此，我觉得我已经发现了一条道路，上帝里边包含着科学和智慧的全部宝藏，通过对真实的上帝的沉思，我们能够认识宇宙间的其他事物。

因为，首先，我认识到它绝对不能骗我，因为凡是欺骗都包含着某种不完满性；尽管能够欺骗他人好像标志着什么机智和能力，但是想要欺骗他人却无疑是恶意和愚蠢的证明。因此，上帝绝对不会包含欺骗。

其次，我认识到在我自己的心里有某一种判断力，这种能力和我所具有的其他一切东西一样，无疑是我从上帝那里获得的。而且，因为上帝不想骗我，所以他肯定没有给我那样的一种判断力，让我在正当使用它的时候总是弄错。

因此，假如不是从这里得出我永远不会弄错的结论的话，那么对这个真理就再没有可怀疑的地方了；因为，如果凡是我所有的东西都是来自上帝的，如果他没有给我能够犯错的能力，那么就应该说，我决不应该弄错。当我单单想到上帝，并且将思绪集中在上帝身上的时候，我在心里并没发现什么错或假的原因；可是后来当我回到我自己身上来的时候，我发现还是会犯无数错误的。而在仔细寻找产生这些错误的原因时，我注意到在我的思维中不仅出现一个实在的、肯定的上帝观念，或者说一个至上完满的存在体的观念，同时我的思维中也存在一个，姑且这样说吧，一个否定的虚无观念，也就是说与各种类型的完满性完全相反的观念；而我好像就是介乎上帝与这虚无之间，也就是说，我被放在至上存在体和非有存在体之间，就我是由一个至上存在体产生的而言，在我心里实在说来没有什么东西能够引导我犯错；但是，如果我是以某种方式由虚无或者非存在体构成的，也就是说，由于我自己并不是至上存在体，我处于一种无限缺陷的状态中，因此我会犯错误，这也没有什么可奇怪的了。这样一来，我认识到，错误就其作为错误而言，不取决于上帝，也不是真实的东西，而仅仅是一种缺陷，从而对于犯错误来说，我不需要有上帝专门为这个目的而给我什么能力，而是我之所以有时会犯错误，是由于上帝给予我分辨真和假的能力是有限的。

虽然如此，我对这个解释却不能完全满意；因为，错误并不是一种纯粹的否定，而是我缺少了我应该具备的某些知识。在当我考虑上帝的本质时，如果说他给了我某种不完满的，也就是说，缺少什么必不可少的完满性的功能的话，我认为这是不可能的；因为，工匠越是精巧熟练，从他的手里做出来的活计就越是完满无缺，这件事如果是真的，那么我们可以想象世间万物至高无上的创造者所产生的东西，有哪一种在其各个部分上不是完满、完全精巧的呢？当然，毫无疑问，上帝没有能把我创造得永远不能犯错；同时毫无疑问地上帝总是要呈现最好的东西。那么犯错相比起不犯错对我更有好处吗？

仔细考虑了一下之后，我首先想到的是，我理解不了为什么上帝做了某些事情，这我倒也不必为此而感到奇怪；同样的，我也没有任何理由因为我经历一些事情而不能理解上帝为什么以及怎样产生了它们，而怀疑上帝的存在。既然已经知道了我的本性是极其软弱、极其有限的，而相反的，上帝的本性是广大无垠、深不可测的，我再也用不着费事就看出他的潜能里有无穷无尽的东西，因为这些东西的原因超出了我精神的认识能力。单单是这个理由就足以让我相信：人们带有目的所追溯的所有原因都不能用于物理的或自然的东西上去；因为，去探求和打算发现上帝的那些深不可测的目的，我觉得那简直是狂妄至极的事。

另外我还想到，当人们探求上帝的作品是否完满时，不应该单独拿一个事物孤立起来看，而应该把所有的事物都合起来看。因为，如果单独地观察一个物体，总是觉得某些方面不够完满；可是，如果把它看成是这个宇宙整体的一部分，它在它的本性上就是非常完满的。而且，自从我决定对一切事物抱有怀疑的态度以来，我仅仅肯定地认识了我的存在和上帝的存在；可是，自从我认识到了上帝的无限潜能之后，我就不得不承认上帝也产生了其他很多东西，或者至少他能够产生那些东西，因而我承认我存在也是作为一切存在的东西的整体的一个部分。

在这以后，更进一步审视我自己，并且研究我所犯的那些错误（只有这些错误才证明我是不完满的）时，我发现这是由于两个原因造成的，即我心里的认知能力和选择能力，或者把这种选择能力称为我的自由意志，也就是说，是由于我的智力和我的意志的共同作用而造成的。因为单单运用理智，我对任何东西都既不加以肯定，也不加以否定，我仅仅是领会我所能领会的东西的观念，这些观念是我能够加以判断的。可是如果从这个角度来观察一件事物，严格来讲，在它里边绝找不到什么错误。而且，虽然在世界上也许有无穷无尽的我不了解、不认识的东西，而我应该说我不了解这些东西，我对于这些东西，头脑里没有任何概念，但不能从严格意义上说，我被剥夺了这些东西，因为，事实上我想不出什么理由能够证明上帝本来应该给我比他已经给我的那些认知功能更大、更广一些的认知功能；并且不管我把上帝想成是多么精巧熟练的工匠，我也不应该因此就认为他应该把他本来可以放到几个作品里的完满性全部放到每一个作品里。

与此同时，我也不能埋怨上帝没有给我一个相当广泛、相当完满的自由意志或意志，因为事实上我体验出这个自由意志或意志是非常大、非常广的，什么界限都限制不住它。我觉得在这里很值得注意的是，在我心里没有一个能比这个自由意志更大、更完满的了。因为，举例来说，如果我考虑在我心里的领会功能，我认为它是很狭小、很有限的，而同时，给我提供另外一个功能的观念，这个观念要广阔得多，甚至是无限的；仅仅从我能形成观念这一事实，我就毫无困难地认识到这个观念是与上帝的本性相契合的。如果我用同样方式检查记忆，或者想象，或者其他功能，这些功能就我自己而言都是受到限制而且是非常有限的，而这些能力之于上帝则是无限的。我体验到，在我之内只有意志是大到我领会不到会有什么别的东西比它更有能力，比它更广的了。这使我认识到，我带有上帝的形象和上帝的相似性的，主要是意志。因为尽管上帝的意志比我的意志大得无法比拟，不论是在知识和能力方面，或者是在意志的对象方面，因为认知和能力在意志里结合到一起使意志更有力量、更有实效，意志无限地扩展到更多的东西上。如果严格的意义上来考察它，那么我觉得它就不是更有能力。因为它仅仅在于我们对同一件事能做或不能做（也就是说，肯定它或否定它，追寻它或逃避它），或者不如说，它仅仅在于为了确认或否认、追寻或逃避理智向我们提供的东西，我们做得就好像并不感觉到有什么外在的力量驱使我们似的。因为，为了自由，我没有必要在两个截然不同的问题上非要选择一个；而是，我越是倾向于这一个（无论是由于我明显地认识到在那里有善和真，或者由于上帝是这样支配了我的思想内部），我选择的就越自由，并且采取了这一个；而且，上帝的恩宠和自然的知识当然不是减少我的自由，而是增加也加强了我的自由。因此，当我没有任何理由迫使我倾向于这一边而不倾向于那一边时，我所感觉到的这种无所谓的态度不过是最低程度的自由。这种无所谓的态度与其说是在意志里表现出一种完满性，不如说是在知识里表现出一种缺陷；因为，如果我总是清清楚楚地认识什么是真，什么是善，我就决不会费事去掂算我到底应该采取什么样的判断和什么样的选择了，这样我就会完全自由，决不会抱无所谓的态度。

从所有这些，我认识到，我错误的原因既不是意志的能力本身，它是我从上帝那里接受过来的，本质非常完满，涵盖了方方面面的东西，也不是理解的能力或领会的能力，因为，既然我用上帝给我的这个能力来领会，那么毫无疑问，凡是我所领会的，都是实事求是地去领会，我不可能由于这个缘故弄错。那么我的错误从哪里产生的呢？是从这里产生的，这就是因为意志比理智大得多、广得多，而我却没有把意志加以同样的限制，反而把它扩展到我所理解不了的东西上去，意志对这些东西既然是无所谓的，于是我就很容易陷于迷惘，并且把恶的当成善的，或者把假的当成真的。这就使我作出了错误的判断或选择。

举例来说，过去几天我仔细考察了这世界上是否存在什么东西，并且认识到仅仅由于我考察了这一问题，显然让我认识到我自己是存在的，于是我就不得不得出这样的结论，即我领会得如此清楚的事情是真的，不是由于什么外部的原因强迫我得出这样的结论，而仅仅是因为我的理智强大的倾向性，并且我越是觉得不那么无所谓，就越是自由地去相信。相反，目前我不仅知道我是一个在思维的存在，而且还注意到了物质性的本质，这使我怀疑我内在的思维本性，或者我的这个本性与这个物质性的本质的不同，怀疑这二者是否是一个东西。我现在假定我还不认识有任何理由使我相信后一种情况而不相信前一种情况。因此对于否认它或肯定它，或者甚至不去加以任何判断，我都保持着超然的态度。

而且这种超然之心不仅扩展到理智完全认识不到的东西上，而且一般也扩展到当我想要考虑到这些东西时却不能完全清楚地发现所有这些东西上。因为如果仅仅是一些猜测就会使我更倾向于某个方向，但是这一认识不过是一些猜测，而不是可靠的、无可置疑的理由，这就足以给我机会去作出相反的判断。这几天我充分体验到，当我把我以前当作非常真实的一切事物都假定是假的，光是从这里我就看出了我们之所以对这些事物采取某种怀疑态度的原因。

可是，如果我未能清晰、明确地判断什么是真实的，只要我不作出判断，我的行为就是正确无误的。可是如果我决定去否定它或肯定它，那么我就不正确地使用我的自由意志了；如果我选择了不是真的东西，那么显然我是弄错了。即使我判断对了，这也不过是碰巧罢了，我仍然难免弄错，难免不正确地使用我的自由意志。因为，理性之光告诉我们，理智的认识永远必须先于意志的决定。自由选择意志的不当使用构成错误的形式，就来源于我自己产生的能力，而不是我从上帝那里接受过来的能力，也没有存在于那些依靠上帝来行使的能力。

我没有理由埋怨上帝没有给我一个更强的理解力，或者更强的理性之光。因为事实上理解不了这无穷无尽的事物，这对于有限理智体来说是自然而然的事情，是一个天生就是有限的本性。但是我有一切理由对上帝充满感激之情，而不应该认为上帝没能给予我什么，或者说上帝把本应该给我的东西从我这里拿走了，因为他从来没有欠过我什么，却对我如此慷慨。

我也没有理由埋怨他给了我一个比我理智范围更广大的意志力，因为意志力只在于一件事，就是它和它的主体就像是不可分似的，它的本性看来是这样的，什么都不能从它的身上拿走。而且，当然，它扩展得越广，我就越要感谢上帝给了我这个能力。最后，我也不应该埋怨上帝助长我发挥自己意志的行为，或者说因为我自己作出了一些错误的判断而埋怨上帝。因为这些行为既然是取决于上帝的，所以就是完全真实的、绝对善良的；在某种意义上，我能够做成这些行为比我不能做成这些行为，在我的本性上有着更多的完满性。至于缺陷，也就是谎言和错误的本质，它不需要上帝方面的什么帮助，因为它不是一个东西，也不是一个存在体，而且假如把缺陷与上帝相互联系起来，把上帝看成缺陷出现的原因，那么它就不能叫作缺陷，而应该叫作否定。因为显而易见的是上帝给了赞同或者不赞同什么事的自由，却没有在我的理解力里面给我清晰、明了的洞察力，这也不是在上帝方面的一种不完满，而无疑地是在我的方面的不完满，是我没有使用好这个自由，因为是我在我领会得不清楚和糊里糊涂的一些事物上鲁莽地下了判断。可是，我看得出，上帝可以轻易地把我造就成不会犯错的人，尽管我一直是自由的，并且具备有限的认识。当我想要思考时，上帝给了我能够清楚感知并理解世间万物的能力，或者上帝可以只是简单给我灌输记忆，这样一来我对领会得不清楚、不明白的事物，永远不要下定什么判断，这样的一个决心深深地刻在我的记忆里，使我永远忘不了它。而且我看得出来，如果我把自己看成具备某些全体性（就好像世界上只有我自己似的），上帝会把我建造的比现在要完满得多。可是我不能因此就否认在某种意义上，宇宙的某几个部分难免出现错误比一切部分都出现错误，会有更大的完满性。而且上帝并没有想把我的角色放在最高贵、最完满的东西的行列里去，我也没有任何权利去埋怨。

加之，如果他没有给我由于我前面说过的第一个策略而不犯错误的能力，这种能力取决于我对于我所能够考虑的一切事物的一种清楚、明白的认识，他至少在我的能力里边留下了另一种策略，那就是下定决心在我没有把事情的真相弄清楚以前无论如何不去下判断。因为，虽然我认识到我的本性中的这种缺陷，即我不能把我的精力持续集中在一件事上，可是我仍然可以专心致志地做事并且时常反复地沉思，能够把它强烈地印到我的记忆中，使我每次在需要它的时候不能不想起它，并且由于这种办法能够养成不犯错误的习惯。

由于人的最大的、主要的完满性就在于此，我认为我从这个“沉思”里获益匪浅，因为我发现了虚假和错误的原因。而且当然，除了我所解释的那个原因以外不能还有其他原因了。因为每当我把我的意志限制在我的认识范围之内，让它除了理智给它清楚、明白地提供出来的那些事物之外，不对任何事物下判断，这样我就不会弄错；因为凡是我领会得清楚、明白的，都毫无疑问的是实在的、肯定的东西，从而它不能是从无中生出来的，而是由上帝创造出来的。关于上帝，我要说的是，他既然是至上完满的，就决不能是错误的原因；因此我在这里可以肯定的是：这样的理解或者像这样一个判断是真实的。此外，今天我不但知道了必须避免什么才能不犯错误，而且也知道了我必须做什么才能认识真理。因为，如果我把我的注意力充分地放在凡是我领会得完满的事物上，并把这些事物从其他我一知半解的事物中区分出来，我自然会认识真理。这就是我今后将要认真加以注意的。

第五个沉思

论物质性东西的本质；

再论上帝的存在

关于上帝的属性以及我自己的本性，也就是说，我的精神的本性，我还剩下很多东西有待检查；不过我会另外再找机会去研究，因为（一旦在看出了必须去做什么或者必须不去做什么才能认识真理之后）目前我首要之务是把我自己从这几天所陷入的全部怀疑中解脱出来，甩掉那些怀疑，看看我对于物质性的东西是否有一个清晰的概念。

可是，在我检查我以外是否有这样的一些东西存在之前，（因为这些东西的观念是在我的思维之中的）我应该先考虑这些观念，看看哪些是清楚的，哪些是模糊的。

首先我清楚地想到哲学家通常称之为“连续量”的量，或者一种量的广延，或者说一个东西的长、宽、厚的广延。我可以在这种量里面举出许多不同的部分，在每一部分上加上各种大小、形状、位置和运动。最后我可以给每个运动规定出它延续的不同时间。当我这样一般地加以考虑的时候，我不仅清楚地认识了这些东西，而且在我稍微加以注意的时候，我就认识到有关数目、形状、运动以及诸如此类的无数特点，这些特点的真实性不但表现得非常明显，而且和我的本性竟然也十分契合，以致当我开始发现这些特点时，我似乎并没有获知什么新的东西，而是想起了我从前已经知道了的东西，也就是说，发现了一些早已在我心里的东西，尽管我以前没有想到它们。

我认为目前最重要的是，我觉得在我心里对某些东西有无数观念，虽然这些观念只是存在于我的脑海里，可是不能就认为它们全然不存在；而且，虽然我从某些程度上是凭借自己的意志想到或是没有想到他们，但是它们并不是我凭空捏造的，而是有它们真实、不变的本性的。举例来说，当我想到一个三角形时，即使在我的思维以外也许世界上根本没有什么地方存在这样的一个形状，可是毕竟这个形状具备一些特定的属性、本质或者外形，它是不变的、永恒的，不是我凭空捏造的，也决不取决于我的精神，显而易见的是，我们可以推断出三角形的各种特性，比如，它的三个角之和等于两个直角之和，最大的角对最大的边，以及诸如此类的东西，这些东西，尽管在我从前第一次想到一个三角形时我绝对没有想到过，那么现在我认识得非常清楚、非常明白，不管我愿不愿意，它们都是三角形的特征，这并不是我凭空捏造的。

如果说也许三角形的这个观念是通过我的感官来到我心里的，因为我时不时地看到过一些三角形的物体，可是这不过是我自己反驳自己罢了，因为我在心里可以想到不可计数的其他形状来，这些形状是不会让人们觉得我是通过感官来认识的，不过这并不妨碍我能够推证出它们的本性的各种特点，就像我可以推证出三角形的本性的各种特点。这些东西当然一定都是真的，因为我把它们领会得非常清楚，因而它们一定是存在着的事物而不是全然的虚无；因为，显而易见的是，凡是真实的东西都是客观存在的事物。并且我前面已经充分证明过，凡是我认识得清楚、分明的东西也都是真实的。虽然对这一点我没有加以证明，可是当我把它们领会得清楚、分明时，我的精神实质使得我不能不认为它们是真的。而且我记得，即使我全然把思绪集中在感官的对象上时，我仍然把我领会得清楚、明了的有关形状、数目和其他属于算数和几何学，或者总体归为纯粹而抽象的数学的东西列入真理之中。

那么现在，如果仅仅由于我可以从我的思维中得出什么东西的观念就断言凡是我清楚、分明地认识到是属于这个东西的都实际属于这个东西，那么难道我不可以由此得出关于上帝存在的一个论据和一个论证性的证明吗？当然我在我的心里觉察一个上帝的观念——也就是说，一个至上完满的存在体的观念——这个和我的大脑中形成的有关形状和数量的观念是一样的。我清楚明了地认识到一个现实的、永恒的存在性是属于它的本性，这和我清楚、明了地认识凡是我可以证明什么形状或什么数目是真正属于这个形状或这个数目的本性一样。从而，即使在前几个沉思里所断言的都不是真的，而在我心里，上帝的存在至少应该算是和我迄今所认为仅仅有关数目和形状的一切数学真理同样可靠。

然而，事实上乍看起来并不那么显而易见，好像有些诡辩的样子。因为，我已经习惯于把事物的存在和本质分开，我很容易相信上帝的存在是可以同他的本质分得开的，这样就能够把上帝领会为不是现实存在的。虽然如此，如果仔细想一想，我就明显地看出上帝的存在不能同他的本质分开，这和一个三角形的本质不能同它的三角之和等于两直角分开，或一座山的观念不能同一个谷的观念分开一样。因此，想到一个上帝（也就是说，想象一个至上完满的存在体）而它竟缺少存在性（也就是说，它竟缺少某种完满性），这和设想一座山而没有谷是同样不合适的。

可是，虽然事实上我能想象一个存在着的上帝，能设想一个有山谷的山，不过，既然仅仅由于我想到了一个带谷的山不能因此就说世界上有山，同样，虽然我领会带存在性的上帝也不能因此就说有一个上帝存在，因为我的思维并不给事物强加什么必然性；而且，尽管并没有什么带翅膀的马，而我却想出来一个带翅膀的马，同样，尽管并没有什么上帝存在，我也许能够给上帝加上存在性。

这个反驳的外表掩盖下的逻辑错误就在于此。因为，从我不能领会一个不带谷的山这一事实，不能得出世界上根本没有山，也没有山谷这个结论，而只能得出山和山谷无论存在与否，都不可分这个结论；同样地，仅仅由于我不能把上帝领会成不带存在性，因此存在性和上帝是不可分的，因此上帝是存在的。不是因为我把事物想成怎么样事物就怎么样，并且把什么必然性强加给事物；而是相反地，是因为事物本身的必然性，即上帝的存在性，决定我的思维去这样领会它。因为我可以随便想象一个马不带翅膀或者带翅膀，可是我并不能随便领会一个没有存在性的上帝（也就是说，我不能随便领会一个缺少一种至上完满性的至上完满的存在体）。

我承认了上帝具备种种完满性，我便就真的必然要承认上帝存在，因为存在性就是各种各样的完满性之一，而这一点是不应该反驳的。而且事实上，我的第一个假定并不是必然的，同样，去想凡是四边形都能内切于圆，也不是必然的；如果我有这样的想法的话，那么我就不得不承认菱形也能内切于圆，因为菱形也是四边形，而这显然是不正确的。即使每当我想到一个第一的、至上的存在体，我不是非想到上帝不可，并且从我内心深处提出（姑且这样说）它的观念时，我必然要加给它各种各样的完满性，虽然我不能把这些完满性都一一列举出来，也不能去一一考虑在这其中的每一个完满性。这种必然性是如此的清晰、明了，足以使我（在我认识了存在性是一种完满性之后）得出结论说，这个第一的、至上的存在体是真正存在的。同样，我并不是非得想象一个什么三角形不可；不过，每当我要考虑仅仅由三个角组成的直线图形时，我就必须要把使三角之和不大于两直角这个结论的东西都加给它，即便也许当时我没有特别考虑到这一点。但是当我检查哪一些图形能够内切于圆时，我根本不用考虑这些包含所有的四边形；相反，我不能捏造事实，因为我只能接受那些我能够理解得清晰、明了的东西。因此，在像上面这样的假定跟我与生俱来的真的观念之间有很大的差别，而这其中第一个并且主要的是上帝的观念。因为事实上我从很多方面都看出这个观念并不是凭空捏造的，这不是只属于我的思维的东西，而是一个真实、不变的本性的形象。首先，因为除了上帝以外我不能领会存在什么别的东西是必然属于他的本质的；其次，因为我不能理解会有两个或许多个跟他一样的上帝；而且既然肯定了现在有一个上帝存在，我看得清楚，他过去必然是完全永恒地存在过，将来也永恒地存在着；最后，我在上帝身上认识了其他许许多多的东西，而这些东西我既不能改变也不能削减。

但是，不管使用什么论据来证明，我也必须回到这一点上来：我只完全相信我能领会得清楚、分明的东西。而且在我能完全领会的东西当中，有一些是事实上每人都显然认识的，也有一些只有经过仔细考虑，经过更认真检查过的人才能发现；不过，这些东西一经被发现出来之后，大家都认为它们是靠得住的。举例来说，一切直角三角形，虽然起初很不容易看出用底边的平方等于其他两个边的平方之和，因为显然这个底边是和最大的角相对的，不过一旦认出了这一点之后，我们就相信二者同样都是真实的。至于上帝，如果我心里事先一点成见也没有，如果我的思维没有被不断出现的可感知的事物所干扰，那么我所认识的事物中我是最早、最容易认识上帝的了。因为，难道还有什么东西比我想有一个上帝，这么一个至上的、完满的存在体这件事，更清楚、明了的吗？因为光是在它的观念里就包含着必然的或永恒的存在性。为了很好地领会这个真理，虽然我费了不少精力，可是现在我不但从这里确实相信了一切在我看来是最可靠的东西。而且，除此之外，我也看出其他一切事物的可靠性也都是以它为基础的；如果没有这种认识就永远不可能完满地知道其他事物。

尽管我一旦非常清楚明了地理解了什么事物，我自然相信它是真的——这是我的本性使然，为了把这件事情弄清楚，我心里不能总是想到一个事物上去。当我不再去考虑促使我作出这样判断的理由时，我经常想起我之前所作出的早期判断。假如我不知道有一个上帝，就有可能出现别的理由使我很容易改变看法，这样一来，对不管什么事物我就永远不能有真实、可靠的知识，而只能有空泛的、靠不住的见解。举例来说，当我考虑三角形的性质时，作为几何学的内行，我显然知道三角形三角之和等于两直角，而且当我运用我的思维证明它的时候，我不可能不相信这一点；可是假如我不知道有一个上帝的存在，只要我的注意力稍微离开证明，虽然我记得我是清清楚楚地理解了它的三角之和等于两直角，我还是很可能会怀疑它的真实性的。因为我可以说服我自己：大自然使我生来就很容易能够在我以为理解得最明显、最可靠的东西上弄错，特别是那些我认为是真实、可靠的事物，后来又因为别的理由的出现使我把这些事物判断成是绝对错误的。

可是当我认识到有一个上帝之后，同时我也认识到一切事物都取决于他，而他并不是骗子，从而我断定凡是我领会得楚楚、分明的事物都是真的，虽然我不再去想我是根据什么理由把一切事物断定为真实的，只要我记得我是把它清楚、分明地理解了，就不能给我提出任何相反的理由使我再去怀疑它，这样我对这个事物就有了一种真实、可靠的知识。这个认识也可以推广到我记得以前曾经证明过的其他一切事物，比如推广到几何学的真理以及其他类似的东西上去。剩下的反驳我的观点是什么呢？是因为我的本性如此，使我老是弄错？可是我已经知道对于认识得清楚、了解了的事物中，我是不会弄错的。是因为我从前把很多东西认为是真实、可靠的，而以后我认识到它们是错的吗？可是这些东西没有一个是我认识得清楚、明白的，而且那时我还不知道使我确实认识真理的这条规律，我是由于一些理由相信了它们，而以后我看出那些理由还不如我当时想象得那么有说服力。还能再有什么可反驳我的吗？是因为也许我睡着了（就像我以前反驳过我自己的那样），或者是因为我现在的这些想法和我们想象是睡着了时做的梦一样不真实呢？可是，即使我睡着了，凡是明明白白出现在我心里的都是绝对真实的。

因此我非常清楚地认识到，一切知识的可靠性和真实性都取决于对于真实的上帝这个唯一的认识，因而在我认识上帝以前，我是不能完满知道其他任何事物的。而现在我既然认识了上帝，我就有办法取得关于无穷无尽的事物的完满知识，不仅取得关于上帝的那些东西的知识，同时也取得属于几何学家研究范围的物质性质的那些东西。

第六个沉思

论物质性东西的存在以及

论人的灵魂和肉体之间的真正区别

我仍然需要考虑一下是否存在物质性的东西了。不错，既然人们把物质性的东西看成是数学论证的对象，既然我用这种方式把它们领会得十分清楚、分明，这就表明物质性的东西是存在的。因为毫无疑问，凡是我能够领会得清楚、分明的东西，上帝都有能力创造出来，而且我从来没有断定过他有什么做不出来的东西，除非是由于我不能很好地领会。再说，我的想象力是能够让我相信物质的东西存在的。因为当我仔细考虑什么是想象时，我看出它不过是认知功能对向它直接呈现的物体的某种运用，因而这个物体是存在的。

为了把这一点弄得非常明白，我首先看出想象和纯粹理解活动之间的区别。举例来说，当我想象一个三角形时，我不仅领会到这是一个由三条线相连为边组成的形状，而且与此同时，我也仿佛看见这三条线出现在面前，而这正是我所说的想象。如果我要想一个千边形，我当然知道这是一个由一千个边组成的形状，和我了解一个三角形是仅仅由三个边组成的形状同样容易，但是我却不能像我想一个三角形的三个边那样想一个千边形的一千个边，也不能用眼睛看到这一千个边出现在我面前。而且虽然当我想物质性的东西时，我总是倾向于使用我的想象，于是在我领会一个千边形时，我模模糊糊地表象出一个什么形状；不过这个形状显然并不是一个千边形，因为这个形状跟我想一个万边形或一个有非常多的边的形状时所表象出来的形状没有什么不同，而且决不能用它来发现千边形和别的多边形之间的差别。如果问题在于考虑一个五边形，我当然可以跟一个千边形一样，去理解它的形状，不需要使用想象力；可是我也可以使我的眼睛看到五个边的每一个，以及所组成的图形构成的面积，用这样的办法来想象这个形状。这样我就清清楚楚地认识到我需要特别集中精力来想象，而我不需要特别集中精力去理解；从特别集中精力中显然可以看出想象同纯粹理解活动之间是有差别的。

此外我认为想象力与理解力并不相同，并且对我的本性或对我的精神的本质，也并不是必不可少的；因为，即使我没有这种想象的能力，无疑我仍然会和现在的情况没有什么两样，从而可以断言，它并不取决于我的精神，而是取决于我精神之外的其他东西。而且我也很快地明白，如果说有什么物体存在，而我的精神和它联结得非常紧密，随时都可以调用这种能力，那么就可以用这种方式去想象物质性的东西了。因此，这种思维方式与纯粹的理解活动就不相同了：当理解事物时，精神活动总是回到观念的本身，探寻观念内的问题；而在想象时，它转向物体，并且在物体上考虑某种符合观念本身，或者通过感官来获得观念。我说，我很容易领会到，如果真有相应的物体，想象便是这样产生的，而且，由于我找不到什么别的办法来说明想象是怎么形成的，所以我便推想或许物体本来是存在的；可是，这只能说是“或许”。尽管我仔细检查，从我想象中的这种关于物体本性的清楚观念里，我仍然看不出能够得出任何结论，以证明这类物体存在的必然性。

可是，除了作为数学对象的物质性质以外，我经常想象许多其他的东西，比如颜色、声音、味道、疼痛以及诸如此类的东西，虽然这些事物对我来说不是很清晰。而且因为通过感官我就能更好地觉察这些东西，并且通过原有的记忆，这些东西就好像直接出现在我的想象之中了。因此，在探究这些东西的同时，我觉得也应该考虑一下什么是感官，看看从我称之为感觉的这种思维方式接收到我的心里来的这些观念里，是不是能得出什么可靠的证据来证明物质性东西的存在。

首先我要提醒自己，我以前通过感官得来的东西有哪些是真的，我是根据哪些理由才相信的；其次，我要检查一下，为什么从那以后，我对这些东西发生疑问的理由；最后我要考虑一下我现在认为它们应该是什么。

因此首先我感觉到我有一个头、两只手、两只脚以及其他组成部分，这在我看来是我自己的一部分或者是我的全部。此外，我感觉到这个肉体存在于其他很多物体之间，它有能力感受到其他物体给它带来的不同种类的舒适和不舒适感觉。我通过某一种愉快或满足欲望的感觉而判断出舒适，通过某一种痛苦的感觉而判断出不舒适。在愉快和痛苦之外，我的肉体内部还能感觉到饥饿、口渴以及其他类似的饮食之欲，我也感觉到对于喜、哀、怒以及其他类似情绪的某些物质性的倾向。在外部，除了物体的大小、形状和运动之外，我还在物体里感觉出软硬、干湿以及其他触摸起来的特性。此外，我在那里感觉出明暗、颜色、声音、气味和滋味，这样便使我把天、地、海以及总而言之其他一切物体都彼此分辨出来。

鉴于出现在我思维里的所有这些具有特性的观念，而且这些观念是我真正、直接感受到的，于是我相信我感觉到了一些从我的思维中直接产生的东西，它们最初源自于这些观念，而这种说法也是合理的。因为这些想法事先没有经过我的同意就产生了，因此不管什么东西，如果它没有通过我的感官表现出来，尽管我很希望能够感受到它，我也感觉不到它；而当它表现在我的感觉器官之一的时候，我根本不可能不感觉到它。而且因为我通过感官得来的那些观念比起我沉思时所能虚构的任何观念，或者比起我认为印在我的记忆里的任何观念都要生动得多，明显得多，甚至都以其特有的方式表现得清楚得多，看来它们不能是从我心里产生的，所以它们必然是由一些别的什么东西在我心里引起的。既然除了那些观念给我的认识以外，我对那些东西什么认识都没有，那么除非是那些和它们相似的东西，此外我就不能再想到其他的东西了。因为，我也知道我在运用理性之前总是先使用感性，并且我认识到我自己形成的那些观念不如我通过感官得来的观念那么明确，何况那些观念经常也是由我通过感官得来的观念而构成的，所以我便相信在我头脑中的观念都是通过感官得来的。

因此我相信，由于某种特殊权利，这个肉体比其他任何物体都更紧密地属于我，是有道理的。因为，事实上我决不能像分开其他物体一样同我的肉体分开。我可以感受到我的一切饮食之欲和我的一切情感，也能感受到外界对我的各种情感。最后，我也能感受到我身体中每一部分的愉快和痛苦，而对于在其他物体上产生的愉快和痛苦我却全然感受不到。可是，为什么某种莫名的痛苦之感会引起心里的悲伤，感官上愉快之感就引起思维上快乐？或者为什么这种胃的莫名紧张之感（我把它叫作饿）让我想要吃东西，喉咙发干让我想要喝水，以及其他类似的情况为什么会存在呢？这除了是自然这样告诉我的，我找不出别的道理来。因为在胃的紧张和想要吃东西之间，以及引起痛苦的东西的感觉和这个感觉引起悲伤思想之间，没有任何关系（至少，在我了解的范围内没有任何关系）。同样道理，有关我的感官对象所了解的其他东西，也是自然教会我的；在我考量其他的原因以证明这一点之前，我对此是坚信不疑的。

可是以后，许多经历逐渐破坏了我对感官的信任。因为我多次看到，有些塔我远看好像是圆的，而近看却是方的；耸立在塔顶上的巨大塑像从塔底下看却是小小的塑像。无数其他类似的情况使我相信，我根据外部感官所下的判断是有错误的。不仅如此，就连根据内部感官所下的判断也一样。因为，对于我来说，还有比痛苦更有切肤之感的东西么？可是从前有些把胳臂或腿截去了的人对我说有时他们还感觉到已经截去了的那部分疼，这使我有理由想到，虽然我感觉到我某一个肢体疼，我也不能肯定它疼。除了这些怀疑的理由以外，最近以来我还加上其他两个更为普遍的理由。第一，我醒着时从来没有相信我感觉过我在睡着时有时也以为能感觉的东西；而且，因为我不相信我在睡着时好像感觉的东西是从外部的世界得来的，所以我看不出对于我为什么应该更信任在我醒着时好像感觉的那些东西。第二，既然我还不认识，或者不如说我假装不认识我的存在的创造者，我看不出有什么能够阻止我就是这样由自然构成的，使我甚至在给我表现得最真实的那些东西上弄错。关于以上使我相信可感觉的东西的真实性的那些理由，我可以比较容易地回答这些问题。因为自然给了我很多在道理上使我弄不通的东西，我认为我不应该过于相信自然告诉我的事。而且，虽然我由感官得来的那些观念并不取决于我的意志，我却不认为因此就不应该断言那些观念是从不同于我的东西得出来的，因为也许在我这方面有什么功能是产生这些观念的原因，虽然一直到现在我还不认识它。

可是现在既然我开始更好地认识了我自己，开始更清楚地发现了我的来源的创造者，那么我认为我不应该糊里糊涂地接受感官好像告诉我的一切事物；不过我也不认为我应该把什么都统统拿来怀疑。首先，因为我知道凡是我清楚、分明地领会的东西都能像我所领会的那样是上帝产生的，所以只要我能清楚、分明地领会一个东西，而不牵涉到别的东西，这样就足以确定这一个东西是跟那一个东西有分别或不同的，因为它们是可以分开放置的，至少由上帝的全能把它们分开放置；至于什么力量把它们分开，使我把它们断定为不同的东西，这倒没有关系。结果，就是因为这样，我确实认识到我存在，同时除了我是一个在思维着的东西之外，我又看不出有什么别的东西必然属于我的本质，所以我确实有把握断言我的本质就是由这个构成的，也就是说我是一个在思维的东西。而且，虽然也许（或者不如说的确像我将要说的那样）我有一个肉体，我和它非常紧密地结合在一起；不过，因为一方面我对我自己有一个清楚、分明的观念，即我只是一个在思维的东西，这个东西不能伸展，而另一方面，我对于肉体有一个分明的观念，即它只是一个能伸展的东西却不能思维，所以肯定的是：这个我，也就是说我的灵魂，是完全、真正跟我的肉体有分别的，灵魂可以没有肉体而存在。

还有，我发现我自身还有几种不同的思维能力，即想象的功能和感觉的功能，没有它们，我虽然能清楚、分明地全部领会我，但是光能理解它们而没有我的存在，也就是说，没有一个它们所附之于其上的理智性实体，我就不能理解它们了。因为，在这些功能的形式概念里包含着某种理智作用。这样，我便理解到它们跟我不相同，物体的模式、风格和物体本身不一样。我也认识到一些其他功能，就像改换地方、采取各种姿势以及类似的其他功能，这些功能和之前提到的几个功能一样，如果没有它们可以依附的实体就不会被人领会，因此，没有这个实体它们就不能存在。可是，显而易见的是，如果这些功能真的存在，那么它们就必然依附于物质性的或有广延的实体之上，而不是依附于一个理智性的实体之上，因为这些功能的准确定义里面确实包含有某种延伸性质，但是却并没有包含理智。

此外，我有某种受动的感觉功能，也就是说，接受和认识可感知东西的观念的功能；可是，如果在我心里或者在别人心里没有一种能动的功能以形成和产生这些观念，那么我就不能使用这种受动的功能。既然我不过是一个在思维的东西，那么这种能动的功能不可能在我心里，而那些观念的存在并不以我的理解为先决条件，甚至经常和我的意愿相反；因此它一定是在不同于我的什么实体里，在那个实体里正式地包含着（如同我以前指出的那样）能动地存在于由这个功能所产生的观念里的全部实在性。这个实体要么是一个物体，也就是说一个形式地、实际地包含了凡是能动地并且通过表象在这些观念里的物质性的东西；要么是上帝本身，或者别的什么比物体更高贵的造物，在这个造物里卓越地包含着同样的东西。可是，既然上帝不是骗子，那么显然他不会自己直接地，也不会通过什么造物的媒介把这些东西的观念送给我。因为，上帝既然没有给我任何功能来认识这样的事情，相反的，这样便使我更加倾向于相信观念是物质性的东西发出的，或者来自物质性的东西，那么如果事实上这些观念不是来自或产生于物质性的东西而是来自于别的原因，我就看不出怎么能辩解它不是一个骗局。因此，必须承认有物质性的东西存在。虽然如此，它们也许并不完全像我们通过感官所感受到的那样，因为感官的知觉在很多方面是非常模糊不清的；不过至少必须承认凡是我领会得清楚、分明的东西也都包含在这里面了，也就是说，一般说来，那些凡是我清楚地领会的东西也都包含在纯粹的数学之中了。

不过，至于其他东西，有些仅仅是个别的（比如太阳是不是这么大、这样的形状等等）或者被我们领会得不那么清楚、不那么分明的东西（就像光、声音、痛苦以及诸如此类的东西），虽然它们是十分可疑、十分靠不住的，但是可以肯定的是上帝不是骗子，因而他没有允许在我的见解里能有任何错误，这样我就认为能够断言在我心里有确实可靠的办法认识它们，除非上帝又同时给我纠正错误的功能。首先，毫无疑问，凡是自然告诉我的东西都含有某种真实性。因为一般来说，自然，我指的不是别的，而是上帝本身，或者上帝在各造物里所建立的秩序和安排。至于我的本性，我不是指别的东西，而是指上帝所给我的一切东西的总和。

可是没有再比这个自然告诉我的更明白、更显著的了，那就是我有一个肉体，当我感觉痛苦的时候，它就不舒服；当我感觉饿或渴的时候，它就需要吃或喝，等等。因此我决不怀疑在这上面的真实性。

自然也用疼、饿、渴等等感觉告诉我，我不仅像一个舵手住在他的船上一样，存在于我的肉体里，而且除此而外，我和它非常紧密地联结在一起，融合、掺和得像一个整体一样地结合在一起。因为，假如不是这样，那么当我的肉体受了伤的时候，我（这个仅仅是一个在思维的我）就不会因此感觉到疼，而只会用理智去知觉这个伤，就如同一个舵手用视觉去察看是不是在他的船上有什么东西坏了一样；同样的，当我的肉体需要饮食的时候，我就会直截了当地认识这件事，而不会产生那种模糊的饥渴感觉。因为事实上，所有这些饥、渴、疼等等感觉不过是某些模糊的思维方式，并且就像这样，它们是来自并且取决于精神和肉体的混合。

此外，自然告诉我，我的身体周围还存在着许多别的物体，在这些物体中我应该趋就一些而同时躲避另一些。而且当然，从我感觉的不同种类的颜色、气味、滋味、声音、冷热、软硬等，我确有把握地断言，在产生这些与之对应的不同感官知觉的物体里，彼此之间也是不一样的，即便他们的时间彼此不一样，他们之间也是彼此类似的。而且在不同的感官知觉之间，有些使我舒服，有些使我不舒服，所以我可以得出一个完全可靠的结论，即我的身体（或者就我是由肉体和灵魂组合成的而言，不如说整个的我自己）是能够感受到环境周围的有利的影响和不利的影响的。

可是除此之外，也有许多别的东西，这些东西好像是自然教会我的，但是实际上我并非从自然中领会了这些东西，而是从我的某种随意判断认识了这些东西，这种情况经常容易发生，这样会很轻易导致虚假的因素。举例来说，就如同这个地方没有什么能够触动我感官的东西，我认为一个特定的空间空无一物；又比如说，在一个热的物体里有跟我心里的热的观念相似的什么东西；在一个白的或黑的物体里有我所感觉到的同样的白或黑；在一个苦的或甜的物体里有我所感觉到的同样的味道或滋味，以及其他类似的东西。星体、塔以及其他一切距离远的物体都是像它们在离我们的眼睛很远的地方所表现的那样的形状和大小等等。

可是，为了在这方面把什么东西都领会得清清楚楚，当我说自然告诉我什么东西时，我应该准确地规定一下这个定义。因为我在这里对自然所采用的意义是狭义上的自然定义，比我把上帝给我的一切东西的总体称之为自然的意义狭小，因为那种包罗万象的总体包括了很多只属于精神的东西。我在这里说的自然，不是指那些东西。举例来说，通过自然之光我理解到事情一旦做出来了就不再返回去，以及其他许许多多类似的事情，在这里我就不再考察这一类东西了。

同时，也还有只属于物体的东西，那些东西在这里也不包括在自然的名称之下，比如物体具有重量的性质，以及诸如此类的很多东西，我也并不讨论这些东西。我在这里所讨论的东西也仅仅是指上帝所给的、作为精神和肉体的总和的那些东西。

这个自然确实告诉我躲避给我引起痛苦之感的东西，趋就给我引起愉快之感的东西；可是，除此之外，除非经过精神加以仔细、成熟的检查，我看不出它还告诉我，我们从这些不同的感官知觉里应该对于在我们之外的东西作出什么结论。因为，我认为认识这一类事物的真实性，这只是精神的作用，而不是通过精神与肉体的结合体。比如，星星给我眼睛的印象虽然并不比蜡烛的小小火焰给我的印象大，可是在我心里却绝没有一种实在的或自然的功能使我相信星星并不比蜡烛的火焰大，不过我自幼年起就是一直这样判断的，没有任何合理的根据。虽然在我挨近火的时候感觉到热，在我挨得太近的时候感觉到疼，却没有任何理由可以让我相信火里有什么跟热一样的东西和我所感受到的疼是一样的，我不过是有理由相信火里有什么东西，姑且不管这个东西是什么吧，它能给我带来热或者疼的感觉。同样，在有些空间里虽然我找不出什么能刺激和触动我的感官的东西，可是我不应该因此就断言这些空间里绝对没有物体。不过我看出，不管是在这方面或者在其他许多类似的事情方面，我经常是把自然的秩序给弄坏、弄乱了，这是因为，感官的这些感觉或知觉被放在我里边仅仅是为了警告我的精神什么东西对总和体（精神是这个总和体的一部分）是有好处或者坏处的，到这里为止，它们本来是相当清楚、相当分明的，可是我却把它们当成好像是非常可靠的、我可以由之而直接认识在我之外的规律一样来使用了，而关于物体的本质或本性，它们能告诉我的却都是非常不清楚的。

可是，我前面已经检查得足够充分了，尽管上帝是至善的，我有时在这一类的判断上仍会有错。在有关自然告诉我应该趋就或躲避的东西上以及在有关自然放在我里边的内部感觉上，到现在还出现困难，因为我有时看出错误，这样我就直接被我的自然所欺骗。举例来说，有人受到了食物美味的欺骗，吞下了藏在食物中的毒药。在上面的例子中，人受到自然的驱使，去追求任何味道可口的东西，并没有让人吃他所不知道的毒药。因而我只能由这件事得出这样的结论，即这个自然不能全能地、普遍地认识所有的事物。这当然是没有什么奇怪的，因为人既然是一种有限的自然物，就只能有有限完满性的认识。

不过我们有时也在我们直接由自然得到的那些东西上弄错，就像有时病人希望吃喝可能对他们有害的东西一样。在上面的例子中，人们可能会得出这样的结论，引起他们弄错的是因为他们的本性已经紊乱了。可是这样却不能解决什么问题，因为一个病人也和健康的人一样，同样也是上帝的造化；这样一来，如果说那些生病的人被上帝赋予了具有欺骗性的本性，这是非常有争议的了。就像一个由轮子和摆装组成的钟表一样，当这个钟表做得不好，不能完全满足钟表工匠的希望来指示好时间时，也是同样准确地遵守自然的一切规律的；同样的，如果我把人的肉体看成是由骨骼、神经、筋肉、血管、血液和皮肤组成的一架机器一样，即使里边没有精神，也并不妨碍它以跟现在完全一样的方式来运作，这时它不是由意志指导，因而也不是由精神协助，而仅仅是由它的各个器官的安排来运作。因此我很容易认识到，既然这个身体，比如说，是水肿病患者，他自然就由于喉咙发干感到难受，喉咙发干习惯地给精神渴的感觉，因而趋向于引动他的神经和其他部分让他要求喝水，这样一来就增加他的病痛，害了他自己，这和他没病时由于喉咙发干而喝水以适应身体的需要是同样自然的。虽然我看到一个钟表被造这个钟表的人指定了它的用途，我可以说，如果这个钟表走得不准，那是因为它违反了它的本性，这和我把人体这架机器看成是上帝做成的，使它在自身里有它应有的一切运动，虽然我有理由意识到，如果它的喉咙发干，没有按照它的本性的秩序办事，喝了有害于保持它健康的东西，是一样的。可是我认识到，用后一种方式去解释本性和用前一种方式解释本性很不相同。因为后一种方式不是一种单纯的称号问题，它完全取决于我的思维，是我的思维把一个病人和一座做坏了的钟表拿来跟我关于一个健康的人和一个做好了的钟表的观念相比较，而且它决不意味着任何存在于它所指的东西里的东西；相反，用前一种方式来解释本性，我是指某种真正存在于那些东西里的东西，可以说它并不是没有真实性的。

可是，从一个水肿病患者的身体本质来看，当然这不过是一种外部的名称问题，这是因为它的本性坏了，因为人们说在不需要喝水的情况下，它的喉咙仍然发干，可是这个命名显然是人们随便添加上去的。虽然如此，可是从整个的总和来看，即从精神或灵魂和肉体的结合来看，这就并不是一个单纯的命名问题了，实际上纯粹是一个本性上的错误，当口渴时喝水对身体是非常有害的。这样一来，还有待于去检查的就是，像这样的人的本性既然是虚伪的、骗人的，善良的上帝为什么没有能够阻止这件事情。

我首先看出精神和肉体有很大差别，这个差别在于，就其性质来说，肉体永远是可分的，而精神完全是不可分的。因为事实上，当我考虑我的精神（也就是说，作为仅仅是一个在思维的东西的我自己）的时候，我在精神上不能分出各个部分来，我认识到我自己是一个单一、完整的东西。而且尽管整个精神似乎和整个肉体结合在一起，可是当一只脚或者一只胳臂或别的什么部分从我的肉体截去的时候，肯定从我的精神上并没有截去什么东西。愿望、感觉、领会等功能，其作为精神的一部分也没有被截去，因为只有这唯一的一个思维来从事于愿望、感觉、领会等活动。可是物质性的或者有广延的东西就完全相反；因为凡是物质性的、有广延的东西，都能通过我的思维被分成不同的部分。如果我还没有从别处知道，那么这一点就足以告诉我人的精神或灵魂是和肉体完全不同的。

其次，我还看出精神并不直接受到肉体各个部分的影响，它仅仅受到大脑或者甚至大脑的一个最小的部分之一，即行使他们称之为“共同感官”这种功能的那一部分的影响，每当那一部分以同样方式感受时，就使精神感觉到同一的东西，虽然这时候肉体的其他部分可以有不同的感受，这种情况已经被无数的经验所证明了，在这里就不必一一细说了。

此外我还看出，物体的性质是这样的，即它的任何一个部分不能被有隔开一定距离的部分推动，除非尽管这个离得较远的部分不动，它可以被其他别的东西所移动。举例来说，在一条完全抻开的绳子上有甲、乙、丙、丁四个部分，如果丁这段被拉动了，那么在另一端的甲也会跟着一块儿动起来，它动的方式与抻动中间的乙部分或者丙部分同时丁保持不动的方式一样。和这个情况相同的是，当我觉得脚上疼的时候，物理学告诉我，这个感觉是通过分布在脚上的神经传来的，这些神经就像绳子一样从脚上一直通到大脑里，当它们在脚上被抻动的时候，同时也抻动了大脑里边这些神经的起点和终点的那个地方，并且在那里刺激起来为了使精神感觉疼而制定的某一种运动，就好像疼是在脚上似的。可是因为这些神经要从脚上通到大脑里，就一定经过腿、臀部、腰部、背和颈，所以也有这样的可能，即虽然它们在脚上的末端并没有被抻动，而仅仅抻动它们经过腰或颈的某些部分，也会在大脑里刺激起一些和脚上受伤所接到的同样运动，然后精神也将必然觉得脚上疼，就好像脚上受了伤似的。我们的感官的其他各种知觉，情况也应该是这样的。

最后我看出，在影响着思维的大脑中产生的任何一个活动都只能引起某一个感觉，这样一来，能够想到的最佳的安排方式就是这个运动在它能够引起一切感觉之间，只能引起使精神感到最真正、对于维持人体的健康最通常有用的那个感觉。经验使我们认识到，自然所赋予我们的一切感觉就是像我刚才说的那样，因而在这些感觉里边表现出来的无非都是产生它们的上帝的能力和善心。这样，例如当脚上的神经比平时更强烈地动起来的时候，这些神经的运动经过脊椎一直到大脑，在大脑那里给精神一个信号使精神感觉到什么东西，比如在脚上的疼痛，精神就因此受到刺激，尽可能驱除疼的原因，把这个原因当成是对于脚非常危险、非常有害的东西。上帝可以把人的本性建立成这样的，即同样是这个运动，它在大脑里使精神感觉到其他不同的东西，举例来说，这个运动或许在大脑里，或许产生在脚上了，也许在脚和大脑之间别的什么地方，也许不管它是什么别的东西，不过所有这些都比不上它使精神感觉到那样好地有助于保存肉体的东西了。同样，当我们需要喝水的时候，它就在喉咙里发干，这就运动它的神经，用神经运动大脑里面的一些部分，这个运动使精神有渴的感觉，因为在这个过程中，没有别的比知道我们需要喝水来保存我们的健康更有用的东西了。其他情况也一样。

从以上这些就可以明显地看出，尽管有上帝的至善，由精神和肉体组合而成的人的本性，有的时候不可避免地显示出欺骗性。因为如果有什么原因不是在脚上，而是从脚一直到大脑抻起来的神经的某一个部分上，或者甚至在大脑里，刺激起来通常和脚不舒服时所刺激起来的是同样运动，那么人们将感觉到疼，就和疼是在脚上一模一样，感官就自然地要受骗了；因为既然在大脑里的一个同样运动只能在精神里引起一个同样的感觉，而这个感觉是脚受伤了的一个原因所刺激比在别处的原因所刺激的时候多得多，那么这个运动把脚疼而不是什么别的部分疼带给精神，这样说总算是更合理一些吧。而且喉咙发干不是像平常那样总是由于喝水对于身体的健康是必要的原因，而是有时由于什么完全相反的原因，就像患水肿病人所遭遇的那种情况，即使是这样，喉咙发干在这地方骗人也总比相反地当身体没有不舒服时骗人要好得多。其他情况也一样。

当然，这个考虑对我有很大好处，不仅体现在使我认识到我的本性可能犯的各种错误上，同时也体现在使我避免错误或者改正错误上。因为在对身体是否合适这一方面，我的各个感官告诉我的多半是真实的而不是虚假的，并且我总是使用多种感官来检查一种事物。而且，除此之外，我还能运用记忆，我的记忆把当前的一些认识和过去的一些认识关联起来，我也能利用我的理智，我的理智已经发现了我的各种错误的一切原因，那么从今以后我就不必害怕我的感官最经常告诉我的那些东西是假的了。而且我应该把我这几天的一切怀疑都抛弃掉，把它们都当作是言过其实、荒谬绝伦的东西，特别是把有关我过去不能把清醒和梦境分别开来的那种非常普遍不肯定的态度抛弃掉，因为我现在从这上面看出一种非常显著的区别，这个区别在于我们的记忆决不能像它习惯于把我们醒着时所遇到的那些事情连接起来那样，把我们的各种梦互相连接起来，把它们跟我们生活的连续性连接起来。而且事实上，假如有人在我醒着时突然出现在我面前又突然不见了，就像我在睡着时所见到的情景那样，我看不出他是从什么地方来的，也看不出他到什么地方去了，那么我就把他看成是在我大脑里形成的一个怪影或者一个幽灵，和我睡着时在大脑里形成的那些怪影或者幽灵一样，而不会把他看成是一个真人，这也并不是没有道理的。可是，当我知觉到一些东西，我清清楚楚地认识到它们是从什么地方来的，它们在什么地方，它们出现在我面前的时间，并且我能把我对它们产生的感觉毫无间断地同我生活的其余部分连接起来，那么我就完全可以肯定我是在醒着的时候而不是梦中知觉到它们。而且，如果在唤起我所有的感官、我的记忆和我的理智去检查这些东西之后，这些东西之中的任何一个告诉我的都没有任何东西跟其余的那些所告诉我的不一致，那么我就决不应该怀疑这些东西的真实性。因为，从上帝不是骗子这件事得出来的必然结果是，我在这方面并没有受骗。然而，由于事情的必然性经常迫使我们在我们得抽出时间在把这些事情加以非常仔细地检查之前去决定，那么就必须承认人生是有可能经常在那些个别的事情上犯错误的；并且最后，必须承认我们的本性存在着缺陷和弱点。

反驳和答辩（节选）

第一组反驳

（a）请问：一个观念的存在是否需要原因？或者请你告诉我，观念，到底是什么东西。就其客观地存在于理智之中而言，观念本身是被思考的东西吗？但是，客观地存在理智之中又是什么意思？如果我理解的没错的话，这就是按照一个对象的方式完成理智的行为；实际上，这无非是对其命名的调整，并没有给这个观念本身增加什么实在的东西。因为，就像被看见一样，在我心里不过是看的动作向我延伸，同样，被思维或者被客观地放在理智之中，这本身就是把思维终止或者使它停下；这在事物本身上用不着什么运动和改变，甚至用不着事物存在。我要问了，一个现实并不存在，或者说仅仅是一个缥缈的名字的“存在”需要什么原因呢？

虽然如此，这个伟大的人物说：当一个观念包含一个特定的客观实际性而非其他时，它无疑地要有什么原因。恰恰相反，什么原因也没有！因为客观实在性是一个纯粹的称号，它在现实上并不存在。可是，一个原因所给予的影响是实在的、现实的；现实不存在的东西并不能有原因，从而既不能取决于也不能产生任何真正的原因，也决不要求原因。因此，我有一些观念，可是这些观念没有原因，也绝对说不上存在一个比我更大的，本身无限的原因了。

（b）虽然人们同意，一件自然而然就在那里的东西，就已经暗示着它的存在，可是这不等于说这种存在性在大自然里就现实地是什么东西，而仅仅是，“存在”这个概念无可分割地和这个“至上存在体”联系到了一起。你无法由此推断出上帝的存在是实实在在的一件东西，除非你假定上帝是存在了的“至上存在体”。那样一来，它将包含一切完满性，甚至也包括了“现实存在”的完满性。

对第一组反驳的答辩

（a）我原先在什么地方曾经提及过，就其客观地存在于理智之中而言，观念就是领会或想到的东西本身。对于这句话，他故意理解的和我所说的有所不同，以便给我机会再清楚地解释一下。他说：客观地在理智之中，这就是按照对象化的方式来确定理智的行为，这无非是对其命名，并没有给观念本身增加什么实在的东西等等。大家应该注意到，他的意思是这件事情本身是在理智之外；这也是为什么他说那无非是对其命名。但是我所说的观念从来就不是理智之外的，所以，客观地存在只意味着它是以对象习惯在那里存在着的方式而存在于理智之中的。就好像如果有人问我，太阳，存在于我的客观理智中，对它而言会发生什么？最好的回答便是，除了他被外部的东西命名之外，什么也没发生，即它以一个对象的方式完结了我的理智的活动。但是如果人们问我，太阳的观念是什么，那么这又是什么东西呢？而人们回答说这就是被思维的那个东西本身，就其是客观地在理智之中而言，没有人会把它理解为就是太阳本身，就其是这个外部的名称在理智之中而言。而“客观地在理智之中”也并不意味着以一个对象的方式完结的活动，而是意味着以这些东西经常在那里的方式而在理智之中，这样一来太阳的观念就是太阳本身存在于理智之中，不是形式地，就像它在天上那样，而是客观地，也就是说以对象经常存在的方式而在理智之中。不错，这种存在的方式比什么东西存在于理智之外的方式要不完满得多，可是这并不是一个纯粹的什么都不是，就像我从前说过的那样。

当这位学识渊博的神学家说上面的说法有歧义时，他好像是想要提醒我刚刚说过的话，以免我不小心忘记。他说，首先以观念的形式存在于理智之中的这样一个东西并不是一个实体，也就是说，不是存在于理智之外的什么东西。这话不错。然后他又说，这并不是虚构的东西，或者说一个由理论推论出来的存在体，而是被清楚领会的一个实在的东西；通过这几句话，他完全接受了我所提出的东西。不过他接着说：这个东西仅仅是被领会的，而在现实上并不存在（也就是说，它仅仅是一个观念，而不是在理智之外的什么东西），它可以被领会，但是它不能被什么原因所引起，也就是说，它存在于理智之外这一点，并不需要原因。这一点我承认，不过为了被领会，它当然需要原因，而这就是问题所在。

比如，如果有人在心里有一个什么非常精巧机器的观念，人们有理由问是什么让人产生了这种想法；如果有人说这个机器在理智之外根本不存在，它也不能被什么原因所引起或者被领会的，这种说法是不会令人满意的；因为人们在这里问的唯一问题就是这个东西之所以被领会的原因是什么。有人说理智本身就是它的原因，因为它是自己活动的原因，这样的回答似乎也不尽人意。因为人们对于这一点并不怀疑，而争论的焦点只是在机器里面的客观人工技术的原因。因为这个观念会有这样一个而不是那样一个客观人工技术，它无疑要有一个原因。而具体技术在这个观念方面是和在上帝的观念的客观实在性或完满性方面是一致的。人们可以给这个技术指定各种原因；可能是某个实在的、相似的机器，这个观念就是模仿这个机器做成的；或者是在那个具有这个观念的人的理智之中的、对于机械的丰富的知识，或者也许是那个人的一个巧妙创造，能够在没有背景知识的情况下发明这个机器。必须指出，任何技巧（仅仅是客观地在这种观念之中）都必然要，或形式或卓越地，存在于它的原因之中，不管这种原因是什么。同样，关于上帝的观念的客观实在性也应该以同样的方式被理解。但是假如上帝不是真实存在的话，那么这个全部的实在性或者完满性能够在什么地方呢？

这位才华超众的人已经看到了所有这些事情；这就是为什么他十分合理地问道：为什么是这个观念而不是那个观念含有这种客观实在性；对于这个问题他首先回答说：一切观念都和我说过的关于三角形的观念一样，即，即使也许世界上任何地方都没有三角形，可是这并不妨碍有三角形的某一种确定不移的性质，或形式，或本质；这种性质是不需要原因的。不过他意识到，他所判断的并不能令人满意；因为，即使三角形的性质是不变的、永恒的，这并不能停止人们追问它的观念为什么在我们心中。因此他接着说：不过如果你们硬要我说出一个道理，我将告诉你们这是因为我们理智的本身就是不完满的，等等。不过这一回答，好像就意味着，那些想在这里反对我的人拿不出令人信服的东西来回应。显而易见的是，我们精神的不完满性才是上帝的观念在我们心中的缘故，并不比这样一件事更有道理，即我们想象一个非常精巧的机器而不去想象一个不完满的机器是由于对机器的无知。刚好相反，如果有人有一个关于机器的观念，在这个观念里含有人们可能想象出来的全部技巧，那么人们就有理由以此推论出这个观念是从一个原因产生的，在这个原因里确实的、有全部可想象的技巧，虽然这种技巧仅仅是客观的而不是事实上存在于这个观念之中的。同样道理，既然我们在心里有上帝这样一个观念，在这个观念里含有人们所能领会到的全部完满性，那么人们就可以由此轻易地得出结论，说这个观念取决于并产生于某些原因，这个原因本身真正地含有全部此种完满性，即上帝实际存在的这种完满性。

（b）我的论据是：只要是我们能够清楚地、分明地领会，属于什么东西的常住不变的、真正的本性，或本质，或形式的事物，那么就可以真正地说，这是属于这个事物的；可是，在我们足够仔细地追问上帝是什么的时候，我们能够清楚、明白地意识到他的存在是属于他真正、常住不变的本性，所以我们能够真正地肯定他的存在；至少这个结论的得出是符合前提的。不过这个大前提现在不能否定，因为大家已经在这上面达成了共识，即：凡是我们清楚、分明地理解或领会的东西都是真实的。剩下的问题就只有小前提了，我承认这方面是有不少困难的。首先，因为我们是如此习惯于在其他一切东西里把存在同本质加以区别，却不大注意存在性怎么属于上帝的本质而不属于其他东西的本质；其次，由于我们不习惯把那些属于什么的、真实的、常住不变的本质的东西同那些仅仅由于我们理智的幻想而归之于它的东西加以区别，那么，虽然我们相当清楚地看出存在性是属于上帝的本质，我们却不能由此而得出结论说上帝存在，因为我们不知道他的本质是否是常住不变的、真实的，或者他的本质是否仅仅是由我们的精神虚构的、捏造的。

不过，为了排除这个困难的第一部分，必须在可能的存在性和必然的存在性之间加以区别，并且指出可能的存在性是包含在我所清楚、分明地领会的一切东西的概念或观念里，而必然的存在性只是包含在上帝的观念里。只要是仔细地考虑在上帝的观念同其他一切观念之间的区别的人，会毫无疑问地看出以下的事实，即：虽然我们仅仅把其他东西领会为是存在的，但这并不意味着它们确实存在，而只说明它们有能力存在；因为我们领会到，现实的存在性与这些东西的其他特性间的关联不是必然的，而从我们清楚地领会现实的存在性是必然地、永远地和上帝其他属性联结在一起的，随之而来的必然是上帝存在。

为了排除困难的另外一个部分，必须注意不包含真实、常住不变的本性而只包含虚构、由理智组合成的那些观念，他们可以被理智本身，不仅用它的思维，而且用一种清楚、分明的活动，加以分割；这样一来，不能被理智这样分割的东西就无疑地不是由它组合而成的。举例来说，当我想象一个带翅膀的马，或者一个现实存在的狮子，或者在一个正方形里画出的三角形时，我很容易领会到，我也可以完全相反地想出来一个没有翅膀的马，一个不存在的狮子，一个不带正方形的三角形，从而这些东西没有真实的、常住不变的本性。如果我想出来一个三角形，或一个正方形（我在这里不去说狮子和马，因为它们的本质还没有完全被认识），那么当然，凡是我认为属于三角形这个观念的东西，比如它的三角之和等于二直角，等等，我都将真实地肯定它是一个三角形，并且凡是我认为属于正方形这个观念的东西都是属于正方形的；因为，对于领会一个三角形，虽然我可以把思维限制到无论如何我只能领会三角之和等于二直角，我却不能用一种清楚、分明的活动，也就是说清楚并理解我所说的，去从它身上否定这个东西。还有，如果我考虑一个画在正方形里边的三角形，不是为了把只属于三角形的东西归给正方形，或者把属于正方形的东西归给三角形，而是仅仅为了检查由二者的结合而产生的东西，那么由三角形和正方形组合起来的这个图形的本性就不会不如只是正方形或者只是三角形的本性真实、不变。这样一来我就可以一点不错地确认正方形并不比里边的三角形的两倍小，对于属于这个组合成的图形的本性的其他东西来说，道理是一样的。

可是，如果我考虑一个非常完满的物体的观念，这里包含着存在性，这是因为在事实上存在，同时也在理智中存在，比只是在理智中存在有更大的完满性，我就不能由此断言这个非常完满的物体存在，而只能说有存在的能力。因为我清楚地认识到这个观念是由我的理智本身作出来的，理智把一切物体性的完满性都结合在一起了；同样，存在性并不从包含在物体的本性中的其他完满性中得出来，相反，我们既可以肯定它们存在，也可以否定它们存在。由于在检查物体的观念时，我在物体里边看不出有任何力量足以使它自己产生自己或者自己保存自己，我就可以很肯定地断言必然的存在性（问题在这里只在于这种存在性），尽管它是多么完满，和它属于一个没有谷的山的本性，或者属于一个比二直角更大的三角形的本性是一样的不合适的。

如果现在我们问的，不是关于一个物体，而是关于一个不拘泥于任何形式的东西，它本身具有一切完满性，是否存在性应该被算在这些完满性里，我们应该在最开始的时候就怀疑这样的事情。由于我们有限的思维只习惯于把那些完满性分别考虑，也许无法瞬间注意到他们之间必然的紧密联系。可是，如果我们仔细地考查一下，即：存在性是否，以及什么样的存在性适合于“至上存在体”，我们就会清楚、分明地认识到如下事实。首先，可能的存在性至少对它是合适的，就像我们具有清晰观念的其他东西一样，甚至对那些由我们的精神幻想组合而成的东西都适合一样；现在如果我们认知到他强大的力量，我们无法想到它的存在性是可能的，除非，与此同时我们能够认知它是依靠自己力量存在的。我们就会由此断言它实实在在地存在，它曾经是完全永恒地存在。非常明显的，自然之光告诉我们，能够依靠自己力量存在的，就会永远存在；这样，我们将认识到必然的存在性是包含在一个“至上存在体”的观念里，不是由于理智的虚构，而是由于它属于这样一个存在体的真实、不变的本性而存在；我们也将很容易认识到，这个“至上存在体”不可能在他自身内不包含上帝观念里的其他一切完满性，因此，它们都是由于其本性，不是由于理智的任何虚构而联结在一起的，并且存在于上帝之中。

第二组反驳

（a）你认识到你是一个在思维着的东西，可是你不知道这个在思维着的东西是什么。你怎么知道这不是一个物体，由于它的各种不同的运动和接触而做出我们称之为思维的这种行动呢？因为，虽然你认为你已经抛弃掉了一切种类的物体，但是你可能在这里犯了一个错误，即，你并没有把你自己抛弃掉，而你自己也很可能只是一个物体。你如何证明一个物体不能思维，或者某些物体性的运动不是思维的本身呢？为什么你认为已经抛弃掉的肉体的全部系统，或者这个系统的某几个部分，比如说大脑那些部分，不能有助于做成我们称之为思维的那些种类的运动呢？你说，我是一个在思维着的东西：可是你怎么知道你不也是一个物体性的运动或者一个被移动的物体呢？

（b）既然你还不确切地知道上帝的存在，而且你不能肯定你是那种确定的东西，或者说你对任何事物有任何清楚、明确的认知，除非你能预先明确、清楚地知晓上帝的存在，由此推演，你无法清楚地知道你是一个思考着的东西，按照你的说法，这种认识取决于对一个存在的上帝的清楚认识，而这种认识你还没有在你确定清楚地认识你是什么的那些地方证明过。

此外，一个无神论者清楚、分明地知道三角形三角之和等于二直角，但是他决不信上帝存在，并完全否认它的存在，他说，假如上帝存在，那就会有一个至上的存在体和一个至上的善，也就是说，一个无限；然而，在一切种类的完满性上，这种无限排除一切其他完满性，不仅排除一切种类的存在体和善，而且也排除一切种类的非存在体和恶。鉴于仍然有许多存在体和许多善，也仍然有许多非存在体和许多恶，我们认为你应该给予回应才好，使不信神的人再没有可反驳的，再没有什么可被用作他们不信神的借口。

（c）你如何知道，自己在清楚、分明认识的东西上从来没被蒙蔽，而且也不会被蒙蔽？多少次我们看到有人在他们认为比太阳还清楚的一些事物上受蒙蔽？由此可见，需要把清楚、分明的认识这条原则解释得非常清楚、分明，使但凡有理智之人不会在他们认为知道得清楚、分明的事物上受蒙蔽。

（d）当你对前一组反驳作出回应时，你得出的结论似乎不正确，结论如下：那些被我们清楚、分明地理解，属于什么事物常住不变的、真实的本性，可以被真正地理解为是属于这事物的；但当我们足够仔细地观察了上帝是什么之后，我们清楚、分明地理解他的存在是属于他真正、常住不变的本性。于是你可以得出如下结论：在我们足够仔细地观察了上帝是什么之后，我们能够确认这个真理，即上帝的存在是属于他的本性的。这并不等于说上帝事实上存在，而只能说他应该存在，如果他的本性是可能的或者不相矛盾的话。也就是说，上帝的本性或本质不能领会为没有存在性，鉴于这种本质存在，他就实际上存在。这和其他的某些论证不谋而合：如果在上帝的存在上没有矛盾，那么上帝存在就是肯定的；而在上帝之存在上没有矛盾。但问题在于小前提，即：上帝之存在没有矛盾，那些不同意的人中有些持怀疑态度，另外一些就干脆否认。

（e）从灵魂与肉体的区别上似乎不能得出灵魂是不可毁灭的或不死的这个结论来；若是灵魂的本性因肉体生命的长短而受到限制呢？若是上帝曾赋予自身力量和存在性使它同肉体一起完结呢？

对第二组反驳的答辩

（a）你们又问：我如何论证物体不能思维。如果我回答说我还没有谈到这个问题，就请你们谅解我，因为要到第六个沉思时我才会谈这个问题。我是用如下几句话论述的：我能够清楚、分明地领会一个东西而不牵涉到别的东西，就足以确定这一个东西和那一个东西有所不同，等等，后面不远的地方又谈道：

虽然我有一个肉体，我和它非常紧密地结合在一起，不过，一方面我对我自己有一个清楚、分明的观念，即我只是一个在思维的东西而没有延伸空间，而另一方面，我对于肉体有一个清楚、分明的观念，即它只是一个有延伸空间的东西而不能思维，所以肯定的是这个我，也就是我的精神或我的灵魂，即我之所以为我的那个东西，是完全、真正跟我的肉体有分别的，它可以没有肉体而存在。

在这上面可以加上一句：凡是能够思维的就是精神，或者就叫作精神。由于身体和精神是实际上有分别的，那么任何身体都不是精神。所以任何物体都不能思维。

在这上面我看不出有什么是你们可以否认的；是因为你觉得我们清楚地领会一个东西而不牵涉到另外一个东西就不足以知道它们实际上是有分别的吗？要是那样的话，你应该提供一些能够分辨真正不同的标准，但我很肯定，你给不出来。你们又会说什么呢？如果两个东西能够不依托于对方而存在，他们就真的有分别了吗？可是我再问你们，你们怎么知道一个东西可以不依托另一个而存在？如果这是一个分别的标准，人们应该知道它。也许你们会说：感官使你们知道，因为你们看见两个东西彼此分离，不依附，或者你们摸到了它，等等。可是对感官的信任比对理智的信任更不可靠；同一个东西可能以不同的方式给我们的感官表现出各种不同的形式，或者在几个地方表现为几种样子，这样它就被当作是两个。最后，如果你们还记得我在第二个沉思的末尾说过的关于蜡的话，你们就会知道物体本身不能真正地被感官认识，而只能被理智认识；因此，感觉一个东西而不牵涉到另一个东西无非是一个东西的观念，即这个观念和另外一个东西的观念不是同一的。我们只能从这样一个事实来理解，一个东西在不受另一个东西的影响下可以被感知，而且只有一个东西在不牵涉到另一个东西也能被领会的情况下才能被认识。这样一来，关于“真正的区分”的标准就应该还原到我的标准上才是靠得住的。

（b）当我说我们不能确切地认识上帝，除非我们预先知道他的存在时，我声明，我谈论的只是那些不用考虑前提条件就能推导出结论的知识。但是逻辑学家还没有把原理的知识称作科学知识的习惯。但当我们发觉我们是在思维着的东西时，这是一个第一概念，这个概念并不是从任何三段论式推论出来的。即使有人说：我思维，所以我存在，他因思维而得出存在这个结论并不是根据三段论式，而是从一种不言自明的简单精神洞察出来的。从以下的事实看，事情是很明显的，如果他是从一种三段论式推论出来的，他必须预先认识这个大前提：思维的东西都存在。然而，他是从他不存在就不能思维这个事实体会到这一点的。由个别的认识推论出广泛通用的命题，这是我们精神的本性。

（c）我们一旦认为清楚地领会了一件事情，我们就自然地相信它。如果这种信念坚强到我们永远没有任何理由怀疑那些像这样相信的东西的程度的话，那么就没有任何东西要去进一步追寻了，我们已经有了我们希望的一切。如果也许有人硬说我们如此强烈相信其真实性的东西在上帝眼里或者在天使眼里是有偏差的，并且因此说他是完全错误的，这跟我们有什么关系呢？既然我们根本不相信，也没有丝毫有力的证据，我们为什么要在意这样一个绝对的错误？我们坚信一个信念，坚信到不可动摇的程度，那么这个信念就成了非常可靠的真理。

但人们可能会怀疑是否有人有像这样的可靠性，或者某种坚定不移的信念。

当然，人们不能对于模糊不清的东西有什么信念，即使是一点点的模糊不清也不行；因为不管是什么样的模糊不清都是使我们对这些东西产生怀疑的原因。对于由感觉得来的东西也不能有信念，因为我们经常发现感官会出现偏差，就像一个水肿病人口渴或者有黄疸病的人看雪是黄色的，那个人看雪清楚、分明的程度不比我们差，而我们看雪却是白色的。因此，如果人们能够有信念，那仅仅是精神领会得清楚、明白的东西。

可是，在这些东西里边，有一些是那么清楚，同时又是那么简单，以致我们不可能认为它们不是真的。例如，当我思维时我存在；做了的事情无法回到没做的状态；以及诸如此类的东西。对于这些东西，我们显然是有十足把握的。因为如果我们不想那些东西，我们就不能怀疑它们；但如果我们不相信它们是真的，我们就决不会想到它们，就像我刚才说的那样。所以如果不同时相信它们是真的，我们就不能怀疑它们，也就是说，我们永远没办法怀疑它们。

我们时常遇到有些人在他们以为比看见太阳还清楚的一些事物上弄错，这也没有什么用处；因为，不管是我们或者任何人都没有看见过这样的事情发生在那些能够单独从他们理智知觉中得出全部清楚、分明性的人的身上，只看见过这样的事情发生在那些从感官或者从什么错误的偏见中得出全部清楚、分明性的人的身上。

想要假装认为这样的事情在上帝或者天使看来是错误的，也没什么用，因为我们知觉的明显性决不允许我们去相信如此假装的人。

还有一些其他东西，我们不能怀疑它们，因为我们的理智，根据我们已有的理解能力，对它们领会得十分清楚；但是，我们可能忘记那些原因，并且记住从这些原因推论出的结论，人们问道，对于这些结论，在我们记得它们是从一些非常明显的原则推论出来的时候，是否能够有一个坚定不移的信念；因为这个记忆必须设定，以便这些结论能够被称之为结论。我回答说，只有那些认识上帝到如此程度，以致他们知道由上帝给予的理解功能只能以真理作为对象的人，才能够对于这些结论有一个坚定不移的信念；不过其他人不能够有这样的信念。

（d）当批评我由一个三段论式构建的结论时，你们好像犯了一个错误。因为，为了得出你们所要的结论，大前提应该是这样的：凡是被我们清楚、分明地领会为属于某事物本性的东西，都能真正地被说成或者被肯定为是属于这个事物的本性。这样一来，这个大前提除了无用的、多余的重复以外，没有包含什么东西。可是我的论据的大前提是这样的：凡是被我们清楚、分明地领会为属于某事物本性的东西，都能真正地被说成或者被肯定为是属于这个东西的。这就是说，如果“是动物”属于人的本性，那么可以肯定人是动物；如果三角之和等于二直角属于三角形的本性，那么就可以肯定三角形三角之和等于二直角；如果存在属于上帝的本性，那么就可以肯定上帝存在，等等。小前提是这样的：而存在是属于上帝的本性的。从这里显然必须得出像我所说的那样的结论，即：所以我们可以真正地肯定说上帝存在，而不是像你们所想那样：所以我们可以真正地肯定说存在是属于上帝本性的。

这样，为了能够使用你们提出的特例，你们本来应该否认大前提，说我们清楚地理解什么是属于东西的本性，不能因此就被说成是或被肯定是属于这个东西，除非是它的本性是可能的，或者不矛盾的。不过，我请你们看一看这个特例的缺点。因为，要么是你们用可能这个词，像一般人所做的那样，指的是凡是与人类思想不相矛盾的东西，在这种意义上，上帝的本性，按照我所描写的方式来说，显然是可能的，因为在上帝的本性身上，除了我们清楚、分明地领会为应该属于他的东西以外，我并没有假定什么东西，这样我就没有假定什么与思想或人类概念相矛盾的东西；要么是你们假想出什么其他的可能性，从对象本身来说，这种可能性如果与前一种可能性相矛盾，就决不能被人类理智所认识，从而它就和否定人的认识中的其他一切东西一样，没有什么力量来迫使我们去否定上帝的本性或者上帝的存在。因为，如果把上帝的本性是可能的这件事加以否定，虽然从概念或从思想方面来说没有什么不可能，可是相反，凡是包含在上帝本性的这个概念里的东西都是如此地互相衔接，以致如果说其中有某一个不属于上帝的本性，这对我们来说似乎是矛盾的；因此，如果上帝的本性是可能的这件事可以去否定，那么同样道理，也可以去否定一个三角形三角之和等于二直角是可能的，或者现实在思维的人存在是可能的；尤有甚者，人们甚至可以否定凡是我们由感觉知觉到的一切东西都是真的。那样一来，人类的一切知识都将既无丝毫理由，又无任何根据而被完全推翻。

（e）至于你们补充说，从灵魂与肉体之间的区别不能得出灵魂不死这个结论来，因为虽然有区别，可是人们可以说上帝把灵魂做成这样一种性质，使它的延续时间和肉体的生命的延续时间同时完结，我承认我没有什么可答辩的，因为我没有那么大的胆量去企图用人类的推理力量来规定一个只取决于上帝的纯粹意志的东西。自然的认识告诉我们精神是与物体有别的，精神是一种实体；同时，人的肉体，就其与其他物体有别而言，不过是由某一种外形的肢体以及诸如此类的偶性组合而成；最后，肉体的死亡仅仅取决于形状的某种分解或改变。然而，我们没有任何论据也没有任何例证使我们相信，像精神这样一个实体的死亡或毁灭必须遵循这样一个微不足道的原因，如形状的改变，而形状的改变不过是一个样态，更何况这个样态又不是精神的样态，而是与精神实际上有别的肉体的样态。我们甚至没有任何论据或例证可以使我们相信有些实体是可以被毁灭的。这就足以得出结论说，人的精神或灵魂，按其能够被自然哲学所认识的程度来说，是不死的。

可是如果有人问道，是否也许上帝用他的绝对能力，规定了人的灵魂会因它与之联合的肉体的毁灭而同时停止存在？这只能由上帝自己来回答。既然他现在向我们启示这样的事不会发生，关于这件事我们不应该再有任何怀疑了。

证明方式是双重的：一个是由分析法或决定法做的，一个是由综合法或组合法做的。

分析法指出一条一件事物由之而被有条不紊地发现出来的真正道路，同时也指明结果如何取决于原因；这样，如果读者们愿意遵循这个方法并且仔细注视它所包含的一切东西，他们就会把这样证明了的东西理解得同样完满，就跟他们自己发现了它一样成为他们自己的东西。不过这种证明不足以使顽固的、不用心的读者信服；因为，如果一不经心漏掉了它所提出的一点点小事情，它的结论的必然性就不会出现；人们没有习惯大量检查那些本身足够明确的东西，虽然那是最应该注意的东西。

综合法则相反，它走的是一条完全不同的道路，好像从结果里检查原因一样（虽然它所包含的证明经常也是由原因检查结果），它固然清楚地证明在结论里所包含的东西，并且使用了一长串的定义、要求、公理、定理和问题，以便如果否认它的什么结论的话，它就指出这些结论是怎样包含在前提里边的，这样它就会使读者们（不管他们是多么顽固不化）不得不同意，不过它不像另外那种方法那样，使那些希望学习的人感到完全满足，因为事物是用什么方法发现的，它不告诉你。

几何学方式证明上帝的存在和人的精神

与肉体之间的区别的依据

一、关于思维这一词，我是指凡是像这样存在于我们的心里，使我们对之有直接认识的东西。这样一来，凡是意志的活动、理智的活动、想象的活动和感官的活动都是思维。可是我加上“直接”这个词，这是为了把附加和取决于我们思维的东西排除在外。举例来说，出于意愿的运动虽然真正来说是以意志为其原则的，但是它本身并不是思维。

二、关于观念这一词，我是指我们的每个思维的这样一种形式，由于这种形式的直接知觉，我们对这些思维才有认识。因此，当我理解我所说的话时，除非肯定在我心里具有关于用我的言词所意味着的东西的观念，我用言词什么都表明不了。因此，仅仅是任意描绘出来的影像，我不把它们称之为观念；相反，这些影像，当它们是由肉体任意描绘出来的时候，也就是说，当它们是大脑的某些部分描绘出来的时候，我不把它们称之为观念，而只有当它们通知到大脑的这一个部分的精神本身的时候，我才把它们称为观念。

三、关于一个观念的客观实在性，我是指用观念表象的东西的实体性或存在性，就这个实体性是在观念里边而言。同样，人们可以说一个客观的完满性，或者一个客观的技巧等等。因为凡是我们领会为在观念的对象里边的东西都是客观地或者通过表象存在于观念本身里。

四、当这些东西在观念的对象里边就如同我们所领会那个样子时，这些东西就叫作形式地存在于观念的对象里；当这些东西在观念里边实际上不是像我们所领会的那个样子，而是如此的伟大以致它们能够用它们的优越性来弥补这个缺点时，它们就叫作卓越地存在于观念的对象里。

五、凡是被别的东西作为其主体而直接寓于其中的东西，或者我们所领会的（也就是说，在我们心中有其实在的观念的某种特性、性质或属性的）某种东西由之而存在的东西，就叫作实体。因为实体是这样的一种东西，在它里边形式地或卓越地存在着我们所知觉的，或者客观地在我们某一个观念里边的东西；除此而外，严格说来我们对实体没有其他概念，因为自然的光明告诉我们“无”不能有任何实在的属性。

六、思维直接寓于其中的实体，在这里就叫作精神。我所指的是精神不是灵魂，因为灵魂这个名称是有歧义的，人们可能会用它来指代物质性的东西。

七、作为广延以及以广延为前提的偶性（如形状、位置、地点的运动等等）的直接主体，叫作物体或肉体、身体。不过，如要知道叫作精神的实体是否同时就是叫作物体的实体，或者是否它们是两个不同的实体，这留待以后再去研究。

八、我们把理解为至上完满的、我们了解其中没有包含着任何缺点或对完满性有限制的东西的实体就叫作上帝。

九、当我们说某种属性包含，或者在其概念里在一个东西的本性时，我们可以说如果这个事物是真实的，那么它所包含的事物也是真实的。

十、当两种实体之间，不以另一个的存在为前提而存在的，这两种实体就是相互区别的。

第三组反驳

反驳

因为从我思维或从我有一个观念，可以推论出我是有思维的，因为我思维和我是在思维的，二者是一个意思。从我是在思维的，得出我存在；因为思维的东西并非什么都不是。不过，我们的著者在这里加上了“也就是说，一个精神，一个灵魂，一个理智，一个理性”，从这里我就产生出来一个疑问。因为我认为：说我是在思维的，因而我是一个思维，或者说，我是有理智的，因而我是一个理智，这样的推理是不正确的。因为我也可以用同样的推理说：我是在散步，因而我是一个散步。笛卡尔先生把有理智的东西和理智当作一回事了；或者至少他说在理解的东西和理智是一个东西。可是所有的哲学家都把主体跟它的功能和行为，也就是说，跟它的特性和本质区别开来。因为这跟东西本身的存在和它的本质不是一回事；因此一个在思维的东西可以是精神、理性或者理智的主体，从而是物体性的东西，可是他提出来的倒是与此相反的东西而没有加以证明。虽然如此，笛卡尔先生想要建立的结论，其根据好像就在于此。

在同一地方，他说道：“我认识到了我存在，现在我追问，我认识了我存在这个我究竟是谁。可是，非常可靠的是，关于我自己的这个概念和认识，严格来说不取决于我还不知道其存在的那些东西。”

他说得非常正确：对我存在这个命题的认识之取决于我思维这个命题是非常可靠的；可是对我思维这个命题的认识是从哪里来的呢？不错，这无非是来自：没有主体，我们就不能领会其任何行为，就像没有一个在思维的东西就不能领会思维，没有一个在知道的东西就不能领会知道，没有一个散步的东西就不能领会散步一样。

答辩

我曾经说的“也就是说，一个精神，一个灵魂，一个理智，一个理性……”，我用这几个名称不是指单独的功能，而是指能有思维功能的东西，就像人们习惯于用前头两个所指的，以及人们经常用后头两个所指的那样。这是我经常而且用非常明显的词句解释过的，我看不出有什么可疑的地方。

在散步和思维之间，没有什么关系；因为散步除了行动本身之外，从来不指别的，而思维有时指行动，有时指功能，有时指寓于这个功能之内的东西。

我并没有说理智和在理解的东西是一回事，也没有说，如果把理智当作一种功能，而仅仅是当理智被当作在理解的东西的时候，我才说它们是一回事。我坦率地承认，为了说明一个东西或一个实体，我要把凡是不属于它的东西都要从它身上剥掉，我尽可能使用了简单、抽象的词句；而相反，这位哲学家为了说明同一的实体，却使用了另外的一些非常具体、非常复杂的词句，比如主体、物质以及物体，以便尽可能地不把思维和物体（或身体）分别开来。

我并不害怕他所使用的方法，也就是说把几种东西连接在一起，比我所使用的方法（即用以尽可能地分辨每一个东西）更能有效地认识真理。但是不要再多说空话了，还是让我们看看问题的所在吧。

他说：“一个在思维的东西可以是物体性的，可是他提出来的倒是与此相反的东西，而没有加以证明。”这是不对的，我没有提出相反的东西，我也绝对没有把它当作根据，我不过是完全未置可否，一直把它留到第六个沉思才对它加以证明。

后来，他说得很好：“没有主体，我们就不能领会其任何行为，就仿佛没有一个在思维的东西，就不能进行思维一样，因为在思维的东西不是无。”不过他接着说，“从这里似乎应该得出这样一个结论，即一个在思维的东西是某种物体性的东西”，这就毫无道理，不合逻辑，甚至跟通常说话的方式相反了。因为一切行为的主体当然是指实体说的（或者，如果他愿意的话，是指物质，即抽象的物质）；不过不能因此就说它们是物体。

反驳

而且，当笛卡尔说上帝的观念和灵魂的观念是与生俱来的，我想知道那些正在熟睡而没有做梦的人是否在思考。如果他们没有，那么他们在那个时候则没有观念。因此，没有任何观念是与生俱来的，而任何与生俱来的都是当下存在的。

答辩

当我们说有些观念是与生俱来的，这并不意味着这种观念时时伴随着我们，依照那样的说法，没有任何观念是与生俱来的了。我们这里仅指我们自身有产生观点的能力。

第四组反驳

（a）假如有人知道半圆上的圆周角是直角，从而用这个角和圆的直径做成的三角形是直角三角形，可是，他怀疑并且还不确定，并且由于一些诡辩误导了他的思维，他会否认由直角三角形的斜边做成的正方形等于由两条直角边做成的两个正方形之和，按照笛卡尔先生的意见，他好像应该坚持他的错误见解。因为他会说，我清楚、分明地领会这个三角形是直角三角形，但是我怀疑由它的斜边做成的正方形等于由它的两条直角边做成的两个正方形之和。因此，由直角三角形的斜边做成的正方形等于由两个直角边做成的两个正方形之和是不属于这个三角的本质的。

另外，虽然我否认由它的斜边做成正方形等于由两个直角边做成的两个正方形之和，不过我确实知道它是直角的，而且这个三角形的一个角是直角这件事在我的心中一直是清清楚楚的，就是上帝自己都不能使它不是直角三角形。

从而，我所怀疑的，我甚至可以否认的，一直存在于我心中的这个观念并不属于它的本质。

此外，由于我知道凡是我清楚、分明地领会的东西，都能像我领会的那样由上帝产生，所以只要我能够清楚、分明地领会一个东西而用不着一个别的东西，就足以确定这一个东西和那一个东西有分别，因为上帝可以把它们分开。可是我清楚、分明地领会这个三角形是直角三角形，用不着我知道由它的斜边做成的正方形等于由它的两直角边做成的两个正方形之和；因此，有可能是由三角形的斜边做成的正方形不等于由它的两直角边做成的两个正方形之和，至少是上帝可以使它这样。

我看不出在这里能够回答什么，除非这个回答的人不是清楚、分明地领会直角三角形的性质。可是我怎么知道我认识我的精神的性质比他认识这个三角形的性质认识得更好呢？因为，他之确知半圆的圆周三角形有一个直角（这是直角三角形的概念），和我之确知我思维所以我存在是同样的。

所以，跟那个认为这个三角形的斜边上做成的正方形等于两直角边上做成的两个正方形之和并不是这个三角形（他所清楚、分明认识的直角三角形）的本质这件事上弄错的人完全一样，也许我也在我认为除了我是一个在思维着的东西以外，没有什么别的东西是属于我的本性（我清楚、分明地知道我是一个在思维着的东西）这件事上弄错，因为也许我是一个有广延的东西这件事也是属于我的本质的吧？

（b）我只剩下一个疑虑了，那就是，对于他所说的话，只有由于上帝存在，我们才肯定我们清楚明白地领会的东西是真的，他怎么辩护才能免于陷入循环论证。因为，我们之所以肯定上帝存在，只因为我们对这件事领会得非常清楚、非常明白，因此，在我们肯定上帝存在之前，我们必须先肯定凡是我们领会得清楚、分明的东西都是真的。

有一件事情我之前想不起来了，现在把它提出来，那就是，就他是一个在思维的东西而言，不管什么东西，如果他对这个东西没有认识，就不能存在于他的内心。这个命题我认为是错误的，而笛卡尔先生认为是非常正确的。因为在他的内心，就其是一个在思维的东西而言这句话，在他的内心里面的“他”，就精神之有别于肉体而言，除了指他的精神，不指别的东西。但是，有谁看不出来，在精神里能够有很多东西，而精神本身对这些东西毫无认识？举例来说：一个在母亲肚子里的小孩子的精神当然有思维的能力或功能，可是他对它没有认识。类似这样的东西还有很多，我就不讲了。

对第四组反驳的答辩

（a）虽然如此，我们这位博学的朋友强调说：虽然我可以对我自己不用物体的概念而取得什么概念，可是不能由此得出结论说这个概念是完全的、全部的，从而我可以确知当我从我的本质排除物体时，我没有弄错。他用内接于半圆的三角形的例子来说明我们能够很清楚、分明地领会这是直角三角形，虽然我们不知道或者甚至否认在它的斜边上的正方形等于两个直角边上的正方形。虽然如此，我们不能由之而得出我们能够作出一个直角三角形而其斜边上的正方形不等于两个直角边上的正方形之和。

不过，就这个例子来说，它在许多方面跟所提出的东西不同；因为，第一，虽然也许对于一个三角形，我们可以把它理解为一个实体，这个实体的形状是三角的，可是有着斜边上的正方形等于两个直角边上的正方形之和这个特点肯定不是一个实体，从而这两个东西的任何一个都不能被理解为完全的东西。精神和肉体也是这样。甚至这个特点也不能称之为东西，按照我说过这足以使我能够领会一个东西（指一个完全的东西）而用不着领会另外一个东西等等的意思，下面的话是非常容易理解的：再说，我在里边找到一些功能，等等。因为，我并没有说这些功能是东西，不过我特别想在东西（也就是说实体）与这些东西的方式（也就是说这些实体的功能）之间作出分别。

第二，虽然我们用不着知觉到它的斜边上的正方形等于两个直角边上的正方形之和，就能够清楚、明白地领会内接于半圆的三角形是直角三角形，可是我们不能这样清楚地领会一个三角形的斜边上的正方形等于两个直角边上的正方形之和，而用不着同时领会这个三角形是直角的；不过我们用不着肉体就清楚、分明地领会精神，反过来也一样，我们用不着精神就清楚、分明地领会肉体。

第三，虽然内接于半圆的三角形的概念或观念可以不包含斜边上的正方形等于两个直角边上的正方形之和，可是这个概念或观念不能是这样的，即我们不能领会能够在斜边上的正方形和两个直角边上的正方形之间，没有一个比例关系是属于这个三角形的。从而，当我们不知道这个比例关系是什么的时候，除了我们清楚地领会的那个比例关系不属于它以外，我们不能否认任何一个别的比例关系。不过，在它们两个之间的相等的比例关系上来理解这一点，这是绝对办不到的。但是，在肉体的概念里边不包含任何属于精神的东西；反过来，在精神的概念里边也不包含任何属于肉体的东西。

因此，虽然我说过只要我用不着一个别的东西就能够清楚、分明领会一个东西就足够了，等等，不能因此就作出这个小前提：可是我清楚、分明地领会到这个三角形是直角三角形，虽然我怀疑或者否认它的斜边上的正方形等于两直角边上的正方形之和，等等。因为第一，在斜边上的正方形和两直角边上的正方形之间相等的比例关系并不是一个完全的东西；第二，这个相等的比例关系只有在一个直角三角形中我们才能清清楚楚地理解到。第三，如果我们否认在一个三角形的斜边上的正方形和它的两直角边上的正方形之间的比例关系，我们就不能清清楚楚地领会这个三角形。

（b）最后，我已经在我对第二组反驳的答辩中……清楚地指出，当我说我们确知我们非常清楚、非常明白地领会的东西之所以都是真的是因为上帝存在，而我们确知上帝存在是因为我们对上帝存在领会得非常清楚、非常分明。我这样说并没有陷入循环论证中，我是把我们事实上领会得非常清楚的东西同我们记得以前曾领会得非常清楚的东西区别开来。之所以这样是因为，首先我们确信上帝的存在，因为我们注意到那些证明上帝存在的理由；不过在这以后，还需要我们记得曾经把一个东西领会得清清楚楚以便确知它是真的，如果我们不知道上帝存在，不知道他不可能是骗子，这就不行。

关于是否任何东西都不能存在于我们的精神里（就精神只是一个在思维的东西而言），假如精神本身对那个东西没有实现认识的话，这个问题，我认为非常容易解决，因为当我们这样认为它的时候，我们看得很清楚，就精神只是一个在思维着的东西而言，除了思维或者完全取决于思维的东西之外，没有什么东西存在于它里边，否则就不属于精神；而在我们心中不可能有任何思维（在它存在于我们心中的同时）是我们对之没有一种现实认识的。因此我不怀疑精神渗入到一个小孩子的身体里就开始思维，从这时起他就知道他思维，虽然他以后不记得他思维什么，因为他所思维的东西没有刻印在他的记忆里。

不过需要注意的是，我们对于我们的精神的行为或活动有一种现实的认识而并不总是对于它的功能才有现实的认识，除非是潜在的。因此，当我们打算使用什么功能的时候，如果这个功能是在我们的精神里，我们立刻就得到关于它的现实认识。就是因为这个缘故，如果我们不能得到关于它的这种现实认识，我们就可以确定无疑地否认它在那里。

第五组反驳

（a）每当你说出或在心里想到“有我，我存在”这个命题时，它就必然是真的。不过我看不出你为什么需要费那么多的事，既然你已经确实知道你存在，既然你能够从你别的什么行动上得出同样的结论，既然自然的光明明显地告诉我们，凡是起作用的东西，都有，或都存在。

（b）你接着又说如果事物的一部分有可能出现错误会比所有的部分都一样不出现错误更完满，这就好比说，一个国家，如果一部分公民作恶多端反而比所有的公民都是遵纪守法的公民要完美。这样一来就可以得出，既然统治者希望他的臣民都是遵纪守法的公民，那么宇宙的创造者在创造世间万物的各个部分时会让他们免于犯错误，并且也应该这样做。尽管你可以说与容易犯错误的部分相比，那些不会犯错误的东西才显得更为完美，这是很偶然的事情。同样地，与邪恶之人相比善良之人的品格在某些程度上大放光彩，这也是偶然才大放光彩的。这样，要是有些公民作恶才能显示出另外一部分公民的良好品德，这显然是不合适的。如果为了显示部分不会犯错的更完满而把另一部分创造得容易出现错误，这显然是不应该的。

如果上帝是为你在这个世界中选择一个特定的角色，而这个角色既不是最完美的也不是最重要的，你说你没有权利去抱怨这件事。但是，这样的回答却不能帮助我们解答这个问题，也就是说，比起一个不完满的角色，上帝为什么不在各种完满的角色中为你挑选一个级别比较低的呢？如果一个统治者并没有委任所有的公民以高位，相反地却把一部分人安排在中层，一部分人安排在基层，这没有什么不对的。如果一个统治者不仅仅把一些人安排在最基层位置，还把一些人安排在违法作乱的位置上，那么这个统治者就会遭到人们的诟病了。

（c）然后，对于你对你自己的观念，尤其是讨论第二个沉思时已经说过了的，我没有更多的话说。因为，在那上面，大家看得很清楚，你绝不是对你自己有一个清楚、分明的概念；相反，似乎你对你自己根本没有概念。因为虽然你肯定知道你在思维，可是你并不知道在思维的你是什么东西，因而尽管你清清楚楚地知道了这一个活动，但主要的你还不知道，即你还不知道这个实体是什么，而思维只是这个实体的许多活动之一。从而我觉得我很可以用一个瞎子来比喻。瞎子感觉到热，听人说热是来自太阳的，因而会以为对于太阳有一个清楚、明白的观念；这样，假如有人问他太阳是什么，他就会回答说这是一个发热的东西。

但是你将会说，我在这里并不是只说我是一个在思维的东西，我还说我是一个没有广延的东西。不过，先不要说这是一件你并没有证明的事，虽然这在我们之间还是问题；我请你告诉我，你由此对你自己就有一个清楚、分明的概念吗？你说你不是一个有广延的东西；当然我由此就知道了你不是什么，但不知道你是什么。为了对于某一个东西有一个清楚、分明的概念，也就是说，有一个真实、自然的概念，难道不是必须正面地认识那个东西本身是什么，也就是，姑且这样说，肯定地认识那个东西吗？光知道它不是什么就够了吗？谁要是仅仅知道布塞法勒不是一个苍蝇，他对于布塞法勒就算有一个清楚、分明的概念吗？

然而，为了不在这上面有什么更多的纠缠，我只请问你：你说你是一个没有广延的东西，那么你不是渗透到全身去吗？当然我不知道你要怎么回答，因为虽然在一开始我认为你仅仅是在大脑里，这不过是仅仅由于猜测，而不是真正相信这是你的意见。我的猜测是根据你不久以后所说的那句话。你说：灵魂并不直接接受肉体一切部分的感染，而仅仅接受大脑的感染，或者也许大脑最小的那些部分之中的一个部分的感染。不过这并不能使我完全肯定你究竟是在大脑里，还是在大脑的一部分里，因为你可以是散布在全身里而只能在一部分里感觉到，正好像我们平常所说的：灵魂散布在全身，然而它只能通过眼睛去看。

（d）关于你必须发送到全身来传达感觉和运动的那些精气，我认为也是那样，且不说不可能理解你怎么把运动印到那些精气上，假如你是在一个点里，假如你不是一个物体，或者假如你没有一个物体用来整个地接触和推动它们的话。因为，假如你说它们是自动的，而你只是指引它们的运动，你要记得你在某一个地方曾说过物体不能自动，因此我们可以推论你是它运动的原因。然后请你给我们解释，没有某种专注，没有从你这方面的某种驱动，这种指引怎么进行？没有能动和被动的相互关联，怎么能够对一个东西或其驱动有压力呢？既然自然的光明告诉我们只有物体才能触动和被触动，那么没有物体怎么能有这个触动呢？

对第五组反驳的答辩

（a）当你说我从我的任何一个行动中都本来可以毫无差异地得出同一的结论时，你完全弄错了，因为这些行动中没有一个是我完全清楚的，我是指这种抽象的可靠性，除了思维以外，在这里，问题只在于这种抽象的可靠性。因为，举例来说，我散步，所以我存在，这个结论是不正确的，除非我具有的、作为内部认识的是一个思维，只有关于思维，这个结论才是可靠的，关于身体的运动就不行，它有时是假的，就像在我们的梦中出现的那样，虽然那时我们好像是在散步，这样从我想我是在散步这件事我就可以推论出我的精神（是它有这种思想）的存在，而不能推论出我的身体（是它在散步）的存在。其他一切也都是这样。

（b）你在这里到处不恰当地把好犯错误当成正面的不完满性，而这不过是（主要是有关上帝的）对存在于造物之中的更大的完满性的否定。把一个国家的公民们拿来同宇宙的各部分作比较也套不上；因为一些公民们是不好的，对于国家来说，是一件肯定的事；可是人是好犯错误的，也就是说，人并不具有一切种类的完满性，这跟宇宙是好的，不能同日而语。不过，拿下面这样两种人来作比较更好一些：有人希望人的身体满都是眼睛以便他表现得更美一些（由于对他来说没有比眼睛更美的部分），另一个人认为在世界上不应该有不犯错误的创造物，也就是说，不应该有完满无缺的创造物。

（c）你所说的关于太阳的观念，一个天生的瞎子是单独用他对于热的认识做成的，这是不难反驳的；因为这个瞎子对太阳虽然没有想一个明亮的、发光的东西那样的观念，可是他总还有一个发热的东西的清楚、明白的观念吧。你把我拿来同这个瞎子相比，这是毫无道理的。首先因为对一个在思维的东西的认识比对一个发热的东西的认识要延伸到远得多的范围，它甚至比我们对于任何别的东西所有的认识更广阔，就像我在别处已经指出过的那样；其次也因为没有人能证明这个瞎子对太阳所形成的观念并不包含人们对太阳所能认识的一切东西，只不过是那个有视觉器官的人除此而外还认识它的形状和它的光。可是对你来说，关于精神，你不但不比我认识得更多，而且你并没有看到我在那里所看到的全部东西。因此不如说是你，是你像一个瞎子，而从你那方面来说，我最多只能被称为近视眼或者目光短浅的人，和其他的人一样。

（d）即使思想与整个肉体融为一体，思想也无须随着肉体的伸展而伸展，因为思想不是肉体伸展的必须因素，却是思想的必须因素。因此，即使思想能够移动肉体，却不是构成肉体的必须要素。

第六组反驳

（a）第六个问题来自判断的无所谓或者自由。按照你的学说，它远不是使自由意志更高贵，更完满，而是相反，你是把它的不完满放在无所谓里，因此，什么时候只要理智清楚、分明地认识必须相信的、必须做的，或必须不做的事物，意志就绝不是无所谓的。因为，难道你没有看见当上帝创造这个世界而不创造别的世界，或者当他什么世界都不创造时，你用这些原则完全破坏了上帝的自由，从上帝的自由上你去掉了无所谓吗？虽然这是由于信仰让我们相信上帝曾经在创造一个世界或者很多世界或者甚至连一个世界也不创造，他是完全永恒地无所谓的。有谁能怀疑上帝对一切事情什么应该做，什么不应该做不是永远看得非常清楚？因此，不能说对事物的非常明白的认识和对这些事物的清楚的知觉，排除了自由意志的无所谓，这种无所谓，如果它对于人的自由不符合，对上帝的自由就绝不符合，因为事物的本质，就连数目的本质也一样，是不可分的、常住不变的；从而无所谓包含在上帝的自由意志的自由里并不比包含在人的自由意志的自由里少。

（b）第七个问题是面。你说一切感觉都发生在面上或者通过面而发生。因为我们看不出来为什么它不可以是被知觉到的物体的一部分，或者是空气的一部分，或者是水汽的一部分，甚至是这些东西任何的外表；我们还不很理解你怎么可以说没有实在的偶性（不管它们是属于什么物体或实体的）能够被上帝的全能从它们的主体分开并且没有主体而存在，而在祭台上的圣体中这样的事确确实实地存在。虽然如此，我们的博士们在看见是否在你向我们答应的那本《物理学》里你将充分证明所有这些东西之前，是没有理由感到烦恼的；不错，他们很难相信那本《物理学》能够把这些东西给我们提出得如此明白以致我们应该接受它们而抛弃掉古人教导我们的东西。

（c）你给第五组作的答辩引起第八个问题。真的，几何学的真理或者抽象的真理，就像你在那个地方所提到的那样，怎么能够是常住不变的、永恒的，而同时却是取决于上帝的呢？因为，它们是在什么种类的原因上取决于上帝的呢？他怎么能够把三角形的性质消灭掉？或者他怎么能使二乘四等于八从来就不是真的，或者一个三角形没有三个角？从而，这些真理或者只取决于理智，当理智在思维的时候；或者取决于事物本身的存在性；或者是独立的。因为，上帝能使这些本质或真理之中的任何一个从来就不存在，这似乎是不可能的。

（d）第九个问题是，你说不应该信任感官，理智的可靠性比感官的可靠性大得多，因此我们认为这个问题是非常重要的。因为，如果理智本身只有从安排得很合适的感官搬过来的可靠性而没有别的可靠性，这怎么能够做到呢？事实上，难道我们看不见，如果首先不是一个别的感官把它从错误中挽救出来，它就不能改正我们的任何一个感官的错误吗？举例来说，一根棍子插在水里，由于折光作用而表现为折断了，谁来改正这个错误？是理智吗？绝不是，而是触觉。其他的感官也一样。从而，如果一旦你的一切感官都安排得很合适，而且它们总是给我们报告同样的东西，你就把用感官的办法获得的、一个人所自然地做得到的最大的可靠性认为是可靠的吧；如果过于信任你的精神的推理，你肯定会经常弄错；因为时常发现我们的理智在它认为毫无可疑之处的一些东西上骗了我们。

（e）以上这些就是我们的主要问题。对这几个问题，也请你加上什么可靠的规则和一些肯定有效的标记，以便我们按照它们得以靠得住地认识到，在我们领会一件事物到这样的程度，即完全用不着别的东西，真的是一个东西完全与另外一个东西不同，以致它们能够分开存在，至少由于上帝的全能能够把它们分开，也就是说，一句话，请你告诉我们，我们怎么才能清楚、分明、真切地认识我们的理智所形成的这个区别不是建立在我们的精神之上，而是建立于事物本身。因为，当我想到上帝的广大无垠而不想到他的正义时，或者当我们想到他的存在性而不想到圣子或圣灵时，也就是说，离开三位一体的其他两位，我们就不能完整地领会这个存在性，或者上帝本身存在吗？而这个存在性是一个不信教的人可以有和你否认物体有精神或思维同样多的理由否认它的神圣性的。这和有人错误地得出结论说，圣子和圣灵在本质上是和圣父有分别的，或者他们可以和他分开一样，人们永远不会向你让步，认为思维，或者不如说人类精神，是实在与物体有分别的，尽管你清楚地领会这一个而用不着另一个，尽管你承认一个而否认另一个甚至你可以承认用你的精神的任何一个抽象作用能够这样做。但是，当然，如果你能充分地解答所有这些问题，你就可以肯定再没有什么东西能够使我们的神学家们不安了。

最后，既然我们不认识肉体的能力和运动能够做什么，因为你自己承认没有人能知道，除非是由于上帝的特别启示，上帝都是给一个主体里放进了或能放进什么，那么你从哪里能够知道上帝没有把这种能力和特性如思维、怀疑等等放进什么物体里呢？

对第六组反驳的答辩

（a）至于意志的自由，毫无疑问，上帝的自由和人的自由大不相同；因为如果说上帝的意志对已有的或者将要有的一切东西亘古以来就不是无所谓的，这是说不通的，因为我们想象不出有任何代表善或真的观念，什么应该相信的观念，或者什么应该做或者不应该做的观念在上帝的意志规定他自己这样做之前就存在于他的理智之中。而且我在这里并不是谈一种时间上的在先，而更重要的，我是说这样的一种观念不可能由于一种次序的在先或者性质的在先，或者像经院哲学中所说的那样，经过推理的道理在先，而在上帝的意志规定之先存在，以便善的观念迫使上帝不得不选择这一个而不选择另外一个。举例来说，上帝愿意把世界创造在时间里，并不是因为他看到世界被创造在时间里比创造在永恒里好，他愿意让一个三角形的三角之和等于二直角也并不是因为他认识到这只能是这样，等等。而是，相反，就是因为他愿意把世界创造在时间里，所以它比创造在永恒里好；同样，就是因为他愿意一个三角形的三角之和必然等于二直角，所以它现在就是这样，并且不可能不是这样；其他一切事情也都是如此。而且这并不妨碍人们说圣人们的功绩是他们得到永恒的天福的原因，因为圣人们的功绩并不是他们规定上帝愿意做什么的原因，它们不过是上帝永恒地愿意它们成为一个结果的原因。这样，在上帝那里的一种完全无所谓是他的全能的一个非常大的证明。然而在人这里可不是这样，由于人已经找到了上帝所建立和规定的善意和真理的性质，而且人的意志只能自然地趋向于好的东西，那么显然，人越是明显地认识好和真，就越能自由地接受好和真，只有在人不知道什么是更好的或者更真的，或者至少当他看得不够清楚，不能不怀疑的时候，他才抱无所谓的态度；这样一来，合适于人的自由的无所谓就跟合适于上帝的自由的无所谓完全不一样。而且说事物的本质是不可分的，这也毫无用处，因为首先，没有什么本质同样地既合适于上帝又合适于创造物；最后，无所谓并不属于人的自由的本质，因为，不仅仅是当我们对于善和真的无知使我们抱无所谓的态度时我们是自由的，而且主要也是当我们对一件事物的清楚、分明的认识推动和迫使我们去追求时我们是自由的。

（b）为了全面驳斥那些承认实在的偶性的人的意见，我认为我所提出的那些理由就够了，用不着再提别的理由。因为，首先，没有接触就没有感觉，除了物体的面没有什么能被感觉。然而，假如有实在的偶性，那么这些偶性一定是和这个仅仅作为一个样态的面不是一回事；因此，假如有实在的偶性，这些偶性也不能被我们感觉。但是，谁曾相信过它们之存在仅在于他认为它们被他感觉到？

其次，如果说实在的偶性是存在的，因为凡是实在的东西都能同任何别的主体分开存在，那是一件说不通的事，完全没有可能。能够分开存在的是实体，而不是偶性。光说实在的偶性不能由自然的力量而只能由上帝的全能同它们的主体分开，这是毫无用处的；因为由自然的力量做成和由上帝平常的能力做成完全是一回事，而上帝平常的能力和上帝特别的能力没有什么不同，这种能力，由于不在事物里面加上任何东西，因此不改变事物的性质，所以，如果凡是可以由自然的力量没有主体而存在是一个实体的话，那么凡是由于上帝的能力（无论它有多么特别）没有主体而存在的东西，也必须用实体这个名称来称呼。老实说，我承认一个实体可以是另外一个实体的偶性；不过在发生这样的事的时候，采取一个偶性的形式的并不是实体，而是样态或方式。举例来说，当一件衣服穿到一个人身上的时候，成为偶性的不是衣服，而是被穿。对于促使哲学家们建立一些实在的偶性的主要理由是，他们认为没有实在的偶性，我们就不能解释我们感官的知觉是怎么做成的，因此我答应在写《物理学》的时候细致地解释我们的每一个感官被它的对象所触动的方式。这并不是我想要在这上面或者在任何别的东西上面让人们相信我的话，而是因为我相信我在我的《折光学》里所解释的视觉能够用作对于其余感官的足够证明。

（c）很显然，对于认为上帝无限的人来说，没有什么不是取决于上帝的，不仅包括存在的一切，甚至命令或法律，而且包括决定什么是善或真的原因。否则，就像之前说的那样，上帝不会对创造他所创造出的东西完全无所谓。因为，如果好的理由或现象是先在于他事先安排的，那么他一定规定他去做更好的。但是，恰恰相反，因为他规定他自己去做出世界上的东西是因为这个理由，就像在《创世记》里所说的那样，它们是非常好的，也就是说，它们的好，其理由取决于他愿意把它们做成这样。而且用不着问这个好以及其他一切真理，无论是数学的或形而上学的，在什么种类的原因上取决于上帝；因为，原因的种类既然是由那些也许没想到因果关系这个理由的人建立的，因而当他们没有给它起什么名称时，就没有什么可奇怪的了。虽然如此，他们还是给它起了一个名称，因为他可以被叫作动力因；和君主的意志可以说成是法律的动力因一样，虽然法律本身并不是一个自然的存在体，而仅仅是（就像他们在经院里说的那样）一个精神上的存在体。问上帝怎么能一直使二乘四等于八，等等，也同样没有用，因为我承认我们无法知道；不过另一方面，我知道得很清楚，不取决于上帝，什么都不能存在，不管是哪一种存在体，以及把某些东西安排得使人们不可能知道它们可以是另外一个样子而不是现在这个样子，这对他来说是非常容易的，如果由于我们不知道并且我们看不出我们应该知道的什么别的东西，而怀疑我们知道得很清楚的一些东西，这是完全违反理性的。因此，不要以为永恒的真理取决于人的理智或者事物的存在，而是仅仅取决于上帝的意志；上帝，作为一个至上的立法者，永恒地安排了并且制定了这些真理。

（d）要明白感官的可靠性是什么，就要把感官分为三个阶段。在第一个阶段里应该考虑的只是外在对象直接在物体性的感官之内所引起的东西；这只能是这个官能的分子的运动以及由这个运动产生的形状和地位的改变。第二个阶段包含直接在精神上产生的一切东西，这是由于精神与物体性的官能结合所产生的，而物体性的官能是受它的对象所推动和感染的，就像疼痛、痒、饿、渴、颜色、声音、滋味、气味、热、冷以及其他类似的感觉，就像我们在第六个沉思里所说的那样，它们来自精神和肉体的结合，或者（姑且这样说）混合。最后，第三个阶段包含我们的全部判断，我们从幼年时期起在感官运动时对周围事物所习惯于作出的判断。

举例来说，当我们看见一根棍子时，不要想象是从棍子上飞到空中的一些飞舞的、人们普遍称为“有意种类”的细小的图像进到我的眼睛里；这不过是从这根棍子反射出来的光线刺激出来视神经里的什么运动，通过它达到了大脑，（就像我已经大量地在《折光学》里讲到的那样）我们和兽类共同的是大脑的这种运动，这种运动是感觉的第一阶段做成的。由第一阶段接着就进入第二个阶段，它只包括被这根棍子所反射的颜色和光的知觉。并且它是这样产生的：精神跟大脑连接得十分紧密，以致它甚至感觉到并且好像被在它里边的运动所触动似的；这就是必须归之于感官的全部东西，如果我们想要把感官准确地同理智分开的话。因为，虽然从我感到其印象的这种颜色的感觉上我判断在我之外的这根棍子是有颜色的，而从这个颜色的广延、从它的终止点以及从它的地位与我大脑的各部分的关系上，我决定有关这个棍子的大小、形状和距离的什么东西，尽管人们习惯于把它归之于感官，而在这方面我把它归之于感觉的第三个阶段，可是显然它是只取决于理智的；我甚至在《折光学》里指出：大小、距离和形状只有经过推理才能知觉，推理把它们彼此分开。但是在这里只有这一个不同，即对于出现在我们的感官的一切东西所作的新的、不是习惯作出的一些判断，我们把它们归之于理智，同时，对于我们从幼年起关于可感觉的东西，在这些东西在我们的感官上所产生的印象的机会上习惯于作出的那些判断，我们把它们归之于感官；其理由是：习惯使我们推理和把那些东西判断得非常仓促（或者不如说使我们记起我们以前作过的一些判断），我们区分不出这种方式的判断和我们感官的单纯的感知或知觉来。

由此，显然是，当我们说理智的可靠性比感官的可靠性大时，我们的话只意味着由于我们所做的一些新的观察，我们的年纪越大，我们作的判断就比自从我们幼年以来没有经过反复思考而作的判断可靠；这是丝毫不能怀疑的，因为，确实是，这里不是第一阶段的感觉，也不是第二阶段的感觉，因为在这两个阶段里不可能有错误，因此，当人们说，一根棍子插在水里，由于折光作用而表现为折断了时，这就跟人们说一个小孩子判断它是折断了以同样方式显现给我们；这也和按照自从我们幼年以来所习惯的成见一样，我们也这样判断。但是，我不能同意他们接下来的话，即：这个错误不是由理智来改正，而是由触觉来改正；因为，虽然触觉使我判断为一根棍子是直的，而且自从我们幼年以来就习惯于这样判断，因此这也可以叫作感觉，可是这并不足以改正视觉的错误，而是除此之外，需要有什么理由来告诉我们在这个地方相信我们在摸了它以后作的判断，而不相信视觉似乎给我带来的判断，这个理由不是我们自从幼年以来就有的，因而不能归之于感官，只能单独归之于理智。从而，就是在这个例子里，改正感官的错误的只有理智，没有可能提出任何一个例子来说明错误是来自相信精神的活动而不相信感官的知觉。

（e）实际上，我从来没有看见过，也没有了解过人的肉体能思维，而是看到并且了解到同一的人们，他们既有思维，同时也有肉体。而且我认识到这是由于思维的实体和物体性的实体组合到一起而造成的，因为，单独考虑思维的实体时，我一点都没有看到它能够属于物体，而在物体的本性里，当我单独考虑它时，我一点没有找到什么东西是能够属于思维的。但是，相反，把各种样态都拿来检查一下，不管是物体的还是精神的，我看不出有一个样态，它的概念不是完全依附于事物的概念本身，而这个概念就是事物的样态。同样，从我们经常看见两个东西结合在一起这件事，我们不能因此就推论说它们是一个东西；但是，从我们有时看见两个东西之一而没有另一个东西的时候，我们就很可以结论说两个东西是不同的。不要让上帝的能力阻止我们得出这个结论；因为，认为我们清楚、分明地领会为两个东西的一些东西是由一个在本质上同一的东西做成的而绝不是组成的，这和认为可以把一点分别都没有的东西分开，同样是说不通的。从而，如果说上帝把思维的功能放到某些物体里（就像他事实上把它放在人的肉体里那样），他什么时候愿意，什么时候就可以把它们分开，这样一来，思维实际上是可以与这些物体有分别的。

译者导读

索伦·克尔凯郭尔（1813—1855），丹麦人，享年四十二岁，在他短暂的一生里，创作了二十多部宗教哲学巨著。他用丹麦语写作，和安徒生是同一时代的人，却没有像安徒生那样享有盛名。在他身前，其著作知者甚少，但在二十世纪，在他去世多年之后，他的作品逐渐得到关注，并引起了一场影响深远的思想革命，产生了一种新的哲学思想，即存在主义。在当代思想家看来，克尔凯郭尔是一位伟大的天才，他被公认为存在主义哲学之父，其哲学家地位可以和尼采相提并论，还被誉为与弗洛伊德齐名的后精神分析大师。

克尔凯郭尔这位天才度过了短暂、孤独、不为人知的一生。他在幼年时期就被父亲不断地灌输宗教思想，就连他的名字—克尔凯郭尔（Kierkegaard）—都打上了宗教的烙印，因为它在丹麦语中有教堂园地和墓地的意思。这种严格的宗教教育使这位哲学家深受“要敬畏上帝”这样的思想的影响。正是这种思想使他在辛苦追求女友雷金娜·奥尔森（Regine Olsen）三年，并已经举行了订婚仪式之后，又解除了婚约，因为他内心感到上帝不认可这个婚姻。这之后不久，克尔凯郭尔开始了他的写作生涯，以“沉默的约翰尼斯”（John the Silent）这个假名于1843年发表了一部影响深远的哲学巨著—《恐惧和战栗》。克尔凯郭尔写该书的目的是想要理解当上帝考验亚伯拉罕，让他把儿子带到摩利亚山去献祭时，亚伯拉罕所感到的焦虑，想要理解亚伯拉罕在信仰和伦理相悖时所感到的恐惧和战栗。很多人认为《恐惧和战栗》是哲学性的，但也有专家认为该著作是自传性的，把它看作克尔凯郭尔努力度过失去未婚妻雷金娜这一难关的一种方式。若从自传的意义上解读《恐惧和战栗》中讨论的故事，那么，克尔凯郭尔就是其中的亚伯拉罕，而雷金娜就是其中的以撒。

《恐惧和战栗》以圣经里亚伯拉罕杀子故事为线索，来探讨信仰和伦理的冲突。对于上帝要求亚伯拉罕杀死儿子以撒做祭品这个任务，亚伯拉罕可以选择完成它或是忘记它。但是他选择笃信上帝，放弃自己最珍贵的东西—儿子，去完成这项艰巨无比的任务。他选择不告诉妻子撒拉，默默地带着儿子以撒踏上了三天半的行程。在到达上帝指定的献祭地点之后，他默默地劈柴点火，捆住以撒，痛苦却又决绝地对儿子拔刀相向。正在此时，上帝派的天使飞来，拦住亚伯拉罕，告诉他说这是上帝对他的考验。经受了这一残酷考验之后，亚伯拉罕被上帝授命为他世间的代理人，他的世世代代都受到神的庇佑。

在克尔凯郭尔看来，亚伯拉罕向上帝祭献儿子体现了信仰和伦理之间的悖论，人们在面对这样的悖论时，感受到的必然是恐惧和战栗。而勇敢面对这个悖论使亚伯拉罕被视为既是谋杀者又是信仰伟人。在对这个悖论的探讨中，克尔凯郭尔提出了三个问题：可以从目的论意义上暂时停止从伦理角度看问题吗？对上帝有一种绝对的义务吗？亚伯拉罕对撒拉、以利亚撒和以撒隐瞒自己的目的，这在伦理上合乎情理吗？其实这三个问题本质上就是信仰和伦理之间的悖论问题。亚伯拉罕在面对这个悖论时，进行了双重运动—“无限放弃的运动”（他无限决绝地放弃了以撒，准备杀子）和“信仰的运动”（他同时又认为他献出以撒是表现出对儿子和对上帝的爱，凭此信仰他将不一定会失去以撒，上帝会让他重新得到儿子）—因此，他被视为是伟大之人、信仰之父。克尔凯郭尔将基督徒分为了无限放弃骑士（放弃伦理自我，放弃普遍性的基督徒）和信仰骑士（相信上帝的允诺，相信上帝不会拿走一切，相信自己凭借信仰可以重新得到一切的基督徒）两类。他用他敏锐的辩证智慧带领读者思考亚伯拉罕献祭儿子、阿伽门农痛苦弃绝爱女、人鱼诱惑纯洁美女等故事中所体现的信仰价值与伦理价值以及审美价值之间的冲突，思考个人的个体性服从于伦理的普遍性，与个体性因更高的目的而高于普遍性之间的不同，从而理解亚伯拉罕作为信仰骑士区别于仍处于伦理范围之内的悲剧英雄的神圣之处。

笔者在翻译《恐惧和战栗》这部天才巨著时，诚惶诚恐，也可以说翻译过程充满着“恐惧和战栗”。首先，笔者查阅了关于克尔凯郭尔的传记，同时查阅了圣经里关于亚伯拉罕和与他有关的人物的各种故事，以及《恐惧和战栗》中所涉及的各种典故，力求达到对原著的精确理解。但是，原著是丹麦文，后来被翻译成德文和英文，半个世纪以来，对原著的英文翻译有数个版本，但都显得有些晦涩难懂。因此，笔者在翻译阿拉斯泰尔·汉内的这个英译本时，为了更准确地翻译出原著意思，还参阅了其他英译本。在此基础上，笔者殚精竭虑地翻译了半年多，也在翻译过程中经受了书中伟大的思想的洗涤。阅读《恐惧和战栗》可以引发读者对我们这个信仰缺失的时代、对个体性存在的问题进行深刻的思考，从而获益匪浅。

还有一点要说明的是，由于原作者为了对被称为信仰之父的亚伯拉罕的故事作严谨而又充满激情的表述，有时在文中用了大量的排比长句，甚至有一处长达几页。笔者在尽量避免拘泥于原句句式和翻译腔的同时，也尽量译成排比长句，以求最大限度地达到翻译所讲求的“信、达、雅”标准。

译文中错误和疏漏之处在所难免，真诚欢迎读者批评指正。

恐惧和战栗

塔奎尼·苏培布斯在他的花园里借罂粟花所说的话，他儿子领会了，但那个信使却没明白。

——哈曼

前言

我们当今这个时代，人们无论是在商业界还是思想界都在进行一场十足的清仓大甩卖。一切都可以如此廉价地售卖，使人开始思考最终是否会有人想出价。每个认真记录并指引人们关注现代哲学重要趋势的思索者，每一个讲师，临时抱佛脚的应考者，学生，每个处在研究哲学边缘或主流的人，都不愿止步于怀疑一切事物。他们都要更进一步地走下去。或许，询问他们认为自己正去往何处有些不合时宜，尽管我们可以出于客气恭敬，理所当然地认为他们的确已经怀疑一切事物，否则说继续前行就会有些奇怪。他们都已做了这一初步的工作，并且可能轻而易举地做完了，以至于他们觉得没有必要解释如何做的。因为，对于如何着手完成这样庞大的任务，即便是那种真诚地想在此问题上渴求一点启迪的人，也没有找到任何解释，连一个指明方向的引导或一个小小的日常方法都没有。“但是，笛卡尔是做了的，对吧？”笛卡尔，一个受人崇敬、谦恭诚实的思想家，他的著作人人读了都深受震撼感奋。他确实言出必行，言行一致。这样的事情在我们这个时代十分罕见。笛卡尔是一个在信仰上绝不会怀疑的人。正如他自己一再表明的那样，[“但是我们必须记着已经说过的话，并且要谨记只能依赖于良知，只要这良知不违背上帝的旨意……最重要的是，我们要铭记一条绝对正确的真理，那就是，上帝给我们所显示的旨意，与任何其他事物相比，都是无可比拟的确定无疑。即便我们的理智之光似乎极为清楚确凿地揭示出与上帝指示相反的事物，我们也应当服从神圣的权威，而不是相信自己的判断”（《哲学原则》第二十八原则和第七十六原则）。]笛卡尔并没有大叫着“着火了！着火了！”以使怀疑成为每个人的义务，因为他是一位安静而又孤独的思想者，绝非一个大声喊叫的街头守夜人。他很谦虚，知道自己的方法只对自己有意义，而这方法一部分来源于自己早期笨拙的求知过程。[“因此，我的意图并不是要在这儿传授一种每个人都要遵循以便能更好地提高理性的最好方法，而是仅仅表明我是如何致力于运用自己的理性……但是当我刚全部修完课程时（关于沉默的约翰尼斯的额外添加的故事，即，关于他的青春的课程），照例说可以被认为是进入了有学问者级别时，我的观点却完全改变了。因为我发现自己深受许多怀疑和错误困扰，局促不安，由此感到自己努力求学的结果是除了越来越发现自己的无知以外一无所获”（《关于如何在科学中管理理性和寻求真理的方法谈》）]—我们相信那些古希腊人是知道一些哲学知识的，他们付出了怎样的努力来把怀疑当成终生的任务啊！怀疑可不是一种数天或数周就可以习得的技能。这些久经沙场的哲学战士在面对所有诱骗时保持了稳定的怀疑态度，无畏地否定了感性意识和思想的确定性，刚正不阿地反抗自私的焦虑感和同情心的诱惑，他们取得了怎样的成就啊！—而这就是当今人们的起点。

今天的人们不会停止对信仰的追求，他们仍会继续前行。或许，询问他们去往何处会有些鲁莽唐突，但我猜想实际上每个人都有信仰，否则谈论追求信仰就定然是奇怪的，我的这种想法表明我是个文雅有教养的人。不过，古时候的情况不同。因为那时，信仰是一项终生的任务，不是一种三天两日就可习得的技能。当老兵抵达人生的尽头时，他已经经历过英勇的战斗，保持了自己的信仰。他的心依然年轻，不会忘记那些曾经使他经受锻炼的恐惧和战栗，这些恐惧和战栗尽管成年人可以控制，却没有人可以完全克服—除非他得以抓住最早的机会去进一步追求。我们这个时代在这些可敬人物所抵达的地方起步，为了更进一步走下去。

本书的作者绝对称不上是哲学家，他还没有理解哲学的体系，他也不知道这个体系是否真正存在，或者该体系是否已经完善。就他不大聪明的头脑而言，能想到每个人要有多强大的头脑才能拥有如此众多的思想已是足够。即便一个人能够把信仰的全部内容都变成概念的形式，那也不意味着他已经领悟了信仰，懂得了如何得到信仰或信仰如何接近了他。本书的作者绝不是哲学家，他是个有高雅情趣的诗人（要是用诗意的好听的词说的话），他偶尔是个抄写员，但他既不建立体系，也不对体系抱有希望；他既不致力于体系的任何东西，也不受体系的束缚。他写作是因为这对他而言是一种奢侈，他的作品写得越是适合阅读和引人注目，就越少有人买来读。在这样一个为了科学而摈弃激情的时代，他很容易预知自己的命运—在这样的时代里，想要拥有读者的作者必须小心翼翼地写作，以使自己的作品能成为餐后小睡前的轻松读物，而且一定要在世人面前表现得像求职广告中礼貌的园丁那样，手托礼帽，并带有前任雇主的推荐信，向深受尊敬的公众自荐。他预知自己的命运会被人完全忽视，他还有个可怕的不祥预感，就是自己将屡受狂热的批判责难。更让他不寒而栗的是，某位有进取心的记录人，或断章取义、囫囵吞枣之人，为了拯救科学知识，总愿意像托普对《人类的毁灭》所做的那样，为了“保留好的品位”，豪迈地把他的作品切割开来，断章取义，而且会像那个致力于为标点符号科学作贡献的人那样无情地把作者的话按五十个字一句号、三十五个字一分号来分隔断开。我愿拜倒在任何试图寻找体系的搜查者面前解释，这不是体系，它也与体系毫无关系。因为研究体系很难成为高塔，我要祝福体系和丹麦所有致力于构建这种综合多用体系的人好运，繁荣昌盛。

此致

敬礼！

沉默的约翰尼斯

序幕

从前有个人，他在孩提时代就听说过那个美丽的故事，那个动人的故事讲的是关于上帝如何考验亚伯拉罕，而亚伯拉罕如何经受住了考验，保持了信仰，又出乎意料地第二次得到儿子的事情。他长大成人后，又读了那个故事，这次却是怀着更大的钦佩之情，因为他在孩提时代看生活的那种虔诚的单纯在有了生活经历后已变得复杂，不再单纯。他年龄越大就越会经常想起那个故事。不过，他对它的热情和兴趣越来越大，对它的理解却越来越少。最后，他忘了一切他物，心里只有一个愿望，就是亲眼见到亚伯拉罕，他也只有一个渴求，就是亲眼见证那个故事里发生的事情。他想看到的并不是那些美丽的东方地区，不是上帝应许之地的尘世光彩，不是那对对上帝满怀敬畏并在老年得到上帝赐福的夫妇，也不是那位年老可敬族长的画像，以及上帝赐予以撒的青春活力—若是在贫瘠的荒野，那个故事同样也会发生。他渴望的是在亚伯拉罕和他的儿子以撒那三天的旅程里，可以陪伴在他们身边，满怀悲伤的亚伯拉罕要骑驴走在他的前面，以撒要走在他的旁边。他想亲身经历亚伯拉罕举目远望看见摩利亚山，以及他抛下毛驴，和以撒独自上山的那些重要时刻。因为他一心想着的不是精细新颖的想象，而是思想上的战栗。

此人绝不是个思想家，除了追求信仰之外，他不觉得有必要去超越信仰继续深究下去。在他看来，能被人当作信仰之父永恒纪念，并且，拥有强大得让人羡慕的信仰，即便是无人知晓这一点，也肯定是一件无比光荣的事。

此人也绝不是经书评注诠释者，他根本不懂希伯来文，要是他懂得希伯来文，也许他就会很容易地理解亚伯拉罕的故事。

一

“这些事之后所发生的事是，上帝的确引诱了亚伯拉罕，对他说：……现在，带上你的儿子，你最爱的唯一的儿子以撒，到摩利亚之地去，在那儿，把他作为燔祭献到我将指示给你的山上。”

一个清晨，亚伯拉罕早早起床，给毛驴装上鞍子，带着以撒离开了帐篷。但是，他们走下山谷的时候，撒拉一直从窗户那儿注视着他们，直到看不见为止。他们骑着毛驴默默地走了三天，到了第四天早上，亚伯拉罕依旧一言不发，但他举目远眺，看见了摩利亚的那座山。他留下仆人，独自带着以撒向山上走去。但亚伯拉罕心中暗想：“我绝不会对以撒隐瞒将把他带向何方。”他静静地站着，并把手放在以撒的头上为他祈福；以撒弯腰接受他的祝福。亚伯拉罕带着慈父的表情，温柔地凝视着他，说着鼓励的话。但是以撒不能理解他，他的灵魂无法得到提升。他紧紧抱着父亲的腿，在他脚下恳求，他为他年轻的生命求情，为他美好的前途求情；他在哀求中同父亲一起回忆在家里时所经历的欢乐、悲伤和孤独。接着，亚伯拉罕扶起儿子，一边拉着他的手和他一起走，一边说着满是安慰和劝勉的话。但是以撒不能理解他。亚伯拉罕爬上了摩利亚的那座山，以撒依旧没有理解他。接着，他有片刻扭过脸去不看以撒。但是当以撒又看到他的脸时，发现他已神情大变：他用狂野的目光凝视着他，样子恐怖。他一把抓住以撒的胸膛，把他掷在地上，说道：“傻孩子，你真以为我是你的父亲吗？我是个上帝崇拜者。你以为这是上帝的命令吗？不，这是我自己的愿望。”以撒于是在地上瑟瑟发抖，他痛苦地喊道：“天堂里的上帝饶了我吧，亚伯拉罕的上帝可怜可怜我吧！假若人间没有我的父亲，那么你就做我的父亲吧！”不过，亚伯拉罕却悄声自言自语说：“感谢上帝！毕竟他把我视为凶残之人比对您失去信仰要好。”

*

当孩子要断奶时，母亲会把乳房弄黑，因为不让孩子吃奶时，若乳房看起来很诱人是件憾事。这样弄黑的话，孩子会相信乳房已改变，但母亲其实没变，她还是目光慈爱，温柔依旧。那些不需要用更糟糕的方法给孩子断奶的人是多么幸运啊！

二

一天清晨，亚伯拉罕早早起床。他拥抱了撒拉，他的衰老但依然被他视作新娘的撒拉。撒拉又亲吻了以撒，这个为她洗去耻辱，带来永远的骄傲和希望的儿子。之后，他们骑驴默默地走着，亚伯拉罕的双眼总是紧盯着地面。直到第四天，他抬头远望，看见了摩利亚的那座山，但他接着又盯着地面。之后，他默默地架起柴堆，绑住以撒；又默默地拔出了刀子。接着他看见了上帝选定的用以替代以撒的公羊。于是他献祭了那只公羊然后回家了……从那以后，亚伯拉罕变老了。他无法忘记上帝曾向他索要以撒这一切。以撒像往常一样茁壮成长；但亚伯拉罕的眼神已变得黯淡无光，再也看不到快乐的神情了。

*

当孩子长大快要断奶时，母亲处女般地把乳房掩藏起来，于是孩子便没有了母亲。那没有以别的方式失去母亲的孩子是多么幸运啊！

三

一天清晨，亚伯拉罕早早起床。他亲吻了撒拉，这年轻的母亲；撒拉又亲吻了以撒，那带给她永恒欢乐喜悦的儿子。亚伯拉罕心事重重地骑着驴上路了。他想起了夏甲，想起了被自己赶入沙漠的夏甲的儿子。他爬上了摩利亚的那座山，然后拔出了刀子。

那是个静谧的夜晚，亚伯拉罕独自骑驴出去。当骑到摩利亚的那座山跟前时，他扑倒在地，祈求上帝宽恕自己愿意献祭儿子以撒的罪过，宽恕自己作为父亲已忘记对儿子职责的罪过。他更加频繁地独自骑驴出去，但再也找不到内心的平静。他领悟不了为什么自己愿意将自己的最爱献祭给上帝会是一种罪，而且为了这个最爱他是乐意无数次奉献自己的生命的。而倘若这是一种罪，倘若他不是如此爱以撒的话，那么，他是无法理解这可能是可以被宽恕的。因为还有什么罪比这更可怕啊？

*

当孩子快要断奶时，母亲也是不无悲伤的。因为她知道孩子和自己日渐分离，那个开始在自己肚里，后来又被搂在乳房旁的孩子再也不可能和自己如此亲近了。因而，母子一起承受这短暂的悲伤。那和孩子保持亲近不必再悲伤的人是多么幸运啊！

四

一天清早，亚伯拉罕的家里，为动身所作的一切准备已经就绪。亚伯拉罕告别了撒拉后，忠实的仆人以利亚撒一路追随着他，直到他不得不返回为止。亚伯拉罕和以撒骑着驴步调一致地走着，来到了摩利亚的那座山跟前。尽管亚伯拉罕镇定平静地为献祭作好了一切准备，但当他转身抽取刀子时，以撒看到他痛苦地攥紧左手，并且一阵战栗传遍他全身—不过，亚伯拉罕还是拔出了刀子。

之后，他们又回到家里。撒拉跑去迎接他们，但以撒已经失去了信仰。关于此事，他们只字不提，以撒也没有把自己看到的告诉任何人，亚伯拉罕也不曾怀疑过有任何人看到此事。

*

当孩子快要断奶时，母亲在手边准备好更好的食品，这样可以避免孩子夭折。那身边准备有更好食品的母亲是多么幸运啊！

我们现在所谈的这个人以诸如此类的方式思考着那些事件。每次他从去摩利亚那座山的旅途回到家，他都会疲倦地瘫倒，双手紧握，说道：“亚伯拉罕无比伟大；然而，有谁能理解他呢？”

亚伯拉罕颂

如果一个人没有永恒的意识，如果一切归根结底只是狂野火热的骚动力，只是一种能产生一切伟大或渺小之物的翻滚着的昏暗模糊的激情；如果藏匿于一切事物之下的是深不可测的无尽的空虚，那么，生活除了是绝望以外还能是什么？倘若如此的话，如果没有神圣的纽带把人类联系在一起，如果一代人在另一代人之后崛起，就像森林里年复一年堆积的层层树叶，如果一代人取代另一代人就像林子里的鸟叫声一样此起彼伏，如果人类经历这世界就像轮船航过海洋或大风掠过沙漠一样，只是一时兴致下无思无果的活动；如果永恒的湮没忘却就像野兽总是潜伏着，饥饿地等候着猎物，而又没有一种力量可以从它的爪中夺走猎物，那么生活该会是多么空虚和无可慰藉啊！但因为此原因，生活并不是那样的。而正如上帝创造了男人和女人一样，他也塑造了英雄和诗人或演讲家。诗人或演讲家没有英雄的技能，他只能钦佩、爱戴、欣赏英雄。然而，他，像英雄一样，也是快乐的；因为英雄可以说是他所迷恋的自己的更好本性的体现；他很开心英雄并不是自己，很开心自己对英雄的爱戴表现为真正的钦佩。他是回忆之神灵，只能回忆发生的一切事，除了赞美英雄所做的事，他什么也不能做。他对英雄的回忆和赞美里没有自我，只有羡慕。他追寻自己心里的愿望，但当他找到了自己追寻的对象时，就四处游荡，挨家挨户地演讲和歌颂自己发现的英雄，只为了使所有的人都像他那样钦佩英雄，像他那样为英雄而骄傲。这就是他的成就，他的卑微的使命，这就是他为英雄之殿所提供的忠诚服务。如果他对英雄的爱是真诚的，如果他日日夜夜都与那会使人遗忘英雄的阴谋诡计作斗争，那么他已完成了他的任务，他和英雄融为一体了，英雄反过来也一样忠实地爱他，因为诗人可以说是英雄的更好本性的体现，虽然这种存在肯定就像记忆一样无力无效，但也像记忆一样被理想化和美化。因此，任何伟大的人都不会被忘却：即便是误解之云将英雄遮盖，不管需要多久，英雄的仰慕者终将出现，而且他对英雄的忠诚愈久弥坚。

不！这个世界上任何曾经伟大的人都不会被忘却。但是每个人都有自己的伟大之处，每个人的伟大之处都与自己所热爱之物的伟大之处相称。爱自己者因为自身而伟大，爱戴他人者因为他对他人的献身而伟大，而爱上帝者则是这些伟大之人中最伟大的。他们都终将被记住，但每个人所达到的伟大程度是与自己期望成正比的。因而，有人因期望可能的事物而变得伟大，有人因期望永恒的事物而变得伟大，但期望不可能之事物者则是最伟大的。他们都终将被记住，但每个人所达到的伟大程度是和自己与之奋斗的事物成正比的。因而，与世界斗争者因为征服了世界而变得伟大，与自我斗争者因为战胜自我而伟大，但与上帝斗争者则是最伟大的。所以，世界上总有斗争，人与人之间的斗争，一人与成千上万人之间的斗争，但与上帝斗争的人则是最伟大的。所以，地球上总有斗争：有人靠自己的力量征服一切，有人靠无力无助征服上帝。有人靠自己获得了一切，有人对自身的力量很自信，奉献了一切，而那坚信上帝者则是他们中最伟大的。有的人在力量方面伟大，有的人在智慧方面伟大，有的人伟大在充满希望，有的人伟大在充满爱，但亚伯拉罕比他们都要伟大。他的伟大在于他的表现为无能为力的力量，在于他大智若愚的智慧，在于他表面上看似疯狂的希望，在于他实质上是自我憎恨的爱。

亚伯拉罕是靠信仰的力量离开父辈的土地来到应许之地成为异客的。他摈弃了一样东西，带走了另一样东西。他摈弃的是世俗的庸俗理解，带走的是他的信仰。否则，他肯定不会离去的，而且离开故土也肯定是不理智的。他是因为信仰才来到应许之地做异客的。这里没有什么可以让他追忆珍贵过往的，但新奇的一切诱惑着他的灵魂，使他充满忧郁的渴望。而他就是上帝所拣选的，上帝对他深感满意。是的，的确如此！要是他被上帝放弃，不再受上帝的荣光和恩典的庇佑，他或许会对此有更好的理解。实际上，这一切更像是对他和他的信仰的一种嘲笑。曾经也有人离开自己深爱的家园流亡在外。他没有被忘记，反映他痛苦地寻求和找到所失去的悲歌也不会被忘记。而亚伯拉罕没有作悲伤之歌，哀怨是人之常情，与哭泣者同哭泣也是人之常情，但是更伟大的是拥有信仰，更有福气的是注视拥有信仰的人。

是信仰使亚伯拉罕接受了一个应允，即在整个地球上他的民族世世代代都会受到庇护。时光流逝，那个可能性存在，亚伯拉罕拥有信仰；时光流逝，那个可能性减少了，亚伯拉罕依然保有信仰。曾经也有人怀有期望。时光流逝，夜晚临近，他没有忘记他的期望，因此他也不会被忘记。接着他感到悲伤，但他的悲伤没有像生活那样欺骗他，悲伤为他做了所有能做的一切；而他在甜蜜的悲伤中，依然保有他带着失望的期望。与悲伤者一起悲伤，是人之常情。但是更伟大的是拥有信仰，而更幸运的是凝视拥有信仰的人。我们没有看到和听到亚伯拉罕表达悲伤的歌曲。时光流逝，亚伯拉罕并没有忧伤地掐指算日，度日如年，也没有满腹疑心地打量着撒拉，担心她是否正在变老；他没有试图阻止太阳的脚步，使光阴停滞，以便撒拉不会变老并能像他期望的那样永伴自己左右；他也没有对着撒拉抚慰地唱着悲歌。亚伯拉罕老了，撒拉在当地被人嘲笑。而亚伯拉罕依然是上帝所拣选之人，依然承继着那个希望，即他在地球上的后裔将会得到神的庇佑赐福。那么，倘若他没被上帝所拣选，情况不会更好吗？成为上帝所选之人意味着什么呢？是不是意味着年轻时的愿望要被否定，只是为了在年老时艰难地实现它呢？不过，亚伯拉罕相信上帝的应许并且坚守着那份应许。倘若亚伯拉罕动摇过，他就会放弃了它。他就可能会对上帝说：“也许您终究没有实现那个应许的意愿；那么我就放弃我的愿望吧，它曾经是我唯一的愿望，是赐给我的欢乐。我的灵魂是正直诚实的，您拒绝兑现给我的应许，我对此心中毫无怨恨。”那样的话，他不会被忘记，他也会作为楷模拯救很多人，但他不会成为信仰之父。因为放弃愿望很伟大，更伟大的是放弃之后又坚持它；抓住永恒的东西很伟大，更伟大的是放弃永恒之后坚守那暂时性的东西。但那之后，最适当的时机到了。倘若亚伯拉罕没有坚守信仰，那么撒拉定会死于悲伤，而亚伯拉罕也会因为哀伤变得呆滞，不能理解应许的实现，反而会把它当作青年时的梦想微笑了之。但是亚伯拉罕笃信神，因而他永葆青春。这是因为一个总是希望得到最好的东西的人会变老并且会被生活所欺骗；一个总是为最坏情况作好准备的人会未老先衰；但拥有信仰的人则能永葆青春。那么让我们尽情颂扬亚伯拉罕的故事吧！因为撒拉尽管已上了年纪，但心态依然年轻到足以渴求做母亲的愉悦；而亚伯拉罕虽然白发苍苍，但也拥有盼望做父亲的年轻心态。从表面上看，信仰的奇妙之处在于亚伯拉罕和撒拉年轻到足以如愿以偿，得到儿子；从更深意义上看，信仰的奇妙之处在于亚伯拉罕和撒拉年轻到足以去希望，也在于信仰使他们保持了愿望并通过保持愿望保持了青春。亚伯拉罕接受应许的实现，他是从信仰上去接受它，而他也按照自己所被应许的和所信仰的那样得偿所愿；相比之下，当年的摩西用权杖敲击磐石，但他对信仰并没有信心。

所以，当撒拉在金婚之日扮成新娘时，亚伯拉罕家里充满了欢乐欣喜。

但是这种欢乐并不能一直保持；亚伯拉罕还要被考验一次。他和那个创造一切的微妙之力作斗争，和那个从不休息一直保持警惕的对手作斗争，与那个比万物都长寿的老人—也就是时间本身作斗争。也就是说，他与时间本身作斗争，并且保持了自己的信仰。但现在，这种斗争的所有恐怖都集中于这一时刻。“上帝引诱亚伯拉罕，对他说……现在带上你的儿子，你唯一最钟爱的儿子以撒，到摩利亚之地去；把他作为燔祭献到我将指示给你的山上。”

所以一切欢愉都丧失了，而且比不曾有过这一切欢乐还要恐怖。这样看来，上帝只是在戏弄亚伯拉罕！他通过创造奇迹使荒诞之事成真，现在又要看到它被毁灭。这确实是一种愚弄！但起初当那个应许被宣布时，亚伯拉罕并没有像撒拉那样大笑。但现在，一切都要丧失了！七十年忠贞不渝的期望，以及信仰使他们得偿所愿所带来的短暂欢乐，都失去了。是谁从这老人手中夺取心爱之物，是谁还要求老人亲自毁了它？是谁让这个白发男人，显得那么孤苦绝望，是谁还要求他亲自做这事？难道没有对这位可敬的白发老人的同情之心吗？难道也没有对这无辜孩子丝毫的怜悯之心吗？然而，亚伯拉罕是上帝拣选之人，是上帝要对他进行考验。现在一切都将失去！那个将被人类珍藏的美好记忆，即那个对亚伯拉罕子孙后代的允诺，只是上帝一时的兴致，是上帝一种转瞬即逝的念头，而现在亚伯拉罕必须让自己杜绝这种想法。那光辉的珍宝，和亚伯拉罕心中的信仰一样长久，比以撒年岁还要长很多年，是亚伯拉罕生命的果实，在祷告中神圣、斗争中成熟，是亚伯拉罕祷念的祝福，这果实现在将被过早摘掉，也将失去意义。因为如果以撒要被献祭的话，它还能有什么意义呢？那是个悲伤却又神圣的时刻，此时，亚伯拉罕该告别他所珍爱的一切，此时他应再次抬起他那可敬的头颅，此时他的面容应该像上帝的面容那样光芒四射，此时他应全神贯注地祝福以撒，以给他带来终生的快乐—但这一刻终究没有到来！因为，是的，亚伯拉罕的确会告别以撒，但他会是留下的人；死亡会使他们分离，但以撒将会是受难者。老人是不会在心怀祈福时把手放在以撒身上的，但是厌倦生命之心会使他凶残地把手放在以撒身上。是上帝在考验他。是的，唉，唉，那个给亚伯拉罕带来这个消息的信使啊！谁会敢当这样悲惨消息的使者？然而，正是上帝要考验亚伯拉罕。

但是，亚伯拉罕拥有信仰，他对现世有信仰。是的，如果他的信仰只是对来世的信仰，那么为了更快离开这个他并不属于的世界抛弃一切会容易得多。但如果有这样的信仰的话，亚伯拉罕的信仰也是不属于这种的，因为这种信仰不是真正的信仰，而仅是信仰的一种最为遥远渺茫的可能性。这种信仰的对象只是最遥远的地平线上一种模糊的概念，但该信仰又因绝望作祟，与目标之间有着巨大的深渊相隔。但是亚伯拉罕的信仰是为了今生现世的。他相信他会在自己的土地上变老，受到他的人民的尊敬和他的家族的祝福，以撒也永远不会忘记他。他视以撒为掌上明珠，满心爱着他，这种爱仅仅用他忠实地履行了父亲爱儿子的义务这样的字眼来描述是不够的，正如上帝的召唤令里所说的那样：“你最钟爱的儿子。”雅各有十二个儿子，他只爱其中一个；亚伯拉罕却只有一个，他深爱着儿子。

但是，亚伯拉罕拥有信仰而且深信不疑。信仰要使他做荒谬反常之事，他也深信。如果他对信仰有了怀疑的话，那他可能会做别的事情来完成上帝给的任务，他会做某种伟大而光荣的事；因为亚伯拉罕怎么可能做除了伟大光荣之事以外的事呢？如果他有了怀疑的话，他会大步走向摩利亚山，砍些木柴，点燃之后，拔出刀子，他会对上帝呼喊：“请不要藐视这个献祭，我很清楚，它不是我拥有的最好的东西；因为一个垂老之人与一个充满希望的孩子相比算什么呢，但这是我能献祭的最好的东西了。请不要让以撒知道此事，以使他在青春岁月里可以过得心安。”他会将刀刺向自己的胸膛。那样，他会受世人景仰，永垂青史。不过，受人景仰是一回事，做一颗能够救人脱离痛苦的引导星则是另一回事。

但是，亚伯拉罕有信仰。他没有为自己祷告求情，以求打动上帝。只有在上帝宣告对所多玛城和蛾摩拉城进行正义的惩罚时，亚伯拉罕才挺身而出，为此祈祷。

我们可以在圣经经文中读到：“上帝引诱亚伯拉罕说：亚伯拉罕，你在哪儿？但亚伯拉罕回答说：我在这里。”你，正在阅读本文与我交流的读者朋友，这种情况下你会这么做吗？当你远远看见势不可挡的命运之神向你渐行渐近，难道你会不对群山说“把我藏起来”、对山坡说“把我遮挡住”吗？或者，如果你更坚强的话，难道你的双脚不会曳地前行，不会好像渴望重走老路吗？当你被上帝这样召唤时，你是回答还是不回答？也许你会轻声低语地应答？亚伯拉罕没有这样。他是欣喜地、无畏地、满怀信任地大声回答“我在这里”。我们在圣经中接着会读到：“亚伯拉罕一大清早就起身了。”他匆忙前行，仿佛要赶赴什么庆典似的。他在清晨抵达上帝指定的在摩利亚山上的那个地点。他没有对撒拉谈及此事，也没有对以利亚撒言语。毕竟，谁又能理解他呢？这样的考验本身不就是严格要求他宣誓缄默保密吗？“他劈好柴，绑上以撒，点燃柴堆，拔出刀来。”我的听众啊，许多父亲失去过儿子，他们觉得这就像失去了世上最宝贵的东西，就像对未来的所有希望都被剥夺了一样。然而，没有哪个儿子像以撒对亚伯拉罕而言那样前程远大，意义非凡。许多父亲失去过孩子，但那是上帝，万能的上帝的不可更改的神秘莫测的意志使然，而亚伯拉罕的情况并非如此。对他而言一个更大的考验在等着他；和那把刀一同放在他手里的还有以撒的命运。他站在那儿，这个老人和他的儿子，他唯一的希望，站在一起！但他没有迟疑，也没有痛苦地左顾右盼，更没有用他的祷告质疑上天。他知道这是万能的主在考验他，也知道这是上帝能向自己要求的最艰难的牺牲，但是他更知道，当这种要求是上帝的指示时，没有他作不到的牺牲—于是他拔出刀来。

是谁给了亚伯拉罕之臂以力量啊，是谁使他的右臂高举着不至于无助地下落啊！任何人见此情景都会瘫倒在地的。是谁赋予亚伯拉罕的灵魂以力量啊，以使他的眼睛不致昏暗而看不见以撒或那只羔羊！任何目睹此景的人都会变得盲目丧失理智的。尽管那些见此情景瘫倒或失去理智的人很少，更少见的却是那些能够如实公正地讲述此事的人。我们知道，我们都知道，这只是个考验。

亚伯拉罕若是在摩利亚山巅时信仰有任何动摇，或是四顾而犹豫不决，又或是他在拔刀之前偶然间看到了那只白羊，那只上帝允许他用来替代以撒作祭祀用的羊羔，那么他就会回家，一切都会像以前一样，他还会有撒拉，他的儿子以撒也还会活着。但那样会改变一切！因为他的退缩会被视为一种逃跑，他的获救会成为偶然，他的名誉会被玷污，他的未来也会受到诅咒。那样的话，他见证的就不是自己对主的信仰或是上帝的仁慈怜悯，而是摩利亚山之旅的可怕。亚伯拉罕是不会被人们忘记的，摩利亚山也一样。但是它不会像诺亚方舟在洪水中的停靠地—亚拉腊山—那样被人们歌颂，而是会被看作恐怖耻辱之山，因为亚伯拉罕是在这儿动摇了信仰。

可敬的父亲亚伯拉罕啊！当你从摩利亚山之旅回到家中，尽管有所失去，但你不需要赞美之词来安慰，因为实际上你赢得了一切也保住了以撒。不是这样吗？上帝不再把他从你身边夺走，你和他幸福地在帐篷中就餐，正如来世你也会永远这样做一样。可敬的父亲亚伯拉罕啊！那些岁月之后数千年已流逝，但你不需要后世的崇拜者来与遗忘之力争夺人们对你的记忆；因为每一种语言都将你纪念—而你也给你的钦慕者带来了无与伦比的回报。你使他在来世在你的胸膛得到永恒的幸福，而对今生的他而言，你用你的惊世行为征服了他的眼睛和心灵。可敬的父亲亚伯拉罕啊！你是人类的第二父亲！你是第一个见证了那种为了与上帝奋斗，而藐视与凶猛自然元素之间可怕斗争所体现出的巨大激情的人，你理解那种至高无上的激情，是那种异教徒也会崇拜的神圣纯洁而又谦卑的激情的第一位理解者—请原谅那个想赞美你而又没能正确地赞美你的人。他赞美你时言语谦逊，这是他心之所愿；他赞美之词简短，这是适宜的；但他永远不会忘记你等了一百年才在苍老之年出人意料地等到了儿子的出生，也不会忘记在上帝让你保留儿子之前你不得不拔刀对着儿子。他更不会忘记在一百三十年里你对信仰一直忠贞不渝，不曾脱离。

问题

源自内心的引言

一条关于外部可见世界的古谚语说：“只有劳作者才能得食物。”奇怪的是，这说法并不适用于它所根植的世界，因为外部世界是受不完美规律制约的。在这儿经常发生的是，不劳作者得食物，安逸睡大觉者比苦劳者所得的更多。在这外部世界里，所有者拥有一切，一切都受冷漠法则主宰。指环精灵听从戴它的人，不管他是努拉丁还是阿拉丁。拥有世上财富的人得到了财富，不管是用什么方法。精神世界则与此不同。这儿流行的是永恒的神圣法则。雨不会既落在正义上又打在非正义上，在这儿阳光并不会善与恶都普照；在这里只有劳作者才得食，只有明白痛苦者才能得到内心安宁，只有下过地狱者才能拯救爱人，只有拔刀者才能保有以撒。那不愿劳动者不能得到食物，但会受到迷惑，就像神迷惑俄耳甫斯一样。神用幻影替换俄耳甫斯所深爱的人，神迷惑他是因为他是个心肠温柔却不勇敢的人，还因为他是个七弦竖琴手，不是个男子汉。

在这种精神世界里，有亚伯拉罕做父亲或有长达一千七百年的贵族血统没有用。这儿不劳动的人就像传说中的以色列处女一样，只会孕育风，而劳作者则会产生自己的父亲。

传统智慧冒昧地试图把外部世界所抱怨的冷漠法则引入到精神世界里。这种智慧认为知道大真理就足够了，不需要其他的努力。但因此它不得食，当一切都变成金子时，它就会饿死的。它还知道什么呢？希腊历史上曾有成千上万人以及无数后代知道米堤亚得斯所获得的所有胜利，但只有一人为此失眠。同样，亚伯拉罕的故事也被世世代代的人传诵，又有多少人为之难以安眠呢？

亚伯拉罕的故事的卓越非凡之处就在于，不管我们对它的理解多么贫乏，它都会永远光辉灿烂。不过，也可以这么说，只有当我们愿意为理解这故事“辛苦劳动并承担重负”时，才可以理解它。但是，人们不愿意辛苦动脑，却想理解它。有人赞美亚伯拉罕，但又是怎样赞美他的呢？“亚伯拉罕的伟大在于他非常热爱上帝，以至于他愿意献出自己最好的东西”，这种赞美使这故事显得平凡无奇。这是非常正确的，但是“最好的”是个模糊的说法。一个人可以从语言和思想上轻易地认同亚伯拉罕的伟大，这样想的人可以悠然地吹吹烟斗，听人讲述亚伯拉罕故事的人也可以悠闲地舒展双腿。如果基督在路上碰到的那个富裕的年轻人卖掉自己所有的财产送给穷人，我们会像称赞所有伟大的行为一样称赞他，但我们如果不动脑费神的话就会连他也不能理解。然而即便他把自己最好的东西赠予别人，他也不能成为亚伯拉罕。在亚伯拉罕的故事里剩下的是痛苦；因为尽管我没有义务把钱给别人，但是父亲对儿子有最崇高最神圣的义务。而痛苦对柔弱者是件危险的事情，因此尽管人们想要谈论亚伯拉罕，他们却会忘记故事中留下的痛苦。所以他们谈论该故事，而且在讨论中将以下两个词对等：以撒和最好的东西。人们交谈甚欢。如果听众中有人正受失眠之苦，那么就可能产生最可怕最深刻而又悲喜交加的误解。这个听众回家后，他会想要做亚伯拉罕做过的事情，因为儿子的确是他拥有的最好的东西。而倘若那个讲述该故事的教士听说此事，他可能会走向那个人，动用自己作为神职人员的所有权威，对他大声喊叫：“你这个可憎之人，社会渣滓，是什么让你鬼迷心窍到想要谋杀自己的儿子？”而这位教士，在宣讲亚伯拉罕事迹时从没表现得激情澎湃，此刻他会为自己怒喝那个可怜的人时的义愤所惊讶，他会对自己深感满意，因为他从未讲得如此痛切、如此有激情。他会对自己和妻子说：“我是个演说家，我所需要的是机会；礼拜日我宣讲亚伯拉罕的时候，当时一点也不觉得动情陶醉。”倘若这位宣讲者所剩的善辩才智不多的话，那么当那个要杀死儿子的罪人冷静而又带有尊严地回答说“这实际上就是你周日所说教的呀”时，他一定会无言以对。一个教士怎么会产生这样的思想？然而他的确这样传道宣讲了，错误之处只在于他并没有理解自己所说的话。为什么某些诗人不描写这样的情景而要写那些充满垃圾废话的喜剧和小说呢？在此悲剧和喜剧在这绝对无限之处相遇。那传教士的言语本身无疑是够可笑的，但其所造成的后果可以说是更加的可笑；当然产生这样的后果也是相当自然的事情。或许，假设那个罪人没有抗议而接受了传教士的谴责训斥；或许假定那热忱的传教士开心地回了家，开心是因为知道了自己的传教效果不是局限于讲道坛，而最重要的是，自己的工作显然还有不可抵抗的引导灵魂的力量；因为礼拜日那天他激励了教众，而星期一他又像身背火焰剑的小天使降临到那个罪人面前，而那个罪人依从自己说教的行为正好使那个古老的说法黯然失色，那个说法是，世人从不践行传教士所宣讲的。[1]

不过，反过来说，倘若那个罪人未被说服，那么他的境况会很悲剧。他无疑会被处以死刑或送进疯人院；总而言之，他和所谓的现实之间的关系会不妙，尽管从另一种意义上说，我认为思考亚伯拉罕的故事使他快乐：因为思考者不会麻木，不会毁灭。

怎样解释这个传教士自相矛盾的言辞呢？是不是因为亚伯拉罕获得了“伟大的人”这一称号的所有权利，所以他所做的一切都是伟大的，而如果别人做相同的事，则是一种罪过，一种奇耻大罪？倘若如此，我不愿参与这种轻率愚蠢的颂扬。如果信仰不能使这种为了信仰情愿谋杀自己儿子的行为成为一种神圣的行为，那么就让人们像谴责任何其他人一样谴责亚伯拉罕吧。如果一个人没有勇气把这点看透彻，没有勇气说亚伯拉罕是个谋杀犯，那么与其浪费时间对他作不当的称颂，不如去努力获得这种勇气。亚伯拉罕所做的，从伦理道德的角度来说，是他愿意杀害以撒；用宗教的语言来描述，是他愿意献祭以撒。但存在于这种矛盾中的正是那种的确令人无眠的痛苦，然而没有那种痛苦，亚伯拉罕就不是亚伯拉罕他自己。又或许，亚伯拉罕根本就没有做故事里所讲的事，或许在他那个时代的情境里，他做的是和故事里讲的很不相同的事情。那么，让我们忘了他吧，因为何苦要费力劳神地去记住那已不能复制或变成现在的过去呢？或许那讲述者忘了讲某些伦理上的东西，比如他忘了讲以撒是亚伯拉罕的儿子这一事实。因为如果把信仰当作虚无直接去除的话，那么剩下的就只是一个残酷的赤裸裸的事实，即亚伯拉罕情愿杀死以撒；而这对任何没有信仰的人来说，是很容易效仿的。这儿没有信仰指的是没有那使人在杀人时感到为难的信仰。

就我个人而言，我不缺少勇气去透彻全面地思考一个想法。截至目前，还没有什么想法令我害怕。倘若我遇到一种令我惧怕的想法，我希望我至少能够诚实地说：“这种想法使我害怕又令我激动不安，所以我不想去思考它。”如果我这样说是错误的，我无疑会受到惩罚。如果我承认亚伯拉罕是个谋杀犯这个评判是正确的，我不能确定我是否能够平息自己心中对亚伯拉罕的崇敬；但如果我自己有这样的评判，我可能会保持沉默，因为这样的想法是不能传给别人的。但是，亚伯拉罕绝不是虚幻的，他的名声不是不劳而获的；他的名誉也不是命运的随意安排偶然得来的。

那么，要毫不保留地谈论亚伯拉罕而又不冒使某人出轨仿效他做同样的事这种风险，这可能吗？如果我不敢开诚布公地评论亚伯拉罕，我就干脆对他不作评论，而且最重要的是，我不会贬低他，以免他因此成为弱者的陷阱。倘若一个人视信仰为人生主旨，也就是说他纯粹地视信仰为信仰，那么我想，在当今我们这个很难说在信仰方面有所进步或超越的时代，他就可能敢于谈论信仰而不会冒前面所提到的那样的风险。再说，一个人也只有在信仰方面才可以达到接近亚伯拉罕的高度，而不是靠杀子来模仿他。如果一个人把爱变成一种转瞬即逝的情绪，把爱看成对某人感到欣喜激动，那么当他谈论爱的成就和事迹时就等于给弱者设下了陷阱。当然人人都有一时的情感，但人们若因这些情感而做那些可怕却又被爱情神圣化不朽化的事情，一切就会丧失，这一切包括爱的壮举和那些被情感所误导而为情所困的人们。

那么，谈论亚伯拉罕是可以的。伟大之人的伟大之处被正确理解的时候，是绝不会有什么坏处的。它就像一把双刃剑，既可杀人，又可救人。如果命中注定我要评论亚伯拉罕的话，我会首先说明亚伯拉罕是一个多么虔诚，对上帝满怀敬畏的人，他配得上“上帝所选的”这个称号。只有这样的人才会经受这样的考验，但谁是这样的人呢？接着，我会描述亚伯拉罕如何深爱以撒。为了达到这个目的，我会乞求所有善良之神的帮助，以使我的溢美之词像父亲对儿子的爱一样炽烈，我希望把这种爱描述得令这片领土上没有一个父亲敢说自己这样深爱过儿子。不过，要是一个父亲没有像亚伯拉罕那样爱儿子，那么，所有献出以撒的念头就会是一种诱惑。仅此一点，我们就已经足以谈论好几个周日，因此不必着急。如果谈论内容符合主题的话，结果会是，一些父亲如果真的作到了像亚伯拉罕一样慈爱，就会很开心，不想再听更多，而只满足于一时的开心。倘若有人在听了亚伯拉罕事迹的伟大之处和可怕之处之后，竟然冒险也走上了那条路的话，我会骑上马和他一同前往。在抵达摩利亚山之前的每一个驿站，我都会向他说明，他依然可以转身回去，他可以后悔没有理解会被召唤来经受这种性质的矛盾的考验，可以承认自己缺乏勇气，说“如果上帝想要以撒的话，上帝必须自己把他带走”。我深信，这样的人是不会被上帝抛弃的，他会像其他人一样得到庇佑，尽管不是时时得到庇佑。即便是在信仰盛行的时代，难道这样的人不会受到这样的评判吗？我认识一个人，他要是够慷慨的话，是可以救我一命的。他坦率地告诉我：“我很清楚我能做什么，但我不敢。我担心在最后时刻我缺乏力量，还担心我会为此后悔。”他不够慷慨，但谁会因此而不再爱他呢？

说到此处，而且在我已经打动了听众，使他们至少意识到一些关于信仰和其伴随的巨大激情之间的辩证斗争之后，若听众有这样的错误想法：“嗯，他的信仰如此深重坚定，我们只要抓住他衣服的后摆紧紧跟随他就够了”，并将之归咎于我的话，我是不会感到内疚的。因为我会补充说：“我绝对没有什么信仰。我只不过是个本性上比较精明之人罢了。我总是在把信仰付诸行动方面有困难。尽管克服这种困难使精明之人在信仰方面比没有这种困难的简单普通之人到达的程度要高，我并不认为这有什么重要价值。”

爱情，有诗人做它的传教士，人们偶尔会听到一个知道如何捍卫它称颂它的声音；但是人们却听不到关于称颂信仰的一言半语，谁来赞美这种信仰的激情？哲学的赞美者就更多了。神学坐在窗边涂脂抹粉来寻求哲学的青睐恩宠，向它大献殷勤。人们以为，理解黑格尔很难，而理解亚伯拉罕却是小事一件；超越黑格尔是个奇迹，而超越亚伯拉罕则轻而易举。我本人已花费了不少时间来理解黑格尔哲学，并且认为我已多少理解了它。我还冒昧地认为，该哲学的某些部分，尽管我付出很多努力也不能理解，其原因是黑格尔自己也没有完全弄清楚。我理解黑格尔哲学可以说是一切都自然而然，轻而易举，没有怎么劳神。但是当我思考亚伯拉罕时，我几乎可以说是彻底迷糊崩溃了。我无时不意识到亚伯拉罕生活中的那个巨大的矛盾或者说是悖论。不管我带着多大的激情试图去进入它，理解它，我感到总是被击退，丝毫也不能进步。我拼尽全力想去瞥一眼，但总是瞬间就崩溃无力了。

我并不是不了解世间所崇尚的伟大和高尚慷慨。我的心灵深处感受得到它的吸引力，我满怀谦恭之心深信英雄所追求的事业也是我的事业。当我思虑英雄的奋斗时，不禁对自己大喊：“现在你的事业正处在危急之时。”我可以把自己想象成英雄，但我不能把自己想象成亚伯拉罕；当我把自己想象到亚伯拉罕那个高度时，我会跌落下来，因为我面对的是一个悖论。然而我绝不是认为信仰是低下的；相反它的地位是最至高无上的。同时，我认为哲学给我们提供哲学以外的东西并且轻视信仰，这是哲学的不诚实不厚道。哲学不能也不应该给我们阐述信仰，它应该理解它自身，并明白在不减损贬低什么的情况下它究竟要给人们提供什么。哲学最不应该做的就是通过欺骗使人们认为某事物虚无而摈弃它。我不是不熟知生活的诸多困惑与危险，我不害怕它们，我勇敢上前，无畏地面对。我也不是不熟悉恐怖之事。我的记忆是我忠实的伴侣，而我的想象，不像我自己，而像一个勤劳的女仆，她白天静静地勤劳工作，晚上则会甜美地和我闲聊她的工作，以至于我不得不关注她，即便她并不总是像她所描绘的风景，鲜花或牧歌田园那样。我已直面过恐惧，我不会因为害怕逃走。但我深知，不管我多么勇敢地面对它，我的勇气不是信仰的勇气，而且根本不能与之相提并论。我不能做到闭上双眼，充满信任地投身于荒诞之事，这对我而言是不可能的，当然我并不据此赞美我自己。我深信，上帝就是爱；这种想法的正确性对我而言是清新素朴和抒情诗般深情的。当它浮现在我脑海里时，我就难以言表地高兴；当它不见踪影时，我思念它比情人思念挚爱时还强烈。但是我没有信仰，我缺乏这种勇气。上帝的爱，对我而言，不管是从直接的还是相反的意义上来说，与整个现实都是相差悬殊，不可比较的。我没有因此而怯懦到呜咽和呻吟的地步，但我也没有阴险低下到否认信仰是一种层次要高得多的东西。我完全可以以自己的方式继续生活，我可以过得很快乐很满足，但我这种快乐不是信仰带来的快乐，而且与之相比甚至可以叫作不快乐。我不会因小事烦扰上帝，我不关心小事。我仅关注我之所爱，保持我爱的火焰无瑕而又纯粹。信仰深信上帝的关爱无微不至，上帝对最小的事也关注。今生今世我满足于和左手联姻，信仰却谦恭到要求右手的地步。而那确实是谦恭，我没有，也绝不会否认这种谦恭。

但是我好奇我们这个时代的人是否真的能够将信仰付诸行动？除非我搞错了，这一代人倾向于以能做他们认为连我都做不到的事为傲，那就是不完美或叫半途而废。以非正常的方式谈论伟大之人伟大之事，好像几千年是巨大遥远的距离似的，人们经常这样做，但这却是违背我的本性的。我更愿意以正常的方式谈论它，好像它就发生在昨天似的，只让伟大本身成为或被赞扬或被谴责的距离。如果我是一个假扮的悲剧英雄（因为更高的层次我也达不到），被召唤去完成像去摩利亚山那样非凡的旅程，我很清楚我会做什么。我不会怯懦到待在家里不愿出门，我也不会在路上休憩或磨蹭拖延，也不会忘带刀子以便拖延时间。我肯定我会准时到那儿，并且将一切准备就绪。我甚至会提前很早到达，以便早点结束那一切。但是我也知道我还会做些什么。我飞身上马的那一刻，我会对自己说：“现在一切都失去了。上帝索要以撒，我将要献祭以撒，和他一起献上的还有我所有的欢乐—然而，上帝就是爱，对我而言他还将依然如此。”因为在世俗世界里上帝和我无法交谈，我们没有共同语言。也许，我们这个时代里会有人非常愚蠢，非常羡慕伟大之人，以至于认为，或使我认为，倘若我真的那样做了，我就做了比亚伯拉罕做的还更伟大的事，因为我表现出的无比绝望难道不比亚伯拉罕的偏执狭隘要更理想化和富有诗意吗？然而这种想法是大错特错了，因为我的无比绝望替换掉了信仰。我作不到超越无限运动去寻找自我和追求心灵的安宁。我也作不到像亚伯拉罕那样爱以撒。当然我坚决地动手付诸行动这一事实可能证明了我的勇气。从人性的角度讲，我全身心地爱他是个前提条件，没有这个前提条件整件事就变成了邪恶行为。然而我并不会像亚伯拉罕那样爱他，因为那样的话，我会在最后时刻退缩停住，尽管我并没有因为退缩迟迟才到达摩利亚山。而且我的行为还会破坏玷污整个故事，因为要是我重新得到以撒，我会感到茫然尴尬。重新在以撒身上得到快乐，这对亚伯拉罕是最容易的事，对我而言却很难；因为一个人在倾注了全部灵魂，自愿并自行负责地做了自己能力范围内无比弃绝的事[2]之后，他再拥有以撒只能是一种痛苦。

但是亚伯拉罕做了什么？他到达得不早也不晚。他骑上毛驴，沿着那条道慢慢前行。整个路途中，他都怀有信仰，他相信上帝不会向他要走以撒，然而他依然愿意献上以撒，如果上帝会真的想要他的话。他凭借荒诞偏执坚持信仰，因为不存在人的估计和推测的问题。而上帝向他要以撒之后下一刻竟又取消这要求肯定是荒诞的。他爬上山，即便在他手中的刀子闪着寒光的那一刻，他依然保有信仰，坚信上帝不会强要以撒。当然他对事情的结果感到惊讶，但通过这一双重行动，他又回到最初，所以他可以比第一次更欢乐地得到以撒。让我们再进一步分析看看，我们假设以撒实际上被献祭了。亚伯拉罕仍有信仰。他的信仰不是他以后会在来世某个时间得到快乐，而是他会在今世得到受庇佑的幸福。上帝会给他一个新的以撒，使被献祭的以撒复活。他依靠荒诞偏执坚持信仰，因为他早已停止一切正常人会进行的推测。我们清楚，悲痛会使人心智失常，而且这确实令人悲伤；同时我们也明白，有一种叫意志力的东西，它如此强大，可以逆风行驶，与风竞力，足以拯救一个人的理智，即便这个人已经有些古怪（这儿我绝对没有贬低之意）。但是一个人能够失去理智和理解力，以及这个由理智做经纪人打理的有限俗世，然后又凭借荒诞之力重新得回这有限世界，这样的事令我惊骇无比。但我并不因此说它低下或没有价值，正相反，它是唯一的奇迹。人们普遍以为，信仰所能产生的绝不是艺术品，而是只有笨拙之人才会要的粗糙俗气的制品，然而事实远非如此。信仰的辩证法是所有辩证法中最精细最出色的。它有一种提升的作用，对此我只能形成一种概念，但不能详细说清楚。我可以做蹦床跳，跳得极高，我有走钢丝演员那样的后背，这在儿时就已形成，因此这样跳对我来说很容易。一、二、三，我可以倒立着走来走去，但下一步我就无能为力了，因为我不能制造奇迹，我只能为之惊叹。是的，要是亚伯拉罕跨上毛驴的时候对自己说：“现在要失去以撒了。我何不在家里直接把他献祭，权当我走过那漫漫长路到了摩利亚。”那样我就不需要亚伯拉罕了。但事实是，现在我会对他的名字鞠七次躬，对他的英勇事迹鞠七十次躬。因为他没有那样做，我可以通过他重新得到以撒时的欢乐，那衷心的欢乐，他不需要时间和准备就可以调整自己来接受当下及其带来的欢乐这一点来证明。假如亚伯拉罕的情况不是这样，他很可能还是爱上帝的，但是他不会拥有信仰；因为不坚持对上帝的信仰而爱上帝的人反映的是自己，而笃信地爱着上帝的人反映的是上帝。

亚伯拉罕站在这个至高点上。他忽视的这个最后阶段叫无限弃绝阶段。他的确更进一步，达到了信仰。一切对信仰的讽刺，如那可怜的冷漠者的想法，认为“肯定没有必要也不值得提前担心”，那可怜的带有侥幸之心的想法，认为“谁知道会发生什么，也许终究不会有事的”，这些曲解信仰的想法属于生活中的卑劣可怜者，而无限弃绝者无比地蔑视他们。

我对亚伯拉罕无法理解；从某种意义上说，我从他那儿可以学到的只有惊叹。如果有人想象一个人可以通过思考这个故事的结果得到感动，从而有了信仰，那他就是自欺欺人，他也试图从信仰的第一阶段就欺骗上帝，试图从这个悖论中获取人生智慧。可能有人会成功，因为我们这个时代不愿意停止于信仰，这个时代在把水变成美酒后不愿停止制造奇迹；它更进一步，把美酒又变成了水。

难道，不管怎样，止步于信仰不是最好吗？难道人人都想更进一步走得更远不令人不安吗？当如今的人们以种种形式宣称不愿止步于爱时，他们正去向哪里呢？他们会走向世俗聪明、斤斤计较和算计，走向毫无价值、卑劣可鄙，走向一切使人的神圣起源（神授说）受到质疑的东西吗？难道一个人坚守信仰，并小心不要摔倒不更好吗？因为信仰运动必须要凭借荒诞之力持续地进行下去，但要注意，是用这样一种方式，这种方式不会使人失去有限的事物，反而会使他完整地得到它。就我个人而言，我确实可以描述信仰运动，但我不能够完成这些行动。当一个人学习游泳动作时，他可以悬吊在天花板上，我们说他在描述游泳动作还行，但不能说他是在游泳；同理，我可以描述信仰的动作，但当我被扔进水里，尽管我可以说是在游泳（因为我不是蹚水者），我做的是其他的动作，是无限性的动作；而信仰则是相反的动作：在完成了无限性的动作之后，它作的是有限性的动作。能那样完成那些动作，能制造奇迹的人是多幸运多可敬啊，我会永不疲倦地敬佩他。不管他是亚伯拉罕还是亚伯拉罕家里的仆人，是一个哲学教授还是贫穷的女佣，对我而言都绝对是无关紧要的，我只关注他们的行动。但我的确观察他们，以使自己不被自己或别人愚弄。无限弃绝骑士很容易辨认，他们步态轻快而又勇猛。但戴有信仰之珠宝的人却很容易使人迷惑或失望，因为他们从外表上看有一种和贪图享受的中产阶级非常相似的庸俗之气，而这是被无限弃绝和信仰所骄傲地鄙视的。

坦率地说，我在自己的经验中还没有发现任何可靠的有信仰之士的例子，尽管我不会因此否认可能很多人都是这样的例子。不过，我已经为了找到一个这样的人白白努力了好几年。人们一般周游世界是为了游览河流山川，看新发现的星星、羽毛艳丽的小鸟、奇怪的鱼、奇异怪诞的人种；他们陷入一种动物似的麻木无觉状态，只是呆视着一切，他们以为自己看到了值得重视的事物。我不关注这些。但是如果我知道哪儿住着个信仰骑士，我会徒步漫游去见他，因为我对这样的奇人绝对会无比地关心投入。我会一刻不停地陪在他身边，目不转睛地观察他如何进行信仰活动。我会把自己看作终生需要扶持养护的人，会把自己的时间一分为二，以便一边观察他，一边自己也练习那些动作，这样我就可以全身心地崇拜他。如前所述，我还没有发现一个这样的人；不过，我依然可以很清楚地想象这样的一个人。在我的想象中，他来了，来到我面前。我与他相识时，有人介绍我给他认识。我第一眼看到他时，我把他推开，往后跳一步，拍手惊呼：“我的上帝啊！是这个人吗？真的是他吗？他看起来就像个收税者。”然而的确是他。我靠近他，无比仔细地观察他的哪怕最细微的动作，以便看到某些来自无限的、细小的，显示出不一致性的光学传真信息，我观察他的一瞥一笑、一举一动，以及喜怒哀乐的表情，这些行为若与有限性不一致，就暴露出了无限性。没有！我从头到脚地仔细观察他，以便找到某些泄露出无限性的裂缝或破绽来。没有！他的言行是彻彻底底一致的。他的站姿如何？蓬勃有力，完全属于有限性的特点，没有哪个周日下午前往弗雷斯堡闲逛的市民的步态比他更稳健的了。他完全属于这个尘世，没有哪个小资产阶级比他更属于这个世俗世界。一个人很难从他身上发现无限弃绝骑士那种超然离群的怪异和高人一等的气质。他参与各种日常活动，并从这所有活动中获得乐趣。当你看到他正忙于某事时，他的投入执着状态和任何凡俗之人全神贯注做某事时是一样的。他专心于工作。看到他工作的样子你会想到他像一个全身心忙于意大利式簿记的记账员似的，对细节一丝不苟。他礼拜日也休息。他常去教堂。你在他身上看不到任何神圣之光或与凡人不可比拟、格格不入之处。不认识他的人要把他和教众区别开来是不可能的；因为尽管他唱赞美诗时感情充沛、精神饱满，但那至多证明他有健康的双肺而已。下午时分，他会去林间散步。他为见到的一切感到喜悦：蜂拥的人群，新的交通工具公共汽车，动听的水声。在海边小道上碰见他的人会以为他是个正在享受一时放纵的店主。这就是他的娱乐方式；他不是个诗人，而我还曾经徒劳地想从他身上捕获那种富有诗意的非凡之处。傍晚来临时他回家去，步伐依然如邮递员走路那样不知疲倦。路上他想到妻子一定为他特别准备了热乎乎的小菜等他归来，比如说配有蔬菜的烤羊头之类。倘若他遇见一个投缘的人，他会带着饭店经营者似的热情津津乐道地和他谈论这道菜，一直走到东大门。碰巧的是，他身无分文，却坚信他妻子已准备好了那道佳肴等着他。如果她真准备好了那道菜的话，那么看他吃饭一定会是个让上等人羡慕、让普通人刺激的奇观，因为他的胃口比以扫的还要大。若他的夫人没有准备那道菜，不可思议的是，他依然会狼吞虎咽，胃口奇好。在路上，他经过了一个建筑工地，在那儿又遇见了一个人。他们交谈片刻，片刻间，他建立起了一座高楼，他具有办成此事的所有能力。那个陌生人离开他的时候在想：“那人一定曾是个资本家。”而我钦佩的骑士则想着：“是的，就那件事而言，我肯定办得到。”他在一个打开的窗户边休息，同时俯瞰着他所居住的街区广场，观察一切正在发生的事情：一只老鼠从板下溜过排水沟，正在嬉戏的儿童。他泰然自若地看着这一切，冷静恬淡如十六岁的女孩。然而，他绝不是什么天才；我曾想从他身上窥探到天才身上所具有的不同寻常的无可比拟性，但这是徒劳的。晚上他会抽烟袋，看他这样你会发誓说他就像对面那位茫然呆坐着的干酪商。他漫不经心无忧无虑地生活在这世上，像个没有用的家伙，然而他购买他生活中的每一刻，他以最昂贵的价格买适宜的时间，因为他做任何事情都靠那股荒诞极端的劲儿。然而，是的，这却激怒了我，当然我不为别的，只是出于羡慕而生气。只是这个人已经而且是每时每刻都在作具有无限性的运动。他带着无限弃绝的情感饮尽生活中深深的悲哀，他知道无限者的幸福，他已感受到了那放弃一切，放弃世间最宝贵的东西的痛苦。而对他而言，有限者生活的味道也一如不知有更好味道之人所感到的一样美好，因为他在有限性的生活中并没有感到受挫、害怕的迹象；而且他依然有安全感并能享受生活，好像有限生活是一切事物中最确定最可靠的一样。然而，他所体现的完全世俗的样子却依靠荒诞成了一种新的创造物。他放弃一切，接着又靠荒诞之力重新赢回一切。他不断地作着无限者的运动，但是他作得如此精准平稳，他又不断地从中得到有限性，而且没有人会怀疑什么。人们说，对跳舞者而言最难做到的是，以一种轻松而毫不费劲的方式直接跳出某个姿势，而且能在那一跳中保持该姿势。可能没有哪个舞蹈者能做到这一点，但这个骑士却能。大多数人灰溜溜地完全生活在世俗的喜怒哀乐中，他们就像板凳队员一样旁观着，不能加入到跳舞者的队伍中。无限弃绝骑士也是舞蹈者，他们的动作有腾空跳跃的高度。他们做向上的动作，然后又跳下来，这同样是快乐的消遣，看起来也很优美。但是他们下落时，却不能立即形成那个姿势。他们会摇晃踌躇一瞬间，这动摇表明他们终究是这世界上的异客。他们的摇晃程度取决于他们的技术，但可能多少都是显而易见的，即便是最娴熟的骑士也掩藏不了那摇晃动作。人们不需看他们在空中时的样子，只需看到他们落地和刚刚落地时的样子就可以认出他们。但是要能够以这样的方式落地，即在落地时立即看起来像是在站立行走一样，要把充满朝气活力的跳跃转变成行走，还能表现出行走者的崇高和庄严，这是只有信仰骑士才能做得到的事，而且这是唯一的奇迹。

不过，这种奇迹却有着很容易欺骗人的表象，因此我要举个具体的例子来描述信仰骑士的那些动作，以显示出其与现实的联系。而这是一切的关键。一个小伙子爱上了一位公主，这爱情是他生活的全部内容之所在。然而这是一种不可能有结果的，不会从理想转变成现实的恋爱。[3]当然，那不幸的奴隶，那生活如沼泽地里的青蛙的人会惊叫：“这样的爱是愚蠢的；那有钱酒商的寡妇一样是很好的很般配的选择。”让那些青蛙在沼泽里聒噪吧。无限弃绝骑士是不会这样做的，他不会为了一切世俗的虚荣而放弃爱情。他也绝不是轻佻的傻子。他会首先确定爱她确实是自己生活的实质，因为他的心灵太健全、太骄傲，而不能浪费一丁点儿在迷醉之类的错事上。他也不怯懦，他不怕爱潜入蔓延到他最隐秘最深藏的思想深处，不怕它盘绕住自己意识的每一根纽带和神经。如果爱变得不快乐，他会永远也不能脱身。当他任爱兴奋着自己的每根神经时，他感到幸福的狂喜。然而他的心灵却无比庄严肃穆，就像一个饮尽了一杯毒酒，感受毒液渗透到每一滴血的人所感受到的那样—因为这是生死攸关的一刻。当他已经这样吸收了全部的爱，全身心地沉浸于其中后，他将不缺乏勇气去尝试一切，也敢冒一切风险。他反思自己人生的境况，他的敏锐的思想就像训练有素的鸽子一样听他召唤，服从他的每一个信号。他一挥竿，它们即四散飞去。但是现在，当鸽子们都作为悲伤的信使飞回来，向他解释这爱情不可能时，他变得很沉静。他把它们打发开去，独自一人，进行他的运动。如果我在这儿说的会有任何意义的话，那这运动必须是正常进行的。[4]因为，接下来首先，骑士会有力量来把他生活的全部内容和现实的意义集中到一个唯一的愿望上。如果一个人缺乏这种力度和强度的专注性，那他的心从一开始就会溃散分裂，他就绝不可能进行他的运动。他就会在生活中行事谨慎精明，就像那些资本家那样，把资金投放在各种证券上，以便这个赔了的话那个可以赚—简而言之，他不是个骑士。其次，骑士会把自己反思的所有结果集中于一种意识行为。如果他缺乏这个专注力，他的心神会从一开始就分散，那他就不会有时间进行他的运动。他会一直疲于奔命，忙于各种差使，永远不会进入永恒。因为当他刚要接近永恒时，他总会发现忘带了什么东西，因而必须返回。在下一刻他会认为进入永恒是可能的，那也是很真实的。只是有了这些考虑，一个人永远也不会去进行那个运动。反而会因为这些思虑而越来越深地陷入泥沼。

所以说骑士会作那个运动，但是是什么运动？他想忘记整件事吗？因为在忘记此事中也需要有一种专注。不！骑士是不会做自我矛盾的事的。一个人忘却生活的全部实质内容而又保持不变，这本身就是自相矛盾的。他不想变成另一个人，因为那样做毫无伟大可言。只有低等物种才会忘却自己，变成某种新东西。因而蝴蝶已完全忘记自己曾是毛毛虫，也许后面它还会全然忘记自己曾是个蝴蝶以便变成一条鱼。而高级生物绝不会忘记自我，不会变成某种不是曾经的自己的东西。所以，这位骑士会记住一切，但这记忆恰恰是种痛苦。然而，在这无限弃绝中，他与存在达成了和解。对他而言，他对那位公主的爱会变成一种永恒的爱的表现，还会逐渐获得一种宗教的特征，会美化成为一种对永恒存在的爱，这种爱虽然无法实现，依然以一种现实无法予以剥夺的永远有效的永恒意识使他得到平和。愚蠢而年轻的人总爱说，对人而言一切都是可能的，但那是一个巨大的错误。从精神上来说，一切都是可能的，但在有限世界里很多事物是不可能的。但是，这种不可能却被骑士通过精神上的表现变为可能，不过，他是通过放弃这种不可能性来在精神上表现它的。那个本来会带他走向现实但因为不可能而夭折的欲望，现在已转入内心，不过并没有因此丧失或被忘记。有时是他的愿望在无意识下唤醒那段记忆，有时是他自己主动唤醒它，因为他太骄傲，而不愿让那曾经是自己生活的全部内容的事成为一件转瞬即逝的一时的风流韵事。他保持着这种爱情的青春，而这爱也随着岁月流逝增长，并日益美丽。此外，他也不需要作有限的干预来使其增长。从他作那项运动那一刻开始，他就已失去了公主。他不需要看到所爱之人时所感到的情欲上的快感，也不需要在有限的意义上不断地与她告别，因为他对她的记忆是永恒的。他很清楚，那些渴望再见彼此一面来道别的恋人们有理由那样渴望，有理由认为那是他们最后一次见面，因为他们很快就会忘记对方。他已洞悉了一个深刻的秘密，那就是，一个人在爱另一个人的同时也要独立自给自足。他已不再从有限的意义上关心公主在做什么，这恰恰证明他已经在作那无限弃绝运动。在这里，我们有机会发现一个人所作的无限运动是真的还是假的。曾经有一个人以为自己作了那无限意义上的运动，但随着时间流逝，公主做了某件别的事，比方说，她嫁给了一位王子，他的心顿时就失去了弃绝的适应力和达观。他于是知道自己没有正确地作那无限运动；因为一个真正作了无限弃绝的人是独立自主的。而该骑士却不会取消自己的弃绝决定，他将他的爱保持住，一如刚开始时那样青春，他从未放弃过它，恰恰是因为他作了无限弃绝运动。那位公主所做的不会打扰他内心的平静。只有低等秉性的人才会从别人身上找自己行为的法则，才会从外在找自己行动的前提。当然，从另一方面来说，如果公主和他情投意合，那么会有美丽的爱情故事展开。接着她会自己进入骑士的级别，进入该级别不需要选票，任何有勇气自荐的人都可以加入；她会进入这个通过不区分男女这一事实来证明其不朽性的骑士级别。她也会把她的爱情保鲜，她也会克服痛苦，即便她没有，如同歌里所唱的那样：“躺在贵族夫君身旁。”这两人会永远和谐共处，而且他们之间具有如此的前定和谐。假如那样的时刻会来临，不过不是在一个关乎有限性的时刻（因为在有限世界里，他们会变老），假如他们适时表达爱情的时刻会来临的话，那么，倘若他们一开始就结合，他们就能恰好在那个他们本应开始的地方开始。理解这一点的人，不管是男人还是女人，永远不会受骗，因为只有低等秉性的人才会想象自己被骗了。一个没有这种自傲的女孩实际上并不理解爱的意义，但如果她有这种自傲，世上所有的阴谋诡计都欺骗不了她。

一个人在无限弃绝中会有平和与安宁；任何愿意无限弃绝的人，任何没有通过自我轻视而贬低自己的人—这比过于骄傲还可怕得多—都可以自我训练去作这种运动。这种无限弃绝运动使人在痛苦中得到与存在的协调平和。无限弃绝就像一个古老传说中所说的那件衬衫。里面的丝线在泪水中纺成，在泪水中漂白，衬衫也是在泪水中缝制的，但这衬衫给人的保护却比钢铁的还好。这个故事的一个缺陷是第三方可以制成衬衫。生活的秘密是每个人必须自己缝制它；了不起的是男人也可以做得和女人的一样好。如果无限弃绝运动正确进行的话，会得到平和与宁静，以及痛苦中的安慰。我可以很轻松地写一整本书来描述仅仅是我自己在此运动中出现的各种各样的误解，错误的姿势，懒散马虎的动作。人们很少相信精神，然而进行此运动恰恰需要精神。重要的是，它不是一种对必要性的残忍的克制约束的单方面结果，这种单方面克制的情况出现得越多，此项运动正常与否就越值得怀疑。因而，如果一个人认为那种冷酷的毫无结果的必然性必定存在的话，那么他就是相信没有人能够在自己真正死去之前经历死亡，这，在我看来，好像是极端唯物主义。然而，在我们这个时代，人们不怎么关心作纯粹的运动。假设某个想学跳舞的人说：“到现在为止，数百年来一代又一代的人都在学这些舞蹈动作，是时候我利用这些，直接从四对方舞开始了。”人们大概会有些嘲笑他，但在精神世界里，这样的态度却是十分合理的。那么，教育是什么呢？我认为教育是一个人学习如何把握自我、超越自我的课程，而对于不愿学习此课程的人来说，就是生活在最文明的时代对他也没有什么用。

无限的弃绝是达到信仰之前的最后阶段，没有作这一运动的人不能说拥有信仰；因为，只有在无限的弃绝中，我才完全清楚了自己的永恒有效性，唯有如此，一个人才可以说靠信仰把握了存在。

现在，我们让前面那个场合里提及的信仰骑士出场吧。信仰骑士做的和那个骑士做的完全一样：他无限地放弃了对他生活的全部—爱情—的追求，他在痛苦中得到调解平和。但接着奇迹发生了，他又多作了一个比其他都精彩得多的运动，因为他说：“不管怎样，我相信我会得到她；也就是说，凭着荒诞，凭着对上帝而言一切皆有可能这一事实，我深信我会得到她。”这里，荒诞并不属于理解的合理领域内的一种区别，它不同于不可能、意外、无法预见。在那位骑士进行弃绝行动的那一刻，从正常人性的角度讲，他深知那一不可能性，那是理解的结果，他完全能够想明白它。然而，从无限的意义上讲，它却是可能的，也就是说，通过放弃它（它即有限的可能性）；但是，接受这种拥有的可能性同时也是一种放弃。不过，对于理解而言，拥有这可能性绝非荒诞；因为，理解在它具有主宰地位的有限世界里断定，这种拥有曾经是且依然是一种不可能性，在这一点上，理解依然正确。信仰骑士同样清楚地意识到这一点；因此，能拯救他的只有荒诞，而靠信仰他领悟了这一点。于是，他承认那不可能性，但同时又相信那荒诞的可能性。因为要是他想说拥有信仰，却没有全心全意地承认那不可能性，那他就是在欺骗自我；而既然他甚至没达到无限的弃绝这一程度，那么他说自己有信仰的宣言就会在哪里都没有说服力。

因此，正是因为信仰以弃绝为前提条件，信仰才绝不是唯美的感情，而是某种高得多的东西。它不是内心的自发的倾向，而是存在的悖论。因而，若一个面临重重困难的少女确信自己的愿望会实现，这绝不意味着她的自信是对信仰的确信，即便她是由信基督教的父母抚养成人的，而且可能还去牧师那里接受了整整一年的信仰指导。她坚信的是自己的天真无邪，这种信心使她显得本性崇高，给她一种超自然的力量，以至于她可以像魔术师那样施展出存在范围内的有限力量，甚至打动石头，令其哭泣；而当她困惑恐慌时，她则可以跑向希律王，也可以跑向彼拉多，用她的哀求打动整个世界。她的信心总是那么可爱，人们可以从她那里学到很多。但有一件事情是不可能从她那里学到的，那就是如何作那些运动，因为，她的信心不敢在弃绝的痛苦中直面那不可能性。

由此，我明白了，要进行无限的弃绝运动需要力量、精力和精神自由；我还意识到，这是可以做到的。接下来的一步使我惊讶头晕，因为一个人在作了无限的弃绝运动之后，接着要依靠荒诞得到一切，要完完全全地实现自己的愿望，那是需要超人的力量的；那就是一个奇迹。但至少我可以认识到这一点，那就是，那个少女的信心，与认识到不可能却依然不可动摇的信仰相比，只不过是轻浮与轻率罢了。每当我要作这一运动的时候，我都感到头晕眼花，同时我又无比地敬佩它，但又感到巨大的恐惧不安。因为我在想，诱惑上帝意味着什么呢？然而，不管哲学为了混淆概念会怎样努力地使我们相信它有信仰，不管神学怎样想廉价地出卖信仰，这项运动就是信仰运动而且会持续如此。

无限弃绝并不需要信仰，因为在弃绝中我获得的是我永恒的意识，而这是一种纯粹的哲学运动，为此，必要时我会冒险做到，我可以通过自我训练做到；因为每当我达不到某种有限的事物时，我会忍饥挨饿地坚持，直到能作那项运动；因为我永恒的意识是我对上帝的爱，对我而言，那是高于一切的东西。弃绝运动不要求有信仰，但要得到比永恒的意识哪怕多一丁点儿的东西则要求有信仰，因为这正是悖论。这些运动经常被混淆。据说要放弃一切需要信仰；不错，听说更奇怪的是，人们抱怨说他们已失去了信仰，当查看他们所处位置时，才发现他们才来到需要进行无限弃绝运动的地点。通过弃绝我放弃了一切，这是一项我独自进行的运动。当我不作此运动时，那是因为我怯懦软弱，缺乏热情，没有意识到每个人被赋予的崇高尊严的意义，也没有意识到做自己的检察官这一崇高尊严的重要性，它是比做整个罗马共和国总检察长还要高得多的尊严。我靠自己进行这项运动，我因此获得的是我永恒的意识，以及我与自己对永生者的爱之间的一种神圣的和谐一致。凭借信仰，我不放弃一切，相反，凭借信仰我得到一切。就像人们所说的那样，有像芥菜种子一样信仰的人可以撼动高山。要放弃整个暂时性来获得永恒，这需要人具有纯粹的勇气。但我的确得到了它，而且不能为了永恒放弃它，因为那样就会是一种自相矛盾。但是要依靠荒诞去抓住全部暂时性需要有一种相悖而又谦卑的勇气，而这种勇气是信仰的勇气。依靠信仰，亚伯拉罕没有放弃以撒，还是依靠信仰，他又得到了以撒。前面所说的那个富裕的年轻人，借助他的弃绝，本应捐赠了一切，但是他一旦这样做了，信仰骑士会对他说：“依靠荒诞，你会重新得到每一分钱，要相信这一点！”这些话对那个曾经富裕的年轻人绝非无关紧要之言，因为倘若他是因厌烦无聊而放弃他的所有，那他的弃绝就是可怜而又令人遗憾的。

这里，一切的关键是暂时性和有限性。我能够靠自己的力量放弃一切，然后在痛苦中找到平和安宁。我可以忍受一切，即便是那魔鬼，那比恐怖的骷髅还可怕的魔鬼，即便是疯狂本人在我眼前举着傻子的服装，并且我能从它的表情看出它必让我穿上这傻人之服；只要我认为，我对上帝的爱应战胜我心里的一切，它比我世俗的幸福更重要，我就依然能够保住我的灵魂。一个人在最后时刻，依然能够集中全部身心把目光投向那所有美好东西的来源地—天堂，这一瞥是他和他所追寻的人—上帝—都理解的。这凝望意味着他还忠实于他的爱。然后，他会平静地穿上那服装。缺乏这种浪漫主义的人已经出卖了他的灵魂，不管他是用它换了一个王国还是微不足道的一点银子。但是我靠自己的力量不能够得到哪怕是一丁点儿属于有限性的东西，因为我总是不停地在费力放弃一切。我靠自己的力量能够放弃那位公主，我绝不会因此抱怨或闷闷不乐，我会在痛苦中找到快乐、平和与安静。但是我却不能靠自己的力量重新得到她，因为我正好用尽了所有的力量来放弃对她的追求。但是，通过信仰，那位令人赞叹的骑士说，通过信仰，你会靠荒诞之力得到她。

唉，这种运动是我作不了的！只要我一开始作这运动，一切就会逆转，我就会逃回到弃绝的痛苦中。在生活中我会游泳，但我太重了，做不了这神秘的漂浮。以这样一种方式存在，即我对存在的反作用力每时每刻都表现为最美丽最安全的和谐，我做不到。然而，能得到公主一定是荣耀的，我每时每刻都这样说，而那个不这样说的弃绝骑士是个骗子，他不是只有一个愿望，他没有通过痛苦使这个愿望常青。有些人可能觉得没有了这个愿望，刺痛变迟钝会很舒服很方便，但这样的人绝不是骑士。一个有生来自由灵魂的人若发现自己如此，会鄙视自己的，而且绝不会允许自己的灵魂受到欺骗。不过，得到公主一定是很美好的，不过，只有信仰骑士才是快乐的，才是有限世界的继承者，而那弃绝骑士则是个陌生人和外来人。这样，要以这种方式得到公主，要日日夜夜在她的陪伴下生活在幸福快乐中（当然，我们得让弃绝骑士也可能得到公主，即便他已清楚地意识到他们未来幸福的不可能性）；这样，要以这种方式靠荒诞之力每时每刻快乐幸福地生活着，每时每刻都看到利剑高悬于挚爱的人的头顶，同时感到的不是弃绝痛苦中的宁静，却是靠荒诞得来的快乐，那是很美妙的。做到这一点的人，是伟大的，而且是唯一伟大的人，想到这一点，我就很激动，我对伟大的崇拜之情从来都是毫不吝啬、慷慨激昂的。

那么，如果我这一代人中每个坚持信仰的人都是真正了解了生活的恐怖，领会了道勃所说的话（一个在暴风雨之夜独自手持上膛的枪在弹药库边站岗的士兵会有奇怪的想法）的意思的人；如果所有不愿在信仰上止步的人都是有这样的灵魂之力，能够理解并留出时间独自思考他们所希望的是不可能的这一思想的人；如果所有坚持信仰的人都是已经在痛苦中调和平复了自我并已适应痛苦的人；如果每个不愿在信仰上止步的人下一步（要是他们没有做到上述几步，那么他们也就不必在信仰上自寻麻烦了）会实现奇迹，靠荒诞之力理解全部存在的人，那么，我正在写的话，就是一个最渺小卑微、只能作弃绝运动的成员，对同代人所说的最崇高的赞颂。但是为什么他们不愿止步于信仰，为什么我们却又有时会听说人们羞于承认自己有信仰呢？这是我所不能理解的。如果我能设法作到这项运动的话，自那以后我会驾着四轮马车奋力前行的。

情况真是这样吗？我在生活中所看到的所有资产阶级庸俗之气，那些我用自己的行为，而不是言语去谴责的种种风气，真的不是他们表面上所显示的那样吗？它真的是那奇迹吗？这当然是可以想象得到的，因为我们的信仰英雄的确和它惊人地相似，我们的信仰英雄并非讽刺者或幽默家，而是具有某种高得多的品质的人。我们这个时代大量地讨论讽刺和幽默，尤其是那些在此方面从未成功却知道如何解释一切的人爱谈论它们。我对讽刺和幽默这两种爱好并非完全不懂，还略多于我对德语和德国-丹麦的概略了解。因此我知道这两种爱好从本质上与信仰的激情不同。讽刺和幽默是反映自身性的，因而属于无限的弃绝范畴，其灵活性应归结于个人与现实的不可比较性。

最后一项运动，信仰的悖谬运动，不管它是义务还是别的什么，是我做不到的，尽管实际上我极想做到。一个人是否有权作出这样的断言必须取决于他自己；他是否能够在这方面达成心平气和的妥协一致，这是他和永生者，即人们信仰的对象，上帝，之间的问题。不过，每个人都能作的是无限弃绝运动，对任何认为自己做不到的人，我个人会毫不犹豫地称其为懦夫。而信仰就是另一回事了。但是，任何人都没有权利使别人以为信仰是什么卑下或容易的事，而实际上它是世上最伟大，最困难的事。

有些人以另一种方式理解亚伯拉罕的故事。他们赞美上帝的仁慈，因为他再次把以撒给了亚伯拉罕，整件事只是个考验而已。考验，这个词可以意味着很多的东西，也可以意味着很少东西，但是整件事在讲述中却是说时迟那时快，很快就结束了。在讲述的故事中，人们骑上了插翅的飞马，在同一瞬间人们就到了摩利亚山，在同一瞬间人们就看到了那公羊。人们忘记了亚伯拉罕骑的是一头毛驴，那毛驴只能慢悠悠地走着，忘了他经历了三天的路程，忘了他需要时间来砍些木柴，捆缚以撒，还要把刀子磨锋利。

然而人们还是歌颂亚伯拉罕！那演讲者完全可以在宣讲前十五分钟还在睡觉，那听众不妨在整个宣讲过程中睡觉，因为一切都进行得很顺利，演讲者和听讲者都没有什么麻烦。假如某个在场的人无法入睡，很难受，他可能会回家，在一个角落坐下，然后想：“整件事瞬间就结束了，如果你等一分钟，你就会看到那公羊，然后考验就结束了。”倘若那演讲者在这种情况下遇见他，我想，他会庄严地走向他，对他说：“可怜的人啊，你竟让自己的灵魂沉沦于这样的愚蠢！不会发生什么奇迹，整个人生就是一场考验。”他说得越是热情洋溢，就越激烈，也就对自己愈发满意，他注意到自己在谈论亚伯拉罕时没有血脉偾张涨红了脸，而此时却能感到额头上青筋直冒。当那被他说教的罪人平静而又有尊严地说“但那就是你上周日所讲的啊”时，也许他会张口结舌，目瞪口呆。

那么，让我们要么完全忘掉亚伯拉罕，要么就学会应对我们在想到亚伯拉罕生活的重要意义—那怪异荒谬的悖论—时所感到的恐怖惊慌吧，这样我们就可能明白，像其他时代一样，我们这个时代，如果有信仰，是值得高兴的。如果亚伯拉罕不是虚无、幽灵，或人们用来消磨时间的浮夸炫耀的言谈，那么那个罪人想要效仿他就绝对没有错，问题的关键在于要认识到亚伯拉罕的行为的伟大，以便他可以判断自己是否有经受这样考验的意愿和勇气。那个演讲者行为中滑稽可笑的自我矛盾之处是他一方面自己使亚伯拉罕显得无关紧要，另一方面他又禁止别人这样做。

那么，我们是否不应该敢于谈论亚伯拉罕？我想不是的，我们应该敢于这样做。假如我自己要谈论亚伯拉罕的话，我首先要描述那考验的痛苦，为了达到此目的，我会像蚂蟥一样，吸尽亚伯拉罕作为父亲所承受的痛苦中的所有惧怕、悲痛和折磨，以便能描写出他尽管饱受痛苦依然还坚持信仰。我会提醒人们那旅途持续了三天半；是的，那三天半肯定比我与亚伯拉罕相隔的两千年还要长。接下来我还会提醒他们的是，我认为，每个人都可以在开始做这样的事之前改变主意，在任何时刻都可以退缩返回。如果有人做此事的话，我不认为有危险，也不担心在人们身上激发起想要经受亚伯拉罕所经受的那样的考验的欲望。但是，如果有人想推销亚伯拉罕故事的廉价版本，接着又严禁人们去做亚伯拉罕所做的事，那就真是可笑之极。

为了领悟信仰是多么怪异惊人的一种悖论，是一种可以使谋杀变成神圣的令上帝满意的行为的悖论，是一种把以撒又还给亚伯拉罕的悖论，是一种没有人能理解的悖论，因为信仰正是从思维停止的地方开始，我现在打算提炼出亚伯拉罕故事中内在的辩证因素，并将其以问题的形式描述出来。

问题一　可以从目的论的角度暂时停用伦理吗？

伦理就其本身而论是具有普遍性的，作为普遍性的东西它适用于每个人，从另一个角度而言，也可以说，它在所有时刻都适用。它是自身内在固有的，没有任何外在的东西是它的目的，而它本身则是它以外所有东西的目的，以上所述的就是伦理所包含的所有内容了。每个直接被视为具有身体的和精神的两方面生命的个人，是有普遍性的目的的。每个人的伦理任务就是在其中不断地表达自我，消除自己的个别性以变成具有普遍性的人。一旦个人想要坚持自己的独特个性，直接与普遍性作对，他就是犯罪了，而只有认识到这一点，他才能重新与普遍性达成和谐一致。在具有普遍性之后，每当单个个体有坚持自己的个体性的冲动时，他就处于诱惑中，他只有通过忏悔地把他的个体性上交给普遍性才能把自己从诱惑中解救出来。如果这就是我们对一个人和他的存在所能说的最高层次的东西，那么伦理和一个人的永恒幸福，是完全相同的。一个人的永恒幸福也就是他所有时刻的永恒的目的。那样的话，说一个人放弃那个目的（也就是说，从目的论意义上暂停那个目的）就是自相矛盾的，既然一个人暂停那个目的就意味着丧失它，而其实，这个意义上所说的被暂停的东西并不是丧失了，而是被保存在某种更高的东西里，后者正好是它的目的。

如果是这样的话，那么黑格尔在他写的“善与良心”中所说的就是对的。他在其中讨论的是，人仅仅被看作单一的个体，他认为这种界定是“恶的道德形式”，是应该在道德目的论中被废除掉的，这样，停留在此阶段的个人不是处于罪孽中，就是处于诱惑中。然而，黑格尔谈论信仰时却犯了个错误，他错在当亚伯拉罕应该被传到低等法庭判定为谋杀者时，他没有大声清楚地抗议亚伯拉罕作为信仰之父所享受的荣耀。

因为信仰就是这样的悖论，它意味着个体性比普遍性要高一等。不过，要注意，是以这样的方式高于普遍性，即，信仰运动是自我重复的，结果是，个体在具有普遍性后，把自己作为凌驾于普遍性之上的个体分离开来。如果这不是信仰，那么我们就丧失了亚伯拉罕，而且，正因为信仰一直存在于这世上，就意味着信仰从未在这世上存在过。因为如果伦理的东西（也就是道德的东西）是最高的，人身上剩下的除了邪恶意义上的东西（即必须用普遍性表现的个体性）以外没有什么不可比较的了，那么，除了那些希腊哲学家所界定的范畴或任何可以从那些希腊人的范畴里演绎出的范畴以外，我们就不需要什么其他的范畴了。这一事实是黑格尔本不应该隐瞒的，因为他毕竟是研究过希腊哲学的。

人们常听那些不作研究只专注于陈词滥调的人说，基督教世界阳光闪耀，而异教徒的世界则是黑暗笼罩的。这种说法总让我觉得奇怪，因为任何有适度深刻思想的人，任何足够认真的艺术家都依然希望在希腊思想的永恒青春中恢复青春活力。他们这样说的原因可能是他们不知道说什么，只知道他们得说点什么。说异教徒没有信仰没有什么错，但若这样说要想有什么意义的话，说的人一定要把他所说的信仰是什么意思，解释得更清楚点，否则的话，他也将落入陈腔滥调的俗套之中。在不了解信仰是什么概念的情况下去解释一切存在，包括信仰，是很容易的，而且，作了此类解释还指望别人钦佩的人也不算是作了最糟糕的估计，[5]因为正如布瓦洛所言：“傻瓜总能找到更大的傻瓜来钦佩自己。”

信仰就是这样的悖论，它意味着个人作为个体性高于普遍性，比后者更合乎情理，它不是从属于后者而是高于后者。不过，要注意，是以这样一种方式，那个曾经作为个人从属于普遍性的独特个体，现在借助普遍性变成了与绝对处于一种绝对的关系中的作为个体的个人，因而成了高于普遍性的个体。这种精神态度是不可调解或改变的，因为所有调解都恰恰需要借助普遍性来完成；它是而且永远将是一个悖论，靠思想无法理解的悖论。然而信仰就是这样的悖论，要不然（我想请读者永远记住这些推理启示，尽管我自己每次把它们讲清楚都很复杂很冗长）—要不然，正因为信仰一直存在于这世上，就意味着信仰从未在这世上存在过。而换言之，我们也就丧失了亚伯拉罕。

某些个人确实容易把这个悖论与诱惑混淆起来。但是人们不应因此对这一点保持隐晦。很多人也确实对悖论有种自然的排斥厌恶，但那绝不能成为他们把信仰变成别的东西以便自己也可以拥有信仰的理由。而那些的确拥有信仰的人应该准备提供某些区别悖论和诱惑的标准。

亚伯拉罕的故事里包含了这样一个目的论意义上的对伦理的暂时中止。我们从不缺乏为这个故事找类比的敏锐的知识分子和高级学者。他们找这些类比的智慧都源于同一个很好的原理，那就是，基本上一切都是一样的。如果人们研究得更仔细一点儿，我很怀疑，除了后来那个说明不了什么的类比，他们是否能在全世界找到一个真正的类比。因为事实一直是这样：亚伯拉罕代表了信仰，信仰在他身上得到合适的表达，因为他的生活不仅是人们能想象得到的最为矛盾荒谬的，而且悖谬得简直不可思议。他靠荒谬怪诞行事，因为他作为个体却高于普遍性的东西，这就是荒诞。这个悖论是不能调整改变的，因为他一旦开始这样做，他就得承认他处于受诱惑的状态中，这样的话，他就永远不会走到牺牲以撒的那一步，或者，假如他献祭了以撒，他一定会愧疚地返回普遍性。他是靠荒诞重新得到以撒的，因此亚伯拉罕绝不是悲剧性的英雄，而是不同的一种人，他要么是个谋杀者，要么是一个坚持信仰的人。亚伯拉罕身上缺的就是那可以拯救悲剧英雄的中间特质。这就是为什么我可以理解一个悲剧英雄，却无法理解亚伯拉罕，尽管在某种疯狂的意义上我对他的钦佩超越了对所有其他人的钦佩。

亚伯拉罕和以撒的关系，从伦理的角度讲，可以这样简单描述：父亲对儿子的爱超过对自己的爱。然而，伦理在自己的范畴里有几个不同的层次。让我们看看在亚伯拉罕的故事里能不能找到对伦理的更好、更高层次的表达，这样就可以从伦理上解释他的行为，从伦理上为他中止对儿子伦理上的义务作辩护，而同时又不因此逾越伦理自己的目的论范畴。

当一件关乎整个国家的大业受到阻碍时，当该国家大业因为上天的不悦而被中止时，当愤怒的天神用平静来嘲笑一切努力时，当算命者严肃地完成任务，悲哀地宣告神灵要求一个年轻姑娘做祭品时，那么父亲就得英雄般地献祭自己的女儿。他会高尚大度地隐藏起痛苦，尽管他可能希望自己是个“敢于哭泣的低下的人”，而不是那行事举止都必须有庄严国王风范的国王。尽管他心中有抑制不住的孤独的苦痛，而且他在他的子民中只有三个心腹知己，但很快全国人民都会知道他的痛苦、他的英勇行为，知道他为了全民的福祉，献出了那个女孩，他的女儿，他那可爱的还是少女的女儿这一事实。啊，她有多么迷人的胸脯，多么美丽的脸庞，多么漂亮的金发！女儿会用眼泪打动父亲，而父亲会转过脸去不看她，这英雄的父亲会举起刀子。当此消息传到老家，所有希腊的美丽少女都会激动得涨红了脸；而假如那女儿已订婚，她的爱人不会生气，反而会为参与分担了父亲的行为而感到自豪，因为那少女从情感上是属于他和她父亲的，但对他而言这感情更温柔珍贵。

当那在紧急时刻拯救以色列的勇敢士师耶弗他用同一个誓言把自己和上帝连在一起时，那么，他就要英雄般地把那少女的欢欣，他所挚爱的女儿的欢乐，变成悲伤，而所有以色列人将会和她一起为她的少女年华悲叹。但是所有生来自由的男人都会理解耶弗他，所有刚毅的女人都会钦佩他，而所有的以色列少女都会想要像他的女儿一样去献身；因为如果耶弗他立下誓言而又不守诺的话，他凯旋又有什么意义？难道这胜利不会被再次从人民那里夺走？

当一个儿子忘了他的职责时，当国家把正义之剑交托给那父亲时，当法律要求父亲出手惩罚罪人时，那么父亲就必须英勇地忘记有罪之人是自己的儿子。他会高尚大度地隐藏自己的痛苦，但是全国所有的人，包括那有罪的儿子，都因此而钦佩这位父亲。每次罗马法被阐释的时候，人们会记起，很多人把它解释得更学术更精深，但谁也没有布鲁托斯用英勇行为阐释得更光荣。

然而，要是阿伽门农是在他的舰队顺风全速驶向目的地时已派遣了去接依菲琴尼亚来献祭的信使；要是耶弗他在没有受制于任何决定他的民族命运的诺言的情况下，对自己的女儿说：“从现在起为你的短暂青春哭泣两个月吧，之后我会把你献祭给上帝”；要是布鲁托斯有一个正直的儿子，他还依然传唤执法吏将儿子执行死刑，谁会理解他们呢？如果这三人在回答你为什么这样做这个问题时，都说“这是一场考验，我们在经受考验”，那么会有人因此对他们理解得更好些吗？

在那关键时刻，当阿伽门农、耶弗他和布鲁托斯英勇地克服了痛苦，勇敢地放弃了挚爱之人，只好作出那外在的牺牲时，世上绝不会有哪个灵魂高尚的人不为他们的痛苦流下同情的泪水，绝不会有哪个灵魂高尚的人不为他们的壮举流下感佩的泪水。但是，如果在那关键时刻，这三个人为他们那借以忍受痛苦的英雄之气加上“它是绝不会发生的”这几个字的话，那么谁会理解他们呢？如果他们又解释性地说“我们靠荒诞相信此事不会发生”，谁会因此对他们理解得更好些呢？因为谁会很难理解它是荒诞的呢？但是，谁会理解一个人能因此相信它呢？

悲剧英雄和亚伯拉罕之间的区别是很明显的。悲剧英雄仍处于伦理的范围之内。他使某一伦理的表达在更高层次的伦理表达中找到其目的；他把父子或父女之间的伦理关系降低成一种和道德观念之间有辩证关系的感情。那么，这里就不可能有从目的论角度上暂时中止伦理本身这样的问题。

亚伯拉罕的情况是不同的。他的行为完全跳出了伦理的范围，而有了伦理之外更高的目的，为此目的他暂时中止了伦理。我们怎样才能把亚伯拉罕的行为与普遍性联系起来呢？除了发现亚伯拉罕的行为逾越了普遍性之外，我们如何找到二者之间任何其他的关联点呢？亚伯拉罕做的事不是为了拯救一个国家，不是为了支持国家的意图，也不是为了平息天神的愤怒。要是有天神愤怒这个可能，那他也只可能是对亚伯拉罕感到愤怒，而且，亚伯拉罕的整个行为与普遍性完全无关，它纯粹是个人的艰巨行为。因此，尽管悲剧英雄凭借体现道德规范的行为而伟大，亚伯拉罕则纯粹是因为个人优点而伟大。在亚伯拉罕的生活中，除了父亲应该爱儿子，没有比这更高的伦理体现了。在这里，道德生活意义上的伦理是完全不可能的。就普遍性的体现程度而言，它的确潜伏在以撒身上，隐藏在以撒心里，因此它必须借助以撒的嘴喊出来：“别这样做，你在毁灭一切。”

那么亚伯拉罕为什么要这样做呢？为了上帝，也为了他自己，这两个目的是完全一样的。他为了上帝这样做，是因为上帝要求他证明他的信仰；他为了自己这样做以便能提供信仰的证据。两者的统一可以用人们常用来描述此关系的话很好地表达出来：它是一个考验，一种诱惑。但这一种诱惑是什么意思呢？我们通常所说的诱惑是某种阻止人履行义务的东西，但这里的诱惑是那会阻止亚伯拉罕执行上帝意志的伦理本身。那么，义务又是什么呢？义务恰恰是上帝意志的表现。

在这里，我们发现为了理解亚伯拉罕，需要一个新的范畴。这种与神的关系是异教徒所不知道的。悲剧英雄不会和上帝建立私人的关系，但对他而言，伦理就是神圣者，因此这里的悖论可以在普遍性中得到调解。

亚伯拉罕的悖论则是不能调解的，这句话也可以这样说，他不能谈论这悖论。因为只要我一说话，我就会表达出普遍性，当我不这样做的时候，就没有人能理解我。因此亚伯拉罕一旦用普遍性表达自己，他就得说他的处境是一种考验，因为对于凌驾于他所违反的普遍性之上的普遍性，他没有更高层次的表达了。

因此，尽管亚伯拉罕使我钦佩，他也使我感到惊骇。为了义务而否定自我、牺牲自我的人通常会为了抓住无限而放弃有限；这样的人足够自信。悲剧英雄放弃了确定的东西是为了获得更确定的东西，旁观者会自信地看着他。但是，那放弃普遍性去获得某种更高层次的但没有普遍性的东西的人，他在做什么呢？有没有可能它远非一场考验？如果它不是一场考验，但那个人弄错了，以为它是考验，那有什么可以拯救他？他承受了悲剧英雄所受的所有苦痛，毁了他世上所有的欢乐，抛弃了一切，也许同时他还禁止自己享受那崇高的欢乐，而这种珍贵的欢乐是他愿意付出任何代价去获得的。旁观者根本不能理解他，也不会自信地注视着他。也许那信徒打算做的事是不可能实现的，毕竟那是难以想象的。或者，如果那件事是可能的，但那个人误解了天神，那么，什么可以拯救他？那悲剧英雄，他需要眼泪，他也获得了眼泪；是的，那干枯的已经不能为阿伽门农哭泣的羡慕的眼睛在哪儿呢？那灵魂如此迷惑以至于竟敢为亚伯拉罕流泪的人在哪儿呢？悲剧英雄在时间里的某个确定时刻完成了他的伟绩，但是随着时间的推移，他还获得了某种同样重要的东西：他拜访满心悲伤的人，那人因叹息抽泣而喘不上气来，思绪悲伤泪流不止；他出现在他面前，解开了他悲伤的心结，松开了他的紧身外套，他使这个痛苦之人在他这个悲剧英雄的痛苦中忘了自己的痛苦，哄得他流出热泪。但是没有人能为亚伯拉罕哭泣。人们接近他时总是带着神圣的恐惧，就像以色列人走近西奈山时的感受一样。那么，要是那位在矗立于奥立士平原的高耸入云的摩利亚山爬行的孤独的老人，不是一个在深渊上步履稳健的梦游者，而山脚下有人看到他在那儿，担心得发抖，但出于尊敬与恐惧，甚至连对他喊叫也不敢—要是他被分心怎么办，要是他已犯了错误怎么办？—谢谢！再次感谢那向被生活苦痛折磨得已经无力保护自我、赤身露体的人伸出援助之手的人，他为他从言语上提供了遮羞叶来遮蔽他的不幸。也谢谢你，伟大的莎士比亚！你能表现一切，一切你都可以描述得无比精确，可是，为什么你从未表达这种痛苦？也许是因为你把它留给了自己，就像一个人不能忍受世人提起自己至爱之人的名字一样。因为诗人以一个他自己不能说的小秘密为代价购买了语言的力量，用来讲述别人的所有可怕秘密。诗人不是使徒，他只能靠魔鬼的力量来驱赶魔鬼。

但现在，当出于目的论的原因伦理被中止了，那个中止伦理的人如何存在呢？他是作为与普遍性相对立的个体而存在着。那么这意味着他是有罪吗？因为从罪的概念上讲，这就是罪的形式。同样道理，一个孩子意识不到自己的存在所以没有罪这一事实本身并不意味着，从概念上讲，它的存在是没有罪的，或者说，这一事实并不意味着伦理不对这孩子在所有时刻有伦理要求。如果人们否认这种形式能以非罪的方式（在成人身上）不断重复，那么就相当于已经对亚伯拉罕作出了定罪的评判。那么，亚伯拉罕是怎样存在的呢？他靠坚持信仰存在。这就是那个悖论。这一悖论使他身处绝境而又无法向别人解释清楚。这个悖论就是，他把自己作为个体置于与绝对者的绝对关系中。但是，他这样做合理吗？他的理由还是那个悖论；因为，如果他就是那悖论，他凭借的不是做某种具有普遍性的人，而是做具有个体性的人。

那么，个体如何确保自己的作为是合乎情理的？要把个体的整个存在调整到与国家或社会的思想观念相一致是一件相当容易的事情。如果一个人这样做了，他无疑很容易调解改变。那样的话，他就根本不会遇到那个悖论，即个人的个体性比普遍性更高这一悖论，我也可以用毕达哥拉斯的一个论点来适当地描述这一悖论，即奇数比偶数更完美。如果在我们这个时代有人碰巧听到了关于那个悖论的回答，它一定是这样说的：“那要以结果来评判。”一个英雄，在已经变成了同辈人进行流言蜚语的丑闻对象后，在意识到自己是一个无人能理解的悖论后，无畏地对着他的同代人大喊：“未来会证明我是正确的！”这样的呐喊现如今不常听到了，因为我们这个时代的缺点是产生不了英雄，这个时代的优势就是几乎产生不了多少讽刺漫画。在我们这个时代，无论何时我们听到“这要根据结果来判断”这句话，我们都可以立即知道我们有幸和谁在谈话。这样说话的一族成员众多，如果要给他们起一个共同的名字，我会叫他们“讲师”。他们活在自己的思想里，生活安稳无忧，他们在井然有序的国家里有稳固的职位和可靠的前程；他们和生存的动荡之间隔着千百年的距离，他们不害怕像动乱之类的事情会再次发生；因为警方和报刊会对此说什么呢？他们毕生的工作就是判断伟大之人，根据结果来评判伟人。这种对伟大的评判行为泄露出一种傲慢与可怜相混合的奇怪样子。傲慢是因为他们认为自己有下判决的使命，可怜是因为他们觉得自己的生活和伟人的生活一丁点儿都不相关。毫无疑问，任何头脑哪怕稍具一点儿高等思维的人在走近伟大之人时，都不会变得完全像湿冷的软体动物那样，看不到这样一个事实，即自从创世纪以来，结果通常就是最后出现，而且一个人要真想从伟人那儿学到点儿什么，他恰恰必须注意那开端。如果任何行将评判伟人的人应该要根据结果评判自己，他是绝不会开始评判这一行动的。即便结果可能会使全世界欢呼雀跃，那对英雄也没什么用；因为他是只有在整件事情结束之后才能知道结果的，他不是靠事情的结果而是靠事情的开端才成为英雄的。

更进一步来说，无论如何，结果（就其作为对无限性问题的有限性回答而言）在辩证方面，和英雄的存在是完全不相容、不一致的。否则，用亚伯拉罕通过奇迹重新得到以撒这一事实来证明他采取与普遍性相对的个体性立场是合理的，这可以吗？假如亚伯拉罕真的把以撒献祭了，那是否会意味着他那样做就不那么合理了呢？

但是，是结果激起了我们的好奇心，这就像一本书的结尾令人好奇一样；我们不想知道其中的任何恐惧、不安和矛盾。我们和结果进行一种在美学意义上的调情，结果就像彩票中奖一样来得既不可预料，又轻而易举；我们在得知结果后，感觉受到启迪。然而，连因抢劫寺庙而带着锁链做苦力的强盗也不如这样掠夺圣人的罪犯卑劣低下，甚至连为了三十块银子而出卖其主人的犹大也没有比这样出售伟大的人更为可鄙。

以无人性的方式讨论伟大，使伟大在遥远的距离里褪色成模糊的轮廓，或者是描绘伟大却没有突出其里面的人性成分，从而使伟大不再是伟大，是违背我的精神的。因为使我伟大的不是在我身上发生了什么事，而是我所做的事。而且没有人会认为一个人变得伟大是因为他中了彩票大奖。即便是一个出身卑微的人，我也会要求他不要对自己如此残忍，以致他只敢远远地想象国王的城堡，模糊地憧憬着它的宏伟，想要抬高它的同时又想要通过很卑鄙的方式抬高它而毁了它。我还会要求他在国王的城堡那儿也要有尊严有自信地走近它。他不应该如此残暴以致想要通过从街上直接冲进国王的城堡而无礼地冒犯所有人。他那样做会比国王损失得还多；相反，他应该在带着快乐自信的热情去遵守每个礼节中找到愉悦的感觉，这正好可以使他光明正大。当然，这只是个类比，因为这里提及的区别只是对精神距离的一种很不完美的描述。我请每个人都不要如此不人道地妄自菲薄，以致不敢涉足那些宫殿，在那些地方居住的不仅是对那些被拣选之人的记忆，还有被拣选之人他们自己。他不应该无礼地挤上前去并把和他们的亲属关系强加到他们身上。他应该每次在他们面前鞠躬都感到高兴，但也要表现得坦率自信，并总是表现得要比清洁女工重要，因为如果他自己不想要那样表现，他就永远也进不去那儿。能帮助他的正是伟大之人被考验时所经受的恐惧悲伤。否则的话，如果他身上还有一点点骨气和热血，他们就只会使他产生合理的羡慕。而且任何只有在远距离看时才伟大的东西，任何人们想要用空洞的语言来提升的东西，都会自己化为乌有。

在这世上，有没有人曾经像那位蒙福的妇女—上帝之母—圣母玛利亚一样伟大呢？然而，我们如何谈论她呢？如果我们说她备受喜爱青睐，这并不会使她伟大，而且要是倾听者和说话者一样不从人性角度思考问题这事不算奇怪的话，那么，每个年轻姑娘肯定都会问，为什么我没有备受喜爱恩宠？即便我没有什么别的话可说，我也绝不会把此问题看作愚蠢的问题而置之不理，因为就偏爱而言，从抽象意义上考虑，每个人都对此有同等的权利。她们忽略的是悲伤、恐惧和悖论。我的思想和一般人的一样纯粹，任何能够以这种方式思考的人的思想必然也会纯粹；不然的话，可怕的事情就要到来。因为一个人一旦有过这些想象，他就再也不能摆脱它们了，而且如果他违背这些想象，与它们对抗，它们就会用安静的愤怒对他进行报复，而这是比凶狠的评论家喧嚣的抨击还要可怕的。玛利亚确实是奇迹般地生下了那个孩子，但这是发生“在月经之后”，而这是个充满恐惧、悲痛和矛盾的时间。无疑，那天使是个起到辅助作用的神灵，但是他可不是个乐于助人体贴的神，他没有四处奔走去跟以色列的其他少女说：“不要鄙视玛利亚，她身上正在发生着特别的事情。”那天使只是来到玛利亚身边，而又无人能够理解她。有哪个妇女遭受过更大的羞辱轻蔑呢？难道不是这样吗？上帝总是在庇佑一个人的同时又诅咒他。这就是那个神灵对玛利亚的解释。对我而言，说圣母玛利亚绝不是个衣着华丽闲坐着和圣子玩耍的好夫人是令我不愉快的，而人们草率不负责任地这样解读她，就更令我生气了。不过，当她说“我是主的使女”时，她是伟大的。我认为要解释她为什么成了圣母是不难的。她不需要世俗的崇敬，正如亚伯拉罕不需要我们的眼泪一样，因为她不是女英雄，而他也并非英雄，但他们都变成了比英雄更伟大的人。不过，他们不是靠解除了不幸、痛苦和矛盾，而正是因为有了它们而变得更伟大。

当诗人把英雄呈现给众人以供崇拜时，敢于说“为他哭泣吧，他配得上眼泪”，这的确是伟大的；而配得上那配流泪的人的眼泪也是伟大的。诗人敢控制众人，敢训斥人们去检查自己是否配得上为英雄流泪，因为弱者啜泣时不值钱的泪水是对神圣英雄的贬低侮辱，他这样做也是伟大的。但是比这些更伟大的是，信仰骑士甚至敢于对要为他洒泪的高尚之人说：“不要为我哭泣，但要为你自己哭泣。”

我们感动了，渴望回到那些美丽的时代，这甜美温柔的渴望引领我们往想要的目标前进，去看基督在应许之地漫步。我们忘记了恐惧、苦难和悖论，可是，不会弄错是如此容易的事吗？想到这个行走于众人之间的人就是上帝，这不可怕吗？坐下和他一同就餐这不恐怖吗？成为使徒是如此容易的吗？但是，那结果，一千八百年，那是一种帮助。那一千八百年帮助了那种自欺欺人的可鄙欺骗。我没有勇敢到愿意生活在发生这样的事件的时代，但因此我不会严厉地评判当时那些弄错的人，也不会鄙夷那些明白了真相的人。

但现在，我要回到亚伯拉罕。在结果出来之前的那段时间里，要么亚伯拉罕每时每刻都被视为谋杀者，要么我们面对一个高于一切调解的悖论。

因此，亚伯拉罕的故事包含了一种从目的论意义上对伦理的暂停。作为个体，他成了高于普遍性的人。这就是一个悖论，一个不可能被调解的矛盾。他如何进入这个悖论和他如何停留在这个悖论之中是一样的无法说明，令人费解。如果亚伯拉罕的处境不是这样的，那么他就连悲剧英雄都不是，而是一个谋杀者。那样的话，想要继续称他为信仰之父，想要跟那些只关注言语的人谈论此事，就是欠考虑的。一个人可以凭自己的力量成为悲剧英雄，却不能成为信仰骑士。当一个人踏上了那成为悲剧英雄的无可否认的艰苦之路，有很多人可以给他提供忠告，但走上信仰那狭窄道路的人却没有人能够给出建议，没有人理解。信仰是个奇迹，但没有人是被排除在信仰之外的，人人都可以拥有信仰；因为将人的一切统一成一体的是激情，[6]而信仰就是激情。

问题二　对上帝有一种绝对的义务吗？

伦理是普遍性的，其本身又是神圣的。因此，从根本上讲，每种义务都是对上帝的义务，这样说是正确的。但是，如果人们就此只能说这些，那么就相当于同时也说了我实际上对上帝没有义务。这种义务通过谈及上帝才成为对上帝的义务，但我并不是在义务本身中和上帝建立关系。因而，爱自己的邻居是一种义务；它之所以是义务是因为涉及上帝，但在履行此义务时，我进入的并不是和上帝的关系，而是和我爱的邻居的关系。如果基于这个关联，我就说爱上帝是我的义务，那我说的实际上只是无谓的同义反复，这种说法是就把上帝从完全抽象意义上理解为一种神圣存在—即普遍性，也是义务—而论的。那样的话，人的整个存在就是完全自我闭合的球体，而伦理则立即成了它的界线和内容。上帝就变成了一个无形的消没的点，一种无力的思想，但上帝的力量只是存在于伦理中，而伦理即存在的内容。所以，如果某个人想到要从上述以外的任何其他意义上爱上帝的话，那他就只是在玩奢侈，就是在爱一个幻影，如果那幻影有力量说话，它会对他说：“留在你属于的地方，我没有要求你的爱。”如果某个人想到要以别的方式爱上帝的话，这种爱会受怀疑，就像卢梭提到那些爱异教徒卡菲尔人而不爱自己邻居的人时所说的那样。

假设以上解释是正确的，假设在人类生活中没有无从比较性，而任何显现出来的不可通约的东西都是找不出结论的某种偶然，那么，就以这种思想来看存在而论，黑格尔就是对的。但是，黑格尔在谈论信仰和论及允许亚伯拉罕被视为信仰之父时却是错误的。因为在后者中，他对亚伯拉罕和信仰都作了评判。根据黑格尔哲学，外在高于内在。有一个例子常被用来阐释这一点。在这个例子中，小孩是内在的，成人是外在的；这就是为什么小孩是由外在的东西决定的，而成人，作为外在性的存在，相反，则恰恰是由内在的东西所决定的。信仰，正相反，是一种矛盾，在信仰这种悖论中，内在性要高于外在性，或者，用我们前面所用过的一个说法来说，奇数要比偶数好。

那么，在这种生活的伦理观中，一个个体的任务就是要迫使自己放弃内在的决定因素，并且把这些内在决定因素以外在的方式表现出来。每当他对此畏缩不前，每当他想坚持留在或重新退回到感情、情绪等内在性因素的领地时，他就犯了罪，他就处于一种考验中。信仰的悖论就在于，有一种与外在性不可比较的内在性，这儿要强调一下，这种内在性和前面提到的（小孩的内在性）不完全相同，是一种新的内在性。这一点不容忽视。现代哲学已经干脆爽快地容许自己用直接性的东西来代替“信仰”。如果我们那样做的话，那么否认信仰一直存在就是荒谬可笑的。那样的话，信仰就与感情、情绪、风格、歇斯底里之类相当简单普通的东西为伍了。哲学做得正确的地方是它说了人不应该止步于那些普通的东西，即人应该追求比情感之类的那些普遍的内在性因素要更高的东西。但是哲学没有理由用那样的话来说信仰。在信仰出现之前进行的是一种无限运动，只有在那之后，信仰才凭借荒诞，（出人意料地）登场了。关于这一点，我不需要借此声称我拥有信仰，也可以理解得很清楚。如果信仰仅仅是哲学所理解的那样，那么苏格拉底自己早已经超越了信仰，并且是超越了很多，而不是相反，即，他没有到达信仰这个高度。从智力方面说，他作了无限运动，他不懂的是无限弃绝。这项任务本身是人类的力量能完成的，尽管当今的人们对此持不屑态度。但只有这项任务被完成，只有人在其中筋疲力尽，排空自己，才可以到达信仰出现的地方。

那么，信仰的悖论就在于，个体是高于普遍性的，用现在很少听到的一个理论上的区别来说，个体依靠自己与绝对者的关系来决定其与普遍性的关系，而不是通过自己与普遍性的关系来决定其与绝对者的关系。也可以这样表述信仰的悖论：有一种对上帝的绝对的义务存在，因为在这种义务关系中，个人把自己作为单一的个体与绝对者绝对地联系起来。当现在的人们说爱上帝是一种义务时，是从一种与上述很不相同的意义上来说的；因为如果这种义务是绝对的，那么伦理就被还原成相对的。不过，由此一点并不能推理出伦理就要被彻底废除。只是伦理有了一种相当不同的表达，一种似非而是的表达，比如，对上帝的爱会引起信仰骑士用相反的方式表达自己对邻居的爱，而用正常的方式爱邻居，从伦理上来说，是他的义务。

如果情况并非如此，信仰在存在中便没了位置；那样的话，信仰就是一种诱惑，而亚伯拉罕也失去伟大的地位了，因为他对它屈服了。

这个悖论不容许有调节的余地：因为它恰恰是建立于个体就只是个个体这个基础之上的。个体一旦想要用普遍性表达他的绝对义务，从普遍性角度上意识到自己的绝对义务，他就会认识到自己处于一场诱惑中（即经受对信仰的考验）。而且，如果他实际上抵制这诱惑，他就不会履行那所谓的绝对义务；而如果他不抵抗它，他就犯了罪，即便他的行为是履行了他的绝对义务。那么，亚伯拉罕应该做什么呢？倘若他想要对某人说：“我爱以撒胜过爱这世上的一切，那就是为什么要献祭他对我是那么的困难。”听者肯定会摇摇头说：“那么你为什么要把他献祭呢？”或者，如果听者是个有感知力的人，也许他甚至可能看透了亚伯拉罕，意识到他正泄露出一种与他的行为非常矛盾的感情。

在亚伯拉罕的故事中，我们看到的正是这样的一个悖论。从伦理上讲，他和以撒的关系是父亲就应该爱儿子。然而，在对上帝的绝对关系对比下，这个伦理关系被还原成了相对的。对“为什么”这个问题，除了说它是一个考验、一个诱惑以外，亚伯拉罕没有答案。而这，如前所述，是两种视角的统一：他这样做是为了上帝，也是为了他自己。在常见用法中，这二者也是互相关联的。例如，当我们看见一个人在做与普遍性不一致的事情时，就会说他几乎不是为了上帝才那样做的，那样说所隐含的意思就是他是为了自己而做的。信仰的悖论已经失去了中间术语，即普遍性。一方面，它体现了极端利己主义（为了自己做这可怕的事）；另一方面，它又是一种对最绝对的献身的表达（为了上帝而做它）。信仰本身是不能被调解成普遍性的东西的，因为那样的话，它就会被毁了。信仰就是这样一种悖论，个人很难使自己被人理解。我们可以想象也许该个人能使另一个处于相同境况的人理解自己。要不是现在的人们想尽办法要混进伟大之列，这样的见解就会是难以想象、无法接受的。一个信仰的骑士根本就帮不了另一个信仰骑士。一个人要么通过承受那悖论而变成信仰骑士，要么他永远不变成信仰骑士。合作关系在这里是无法想象的。要是有任何对牺牲以撒的理念更精确的解释，那这个解释就是，那个要这样做的个体只能给自己的解释。假设一个人可以从一般意义上，精确地解决如何理解献祭以撒这个问题（这无论如何会是个最可笑的自我矛盾，也就是说，一个正好站在普遍性之外的个体，正要作为一个普遍性之外的个体去行动的时候，被带到了普遍性的范畴下），这个人永远也不能通过别人的帮助来确信这个解释是合理的，只有作为个体的他自己才可以做到这一点。所以，即便某个人非常怯懦卑鄙以致想要靠别人承担责任来成为一个信仰骑士，他也绝不会成功；因为只有一个人作为单一的个体，才可以成为骑士，这就是骑士身份的伟大之处。对此，我可以理解得很清楚，虽然我因为缺乏勇气没有达到骑士级别；不过，我同时也深知它的恐怖之处，对此，我理解得就更清楚了。

众所周知，关于对上帝的绝对义务，《路加福音》（14:26）中有一段精彩的教义：“如果任何人到我这里来，若不恨自己的父亲，母亲，妻子，儿女，兄弟，姐妹和自己的生命，就不能做我的信徒。”这是一种冷酷无情的话，谁能听得下去？因此，很少听到这句话。然而，避而不谈这句话，这样的沉默只不过是一种无济于事的逃避。不过，学神学的学生知道，这句话出现在《新约全书》中，而且，在这个那个的注释段落中，他找到了这样的信息：去恨，在这句话和其他文章中，意味着（从弱化的意义上说）爱得少一些，少重视一点，不尊敬，以及不在乎。然而，这些词所出现的上下文似乎并没有证实这种高雅的解释。因为在后面诗节中，讲了这样的一个故事：一个人想盖一座高楼，但他先估计了一下自己的能力，看能否做成这件事，唯恐自己以后成了笑柄。这故事和后面引用的诗节之间的紧密联系似乎恰恰显示了，对这些词人们应该从最恐怖的意义上去理解，以使每个人都审视一下自己盖那座楼的能力。

如果这个虔诚又温和的注释家，这个以为自己可以通过这样减价的方式把基督教偷运进这个世界的人，可以成功地使任何人都相信，从语法上、语言学上以及类比意义上，这就是那段话的意思，那么，我们就希望他这样做的同时也能设法使那同一个人相信，基督教是世界上最可怜的事情之一。因为那段教义，出现在最抒情的段落之一，而且是永恒有效性意识最明显的那段教义，除了有喧哗的言辞之外什么也没有，而那夸张的言辞除了表明人们不应那么和蔼、那么体贴，而应更加冷漠以外，没有任何意义。那教义似乎要告诉我们某种恐怖的事情，结果非但没有带来恐怖，却是胡言乱语，因此它不值得我们支持。

那些言辞是恐怖的，然而我确信，人们可以理解它们，但理解它们的人不一定有勇气去实践它们。但是我们要有足够的勇气承认该教义的存在，承认它的伟大，即便我们自己缺乏勇气去实践它。能这样做的人不会发现自己被排除在外，参与不到后面那个美丽的故事中。因为该故事从某种意义上毕竟对没有勇气开始建造那高楼的人是一种安慰。但我们必须要诚实，不能把缺乏勇气理解成谦逊，因为，其实相反，它是一种骄傲，而信仰的勇气才是唯一谦逊的勇气。

现在，我们不难看出，如果那段话要有意义，就必须逐字逐句地理解。是上帝要求绝对的爱。但是任何人，在要求另一个人的爱的时候，都会认为，这种爱必须靠后者对迄今为止自己所珍视的东西变得冷淡来证明，要求这种爱的人不仅是一个利己主义者，而且是个愚蠢之人，他要求这样一种爱就意味着他的生活就与他所渴望的这种爱紧密相连，而这就相当于同时签下了自己的死刑执行令。举例来说，一个丈夫要求妻子离开她的父母，如果他认为妻子为了他而变成一个冷淡懒惰的女儿等等就是对自己有特殊的爱的证明，那么他就是傻瓜中的傻瓜。要是他有任何爱的概念的话，他会想要发现，她在作为女儿和姐妹对他人的爱是完美的，而他若发现这一点后，也会因此确信他的妻子爱他胜过爱这世上任何其他人。因此可见，一个人身上可能会被认为是利己主义和愚蠢象征的东西，在注释家的帮助下可以把它看作称得上是神的概念的体现。

但是如何恨他们？在这儿，我不作人类爱与恨的区分，这不是因为我多么反对这种区分，这种至少是热烈情绪的区分，而是因为它是利己主义的，而且在这里不合适。不过，如果我把这个问题看作一种悖论，那么我就理解了它，也就是，我会以人们用以理解悖论的方式来理解它。绝对的义务会要求人们做伦理禁止的事情，不过绝不会使信仰骑士停止爱。这一点亚伯拉罕可以证明。他准备献祭以撒的那一刻，他所做的事情的从伦理上表述就是：他恨以撒。但是如果他真的恨以撒，他就可以确定上帝不会向他要以撒；因为亚伯拉罕和该隐不同。他一定全身心地爱着以撒。当上帝索要以撒时，亚伯拉罕一定，如果可能的话，更加爱以撒。而且，只有在这种条件下，他才能献出以撒，因为，的确，正是他的对以撒的爱和对上帝的爱形成矛盾对比，才使他的行为成为一种牺牲。但这个悖论里的不幸和痛苦之处是，从人性的角度讲，他很难使自己被人理解。只有当他的行为和他的感情形成了绝对的矛盾的那一刻，只有那时，他才献祭以撒，他的行为才叫牺牲。但是，他的行为的现实就是他之所以属于普遍性的因素，就那方面而言，他是并且一直是一个谋杀者。

而且，人们对《路加福音》那段话一定要这样理解：信仰骑士对普遍性（也就是伦理）里任何能救自己的东西也没有更高层次的表达方式。因此，倘若教会要求它的一个成员作这样的牺牲，那么我们所能得到的就是一个悲剧英雄。因为教会的概念和国家的概念没有质上的不同，这是就个人可以通过普通媒介理解教会而论，也是就个人如果进入了悖论，就不能领悟教会的概念而言。他也不从悖论境况中跳出来，但他在其中必然会不是找到福音，就是找到诅咒。一个教会英雄在他的行动中表现出普遍性，教会里没有人，即便是他的父母等人，也会理解不了他。但是，他不是信仰骑士，他的回答也和亚伯拉罕的不一样：他不会说那是他正经受的一个诱惑考验。

我们一般会避免引用像上述《路加福音》里那段话那样的文字。因为担心人们会失去约束、随心所欲，害怕个人一旦产生个体就应表现得像个个体这样的想法，最糟糕的事情就会发生。而且，作为一个个体而存在被认为是最简单的事情，人们需要被迫去变成的是普遍性的存在。我既没有这样的担忧，也不同意这样的看法，但是是基于同一个原因的。任何已认识到作为个体来存在是最可怕的事情的人不会害怕说这样也是最伟大的。但是他这样说的时候，他的言辞一定不能给随心所欲的人形成一种陷阱，相反，要有助于那个人成为普遍性的存在，尽管他的话能给伟大留下空间。不敢提及像《路加福音》里那段话那样文字的人也不敢提起亚伯拉罕。认为作为个体而存在是件很容易的事的人暗示了一种很是可疑的间接的自我承认。因为真正有自尊、关注自己灵魂的人会深信，在这整个世界里独自生活在自我监督管制下的人，比闺房少女生活得还要严格和隐僻。当然，可能有些人需要强迫，他们如果放任自流会像桀骜难驯的野兽，这一点无疑是对的。但是一个人恰恰必须通过他知道如何恐惧而战栗地说话这一事实来证明自己不属于那一类人。而且出于对伟大的崇敬，他的确应该说话，以免因害怕不良后果而使这伟大被忘记，当然，如果一个人以一种知道伟大及它的恐怖的方式说话，这最终就不会发生；如果一个人不知道伟大的恐怖之处，他也就不知道它的伟大之处。

接着，让我们更仔细地考虑信仰之悖论里的苦难和恐惧。悲剧英雄为了表达伦理的普遍性而放弃自我；信仰骑士为了成为个体的存在而放弃普遍性。如上所述，一切都取决于人是处于怎样的境况和立场。认为作为个体存在很容易的人肯定永远也不会是信仰骑士，因为流浪者和游民不是有信仰的人。与此相反，信仰骑士明白属于普遍性世界是光荣的。他知道把自己转变成普遍性存在的个体是美丽而善良的，这样的人可以说是重塑了一个整洁优雅的自我版本，尽可能干净无瑕，尽可能易于每个人理解；信仰骑士还知道，当一个人在普遍性中变得易于他自己理解，以便自己理解普遍性，以便每个理解自己的人又反过来通过自己而理解普遍性，并且双方都为在普遍性中获得的安全感而欢庆，这是令人心旷神怡的事情。信仰骑士还知道，一个人生来就有普遍性作为自己的家园，作为他的永久友好居住地，这个家园会在他想逗留的时候立即张开双臂接收他，这是很美好的。但是信仰骑士同时也知道，在更高处有一条孤独的崎岖之路，狭窄而又陡峭；他知道，生来就孤独地存在于普遍性之外，独自行走而碰不见一个旅行者是十分可怕的。他很清楚自己的位置，知道自己和人们的关联。从正常人性角度讲，他是疯子，无法使自己被任何人理解。而其实，说他是“疯子”是最温和的表达。如果他不被人如此看待，他就是个伪君子；他在那条路上爬得越高，他就变成越发可怕的伪君子。

信仰骑士知道，放弃自己而向普遍性屈服投降是激励人的，要这样做需要勇气，而且正是因为这样做是为了普遍性，其中还有一定的安全感。信仰骑士知道，被每个高尚之人理解，而且是以一种旁观者由此也变得高尚的方式被理解，是光荣的。这一点他知道，但感到自己似乎受到约束，他希望这是他被指派的任务。同样，亚伯拉罕一定也时不时地希望他的任务就是以一种符合父亲标准的方式爱以撒，这是所有人都可以理解的爱的方式，是会流芳千古的爱的方式。他一定还希望他的使命就是把以撒献给普遍性，以激励父亲们去效仿辉煌行为。他一定还为下面这样的想法感到恐怖，即对他而言，这样的希望仅仅是诱惑而且必须被当作诱惑对待；因为他明白自己走的是一条孤寂之路，明白自己除了正被考验之外，没有为普遍性做什么。又或者，亚伯拉罕为普遍性做了什么事？让我从人性的角度，真正人性的角度，谈论它！他用了七十年才老来得子。别人很快就得到并享受了很久的快乐，他花了七十年才得到。这是为什么呢？因为他在受检测和考验。那不是疯狂和异常吗？但是亚伯拉罕坚持了信仰，只有撒拉动摇了信仰，让他接受夏甲做妾，但这也是为什么他不得不把她驱走的原因。他后来有了以撒，接着他又要被考验了。他知道表现普遍性是光荣的，和以撒一起生活是美好的。但这不是他的使命。他知道为了普遍性牺牲这样的一个儿子是高贵的行为，他自己会从中找到安宁，而每个人也会在他们对这个行为的称颂中找到寄托，这就像元音依靠辅音一样，但这不是他的使命—他在受考验。那个叫拖延者的罗马著名将军通过拖延战术阻挠了敌人，然而相比之下，亚伯拉罕是怎样的拖延者呢？！而他不是在拯救国家。亚伯拉罕的父亲一百三十岁才生的他啊，这是一百三十年生命的结果，谁能忍受得了这样的拖延？亚伯拉罕的同龄人—如果可以这样称呼他们的话—能不会这样说吗：“亚伯拉罕身上永远有一种拖延在发生；当他终于得到了儿子—那也花费了够长的时间—他却想要把他献祭给上帝。所以他不是疯了吗？要是他至少能解释他为什么要那样做就好了，但是，不，他总是解释说那是个‘考验’？”亚伯拉罕也不能给出进一步的解释，因为他的生活就像是一本被神没收了的书，永远也不会变成公共财产。

这就是亚伯拉罕故事的恐怖之处。任何看不到这一点的人可以确定绝不是信仰骑士。但是的确能看出这一点的人不会否认，与信仰骑士的缓慢爬行似的步伐相比，即便是经受最大考验的悲剧英雄行走时步伐也像舞蹈步伐。看出这一点而又意识到自己没有勇气理解它的人，至少能些许理解到那个信仰骑士所获得的荣耀：那骑士变成了上帝的知己，主的朋友，而且从人类的角度说，他得以称天堂的上帝为“你”，而即便是悲剧英雄也只能用第三人称称呼上帝。

悲剧英雄很快就可以成就，他的斗争也很快就能结束；他作了无限运动，现在在普遍性中获得安全。但是信仰骑士却无法入睡、无法休息，因为他不断地经受着考验，而且他随时都有可能充满忏悔地返回到普遍性中来，这种可能性也可以像真相一样是一种诱惑考验。他无法从任何人那儿得到关于此事的启示，否则他就会处于那悖论之外。

因此，信仰骑士首先要拥有的是把他所违反的整个伦理集中于一个因素的激情；他可以确定自己真的全身心地爱着以撒。[7]如果他做不到这一点，他就处于诱惑的考验中。接下来，他还要有足够的激情能在转瞬之间完整地唤起这种确信，还要使它像第一步里一样有效。如果他做不到，他就不能开始，因为那样的话，他一定会不断地从头开始。悲剧英雄也专注于他在目的论意义上所超越的伦理，但在这方面，他有普遍性作支持。而信仰骑士却只有自己，恐怖之处就在于此。大多数人让自己的义务一次持续一天，但是那样的话，他们的专注绝达不到如此的激情，他们对义务的意识也绝达不到如此的强烈。普遍性从某种意义上也许可以帮助悲剧英雄获得这一点，但是信仰骑士却一切都只能靠自己。悲剧英雄在行动中可以在普遍性中找到安宁，信仰骑士却永远处于紧张之中。阿伽门农放弃依菲琴尼亚，从而在普遍性中找到安宁，接着他就可以开始献祭依菲琴尼亚的行动。要是阿伽门农没有作这运动，要是在那关键时刻，他没有充满激情的专注，而是一心想着听到的关于他应该要好几个女儿，或者也许离奇的事情可能会发生的无聊闲谈，那么自然他就不会是个英雄而只是个可怜的人。亚伯拉罕也具有那英雄的专注，尽管因为他在普遍性中没有支柱，在他这种情况下要有这种专注要困难得多；但他多作了一个运动，借助于此他全身心地专注于创造奇迹。倘若亚伯拉罕没有这样做，他也就会只是个阿伽门农，只要他能解释得出他愿意献出以撒这事如何在没有有利于普遍性的情况下是合理的。

个人是否真的处于诱惑考验中，或是否真是信仰骑士，只有他自己可以判断。不过，基于悖论制定出一些即便是不处于悖论中的人也能理解的标准还是有可能的。真正的信仰骑士永远是绝对孤立的，而假骑士则是宗派主义的。后者试图跳出悖论的狭窄道路，变成一个廉价的悲剧英雄。悲剧英雄表现了普遍性并为此献身。宗派主义者，相反，拥有自己的私人剧院，也就是，有几个好朋友和同志，他们可以像《金色鼻烟盒》里的小吏代表很好地代表正义一样代表普遍性。但是，信仰骑士就是那悖论，他是个个体，绝对只有自己的一个个体，没有其他联系或复杂因素。这是那弱小的宗派主义者所不能忍受的恐怖之处。而那宗派主义侏儒并没有从这恐怖之处意识到自己无法达到这种伟大，并因此而坦率地承认这一点（这是我会情不自禁赞同的，因为我自己也会这样做），这可怜可鄙之人以为他可以通过和其他同类合伙一起成就那伟大。但这是不会起作用的，因为精神世界不容忍欺骗。十二个宗派主义者手拉手联合起来，他们对等待信仰骑士的种种孤独的诱惑考验一无所知，信仰骑士不敢回避这些诱惑考验，正因为他知道如果自己贸然强进情况就会更恐怖。那些宗派主义者的喧嚣和吵嚷声震得彼此都要聋了，他们用尖叫来抵抗恐惧，这样像周日出游的欢呼的人群会以为他们正冲向天堂，以为他们和信仰骑士走的是同一条道路，而信仰骑士其实是在与世隔绝的寂静中，担负着可怕的责任孤独前行。

信仰骑士只能依赖他自己，他感受到不能使别人理解自己的痛苦，但他并没有那种虚荣的想要指引他人的欲望。这痛苦能使他确信自己走在正确的道路上，他太认真，因而不会有虚荣的欲望。假的信仰骑士因为迅速精通指引人之术很容易泄露他的真实身份。他没有领悟的一点是，如果另一个人想要走相同的路，他必须是完全的单独的个体，不需要任何人的建议，更不需要从急于把自己的建议强加于人的人那儿获得建议。同样在这里，忍受不了做不被人理解的烈士的人跳离这条道路，选择了一条方便之路，在这条路上有世人对他们精通此道表达钦佩。真正的信仰骑士是个见证者，绝不是个教师，他的深刻人性就在于此。这深刻人性比那对别人祸福的愚蠢的关心要更有价值，因为那对别人的关心是以同情的名义而受人尊敬，但它其实只不过是虚荣心而已。因此，一个只想做见证人的人会承认，没有哪个人，即便是最卑贱的人，需要他人的同情，或是应该被贬低以使他人抬高自己。但是，因为他自己赢得的东西并不是廉价地轻易得来的，所以他也不会廉价地卖掉它；他也不是小气到接受人们的钦慕后，回报给他们的是轻蔑的沉默，他知道，真正伟大的东西是人人同样都可以得到的。

所以，要么存在对上帝的绝对的义务，那样的话，它就是如前所述的悖论，即作为个体的个人高于普遍性，并且作为个体与绝对者[8]处于一种绝对的关系中；要么，信仰就因为一直存在而从未存在过，或者换言之，亚伯拉罕就丧失了其伟大地位，而人们就必须以那高雅的注释家的方式去解释《路加福音》十四节那段话，并用同样的方式解释相应的和类似的段落。

问题三　亚伯拉罕对撒拉、以利亚撒和以撒隐瞒自己的目的，这在伦理上合乎情理吗？

伦理本身是有普遍性的东西；而作为有普遍性的东西，它是有无蔽性的。而个人，作为直接的、有感觉、有精神和灵魂的存在物，则是隐藏的。因此，他的伦理任务就是从这隐藏状态中打开自我，在普遍性中显露自己，变得无隐蔽性。这样，每当他想要保持隐蔽性状态，他就犯了罪，处于诱惑的考验中，他只有通过显露自我才能从中脱离出来。

如此，我们发现自己再次回到同一地点。如果没有一种基于个体高于普遍性的隐蔽性，那么亚伯拉罕的行为就不可辩护，因为他无视那些直接的伦理因素。但是，如果有这样的一种隐藏性，那么，我们就面临一个悖论，一个无法调解的悖论，这正是因为，这悖论是以个人作为个体高于普遍性这一点为基础的，而那普遍性正是用以调解的媒介。黑格尔派哲学认为，不存在合乎情理的隐藏性，也不存在合乎情理的不能通约性或者无从比较性，因而这和它对无蔽性的要求是一致的，但是它想把亚伯拉罕视为信仰之父和谈论信仰则不是很公平合理。因为信仰不是最开始的直接性，而是后来的直接性。最开始的直接性是美学性的，在这里黑格尔哲学很可能是正确的。但是，信仰不是美学性的，或者如果说它是，那么就可以说，信仰因为一直存在而从未存在。

这里最好从纯美学的角度来研究一下整个问题，并为此开始美学探究，我想请读者暂时全情投入这一研究，而同时我自己也相应地改变我的描述方式。我想更仔细一点研究的范畴是有趣的事物，这一范畴在今天我们这个时代（正因为我们生活在人类事务的转折点上）已经变得非常重要，因为它实际上就是危机范畴。因此，人们不应该在自己全力热爱过这一范畴之后，像有些人那样，因为自己经历过它，超越了它，就蔑视它。但是我们也对此过于贪婪，因为，可以确定的是，要变成有趣的人或过有趣的生活，这和你擅长做什么没有关系，它是一种重大的特权，这种特权，像精神世界的所有特权一样，只有通过深重的痛苦来获得。例如，苏格拉底是在这世上生活过的最有意思的人，他所过的生活是所有生活中最有意思的生活，但是这种存在是神分配给他的，而且既然他不得不为之奋斗，他对麻烦和痛苦而言绝不是陌生人。亵渎这样的存在的人不会成为认真生活的人，然而，现如今，这样的例子并不少见。更进一步来说，有趣这一范畴是一个边界范畴，它是美学和伦理学之间的边界。因为这个原因，我们在探究中必须不断地扫视伦理学领地，为了使我们的探究有重要性，我们必须带着真正的审美情感来领会问题。我们现在这个时代，伦理学很少考虑这些事宜。原因应该是伦理学体系里没有容纳它们的合适空间。那么，人们在专题论文里作这样的研究应该是没问题的，而且，如果人们不想写得冗长啰唆，也可以写得言简意赅却达到同样的目的，只要人们能用好谓语，因为一两个谓语便可揭示出整个世界。伦理学体系里能没有像谓语这样的小词语的一点儿空间吗？

亚里士多德在他的不朽名作《诗学》里写道：“的确，故事的两个部分，即命运突变[突转，（悲剧情节的关键）]和发现，与这些事有关。”当然，在这里，我只关心第二个特点，即发现。有发现这个问题的地方就暗示着先前有一种隐藏存在。所以，正如发现是戏剧性生活中解决矛盾性、放松性的因素，隐藏就是生活之剧中制造紧张的因素。亚里士多德在同一章里关于悲剧中命运突转和认知两者之间是否有冲突撞击的不同价值的讨论，以及他对单一发现和双重发现的论述，我在此不加以探讨，尽管他的讨论中体现出真诚和安静的专注，这对早已厌倦那些学者们百科全书似的肤浅的人而言是特别有吸引力的。这里，一个更为概括的评论就够了。在希腊悲剧中，隐藏（而后发现）是一种史诗般的幸存，这种幸存是以戏剧化行为隐蔽起来这样的命运为基础，它也从这种命运中获得了它的模糊神秘的起源。这就是为什么希腊悲剧所产生的效果类似于那种眼睛缺乏力量的大理石雕像给人的印象。希腊悲剧是盲目的。因此，要想正确地欣赏它，需要进行一定的抽象处理。一个儿子杀了父亲，但他后来才知道他杀的人是自己的父亲。一个姐姐正要牺牲弟弟，但在一个决定性时刻才发现他的身份。我们这个反思性的时代不大可能对这种性质的悲剧感兴趣。现代戏剧已经放弃了宿命这个理念，并且从戏剧性方面解放了自己。它仔细观察，也彻底检查自己，还从戏剧意识角度考虑命运。隐藏和显露因而成了英雄的自由行为，他为自己的行为负责。

发现和隐藏在现代戏剧里同样作为必要因素存在。要举这样的例子就会扯远了。我很谦恭地认为，在我们这个时代，每个人在美学上都如此肆意骄奢，如此有能力，如此激奋，以至于他们就如同亚里士多德所说的松鸡那样，那松鸡只要听到公鸡的声音或公鸡在头顶飞过的响声就很兴奋，他们对一种概念也可以很轻易地作出想象。我设想，我们这个时代每个人只要听到“隐藏”这一单词，就能从袖子里抖落出一打浪漫故事和喜剧故事来。因此，我在这里只简要地直接给出一个相当宽泛概括的评论。如果做隐藏的人，也就是说，把引起戏剧性因素引入喜剧的人，藏了某种无意义的东西，我们就会得到喜剧。但是，如果那藏匿者明白隐藏的概念，他就可能接近于变成悲剧英雄。这儿我就举一个喜剧例子吧。一个男人化了妆、戴上假发，他渴望在美丽异性那儿获得青睐。他确信，化妆和假发无疑会使自己令人难以抗拒，所以会有很多成功。他捕获了一位姑娘，正处在幸福的顶点。现在，让我们看看故事的实质意义。如果他能承认自己的欺术，一旦他显露出自己普通，实际上甚至秃顶的样子，难道他不会失去他迷人的魅力吗？难道他不会再次失去所爱之人吗？隐藏是他的自由行为，而美学使他为此行为负责。但是美学这个学科绝不是秃头的伪君子的朋友，而会使他受人嘲笑。既然我们这里不把喜剧包括在探究的兴趣课题之内，这个例子就足以表明我的意思。

我的探究步骤是辩证地研究隐藏在美学和伦理学上扮演的角色，目的是揭示美学性的隐藏和悖论之间的绝对不同。

先举几个例子吧。一个姑娘和某人悄悄恋爱了，不过双方都还没向对方坦白这份爱。姑娘的父母强迫她嫁给另一个人（她甚至可能考虑到应尽的孝道而服从）。她服从了父母的意愿。她隐藏起自己的爱，“为了不使对方难过，没有人会知道她的痛苦”。或者另一个故事版本：一个小伙子身处两难之境：只要说出那个字，他就可以得到他魂牵梦萦的对象。但是，这个小小的字却会危害到，是的，甚至（谁知道呢）毁了整个家庭。于是，他高尚地选择继续隐藏自己的情感，“绝不能让那女孩知道，这样她也许能在另一个人那儿找到幸福”。这两个人都对各自所爱之人隐瞒了感情，他们互相隐瞒，这是多么可怜啊！否则的话，一个非凡的更优秀的结合就可能产生。他们的隐藏行为是自由行为，甚至从美学意义上讲他们也为此行为负责。不过，美学是一个可敬的多愁善感的学科，它知道的修理东西的方式比物业经理助理知道的还多。那么，它做什么呢？它做一切可能之事来帮助相爱之人。机缘巧合，那相恋双方的规划婚姻里的伴侣得知了对方的高尚决定。接着进行了种种解释。他们得到了彼此，而且作为额外收获，还进入了真英雄的行列。而尽管他们甚至都没有时间去好好考虑他们英雄般的决定，美学还是把他们当作似乎已经为这个决定勇敢地奋斗了多年来对待。因为美学不怎么在乎时间问题，不管是严肃认真还是玩笑，时间在美学里都一样快速地飞逝。

但是，伦理学既不知道这样的巧合，也不懂得多愁善感。它也没有时间飞逝的概念。这样的话，事情就有了不同的一面。你不能和伦理学争辩，因为它运用的是纯粹的范畴。它也不诉诸于经验。因为经验在所有可笑的事情里也许是最可笑的，它远不能使人智慧，如果一个人不懂得任何比经验更高等的东西的话，那么，经验很快就会使他发疯。伦理学也没有什么巧合偶然，所以不需要对事情作种种解释。它不玩弄尊严，它把责任的重担压在英雄孱弱的双肩，它谴责英雄想要在他的行为中扮演上帝是一种傲慢放肆，但也谴责他想要通过他承受的痛苦来这样做。它命令人相信现实，嘱咐人要有勇气反抗现实的所有磨难，而不是反抗他自己承担责任时所受的苍白的痛苦；它警告要提防把信仰置于理性的精明计算之中，这计算比古代的神谕还不牢靠。它警告不要不合时宜的慷慨大度。让现实决定需要显示勇气的场合吧。不过，伦理学同时也会提供所有可能的帮助。如果在那二人之间有某种更深刻的东西在涌动，如果他们有看到这任务，并开始着手行动的认真态度，那么无疑他们会产生某种东西。但是伦理学不会帮助他们。因为他们对它隐瞒了一个秘密，一个他们自己要承担责任的秘密，伦理学觉得受到了冒犯。

所以说，美学要求隐秘行为并回报这种行为；而伦理学要求显露，要求公开隐秘，并惩罚隐秘行为。

但是，有时候，即便是美学也要求公开要求显露。当那被美学幻想所俘虏的英雄认为自己可以通过沉默救另一个人时，美学要求沉默并褒奖它。但当英雄的行为干涉到另一人的生活时，美学则又要求公开隐秘。现在我谈论的是悲剧英雄。这里我们思考一下欧里庇得斯的《奥利斯的依菲琴尼亚》。阿伽门农正准备献祭依菲琴尼亚那一情节。此刻美学要求阿伽门农保持沉默，因为从别人那儿寻求安慰不符合英雄的身份，而且出于对女人的担心，他也应该尽可能长久地对她们隐瞒。但是，从另一方面来说，英雄，正因为要当英雄，才必须受到克吕泰墨斯特拉（阿伽门农的妻子）和依菲琴尼亚的泪水的考验。美学怎么办？它有个权宜之计。它让站在旁边的一个老仆人把一切透露给了克吕泰墨斯特拉。那么一切就顺理成章了。

但是，伦理学里没有巧合，没有随时待命的老仆人。美学的理念一旦运用到现实里就会自相矛盾。因此，伦理学要求公开披露。[9]那悲剧英雄没有成为美学幻想的俘虏，他自己完成了告诉依菲琴尼亚她的命运这个任务，这个行为正好显示了伦理勇气。在这方面，悲剧英雄是伦理学的宠儿，她对他甚为满意。但如果他保持沉默，也许是因为他这样做可以使别人好过些，又或许是这样可以使他自己好过些。但悲剧英雄知道他不受后一个动机的影响。他保持沉默是因为他要作为个体承担责任，他忽视任何外界的议论。但是，作为悲剧英雄，他不能这样做。因为正是由于他一贯表现普遍性，伦理学才爱他。他的英雄行为需要勇气，而他那勇气的一部分本身就是不躲避争论。但是一个人的眼泪是一种为了自己个人利益的可怕争辩，而无疑有那种不为任何事物所动却可能被眼泪所撼动的人。那个剧本里有让依菲琴尼亚哭泣的情节。实际上，像耶弗他的女儿一样，她应该被允许哭泣两个月，而且不是孤独地哭泣，而是在她父亲的脚边。她应该使出浑身解数哭泣，不是用橄榄枝，而是用自己缠住父亲的腿（cf.v.1224）。美学要求公开透露秘密，但是是通过巧合的方式；伦理学也要求公开秘密，它却是在悲剧英雄身上得到满足。

尽管伦理对公开秘密的要求很严格，但不可否认的是，保密和沉默，作为内在情感的决定因素，的确使一个人伟大。当埃莫离开塞琪时，他对她说：“如果你保持沉默，你将生一个圣婴，但是如果你透露了这个秘密，你就会只生个凡人。”悲剧英雄这种伦理学的宠儿，是有纯粹人性的人，我可以理解这种人，他一切的所作所为都是公开的。但是如果我进一步思考，就会碰到那个悖论，神圣者和魔鬼；因为沉默就是这两者。沉默是魔鬼的陷阱；一个人沉默越多，魔鬼就变得越可怕；但是沉默又是神灵与个人之间的默契交融。

然而，在我们回到亚伯拉罕的故事之前，我想介绍几个具有诗意的角色。通过对他们施加辩证的力量，我将把他们置于绝境，同时借助绝望对他们的蹂躏，我阻止他们静止不动，这样，处于痛苦中的他们也许有可能揭示出点什么，给人启迪。[10]

亚里士多德在他的《政治学》里，讲了一个在特尔斐（希腊古都）发生的由一桩婚事引发的一场政治骚乱。一位新郎，因为占卜师预言他会在即将结婚之际遭遇不幸，于是他在就要去迎接新娘时，突然改变了计划，不打算进行婚礼了。这种情节就是我所需要的。[11]在特尔斐，这肯定是引人潸然泪下的。如果一个诗人描述此事，他肯定可以指望引人同情。在生活中经常被流放的爱情在此还要被剥夺上天之助的机会，难道这不可怕吗？难道婚姻是天作之合这条古谚语在此要蒙羞了吗？在通常情况下，是有限运动的考验和苦难，它们像恶鬼幽灵一样试图拆散恋人们，而爱情本身则有上天这个神圣同盟帮助，会战胜一切敌人。此处发生的则是上天本身要拆散它自己促成的联姻。谁能猜到会这样？新娘是最难预料到这样的事的。片刻之前，她还盛装端坐在闺房，可爱的女仆已经精心地打扮好她，准备向世人证明她们的手艺。打扮新娘的过程给她们带来的不只是开心，甚至还有羡慕；她们开心的是她们已不可能变得更加羡慕，因为新娘已经美丽得无以复加了。独坐在闺房时的她已经从一个美女变成了另一个美女，所有可以用的适合她的美的装扮之术都用上了。但是，还缺了一样这些女仆们没有想到的东西，它是一个面纱，比女仆们用来遮盖她的面纱还要更精美，更轻柔而且更有遮蔽性。这是一种女仆所不知道的也不知如何帮她穿的婚纱，是的，连新娘自己也不知道如何获得它和穿上它。它是一种看不见的、友好的力量，这种力量以在新娘不知情的情况下装扮她，包裹住她为乐趣。因为新娘所看见的是新郎在经过走向神庙的路，看到门在他身后关上，她变得更加镇静和喜悦，因为她只知道他现在更加属于自己了。庙门打开，他走了出来，但她端庄文雅地垂下眼睛，因此她没有看见他神色不安。但是他却看见上天嫉妒新娘的美丽和自己的幸运。庙门打开了，女仆们看到新郎走了出来，但她们没有看到他神色不安，她们正忙于把新娘接过来。接着，她文雅谦恭地走了出来，而同时又像被伴娘簇拥的王后，伴娘像通常那样对新娘鞠躬行礼。这样，她站在她那可爱的队列之首等待—却只有一瞬间，因为那庙就在附近—新郎走了过来，却又走过了她的门口。

但我就此打住。因为我不是个诗人，我只辩证地分析事物。首先必须要记住，是在关键时刻，英雄才得知将要发生的事，所以他是清白而无可责备的，他并没有轻浮而不负责任地要和爱人联姻。其次，在他面前的，或确切地说，与他作对的，是神谕，所以他不像那些受狂妄自负所控制的微弱的恋人们。此外，更不用说，这神谕使他同新娘一样难过，甚至可以说他更难过，因为毕竟他是她的不幸的起因。的确，占卜师只是为他预言了灾难，但没说这灾难是否是一种会同时影响到他们的婚姻幸福的灾难。那么他该怎么办？（1）他是否应保持沉默并举行婚礼？同时想着“也许这灾难不会立即发生，无论如何，我对爱人是真诚的，我也不怕使自己难受；但我必须保持沉默，否则连这短暂的时刻也会丧失”。这听起来可行，但实际上绝非如此，因为他若这样做就是侮辱了他的爱人。他的保持沉默从某种意义上说就使她有罪，因为她若知道真相，她绝不会同意这样的联姻。所以，在艰苦时刻，他要承受的不仅是灾难不幸，还有保持沉默的责任以及她对他沉默不语隐瞒秘密所感到的义愤。（2）他是否应保持沉默而且不结婚？那样的话，他就必须进行欺骗，以使自己废除与她的关系。美学可能赞同这样做。那么那灾难就可以像真实故事里那样发生，不过，在最后时刻，会有解释，尽管这解释已经太迟了，因为从美学上必须让他死，除非美学能找到废除那宿命预言的方式。然而，这行为尽管高尚，但它是对那姑娘及其爱情的侮辱和犯罪。（3）他该说出实情吗？当然，我们不应忘记，英雄若认为放弃爱情的重要性和一笔不成功的生意的重要性没有区别，这样未免有些过于诗人气质了。如果他说了实情，那么，整件事就会变成像阿克塞尔和沃尔伯格那样的不幸爱情故事。他们会变成一对上天自己拆散的恋人。不过，在眼下这个例子中，这个拆散要从不同的角度来看待，因为它也是个人的自由行为的结果。对这个例子的辩证分析的最难之处在于该不幸只会影响新郎。那么，这两人，不像阿克塞尔和沃尔伯格那样，可以找到一种表达他们痛苦的共同语言，因为那两人对彼此同等亲近，上天从双方的角度均匀平等地拆散这段姻缘。[12]如果这个例子里的情况亦是如此，那么就可以找到一个出路。因为既然上天没有用可见的力量来拆散他们，而是留给他们自己作决定，那么我们很容易可以想象到他们会藐视天庭和它所预言的灾难，最终结合在一起。

然而，伦理学会要求他说出实情。那样的话，他的英雄主义的本质就在于他放弃了美学上的高尚慷慨这一事实。而这在此几乎不能被认为含有任何与隐瞒有关的虚荣的掺和物，既然他一定很清楚是他使那个女孩难过。但是，这种英雄主义实际上基于这样一个事实：他本可以有机会拥有真爱却取消了这种假设（他真挚地爱她，为了她而不是为自己而保持沉默。—英译者注）；因为否则的话，我们就会有足够的英雄，尤其是在我们这个无比精通于伪造的时代，这个时代擅长跳过中间环节伪造最高标准的赝品。

但是，既然我超越不了悲剧英雄，为什么要有上述的概述呢？因为这概述有可能揭示前面所述的悖论。这都取决于我们的英雄与占卜师所说的话之间的关系，这话无论如何将决定他的生活。那占卜师的话是公开性的宣告还是私人性的呢？故事的场景是在希腊；占卜师的话是所有人都可以理解的—我不仅仅是说每个人可以从词法上理解那话的内容，而是说每个人可以领会占卜师所传达的是上天的决定。所以占卜师的话不仅英雄可以理解，而且每个人都可以理解，这样他的话表达的就绝不是和神灵之间的私人性质的关系。他可以做他想做的，但是被预言的事终将会发生，不管是通过做任何事情还是通过克制自己不做任何事情他都不能更接近神灵，也不能变成神灵怜悯或愤怒的对象。所预言的结果对任何人和英雄而言都是易于理解的，也没有只有英雄才可以读懂的秘密代码。所以他要是想要说出实情的话，他完全可以说得很清楚，因为他可以使自己得到理解；而如果他想要保持沉默，那也是因为他想要通过做单一的个体，成为高于普遍性的人，想要用各种关于她如何会很快忘记悲伤的奇怪幻想来欺骗自己，等等。然而，如果上天的意志不是由占卜师来向他宣告的，如果上天的意志以一种私密的方式让他知道，如果这意志将自己置于一种和他相当私密的关系中，那么我们就遇上了那悖论—假设有这样的一种东西（既然我这里的反思呈现出一种进退两难的形式）—那么，不管他可能有多么想要说出实情，他也不能说。他非但没有在沉默中享受快乐，反而承受了痛苦。然而对他而言，这痛苦正是使他确信自己做了正确的事情的东西。所以，他沉默的原因并不是他想把自己作为单一的个体置于与普遍性的绝对关系中，而是把自己作为单一的个体置于与绝对的绝对关系中。在我看来，他这样做也会找到平静安宁，但是，伦理的要求会不断地搅扰他高尚的沉默。人们只是很渴望美学可以从它多年前停止的地方起步，从对高尚的幻想开始。一旦它这样做了，它就会和宗教联手协作，因为宗教是唯一能够将美学从它与伦理的冲突中拯救出来的力量。伊丽莎白女王就是为了国家，通过签署了埃塞克斯死亡令的方式牺牲了她对他的爱。这是一个英雄主义行为，即便里面涉及因为他没有送给她戒指这样的事引起的一点个人抱怨。其实，我们知道，他的确送了她戒指，但是这戒指被某个恶意的宫女隐瞒了。据说（如果我没弄错的话），伊丽莎白得知此事后，咬着一根手指，静坐了十天，一言不发，于是郁郁而终。这对于知道如何撬开人们嘴巴窥探真相的诗人而言是个好素材；否则的话，它至多对芭蕾舞大师有用，的确，现如今的诗人常常把自己与芭蕾舞大师混淆起来。

接着，我想简述一下涉及着魔之人的事物。为此我将利用一下《艾格尼丝和雄性人鱼》的传说。雄性人鱼是一个从隐蔽的深渊中跃出的诱惑者，在疯狂的欲望控制下，他抓住和毁了那朵静立于海岸边无辜的美丽鲜花，它当时正低头做沉思状倾听着大海的咆哮。目前诗人们就是这样阐释这个传说的。让我们作个改变吧。那雄性人鱼是个诱惑者。他呼唤艾格尼丝，并用他的甜言蜜语从她那儿骗得了她心中的秘密。她从雄性人鱼身上找到了她所寻求的东西，找到了她凝视大海深处所要找的东西。艾格尼丝愿意追随他而去。那雄性人鱼已将她抱入怀中，艾格尼丝则充满信任地用胳膊缠绕住着他的脖子；她全身心地将自己献给了这个更强的人。他已经到了海边，弯腰准备带着他的猎物潜入海中。就在那时，艾格尼丝再次注视着他，那目光不是充满畏惧，不是充满怀疑，不是带着对自己姣好外表的骄傲，也没有沉醉于欲望之中，而是带着绝对的信任，绝对的谦恭，就像她自视为的一朵低下的鲜花；她带着绝对的信任把自己全部的命运托付于他。看！大海不再咆哮，它的狂野的吼声已静下来，大自然的激情—它是这人鱼的力量—遗弃了他，大海变得一片死寂。而艾格尼丝依然那样注视着他。于是人鱼崩溃了，他抵抗不了纯真无邪的力量，他的原有本性背叛了他，他不能够引诱艾格尼丝。于是他又带她回了家，他对她解释说他只是想给她看看大海在平静时有多美丽，而艾格尼丝也相信他说的话。接着他独自返回，大海又狂暴怒吼着，但更加汹涌澎湃的是人鱼的绝望之心。他能够引诱艾格尼丝，他能够引诱成百上千个艾格尼丝，他可以迷住任何女孩，但是艾格尼丝已战胜了他，人鱼已失去了她。只有作为捕获的战利品她才能属于他；而他不能忠实于任何姑娘，因为他只是个人鱼。在此，我冒昧地在这人鱼身上作了一点改变。[13]实际上，我也对艾格尼丝作了些许改变。在那传说中，艾格尼丝也绝不是没有罪过。而且，一般来说，想象一个姑娘在一件引诱之事中绝对地无可责备，是一种胡说，一种对女性的轻视和侮辱。用一种有点现代化的说法来说，在那传说中，艾格尼丝是一个渴求“有趣之事”的女性，每个这样的女人总是确信海面上有雄性人鱼；而人鱼们密切关注这类人，他们会像鲨鱼追踪猎物一样对此类人尾随不放。因此，认为（或者，这是否是人鱼散布的一种谣言？）所谓的文化修养可以保护女孩不受引诱是十分愚蠢的。不，不是这样的，生活是更公正合理的；只有一种保护手段，那就是纯真无邪。

现在，我们将赋予人鱼人类的意识，同时假设他作为人鱼存在意味着一种人的前生（预先存在），因为这前生他的生活变得纠缠混乱。没有什么可以阻止他成为英雄；因为他现在所做的事都是调解性的。他被艾格尼丝拯救了，引诱者已被彻底击垮了，他已屈服于纯真的力量，他再也无力诱惑人了。但是立即有两种力量试图控制他：忏悔（独自忏悔）和对艾格尼丝忏悔。如果独自忏悔控制住了他，那么他可以保持隐蔽，如果对艾格尼丝忏悔控制住了他，那么他就被暴露了。

然而，如果只是忏悔掌控住了他，而他又保持隐秘的话，那么他必定会使艾格尼丝不快乐；因为艾格尼丝无比纯真地爱着他，即便在她看来他似乎在那一瞬间变了似的，不管他隐藏得多么好，说他只是想让她看看大海的平静之美，即便在那个时刻，她依然相信他。但是，就情感而言，人鱼自己甚至变得更不开心。因为他怀着多重情感爱着艾格尼丝，而且还要承受新的负疚感。无疑，忏悔的魔性一面会对他解释说，这正是对他的惩罚（因为他前生的过错），并说这惩罚越折磨他就越好。

如果他屈服于这种魔性因素，他可能会再次尝试救助艾格尼丝，他会用从某种意义上诉诸邪恶的方式来救一个人。他知道艾格尼丝爱他。如果他能从艾格尼丝那儿挣脱她对自己的爱，那么，从某种意义上来说，她就得救了。但是如何做到这一点呢？人鱼很明智，他不会认为开诚布公地坦白可以引起她对自己的厌恶。那么他也许会尝试去激起她所有的负面情绪，去蔑视她，嘲笑她，讥笑她的爱，可能的话，他还会煽动她的自尊心。他还会不遗余力地折磨自己，因为这是魔性深深的自我矛盾之处，从某种意义上，在一个魔鬼身上比一个肤浅微不足道之人身上有多得多的善。艾格尼丝越自私，他欺骗她就越容易（只有没有经验之人才会认为欺骗纯真之人是容易的；生活是深刻的，实际上精明之人觉得精明人之间彼此互相欺骗是最容易的），但是人鱼承受的痛苦也就更可怕。他的欺骗设计得越狡猾，艾格尼丝就越不会羞怯地对他隐瞒自己的痛苦；她会用尽办法，不是为了赶走他，而是为了折磨他，这些办法也不是没有效果。

借助魔性之力，人鱼渴望成为一个作为个体却高于普遍全体的个人。魔鬼拥有和神圣者相同的特点，即个体可以与之建立一种绝对的关系。这就是那类似之处，就是我们所讨论的悖论的对应物。因此，它和悖论有一定的相似性，这相似性容易令人误解。因而，那人鱼显然有事实证明他的沉默是合理的，即正因为沉默，他承受了一切痛苦。当然，毫无疑问，他是可以说出实情的。如果他说出来的话，他就可以成为一个悲剧英雄，在我看来，是一个宏伟堂皇的悲剧英雄。也许只有很少的人可以理解其中的堂皇之处。[14]那样，他就可以有勇气把自己从能够通过诡计使艾格尼丝快乐的自我欺骗中解脱出来；从人性的角度说，他就会有勇气击败艾格尼丝。这里，我要从心理学的角度来作探讨。我们使艾格尼丝越自私，人鱼的自我欺骗就越有效，的确，实际上，人鱼凭借他的魔鬼的精明，从人的角度讲，不仅救了艾格尼丝，还使她显露出最非凡的一面，这也不是不可想象的。因为魔鬼知道如何逼迫即便是最软弱的人，使其显出力量，而他也可能用自己的方式表现出对一个人最善良的意图。

那人鱼处于辩证的一极。如果他从愧悔的魔性一面中解脱出来，那么会有两条可能的道路。他可以控制自己，继续隐藏，但不能依赖他的精明来这样做。那样的话，他不能作为单一的个体与魔鬼建立绝对关系，但可以在悖论的对立面—神灵会拯救艾格尼丝—得到心安。（这就是中世纪会作的推理，根据那时的观念，人鱼显然已致力于献身修道院。）或者，另一条路是，他可以通过艾格尼丝得救。但是这绝不能理解为意味着艾格尼丝的爱将来可能把他从一个诱骗者改变过来（这是美学进行拯救的方式，它总是避开主要问题，即人鱼生活的连续性）；从那方面讲，他已得救。只要他显露自己公开实情，他就会得救。因此他娶了艾格尼丝。但是他必须依然求助于那个悖论。因为，当个体出于内疚感脱离普遍性，他只有凭借变成与绝对者建立绝对关系的个体来回归普遍性。在此，我要插入一个评论，这评论比我们之前任何地方所论述的都要更进一步。[15]罪不是第一直接性，它是后来的直接性。在罪的范畴，个人已经高于普遍性（根据魔鬼的悖论这一方面而言），因为普遍性想要强迫一个缺乏必要条件的人去表现普遍性其实是它本身的自我矛盾。要是哲学，像其他的自负狂妄的学科那样，以为有人可能真的想在实践中遵循它的准则戒律，就会出现一个古怪的滑稽剧。忽视罪的伦理学是个完全无用的学科，但是它一旦要肯定罪为当然的基本条件，它又因此而超越了自身的范畴。哲学告诉我们说，直接性的东西应该被中止。这确实是对的，但它不正确的地方是，罪，理所当然的就是直接性的东西，就像信仰理所当然就是直接性的东西一样。

只要我在这个范围内讨论，一切就都很顺畅，但实际上此处所说的一切也绝对解释不了亚伯拉罕。他没有通过罪变成单一的个体；相反，他是上帝所拣选的正义的人。所以，任何对亚伯拉罕所作的类比只有在那个体能够实现普遍性之后才能出现，而接着悖论又重复出现了。

因此，我可以理解人鱼的行为，却不能理解亚伯拉罕。因为人鱼求助于悖论是为了实现普遍性。如果他继续隐藏，努力承受悔悟的种种痛苦，他就会变成魔鬼，而且会正因如此而归于虚无。如果他继续隐藏，但却并不怀有通过自己受悔恨之枷锁的奴役的折磨，来解救艾格尼丝这样狡猾的想法，那么，他会得到安宁平和，但却失去了世界。如果他公开自己，让自己通过艾格尼丝得救，那么他就是我所能想象得到的最伟大的人。只有美学才会不负责任地认为它可以通过让一个迷失的人得到一个纯真姑娘的爱并由此得救，来歌颂爱情的力量。只有美学才会看错并认为那姑娘是英雄人物，而人鱼不是英雄。所以人鱼不能属于艾格尼丝，除非他在作了无限运动，即悔悟运动之后，又靠荒诞之力作了更进一步的运动。他自身的力量足以作悔悟运动，但为此他用尽了所有的力量，因而他靠自己的力量回归和把握现实是不可能的。如果一个人缺乏足够的激情去作这二者中任何一种运动的话，如果他虚度人生，有些许悔悟，同时又想着剩下的一切都会很简单，那么他就已经永远地放弃了活在理想中的努力，那么他就可以很容易地达到，并帮助别人达到最高境界，即用这样的想法欺骗自己和他人：精神世界就像一种卡片游戏，人人都在其中作弊行骗。因此，我们可以通过反思以下这一点多么奇怪来自娱自乐：即正是在我们这个人人都成就最高事物，达到最高境界的时代，对灵魂不朽的怀疑竟然如此普遍，既然连仅仅，但真正地作了无限运动的人都很难说是个怀疑者。对于激情所作的结论是唯一可靠的，也就是说，是唯一令人信服的。幸运的是，这样的生活比聪明人想要的生活要更仁慈，更忠贞。这种生活不排斥任何人，即便是最卑微的人；它也不欺骗任何人，因为在精神世界里，唯一被欺骗的人是那些欺骗自己的人。如果我允许自己下判断的话，一般人认为，也是我自己认为，进修道院不是最高级最伟大的事。但是我也绝不会因此就认为，如今没有人进修道院这一事实意味着我们都比那些在修道院找到安宁的深刻而又诚挚的人要更伟大。现如今有多少人有激情去思考这一点并诚实地评判自己呢？仅仅想到花时间在良心上，让良心昼夜不停警惕地找出每一个秘密想法，以至于当一个人没有时时刻刻在靠人身上最高尚最神圣之力来作运动时，他可以痛苦恐惧地发现每个人生活中的阴暗的情感，[16]并靠恐惧本身，如果没有其他方式的话，来引诱出这些阴暗的情感，而与之相反的是，当一个人和其他人生活在一起，他很容易忘记，也很容易避免这一切，又以很多方式得以支撑下去，并有机会重新开始—仅仅这个想法，如果带着适当的尊重去领会，我认为这想法本身就可以磨炼我们这个自以为已获得最高成就的时代里的很多人。然而，在我们这个自认为已达到顶峰的时代，尽管实际上没有哪个时代像我们这个时代有这么多滑稽可笑的人，人们并不担忧这些事情。的确，很难理解为什么我们这个时代还没有孕育出，没有自发地孕育出，自己的英雄，很难理解魔鬼肆无忌惮地上演着那可怕的戏剧，这戏剧使整代人发笑而他们却不知道他们在笑自己。的确，当人们在二十岁时就已达到最高点，取得最高成就，这样的存在除了可笑之外，还有什么价值呢？而自从人们不再进修道院以后，这个时代又想出什么更崇高的运动呢？坐在首座，却又胆怯地使人们认为他们已取得最高成就，甚至阴险地劝他们不要尝试任何次等的事情，难道这不是一种可鄙的世俗，可怜的谨慎与懦弱吗？一个已经在修道院作了修行运动的人只有一种运动没有做，那就是荒诞的运动。如今我们这个时代有多少人理解荒诞是什么呢？有多少人是以放弃一切或得到一切的方式生活着呢？又有多少人诚实到足以知道自己是什么，能做什么和不能做什么呢？如果有这样的人，他们最常存在于文化修养不怎么高的人群中和妇女中，难道不是这样吗？正如着魔的人总是自我显露却不理解自己一样，我们这个时代以一种透视的方式暴露出自己的缺陷，因为它总是在要求滑稽之事。如果这真是我们这个时代所需要的，也许剧院可能需要一种新的戏剧，在这种剧中，某人为爱而死被当作喜剧来处理。或者，如果那真的要发生，如果这个时代真的目睹了这样的事，如此，它可能借助发笑获得信仰精神力量的勇气，获得停止蹩脚地扼杀自己好的冲动，停止嫉妒地扼杀别人好的冲动的勇气，难道这对我们这个时代不是更好吗？这个时代真的需要一个热心者的可笑表演来作笑料吗？或者它真正需要的难道不是这样一个热诚人物来提醒它记起已忘记的东西吗？

如果因为悔悟的情感没有被唤醒，我们需要一个主题类似但更感人的故事，我们可以为此使用《托比特传》中的一个故事。年轻的托比亚斯想要娶拉贵尔和艾德娜的女儿撒拉。但是这个姑娘被一种悲剧的宿命所笼罩。她已被许给七个丈夫，他们全都死于新婚之房。从我个人的剧本视角而言，这是该故事的一个瑕疵。因为一个姑娘七次徒劳地想嫁出去，尽管她每次差点就成功了，就像一个七次期末考试都失败但差点就及格的学生一样，想到这一点就会觉得这故事有某种难以抗拒的滑稽之处。当然，《托比特传》的重点在别处，而这使七那个大数字很重要，而且在某种意义上甚至有助于达到悲剧效果。它使年轻的托比亚斯显得更加高尚，部分原因是他是他父母的独生子（6.14），另一部分原因是阻碍物是如此的惊人。所以必须省略这个特点。而撒拉，则是一个从未恋爱过的女孩，她依然怀有一个年轻姑娘对幸福的念想，拥有巨大的以生活作抵押的冒险精神，拥有追求幸福的权力，即全心全意地爱一个男人。然而她却是最不幸福的人，因为她知道那爱着她的邪恶的魔鬼总会在新婚之夜杀死新郎。我已读到过很多悲伤的故事，但我怀疑还能否找到我们在这个姑娘生命中所发现的如此深重的悲伤。不过，当不幸来自于外部事物时，人终究是可以找到一定的安慰的。如果生活没能带给一个人使他幸福的事物，想到他本可以得到它依然是一种慰藉。但是时间也驱散不了、治愈不了的深不可测的悲伤，是意识到即便在一生中做了一切也无济于事。一个希腊作家在说到“……因为可以肯定，还没有人完全逃过爱情，也没有人可以逃过爱情，只要有美存在，只要有发现美的眼睛”[Pantos gar oudeis Erota epfugen i feuksetai mechri an kallos i kal ofthalmoi Bleposin参看朗格的《田园诗集》（cf.Longi Pastoralia）]这些话时，以他的单纯幼稚隐藏掩盖了无比多的东西。有很多女孩在爱情中变得不幸福，但她们是从幸福变得不幸福的；撒拉则是在变得不幸福之前就已经是处于不幸福状态了。一个人找不到可以献身的人就够痛苦了，而找到这样的人又不能献身则是难以言状的痛苦。一个女孩将自己交付给某人后，人们说她就不再是自由的了，但撒拉从未自由过却也从未将自己交给任何人。一个女孩将自己交给爱人却被爱人欺骗了是够悲惨的了，但撒拉在交出自己之前就已受骗。当托比亚斯终于要娶撒拉时，后面会隐含着多少悲伤之事啊！会有多么令人激动的婚礼仪式，多么多的准备啊！没有哪个姑娘受过撒拉那样的欺骗。因为她被骗去了那最圣洁的东西，那即便是最贫穷的姑娘也拥有的绝对财富，她被骗去了那种无忧的、无穷的、恣意的、无拘无束的、自我奉献的爱情。所以，首先得有一个净化涤罪的过程，即把鱼的心脏和肝脏放在炽热的余烬上烘烤的过程。想想这母亲如何与女儿告别啊，这女儿自己被骗走了一切，接下来也要骗走自己母亲的最美丽的财产。我们就读读那故事吧。艾德娜准备好了新房，把撒拉叫进来，然后悲伤地哭了，女儿也流泪了，她对女儿说：“我的孩子，不要灰心。主宰天地的主会用欢乐换去你的悲苦。女儿，不要灰心，要振作起来。”现在，婚礼时刻到了。如果我们能够忍受接下来故事里的悲伤，就让我们继续读下去。“但是当门被关上，他们单独在一起时，托比亚斯从床上站起来，他说：‘妹妹，起来，让我们祈祷主怜悯我们。’”（8.4）

如果一个诗人读了这个故事要写它，我敢打赌他百分之九十九会把重点放在年轻的托比亚斯身上。这种在如此明显的危险中还甘愿冒生命危险所体现出的英雄主义—那个故事在另一处又提醒我们那明显的危险，因为在婚礼的第二天早上，拉贵尔对艾德娜说：“派个女仆去看看他是否还活着，如果他死了，我们好埋了他，这样别人也不会知道。”（8.13）—这种英雄主义一定会是那个诗人要强调的主题。但是，我要冒昧地提出另一个主题。的确，托比拉斯表现得很勇敢、很坚决，也很有骑士风范，但是任何没有勇气做那件事的男人都是懦夫，他既不知道爱是什么，也不知道怎样做男子汉，更不知道什么是值得为之活着的。这样的人甚至还没有领会给予比接受更好这个小秘密，更是一点也不懂那个大秘密，即接受要远比给予困难，也就是说，如果一个人有勇气在没有某必需品的情况下也可以将就继续生活，那么在需要帮助的时刻也不会是懦夫。不，撒拉才是英雄！我渴望走近她，就像我从未走近过任何别的姑娘一样，或者说，就像我很想从思想上走近我所读到过的任何人一样。因为，想想当一个人没有任何过错却从一开始就残疾了，从一出生就是人类失败的样品时，他得要有对上帝怎样的爱才会想要被治愈啊！允许爱人如此的冒险行为却还要自己承担责任，这样的人在伦理上得要有怎样的成熟啊！得要有怎样的谦恭才能面对又一个为自己这样冒险的爱人啊！得要有对上帝怎样的信仰才能在随后的时刻不怨恨被自己所亏欠了一切的丈夫啊！

让撒拉做个男人，那样魔性的一面就容易出来。骄傲高尚的本性可以忍受一切，就是忍受不了一样东西，它忍受不了同情。因为同情暗示着一种侮辱，他只能忍受由一种更高的力量所施加的同情，他自己绝不能成为同情的对象。如果他有罪，他可以忍受惩罚而不感到绝望，但是他不能忍受的是，从娘胎里一生出来就被选作同情的对象，被当作同情喜欢闻的芳香。同情有个奇怪的辩证法：这一刻它要求内疚，下一刻它又想要赶走内疚。所以说，一个人的不幸越是精神方面的，那么命中注定被同情就越可怕。但是撒拉没有内疚，她是被扔给所有不幸的猎物，除此之外，还要承受同情的折磨，因为即便是我，这个对她的钦佩多于托比亚斯对她的爱的人，即便是我在提到她的名字时也总是要说“可怜的姑娘！”让一个男人取代撒拉的位置吧，让他知道，如果他要爱一个女孩，地狱的幽灵就会在新婚之夜到来并杀掉她，那么他很可能会选择魔性的一面，他会自我封闭起来，用一种魔鬼的方式在心里说：“谢谢，我可不喜欢仪式和大惊小怪的忙乱，我也不是绝对需要爱的欢愉，我不妨做个喜欢看姑娘在新婚之夜死去的蓝胡子鬼怪。”人们一般很少听到人性中的魔性一面，尽管这个领域，尤其是在我们这个时代，是一个很需要探索的领域，尽管一个观察者，一旦他和魔鬼建立一定的和谐关系，就可以，至少在某些方面，用几乎任何人作为例子。对于这方面的探索，莎士比亚是个而且会永远是个英雄。那个可怕的魔鬼，莎士比亚所塑造的最具魔性的人物，而且是塑造得无与伦比的成功的人物，格罗斯特（后来又叫理查德三世），是什么东西使他成为魔鬼的？显而易见，是他不能忍受从小就堆积在他身上的同情这个事实使他成了魔鬼。他在《理查德三世》第一幕中的独白比所有道德体系都有价值，因为没有哪个道德体系暗示了存在的种种恐怖及这些恐怖的性质。

我，是上天随意制造的劣质品，

没有可以在漂亮的女子面前昂首阔步的外表，

我，被骗走了好看的身体和面容，甚至没有正常的比例，

我是畸形的，未发育好的，早产的，

我一瘸一拐如此难看，

以至于在我停下不走时，旁边的狗都对我吠叫……

像格罗斯特这样性格的人是不能靠使他们与社会观念相和谐来拯救的。伦理学实际上只会嘲笑他们，这正如，如果伦理学对撒拉说：“为什么你不表现出普遍性，像大家一样去结婚？”这是它在取笑她一样。这种本性的人从最初就处于悖论中，而且他们绝非不如他人完美；只是他们要么会在这魔性的悖论中受尽诅咒，要么会在神性的悖论中得到救赎。而从很久远的时候人们就喜欢认为，女巫、侏儒、妖怪等都是畸形的，而且不可否认，当我们看到一个丑陋畸形的人时，会倾向于把他的外表和道德败坏联系起来。但这是多么巨大的不公正啊！因为情况实际上应该正相反。是生活本身毁坏了他们，这就像继母使继子女堕落一样。从一开始就被置于普遍性之外，不管是先天的还是历史条件使然，这就是人的魔性的起源，而个体本身在这方面是无可责备的。所以，那个坎伯兰郡的犹太人，尽管他做善事，也是个身负魔性的人。因而，人性中的魔性一面也可以以对人的蔑视这种形式表现出来，请注意，这种蔑视，并不使一个人表现得很蔑视人；相反，他的长处在于他知道自己比所有评判自己的人要好—在所有这类事情上，诗人们应该是第一个作出反应，发出警报的人。只有上帝知道现在年轻一代的拙劣诗人在读些什么！毫无疑问他们的研究是局限于死记硬背那些韵文。只有老天知道他们存在的价值是什么！此刻我真不知道他们除了有教化意味地给我们提供关于灵魂不朽的证据以外，还有什么用处，以至于我们可以像巴格森说我们城里的诗人科德维一样安全地对他们作同样的评论：“如果他都可以永垂不朽的话，那么我们就都可以不朽。”以上所述的关于撒拉的一切，几乎是带着创造诗歌的风格而写的，因此实际上对人们只是有想象方面的吸引力，但是如果一个人出于对心理学的兴趣来探索以下这句古语的意思，就会明白上述关于撒拉的描述的全部意义：“没有一点疯狂，就没有伟大的天才。”[17]因为这儿的癫痴就是天才在生活中所要承受的痛苦，是神灵嫉妒的表现，如果我可以这么说的话，而天才的天赋则是神灵宠爱的表现。因而，天才从一开始就是找不到普遍性的方向的，从一开始就被置于悖论中，不论是他在对自己局限性的绝望中—在他看来，这局限性使他从全能变成无能—试图寻求一种魔性带来的自信，因此不会在上帝或人们面前承认这种局限性，还是通过对神灵的爱从宗教方面给自己以自信，他都处于这悖论中。在这里，有些心理学话题，在我看来，似乎可以供人开心地研究一辈子，然而我们却很少听到关于它们的讨论。比如说，疯狂和天才有什么关系？我们能从这二者中的一个构建出另一个吗？在何种意义和到何种程度上，天才能够控制自己的疯狂呢？因为不用说，在一定程度上他的确是自己疯狂状态的主人，否则的话他就真的是个疯子。但是，要作这样的评论需要有高度的独创性和爱心，因为要对优秀人物作评论是很困难的。如果一个人在对这种困难给予适当注意的情况下，去浏览某个极负盛名的天才作家的作品，可以想象得到，尽管需要很多努力，他可能会偶尔发现些什么。

关于个体想要通过隐藏和沉默来保全普遍性这一点，我想再探讨一个例子。为此，我将举《浮士德》传说这个例子。浮士德是一个怀疑者，[18]一个走向死亡的精神方面的变节者。这就是诗人们如何看待这个传说的，而且，尽管每个时代都有自己的浮士德这一点被一再重复，诗人们依然一个接一个固执地沿着相同的老路走下去。让我们作一点小改变吧。浮士德是一个杰出的怀疑者；但是他有同情的本性。即便在歌德对浮士德的诠释中，我也找不到对怀疑与自己进行秘密对话的心理学角度的更深的见解。在我们这个时代，当每个人都确实经历过怀疑时，却还没有哪个诗人往此方向迈出一步。所以我想我愿意给他们提供皇家证券，让他们在上面写下他们在此方面的“所有”经历—因为他们所写的不可能超过左页边的空白那么点儿地方。

只有当人们这样把浮士德转向他自身时，那时怀疑才能显得有诗意，也只有那时他自己才真正地发现怀疑的所有痛苦。那么，他就知道了是精神在支撑着生活，但他也知道了人们生活中的安全感和快乐并不是由精神的力量所支持的，而是可以很容易地被解释为不思考的幸福。作为一个怀疑者，他是超越这一切的，如果有人想骗他，使他认为自己已经超越了怀疑，他会很容易看穿这欺骗。一个已经在精神世界作修行运动的人，因而也是作了无限运动修行的人，他可以从言辞立即判断出说话者是一个经历丰富的人还是个擅长讲故事的闵希豪生。帖木尔能够用他的匈奴人所做的事，浮士德可以用他的怀疑做到—吓得人们惊慌失措，使他们脚下的世界摇晃颤抖，惊得人们四散逃跑，引得四面八方都传来惊恐的尖叫。如果他那样做了，他依然不是帖木尔，因为有思想的授权，他在某种意义上有权这样做。但是浮士德有同情的本性，他热爱生活，他的灵魂不懂得妒忌，他看到自己无法控制那无疑已引发的山崩似的愤怒，他并不渴望赫洛斯特拉托斯[19]式的荣誉—他保持沉默，他比那隐藏腹中有罪的爱情之果的姑娘更小心翼翼地把怀疑在灵魂中隐藏着，他竭尽全力与别的人步伐一致，但是他内心里所发生的事则自己在内心把它毁灭掉，这样，他就把自己变成了普遍性的牺牲品。

有时，当有些古怪反常之人掀起怀疑的旋风，我们会听到这样的抱怨：“要是他保持沉默多好。”浮士德也代表了这一想法。任何了解靠精神生活意味着什么的人也明白对怀疑的饥饿意味着什么，明白怀疑者对精神食粮的饥饿就像对每天要吃的面包的渴望一样强烈。尽管浮士德所承受的所有痛苦都可能很好地证明了他并不受骄傲的控制，但我仍然要采用一个我很容易想出的预防策略。正如里米尼的格里高利因为支持对婴儿的诅咒而被叫作婴儿折磨者一样，我也很想叫我自己为英雄折磨者，因为当涉及折磨英雄时，我是很有发明创造性的。浮士德看见玛格丽特—不是在他已选择了人生的欢愉之后，因为我的浮士德绝不选择欢愉—他不是在靡菲斯特那个魔鬼的凹面镜中见到玛格丽特，而是在她最纯真可爱最冰清玉洁的时候，因为他的心中保持着对人类的爱，所以他可以很轻易地就爱上了她。但是他是个怀疑者，他的怀疑已经毁了他的现实。因为我的浮士德是如此理想化的一个人，他不是那种科学的怀疑者；这些科学的怀疑者每学期在讲台上进行一个小时的怀疑，但是在其他时间可以做任何别的事情，而当他们的确在怀疑时，也没有靠精神的帮助或靠精神的力量。他是一个怀疑者，而怀疑者对精神营养的渴望和对每天的面包的渴望是一样的。但是他仍然忠于自己的决定，保持沉默，他不对任何人说起自己的怀疑，甚至也没有对玛格丽特说起他对她的爱。

不用说，浮士德是一个太过于理想化的人，以至于不能满足于下述的这种闲聊，即，如果他发言的时候，仅仅引起了一场普通的讨论，或者整件事毫无结果，不了了之，等等诸如此类的闲聊。（这里，显而易见，任何诗人都会看出，我们的剧情里潜藏着滑稽成分，这滑稽成分就是把浮士德与我们这个时代的那些追求怀疑的低俗小丑相提并论所体现的讽刺性。那些低俗小丑往往追求怀疑，却用的是表面论据。比如，一个医生的学历证书这样一个事物，为了证明他们真的怀疑了，或者为了发誓他们已怀疑了一切，或者为了通过他们在路上碰见了一个怀疑者这个事实来证明它—这些精神世界的快递员和短跑能手匆忙地从这个人这儿得来一点关于怀疑的暗示，又从那个人那儿搜集到一些关于信仰的线索，然后就根据会众想要细沙还是爱好粗沙去尽力发挥利用那些信息。）浮士德太理想化了，而不能穿着拖鞋四处走动。任何缺乏无限激情的人，都不是追求理想主义的人，而任何真正怀有无限激情的人早已将灵魂脱离了这样的垃圾废话。他保持沉默以牺牲自己—否则他就开口谈论，同时很清楚自己的谈论会将一切都变成困惑。

他保持沉默，因此伦理学谴责他。它说：“你必须承认普遍性，而且你必须把你承认普遍性这一点说出来，你不准同情普遍性。”当我们有时严厉地评判一个怀疑者的言辞时，不应该忘了这一点。我自己并不倾向于宽和地评判这种行为，但像所有情况一样，这一切取决于那些运动是否正常进行。如果事情出了差错，那么怀疑者，尽管因说出怀疑而给世界带来各种不幸，依然比这些可怜的喜好甜食之士要好得多，这些人每样都尝试，但每样都浅尝辄止，他们还没有弄懂怀疑就已打消怀疑，因此他们通常是无法驾驭无法管理的怀疑之所以爆发的直接原因—如果怀疑者一旦说话，他就使人对一切迷惑，把一切抛入混乱状态，因为如果这并没有发生，他也只是事后才发现，而后果在一个人行动时或在其责任问题上并没有什么用。

如果他在自担风险的情况下保持沉默，他可能真的会高尚地行事，但是，他同时又给他的其他痛苦增加了一些诱惑考验。普遍性会永远在折磨他，永远在对他说：“你本应该说出来的，你怎么能确定终究不是某种隐秘的骄傲促使你作出保持沉默的决定？”

但是，如果怀疑者可以作为特别的单一个体与绝对者处于绝对关系中，那么，他就获得了保持沉默的授权。但是那样的话，他就必须把怀疑转变成内疚。因此他就处于悖论中。但是那样，他就治愈了怀疑，尽管他可能又会有另一个怀疑。

就连《新约全书》也赞同这样的沉默。该书中有些篇章甚至赞美讽刺，只要讽刺是被用于隐藏好的一面。然而，这只是一种讽刺活动，它和其他一些活动一样，都是以主观性高于现实为基础的。如今没有人想知道这一点；关于讽刺，人们一般只想知道黑格尔所说的，尽管奇怪的是，黑格尔对此所知甚少，甚至还带有一点怨恨地反对它，但这一点，我们这个时代有理由不放弃，因为它最好要警惕讽刺。在登山宝训里有这样的话：“当你禁食的时候，要往头上涂油梳头，要洗脸，不要让人看出来你在禁食。”这段话清楚地表明了这样的真理，即，主观性与现实是不可通约不可比较的，甚至表明了主观性有欺骗的权利。如今那些四处游荡含糊不清地谈论教会思想的人，只要读一读《新约全书》，就可能会产生别的思想。

但是，现在让我们再回到亚伯拉罕—他是如何做的？因为我还没有忘记，读者也许也乐意记起，这就是我前面所有讨论的意图所在。不是为了借此使亚伯拉罕更令人容易理解，而是为了使他的令人费解显得更全面。因为，正如我前面所说的，我无法理解亚伯拉罕，我只能崇拜他。我也提到过，我所描述的所有阶段没有一个含有对亚伯拉罕的类比，我之所以详细论述它们，只是为了从它们自己领域的角度表明，它们与亚伯拉罕情况的差异之处就如同未知陆地的界限。它们和亚伯拉罕的情况之间如果有类比的话，那一定是在关于罪的悖论中，但这又属于另一个领域，因而不能解释亚伯拉罕，而且，解释它本身比解释亚伯拉罕要容易得多。

因此，亚伯拉罕没有说出隐情，他既没有对撒拉和以利亚撒说，也没有对以撒说，他越过了这三个伦理权威，因为，对亚伯拉罕而言，对伦理的表达并不高于对家庭生活的表达。

然而，在一个人知道自己靠保持沉默可以救助另一个人的情况下，美学是允许，实际上是要求这个人保持沉默的，这就已足以证明亚伯拉罕不处于美学的范围内。他的沉默绝不是表示他有救以撒的意图，从总体而言，他为了自己和上帝而牺牲以撒的整项任务就是对美学的冒犯，因为美学可以轻易理解我牺牲自己，但理解不了我为了自己而牺牲另一个人。美学意义上的英雄是沉默的英雄。然而，伦理学则谴责他，因为他是靠偶然的个性来保持沉默的。是他作为人的预知先见使他决定自己应该保持沉默。这却是伦理学所不能原谅的。因为人的所有这样的知识都只是一种幻觉。而伦理学要求一种无限运动，即要求显露自我，要求公开。所以，美学意义上的英雄可以说出隐情但不会这样做。

真正的悲剧英雄为了普遍性牺牲自己和自己的一切，他的行为和所有情感都属于普遍性，他是显露的、公开的，在这种自我开示中他是伦理学的宠儿。而这并不符合亚伯拉罕的情况：他不为普遍性做任何事，而且他是隐蔽自我的。

现在，我们该说说这悖论了。要么个人作为个体能与绝对者处于绝对关系中（那样的话，伦理的东西就不是至高无上的），要么亚伯拉罕就输了—他既不是一个悲剧英雄，也不是一个美学英雄。

这里，悖论可能看起来是一切中最容易最方便的事了。但是，我必须重申，任何对此深信不疑的人都不是信仰骑士，因为不幸和痛苦是唯一可以想象得到的合理理由，而且不能从一般意义上去想象它们，因为如果那样的话，悖论就不存在了。

亚伯拉罕保持沉默，但是他不能说出来，这沉默中存在着不幸与痛苦。因为如果我开口说了，却不能使自己被理解，那么即便我日夜不停地说，也等于我没说。这就是亚伯拉罕的处境。他可以说他想说的任何事情，但是有一件事他不能说，而既然他不能说，也就是说，不能以一种别人能理解的方式来说，那么他就不说。讲话带给人的慰藉就是它可以把我转变成合乎普遍性的人。现在亚伯拉罕可以说任何语言所能表达的关于他如何爱以撒的话。但是这不是他脑子里所想的事，他所想的是更深刻的事，即他要献祭以撒，因为那是个考验。没有人可以理解后者，因此每个人只能误解前者。这种悲痛是悲剧英雄根本不知道的。因为首先，悲剧英雄有这样的慰藉：一切反对观点都得到了适当的考虑，他也给了每个人反驳他的机会，这些包括克吕泰墨斯特拉、依菲琴尼亚、阿基里斯、合唱团、每个活着的生命，每种发自内心的声音，每种聪明的、惊慌的、控诉的、同情的人的想法。他可以确定每种可以说出来反对他的话都已经被说出来了，都已被严厉无情地说出来了—相比之下，与整个世界抗争是一种舒服的事，与自己作斗争才是可怕的事。他不必担心自己忽视了什么，以致事后会像爱德华四世在得知克拉伦斯的死讯时那样惊呼：

谁向我替他求情？谁在我盛怒之时，

跪在我脚下，请我听从建议？

谁说到了兄弟之情？谁说到了爱？

悲剧英雄不知道孤独的可怕责任。其次，他还有可以与克吕泰墨斯特拉、依菲琴尼亚一同哭泣和哀悼的慰藉—眼泪和哭泣有平息缓和的作用，但是，无可言说的叹息才是折磨。阿伽门农可以快速地集中精神，确定自己要行动，而且他有时间去安慰和宽慰别人。亚伯拉罕却是不能这样做的。当他的心被打动了，当他的话可以对全世界表达宽慰的时候，他却不敢提供宽慰，因为难道撒拉、以利亚撒和以撒不会对他说：“你为什么想要这么做？你毕竟是可以克制自己，不那样做的呀。”如果他在悲痛之中，在他迈出最后一步之前，他想释放情感的重压，拥抱他所珍爱的一切，那么这可能会产生最可怕的后果，即撒拉、以利亚撒和以撒会生他的气，并认为他是个伪君子。他不能说什么，人类的语言无以表达他的思想和情绪。尽管他自己懂得世上所有的语言，尽管他所爱之人也理解这些语言，他依然不能说什么，他说的是一种神圣的语言—他“用不止一个舌头说”。

我非常理解这种痛苦。我钦佩亚伯拉罕。我不担心有人会受这个故事诱惑而不负责任地想要成为那种独一无二的个体。但我也坦率承认，我自己缺乏那样做的勇气，而且，尽管不管在多晚的后来，我要是有可能走那么远，我都乐意放弃更进一步的可能。亚伯拉罕时刻都可以阻止自己，他可以为这作为诱惑的整件事感到后悔。那样，他就可以说了，那样，每个人都会理解他了，但那样他就不再是亚伯拉罕了。

亚伯拉罕不能说。本可以解释一切的话，即它是一场考验—不过，请注意，一场以伦理为诱惑的考验—却是他不能说的话（即无法以一种能使自己被理解的方式来说）。任何身处此境的人都是出自普遍性领域的移民。然而，下一步的事是他更加不能言说的。因为，正如前面已说得很清楚的那样，亚伯拉罕作的是两种运动。他作无限弃绝的运动，并放弃了以撒，因为这是一件私事，所以没有人可以理解。但接着他作的，而且每时每刻都在作的是，信仰运动。这是他的欣慰之处。因为他说：“不过它不会发生，或者如果它发生的话，主会凭借荒诞赐予我一个新的以撒的。”悲剧英雄至少最终知道故事的结尾。依菲琴尼亚听从父亲的决定，她自己作了无限弃绝运动，然后他们达成了一种相互理解。她能理解阿伽门农，因为他所做的事表现普遍性。而如果阿伽门农对她说“尽管神要求把你作为祭品献祭，但凭借荒诞我认为，他也可能并没有索要你”，那么他会立即变得令她无法理解。如果他能靠人的正常推算这样说，那么依菲琴尼亚肯定会理解他。但那就会意味着阿伽门农并没有作无限弃绝运动，那么他就不是一个英雄，而那预言家的话也就不过是一个旅行家的奇闻，整件事情也就变成了一场轻松的歌舞剧。

所以亚伯拉罕没有说什么。他所说的唯一一句话被保留了下来，即他对以撒的唯一回答，这也足以证明他先前没有说什么。以撒问亚伯拉罕供燔祭的羔羊在哪里。“亚伯拉罕说：我的儿子，上帝会为自己提供燔祭的羔羊的。”

这里我要更仔细地思考亚伯拉罕这最后的话。如果没有这句话，整件事就会缺点什么。而如果这句话有所不同，一切就可能陷入混乱。

我经常思考这样一个问题，不管一个悲剧英雄的最终是痛苦还是行动，他是否应该有一句最终的结语呢？在我看来，这取决于他属于哪个生活领域，取决于他的生活有何等程度的思想意义，取决于他的痛苦或行为在多大程度上与精神相关。

不用说，在最后高潮时刻，悲剧英雄，像别人一样，是能够说一些话的，甚至是一些恰当的话。但问题是，他说这些话这个行为是否适宜。如果他生活的意义在于一种外在的行为，那么，他没有什么可说的，因为他所说的一切都只是闲谈，它只能削弱他所产生的影响力，而相反，悲剧的仪式则要求他不管是在行动方面，还是在痛苦方面，都要在沉默中完成他的任务。为了不扯远离题，我干脆用我们最直接最贴切的例子。如果阿伽门农他自己，而不是卡尔克斯那个随军预言家，不得不对依菲琴尼亚拔刀相向，他若在最后时刻想说出一些话，只会降低自己的人格，贬损自己的形象。每个人都知道他的行为的意义，虔诚、同情、情感，以及流泪等整个过程也完成了，而且，他的生活与精神无关，即，他既非精神导师，也不是精神见证者。然而，如果悲剧英雄生活的意义在于精神方面，那么最终话语的缺乏则会削弱他的影响力。他最后应该说的不是某种适宜的话，不是一点雄辩的华丽言辞，而是某种能够传达这样的信息的话：在关键时刻，他圆满完成了自己。这种知性的悲剧英雄应该允许自己有可笑的人们经常追求的东西，即应当有最后的话并且保留下来。我们期待他有任何其他悲剧英雄所有的同样的高贵举止，但此外，我们还期待某句话。所以，如果一位知性的悲剧英雄在痛苦（死亡）中完成了他的英雄主义，那么靠他所说的最后话语将使他在死亡之前就已经永垂不朽，而普通悲剧英雄则只有在死后才永垂不朽。

我们可以以苏格拉底为例。他就是一位智慧的知性的悲剧英雄。他听说了自己的死刑。听到的那一刻他死了。如果你不能领会死亡需要所有的精神力量来完成，不能理解英雄总是在死亡之前就已死去，你在对人生的认识方面就不会走得很深远。因此，作为英雄，苏格拉底被要求保持镇定自若，但是作为有知识的英雄，他则被要求在最后时刻有足够的精神力量去圆满地实现自我。所以，他不能像普通悲剧英雄那样，在最后时刻专注于使自己直面死亡；他必须非常迅速地作此运动，以至于在同一时刻，他已经有意识地超越了这种斗争，转而去继续展示自我。要是苏格拉底在死亡的危急时刻沉默不语，他就会削弱自己人生的影响，而且使人疑心讽刺的弹力在他身上并不是一种原本自然的宇宙性的力量，而只是一种游戏，该游戏的弹性是他在关键时刻要根据相反标准来利用的，以使他悲惨寒酸地支撑下去。[20]

如果有人认为可以通过类比为亚伯拉罕找到适宜的话来在最后时刻说，那么其实我在前面所简短讨论的并不适用于亚伯拉罕；但如果有人认为，鉴于亚伯拉罕作为信仰之父在精神方面有着绝对的意义，他有必要在最后时刻通过说点什么，而不是通过对以撒拔刀，来展示自我的信仰，那么，我上述的讨论还是适用的。至于他说什么，我是无法预先有什么概念的。但他说了之后，我肯定会理解它，不过只是在某种意义上从他的话理解他，我并不能借此比先前更接近他。如果我们没有从苏格拉底那里得到最后之言，我可能可以设身处地为他编一句，而要是我自己做不到这一点，诗人也会做到的。但是没有哪个诗人可以跟上亚伯拉罕，解读亚伯拉罕。

在我继续仔细思考亚伯拉罕的最后之语之前，我必须请大家注意到亚伯拉罕说这最后之语的困难。如前所述，这悖论里的不幸与痛苦就在于这沉默—亚伯拉罕不能说什么。[21]鉴于这一点，要求他说话就是一种自我矛盾，除非我们想让他又脱离那个悖论，即在最后时刻，他中止悖论，因此他也不再是亚伯拉罕，而且会前功尽弃。要是亚伯拉罕在关键时刻对以撒说“是你将被献祭”，这就只会是个弱点。因为如果他可以说的话，他早就应该说了，这种情况的缺点在于他缺乏将整个过程的痛苦都想全想透的精神上的成熟度和专注力，而且他将其中的某些痛苦搁置一边，以致他实际上经历的痛苦超过了他想到的痛苦。而且，他这样的言辞会使他脱离悖论，如果他真想对以撒说的话，他必须得把自己的处境转变成精神诱惑那种处境。否则，他终究是什么也不能说，而如果他那样做的话，他就会连悲剧英雄也不是了。

然而，不管怎样，亚伯拉罕最后的话被保留了下来，只要我能理解那悖论，我就也可以理解亚伯拉罕的整个存在在那句话里的体现。首先，他什么也没有说，他就是以这种方式来说自己不得不说的话。他对以撒的回答具有讽刺的形式，因为说了某些话而又什么也没说，总是一种具有讽刺性的事。以撒问亚伯拉罕是因为他推测亚伯拉罕知道。所以如果亚伯拉罕回答说“我什么也不知道”，他说的就不是真话。他不能说什么，因为他所知道的他不能说。所以他回答说：“我的儿子，上帝自己会准备羔羊做燔祭品。”这里，我们看到了前面所描述的亚伯拉罕灵魂中所进行的双重运动。要是亚伯拉罕仅仅是放弃了以撒，不再做什么，他就会在这最后的话中不说真话。因为他知道是上帝要求献祭以撒，而且他知道就在此刻自己准备好了献祭他。所以我们可以看出，亚伯拉罕在作了这一运动之后，就已时刻不停地进行下一运动了，即依靠荒诞作信仰运动。因此他没有讲假话，因为凭借荒诞，上帝毕竟还是有可能做出相当不同的事来的。尽管他没有说假话，但他也没说什么，因为他说的是外国话。当我们考虑到是亚伯拉罕自己将献祭以撒，这一点就更加显而易见。要是任务有所不同，要是主命令亚伯拉罕将以撒带到摩利亚山，以便用自己的闪电击中以撒，用那种方式收他做祭品，那么，就亚伯拉罕所说的话的直接意义上来说，他那样神秘莫测地说话就可能是对的，因为，在那种情况下，他自己也不会知道会发生什么事情。但是，因为那任务是派给亚伯拉罕的，是他自己必须行动，所以他必须知道在关键时刻他将做什么，因而也必须知道以撒将要被献祭。如果他并不是清楚确定地知道这一切，他就没有作那无限弃绝运动，这样的话，他说的话就的确不是假的。但同时他也就远非真正的亚伯拉罕，他都不如悲剧英雄伟大，实际上，他就成了一个不能对任何事作决定的优柔寡断的人，因此也就会永远说话跟打谜语一样令人费解。但这样的踌躇犹豫者纯粹是对信仰骑士的拙劣模仿，犹如东施效颦一般。

显然，人们又似乎理解了亚伯拉罕，但只能以理解那个悖论的方式理解他。至于我个人，我在某种程度上可以理解亚伯拉罕，但同时我也清楚地意识到我缺乏说的勇气，同样也缺乏像他那样行动的勇气。但我绝不是据此说他所做的是微不足道的，因为正相反，他所做的是绝无仅有的奇迹。

那么，悲剧英雄的同时代人怎么看悲剧英雄？他们认为他是伟大的，他们钦佩他、景仰他。而那可敬的高尚者的集合体，即每代人指派的对上一代人作评判的陪审团，也都达成了相同的裁决。但是没有人可以理解亚伯拉罕。可是想想他的成就！他坚持忠实于他之所爱。但是热爱上帝的人不需要眼泪，也不需要景仰，他在爱中忘记了苦难，而且忘记得非常彻底，以至于事后倘若上帝自己没有记起它，他的痛苦就没有一点儿痕迹了。而上帝是秘密看着的，他知道亚伯拉罕所受的苦痛，数着他流过的泪滴，而且什么也不会忘记。

所以说，要么存在着这样一个悖论，即作为独特个体的个人与绝对者处于一种绝对关系中，要么亚伯拉罕丧失了（他的伟大）。

后记

从前，在荷兰，调味品香料市场价格一度低迷，商人们为了抬高价格让人把几船货物倒入海中。那是一种可以原谅的，也许是必要的欺骗策略。在精神世界是否也需要类似这样的策略？我们真的如此深信我们已经达到了最高点，以至于除了虔诚地相信我们还没有走那么远，还没有达到那高度，以便我们至少有可以消磨时间的东西以外，就没有剩下可以做的事了吗？这是否是现代人所需要的一种自我欺骗？这代人是否应该在自我欺骗的精湛技巧方面受到教育和培训？又或者，难道说这个时代在自我欺骗之术上不是已然精于此道了？又或者说难道它最需要的不是那种无畏而又刚正廉洁地唤起人们注意任务的诚挚精神—这种诚挚精神小心地保护着任务，它不是把人们吓得想要仓促冲向那最高的任务要去完成它，而是使任务令所有人看起来年轻美丽而迷人，但同时又很难，对高尚之人是一种激励，既然本性高尚之人的热情只会受到困难的激励？不管一代人会从另一代人那里学到什么，他们绝无法从前辈身上学到那种真正的人性因素。在这一方面，每一代人都重新开始，和前一代人有着相同的任务，但也不会超越前一代人，如果后一代人没有躲避自己的任务，自欺欺人的话。这种真正的人性因素就是激情，在这种激情中，一代人完全理解另一代人，也理解自己。因而没有哪代人从另一代人那里学会了如何去爱，每一代人都要从头开始，后代的任务绝不比前一代的少，而如果某个人不愿意像前辈们那样止步于爱，而想要更进一步，走得更远，那么那纯粹是愚蠢无聊之谈。

但是，一个人的最高激情是信仰。在这方面，没有哪代人和前一代人有什么不同的起点。每代人都完全重新开始，而后代也不会超越前代，如果后者忠于自己的使命而没有背叛它。这听起来让人觉得厌倦是这代人不能说的话，因为的确是这代人要完成这任务，而这与前一代人有相同的任务这一事实是无关的，除非某个特别的一代或这一代人里某些特别的个人极为自大，以至于占据了只属于统治万物的神灵的位置，而神灵又有足够的忍耐心不厌烦此事。如果这代人开始做这类的事情，那就是反常错误的，那么，对此而言一切存在都是颠倒的，这就不足为奇了，因为肯定谁也没有童话故事里的那个裁缝所看到的世界更颠倒了—那裁缝在他一生中曾来到天堂，从天堂的位置俯瞰这世界。如果这一代人只关注自己的任务使命，一代人所能追求的至高无上的使命，那么他们就不会感到厌倦，因为这任务对一个人一辈子总是足够了。当假日里的孩子在中午之前玩遍了所有游戏，然后不耐烦地问：“没有人能想出新的游戏吗？”这是否说明他们比同时代或前一代的能持续一整天玩自己熟悉的游戏的孩子们要更成熟更先进呢？又或者这恰恰证明这些孩子缺乏我想称之为玩游戏时本来应有的认真精神？

信仰是一个人身上至高无上的激情。每一代人中的很多人可能都走不到信仰那么高那么远的境界，但没有一个人走得更远，没有人超越信仰。在我们这个时代是否有很多人没有发现这一点，对此我暂不作出结论。我只能参考我自己的经历，我不隐瞒自己在信任方面还有很长的路要走这一事实，但也不因此想要通过把信仰描述得很平凡很没有意义，描述得像人们希望尽快结束的童年的一场小病那样，来自欺欺人或背叛信仰这伟大之事。但是即便是对那没有达到信仰境界的人而言，生活也有足够的任务，而当他热爱这些任务时，生活也绝不会被虚度，尽管这样的生活与那种理解和抓住了最伟大的事的生活是不可比拟的。但是任何到达信仰的人（不管是天赋非凡者还是头脑简单者都一样）都不会停在那儿原地不动。要是有人说他止步于信仰，他甚至会大为惊讶，就像若有人说一个恋人在爱情上停滞不前，那个恋人会感到义愤一样，因为那恋人会回答说：“我绝不是在我的爱情中静止不动，我的整个生命都在这爱情中。”然而他也是不会走得更远，也不会走向别处。因为当他发现这一点时，他对此会有另一个不同的解释。

“人必须更进一步，人必须更进一步。”这种继续向前的需要和冲动是自古以来就有的。以“晦涩”闻名的希腊哲学家赫拉克利特把他的思想保存于他的著作中，把他的著作存放于戴安娜神庙中（因为他的思想是他生命的盔甲，因此他将它们悬挂于女神之庙中），晦涩的赫拉克利特说：“人绝不可能两次踏入同一条河流。”[22]赫拉克利特有一个弟子，他没有止步于此，而是更进一步说：“人甚至一次也不能踏进同一条河流。”[23]可怜的赫拉克利特竟有这样的一个弟子！该弟子这一改进把赫拉克利特的原理变成了否定运动的埃利亚学派的论点，而那弟子想要做的只是做一个走得更远的赫拉克利特的徒弟，而不是回到赫拉克利特已经抛弃的观点上。

[1]过去人们说：“可惜的是，世上事并不像传教士所布道宣讲的那样。”但是有一天我们能够说：“世间事不像传教士所讲的那样是多么幸运啊，因为生活中至少有些意义，而说教布道里则毫无意义。”我们说这样的话的那一刻可能会到来，尤其是在哲学的帮助下。

[2]即献祭以撒之事。——译者注

[3]当然，任何其他的个人倾注了全部身心想要实现却不能实现的兴趣点都可以引起无限弃绝运动。但我选择了恋爱故事来作例子，是因为这样的兴趣无疑很容易理解，因而我就不必说些很少有人会切实感兴趣的介绍性的话了。

[4]这要求激情。一切具有无限性的运动都是靠激情发生的。反思不能产生运动。是生活中持续不断的跳跃解释了什么是运动，而中间调停不过是一种虚拟的幻想，它是黑格尔认为可以解释一切的东西，同时又是黑格尔唯一从不曾解释的东西。甚至要明白人们所熟知的苏格拉底作的理解和不理解之间的划分也需要激情；自然，要作真正的苏格拉底似的运动，即无知的运动，则更需要激情。我们今天所缺乏的正是激情，而不是反思。因此，从某种意义上讲，我们这个时代的人太固执于生命而不愿死去，因为去死是最非凡的跳跃之一。有一段诗文总是很吸引我，作者在用五六句诗表达了自己对生活中所有简单而美好的事物的愿望后，以这样一句作了结尾：跳入永恒是一种幸福。

[5]即，作了此类解释还指望别人钦佩的人也不算是最糟糕的自以为是者。——译者注

[6]莱辛曾在某文章中从纯美学的视角说过类似的话。在该文章中，他实际上想表明悲伤也能通过智慧的话语来表达。为此，莱辛引用了不幸的英国国王爱德华二世在某个特别场合所说的话。作为对比，他还引用了狄德罗写的一个农妇的故事和该农妇所说的话。他接着写道：“那也是机智，而且还是农妇的机智，当然，那是情势所迫产生的。因此人们不应该从说话者是优秀的人，是受过良好教育的、智商高的和风趣的这样的事实中为那痛苦和悲伤的机智的表达找借口，因为激情使人人再次平等……对此我们可以找到的解释是，在同样的情况下，很可能人人都会说出同样的话来。那个农妇的思想很可能是王后在那情境下也会说的，正如那国王在那个场合所说的话，一个农民当时也能并且无疑也会说出来。”

[7]这里我要再次解释悲剧英雄和信仰骑士所遇到的冲突的区别。悲剧英雄可以凭借他把伦理义务转变成一个愿望这一事实来确信自己身上还完全存有（对儿子、女儿等的）伦理义务。因而阿伽门农可以说：这就是我没有违反我作为父亲的义务的证据，也就是，我（对依菲琴尼亚）的义务是我唯一的愿望。那么，这里，我们看到愿望和义务彼此相一致。如果我的愿望正好与我的义务一致，或者我的义务和我的愿望相符合，我的命运该多好啊；大多数人的生活使命就是完全忠实于自己的义务，并且凭激情把义务转换成自己的愿望。悲剧英雄为了履行义务而放弃愿望。对信仰骑士而言，义务和愿望也是完全相同的，但是却被要求两者都放弃。所以当他顺从地放弃愿望时，他找不到安宁，因为他放弃的毕竟是他的义务。如果他既忠实于义务，又忠实于愿望，那他就不会变成信仰骑士，因为绝对的义务恰恰要求他放弃二者（他的愿望和义务相同）。悲剧英雄获得的是对义务，但不是绝对的义务的更高等的表达。

[8]即上帝。——译者注

[9]公开透露被隐藏的秘密。——译者注

[10]这些运动和立场也是可以从美学的角度处理的话题。但是从美学角度对信仰和追求信仰的生活进行讨论可以达到何种程度，我暂且不下结论。因为我总是喜欢感谢那些对我有帮助的人，在此我谨表达一下我对莱辛的感激，因为我从他在《汉堡剧评》中写的一个基督教戏剧里得到了一些启示。但是他着重写的是那种生活的纯神性的一面（完美胜利），因此他感到绝望。如果他更关注那种生活的人性的一面，也许他会得出不同的结论（旅人神学）。的确，他所说的很简要，有些部分还有些含糊难以捉摸，但是我见到莱辛的作品总是很开心，所以我立即抓住这机会好好研读。莱辛不仅是德国最博学的智者之一，他治学严谨准确，这样我们在引用他的作品时，可以很放心，不用担心用了不可靠汇编里不准确或捏造的引用，一知半解的语句，或者担心宣传他写的什么新颖的东西而又发现那其实是古人早已描述得更好的东西，因此感到吃惊和受到愚弄；此外，他还有一种非凡的天赋，就是善于解释他所理解的东西。而且仅此而已，他不会解释自己不理解的东西。现在的人们经常更进一步，还要解释自己不懂的东西。

[11]根据亚里士多德所说，该灾难的经过如下：为了复仇，新娘家人把一个神庙花瓶放置到新郎家里的家庭用品中，这样新郎就被谴责为神庙强盗。但这并不重要，因为这里的问题不是新娘家人在报复时所采用的方法是聪明还是愚蠢，这娘家人的存在只是因其对英雄的辩证学有影响才有了理论上的意义。而且，尽管新郎想通过不结婚来避免危险，结果却反而正好陷入危险中，这一事实就够宿命的了；而他的生活从两重意义上与神圣者形成了联系，一重是通过占卜师所说的话，另一重是通过被谴责为神庙盗贼，这一事实也是很宿命的。

[12]在此，我们可以从另一个方向来进行辩证分析运动。上天预言了一场因婚姻而起的个人灾难，所以他不妨放弃婚姻但不必因此放弃那姑娘，他可以和她处于一种浪漫关系中，这也会很令恋人们满意的。然而，这样做对那姑娘是一种侮辱，因为他没有用普遍性[即婚姻。——译者注]来表达他对她的爱，而诗人和伦理学家的任务都是捍卫婚姻。从整体而言，如果诗歌要注意分析它的人物角色的宗教方面和内在情感，它可以驾驭比它现在所忙于的主题更重大的主题。以下就是诗歌反复给我们讲述的故事：一男子为他曾爱过的或者从未真正爱过的女孩所困，因为他现在已经视另一个女孩为理想爱人。人在生活中犯错误，这街道是对的，但房屋错了，因为理想爱人就住在街对面二楼—这就是人们所认为的合适的诗歌话题。一个恋人犯了错误，他借着烛光看见了喜爱之人，以为她长着黑色头发，但是瞧，仔细看，她是金发—然而，她的姐姐才是理想爱人。这就是人们所认为的诗歌的主题。在我看来，任何这样的人在现实生活中是令人无法忍受的无礼蠢人，他一旦试图摆诗歌的架子就应该立即被嘘下舞台。只有激情与激情的碰撞才构成诗歌里的冲突，而同一激情里的关于细节琐事的喧闹则不能形成诗意的碰撞。举个例子，在中世纪，当一个女孩坠入情网，但接着被说服，认为世俗爱情是一种罪，因而喜欢天国爱情，这样我们就有了诗意的冲突；而这女孩也是富于诗意的，因为她生活在理想之中。

[13]其实，还有探讨这个传说的另一种方式。那人鱼不想引诱艾格尼丝，尽管之前他已引诱了很多姑娘。他不再是个人鱼，或者，如果你愿意叫他为人鱼的话，他是个可怜的人鱼，已经悲伤地坐在海底有一段时间了。不过，他知道（正如传说里讲的）一个纯真姑娘的爱可以拯救自己。但是他对姑娘们感到良心不安，不敢接近她们。后来，他看见了艾格尼丝。当他隐身于芦苇中时，他已多次看到她在海滩上行走。她的美，她的安静与泰然自若征服了他；但是他的灵魂充满了悲伤，心中没有了汹涌的欲望。当人鱼的叹息和芦苇的飒飒声融为一体时，她侧耳倾听，然后她一动不动，陷入幻想梦境之中。她比任何女人都迷人，而且像一个美丽的拯救天使一样给了他信心。人鱼鼓起勇气，走近艾格尼丝，赢得了她的爱，他希望因此得到救赎。但是，艾格尼丝可不是个安静的姑娘，实际上她很喜欢大海的咆哮，当时海边的悲叹声之所以使她喜欢是因为这悲叹声使她心中的咆哮更加猛烈。她愿意和她所爱的人鱼远走他乡，狂野地奔向那无穷无限之处，所以她故意怂恿煽动人鱼。她蔑视他的谦恭，于是他的骄傲自尊醒了。大海咆哮着，浪涛澎湃，人鱼抱住艾格尼丝跳进大海深处。他从未如此狂野，也从未如此满怀欲望，因为他希望借助这个姑娘得到解救。不久，他厌倦了艾格尼丝，但是她的尸体从未被发现，因为她已变成了一条美人鱼，她用她的歌声引诱男人。

[14]有时美学用它通常的卖弄方式来探讨类似的主题。那人鱼通过艾格尼丝得救，他们结婚了，一切皆大欢喜。那是个幸福的婚姻！确实，这样处理十分方便容易。但是，如果要伦理学来发表婚礼致辞的话，我想，就会是不同的情形了。美学给人鱼披上爱的外衣，这样一切都被忘记了。认为婚礼上的事就像拍卖，一切都按它在落锤时的样子来决定，那也是够轻率鲁莽的。美学所关心的是恋人们得到彼此，其余的都无关紧要。要是它能够看到事后会发生什么就好了！但是它没有时间关心那个，它立马又全力以赴在撮合另一对恋人了。在所有科学分支中，美学是最没有信仰的。任何真正爱美学的人在某种意义上都变得不快乐；而任何从未爱过美学的人是而且永远是个牲畜（或傻子）。

[15]截至目前，我一直小心地避免讨论罪及其现实问题。一切讨论都以亚伯拉罕为中心，而对他我们仍然可以在直接的范畴里进行讨论，至少在我自己可以对他进行理解的范围内讨论。但是一旦罪这个因素出现，伦理学就因悔悟这个问题而遭受挫败。悔悟是伦理的最高表现形式，但正因为此原因，它也是伦理最深刻的自我矛盾之处。

[16]我们这个严肃的时代不相信这个，然而，值得注意的是，即便是在异教信仰中，更随和的和不那么沉溺于反思的，这两个作为希腊存在概念里“了解自己”的典型代表，都用自己的方式暗示，如果一个人探索自己的内心深处，他首先发现的是邪恶的性情。我几乎不用说我说的是毕达哥拉斯和苏格拉底。

[17]所有伟大的天才都有一点疯狂癫痴。——译者注

[18]如果我们不愿用一个怀疑者来做例子，一个类似的人物也可以。比如说，一个讽刺家，他锐利的眼光看透了生活的滑稽可笑，他通过像轮胎一样势不可挡的神秘理解力探知病人的需求。他知道他掌控笑的力量；如果他动用这种力量，他肯定会胜利，而且，他也确信自己会幸福。他不仅知道会有某种声音反对自己，还知道他自己比那声音更强大；他知道还可以使人们暂时显得严肃，但也知道，秘密地，他们渴望和他一同欢笑；他知道使一个女士说话时暂时将扇子举到眼睛前面依然是可能的，但他也知道扇子后面她在发笑，他知道那扇子不是完全不透明的，他知道人们可以在它上面做隐形的题字，他知道当一个女士用扇子打他，那是因为她已理解了他，他绝无错误地知道笑意如何悄悄溜进一个人的心里并秘密地住下来，知道它一旦留下来会如何埋伏等待。让我们想象一下稍作改变后的这样一个阿里斯多芬尼斯，这样的一个伏尔泰，因为他也是富有同情心的人，他热爱生活，热爱人们，并且知道，即便年轻的、得到拯救的一代人可能从对笑的谴责中获得教益，然而在他自己这个时代，对笑的谴责对很多人来说会意味着毁灭。所以他保持沉默并尽可能地忘记如何去笑。但是他敢保持沉默吗？也许很多人不明白我所指的困难。他们会很可能认为他保持沉默是很高尚很令人钦佩的。那根本不是我所想的。我认为如果任何这样的人没有保持沉默的高尚大度，那他就是生活的变节者。所以我要求他有这样的慷慨大度。但是如果他有的话，他就敢保持沉默。伦理学是一种危险的科学，而且阿里斯多芬尼斯很可能纯粹是出于伦理的考虑才决定让笑声来评判他这个被误导的时代。美学上的高尚大度对于解决人是否应保持沉默这个问题是无济于事的。它的账户没有冒此类风险的信用栏目。如果他保持沉默，他必定会陷入悖论。—但是还有一种故事方案：比如，假设某人拥有一种对一个公众英雄的生活的解释，但是这种解释是一种令人悲叹的解释，然而整个一代人都对这个英雄充满信赖，根本不疑心会有任何这样的事。

[19]赫洛斯特拉托斯：古希腊人，他为了出名，在公元前356年纵火烧毁了著名的亚尔德米斯神庙。——译者注

[20]关于苏格拉底的哪一句话可以被视为最后关键性的话，人们有不同意见，因为苏格拉底已经被柏拉图以多种方式诗意地发挥美化了。我对此作如下建议：当他被判处死刑的那一刻，他死了，并用那句著名的回答完成了自我实现，他的回答是，他对自己被法庭以三票的微弱多数票判处死刑感到惊讶。在他对轻率的市井之语或蠢人之语的评论中也找不到他对自己被判死刑的评论中所体现出的莫大的讽刺性玩笑语气了。

[21]如果此处有任何类比的问题，毕达哥拉斯死亡的情形可以提供一个类比的例子。在他的最后时刻，他必须将他一直保持的沉默贯彻到底，使之圆满结束，所以他说：“被杀死也比说出来要好。”参见《戴奥真尼斯》第八卷，第三十九段。

[22]他比较一条河流中的存在，说：“人不能两次走进同一条河流。”参见柏拉图的《克拉图鲁斯》第四百零二节；《柏拉图全集》第三卷，第一百五十八页。

[23]参见泰尼曼的《哲学史》第一卷，第二百二十页。

Preface

Not just in commerce but in the world of ideas too our age is putting on a veritable clearance sale. Everything can be had so dirt cheap that one begins to wonder whether in the end anyone will want to make a bid. Every speculative score-keeper who conscientiously marks up the momentous march of modern philosophy, every lecturer, crammer, student, everyone on the outskirts of philosophy or at its centre is unwilling to stop with doubting everything. They all go further. It would perhaps be malapropos to inquire where they think they are going, though surely we may in all politeness and respect take it for granted that they have indeed doubted everything, otherwise it would be odd to talk of going further. This preliminary step is one they have all of them taken, and presumably with so little effort as to feel no need to drop some word about how; for not even someone genuinely anxious for a little enlightenment on this will find such. Not a gesture that might point him in the right direction, no small dietary prescription for how to go about such a huge task. 'But Descartes did it, didn't he?' A venerable, humble, honest thinker whose writings surely no one can read without being most deeply stirred — Descartes must have done what he has said and said what he has done. A rare enough occurrence in our own time! Descartes, as he himself repeatedly insists, was no doubter in matters of faith. ('[B]ut we must keep in mind what has been said, that we must trust to this natural light only so long as nothing contrary to it is revealed by God himself ... Above all we should impress on our memory as an infallible rule that what God has revealed to us is incomparably more certain than anything else; and that we ought to submit to the Divine authority rather than to our own judgement even though the light of reason may seem to us to suggest, with the utmost clearness and evidence, something opposite' [from Principles 28 and 76 of Prin-ciples of Philosophy].) Descartes has not cried 'Fire!' and made it everyone's duty to doubt, for Descartes was a quiet and lonely thinker, not a bellowing streetwatch; he was modest enough to allow that his method was important only for himself and sprang partly from his own earlier bungling with knowledge. ('Thus my design here is not to teach the Method which everyone should follow in order to promote the good conduct of Reason, but only to show in what manner I have endeavoured to conduct my own ... But so soon as I had achieved the entire course of study [that is, of his youth — Johannes de silentio's interpolation] at the close of which one is usually received into the ranks of the learned, I entirely changed my opinion. For I found myself embarrassed with so many doubts and errors that it seemed to me that the effort to instruct myself had no effect other than the increasing discovery of my own ignorance' [Discourse on the Method of Rightly Conducting the Reason and Seeking the Truth in the Sciences].) — What those old Greeks, whom one must also credit with a little knowledge of philosophy, took to be the task of a whole lifetime, doubt not being a skill one acquires in days and weeks; what the old veteran warrior achieved after keeping the balance of doubt in the face of all inveiglements, fearlessly rejecting the certainties of sense and thought, incorruptibly defying selfish anxieties and the wheedling of sympathies — that is where nowadays everyone begins.

Today nobody will stop with faith; they all go further. It would perhaps be rash to inquire where to, but surely a mark of urbanity and good breeding on my part to assume that in fact everyone does indeed have faith, otherwise it would be odd to talk of going further. In those old days it was different. For then faith was a task for a whole lifetime, not a skill thought to be acquired in either days or weeks. When the old campaigner approached the end, had fought the good fight, and kept his faith, his heart was still young enough not to have forgotten the fear and trembling that disciplined his youth and which, although the grown man mastered it, no man altogether outgrows — unless he somehow manages at the earliest possible opportunity to go further. Where these venerable figures arrived our own age begins, in order to go further.

The present author is no philosopher, he has not understood the System, nor does he know if there really is one, or if it has been completed. As far as his own weak head is concerned the thought of what huge heads everyone must have in order to have such huge thoughts is already enough. Even if one were able to render the whole of the content of faith into conceptual form, it would not follow that one had grasped faith, grasped how one came to it, or how it came to one. The present author is no philosopher, he is poetice et eleganter [to put it in poetic and well-chosen terms], an occasional copyist who neither writes the System nor makes any promises about it, who pledges neither anything about the System nor himself to it. He writes because for him doing so is a luxury, the more agreeable and conspicuous the fewer who buy and read what he writes. In an age where passion has been done away with for the sake of science he easily foresees his fate — in an age when an author who wants readers must be careful to write in a way that he can be comfortably leafed through during the after-dinner nap, and be sure to present himself to the world like the polite gardener's boy in the Advertiser who, hat in hand and with good references from his previous place of employment, recommends himself to a much-esteemed public. He foresees his fate will be to be completely ignored; has a dreadful foreboding that the scourge of zealous criticism will more than once make itself felt; and shudders at what terrifies him even more, that some enterprising recorder, a paragraph swallower who to rescue learning is always willing to do to others' writings what, to 'preserve good taste', Trop nobly did to The Destruction of the Human Race, will slice him into sections as ruthlessly as the man who, in the service of the science of punctuation, divided up his speech by counting the words and putting a full-stop after every fifty and a semi-colon after every thirty-five. No, I prostrate myself before any systematic bag-searcher; this is not the System, it hasn't the slightest thing to do with the System. I wish all good on the System and on the Danish shareholders in that omnibus; for it will hardly become a tower. I wish them good luck and prosperity one and all.

Respectfully

Johannes de silentio

Attunement

There was once a man; he had learned as a child that beautiful tale of how God tried Abraham, how he withstood the test, kept his faith and for the second time received a son against every expectation. When he became older he read the same story with even greater admiration, for life had divided what had been united in the child's pious simplicity. The older he became the more often his thoughts turned to that tale, his enthusiasm became stronger and stronger, and yet less and less could he understand it. Finally it put everything else out of his mind; his soul had but one wish, actually to see Abraham, and one longing, to have been witness to those events. It was not the beautiful regions of the East, nor the earthly splendour of the Promised Land, he longed to see, not the God-fearing couple whose old age God had blessed, not the venerable figure of the patriarch stricken in years, not the youthful vigour God gave to Isaac — it would have been the same if it had taken place on a barren heath. What he yearned for was to accompany them on the three-day journey, when Abraham rode with grief before him and Isaac by his side. He wanted to be there at that' moment when Abraham raised his eyes and saw in the distance the mountain in Moriah, the moment he left the asses behind and went on up the mountain alone with Isaac. For what occupied him was not the finely wrought fabric of imagination, but the shudder of thought.

This man was no thinker, he felt no need to go further than faith. To be remembered as its father seemed to him to be surely the greatest glory of all, and to have it a lot to be envied even if no one else knew.

This man was no learned exegete, he knew no Hebrew; had he known Hebrew then perhaps it might have been easy for him to understand the story of Abraham.

Ⅰ

And it came to pass after these things, that God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him ... Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.

It was early morning. Abraham rose in good time, had the asses saddled and left his tent, taking Isaac with him, but Sarah watched them from the window as they went down the valley until she could see them no more. They rode in silence for three days; on the morning of the fourth Abraham still said not a word, but raised his eyes and saw afar the mountain in Moriah. He left the servants behind and went on alone up the mountain with Isaac beside him. But Abraham said to himself: 'I won't conceal from Isaac where this way is leading him.'He stood still, laid his hand on Isaac's head to give him his blessing, and Isaac bent down to receive it. And Abraham's expression was fatherly, his gaze gentle, his speech encouraging. But Isaac could not understand him, his soul could not be uplifted; he clung to Abraham's knees, pleaded at his feet, begged for his young life, for his fair promise; he called to mind the joy in Abraham's house, reminded him of the sorrow and loneliness. Then Abraham lifted the boy up and walked with him, taking him by the hand, and his words were full of comfort and exhortation. But Isaac could not understand him. Abraham climbed the mountain in Moriah, but Isaac did not understand him. Then he turned away from Isaac for a moment, but when Isaac saw his face a second time it was changed, his gaze was wild, his mien one of horror. He caught Isaac by the chest, threw him to the ground and said: 'Foolish boy, do you believe I am your father? I am an idolater. Do you believe this is God's command? No, it is my own desire.' Then Isaac trembled and in his anguish cried: 'God in heaven have mercy on me, God of Abraham have mercy on me; if I have no father on earth, then be Thou my father!' But below his breath Abraham said to himself: 'Lord in heaven I thank Thee; it is after all better that he believe I am a monster than that he lose faith in Thee.'

＊

When the child is to be weaned the mother blackens her breast, for it would be a shame were the breast to look pleasing when the child is not to have it. So the child believes that the breast has changed but the mother is the same, her look loving and tender as ever. Lucky the one that needed no more terrible means to wean the child!

Ⅱ

It was early morning. Abraham rose in good time, embraced Sarah, the bride of his old age, and Sarah kissed Isaac, who had taken her disgrace from her, was her pride and hope for all generations. So they rode on in silence and Abraham's eyes were fixed on the ground, until the fourth day when he looked up and saw afar the mountain in Moriah, but he turned his gaze once again to the ground. Silently he arranged the fire-wood, bound Isaac; silently he drew the knife. Then he saw the ram that God had appointed. He sacrificed that and returned home ... From that day on, Abraham became old, he Could not forget that God had demanded this of him. Isaac throve as before; but Abraham's eye was darkened, he saw joy no more.

＊

When the child has grown and is to be weaned the mother virginally covers her breast, so the child no more has a mother. Lucky the child that lost its mother in no other way!

Ⅲ

It was early morning. Abraham rose in good time, kissed Sarah the young mother, and Sarah kissed Isaac, her delight, her joy for ever. And Abraham rode thoughtfully on. He thought of Hagar and of the son whom he had driven out into the desert. He climbed the mountain in Moriah, he drew the knife.

It was a tranquil evening when Abraham rode out alone, and he rode to the mountain in Moriah: he threw himself on his face, he begged God to forgive his sin at having been willing to sacrifice Isaac, at the father's having forgotten his duty to his son. He rode more frequently on his lonely way, but found no peace. He could not comprehend that it was a sin to have been willing to sacrifice to God the best he owned; that for which he would many a time have gladly laid down his own life; and if it was a sin, if he had not so loved Isaac, then he could not understand that it could be forgiven; for what sin was more terrible?

＊

When the child is to be weaned the mother too is not without sorrow, that she and the child grow more and more apart; that the child which first lay beneath her heart, yet later rested at her breast, should no longer be so close. Thus together they suffer this brief sorrow. Lucky the one who kept the child so close and had no need to sorrow more!

Ⅳ

It was early morning. Everything had been made ready for the journey in Abraham's house. Abraham took leave of Sarah, and the faithful servant Eleazar followed him out on the way until he had to turn back. They rode together in accord, Abraham and Isaac, until they came to the mountain in Moriah. Yet Abraham made everything ready for the sacrifice, calmly and quietly, but as he turned away Isaac saw that Abraham's left hand was clenched in anguish, that a shudder went through his body — but Abraham drew the knife.

Then they turned home again and Sarah ran to meet them, but Isaac had lost his faith. Never a word in the whole world is spoken of this, and Isaac told no one what he had seen, and Abraham never suspected that anyone had seen it.

＊

When the child is to be weaned the mother has more solid food at hand, so that the child will not perish. Lucky the one who has more solid food at hand!

In these and similar ways this man of whom we speak thought about those events. Every time he came home from a journey to the mountain in Moriah he collapsed in weariness, clasped his hands, and said: 'Yet no one was as great as Abraham; who is able to understand him?'

Speech in Praise of Abraham

If there were no eternal consciousness in a man, if at the bottom of everything there were only a wild ferment, a power that twisting in dark passions produced everything great or inconsequential; if an unfathomable, insatiable emptiness lay hid beneath everything, what would life be but despair? If it were thus, if there were no sacred bond uniting mankind, if one generation rose up after another like the leaves of the forest, if one generation succeeded the other as the songs of birds in the woods, if the human race passed through the world as a ship through the sea or the wind through the desert, a thoughtless and fruitless whim, if an eternal oblivion always lurked hungrily for its prey and there were no power strong enough to wrest it from its clutches — how empty and devoid of comfort would life be! But for that reason it is not so, and as God created man and woman, so too he shaped the hero and the poet or speech-maker. The latter has none of the skills of the former, he can only admire, love, take pleasure in the hero. Yet he, too, no less than the hero, is happy; for the hero is so to speak that better nature of his in which he is enamoured, though happy that it is not himself, that his love can indeed be admiration. He is the spirit of remembrance, can only bring to mind what has been done, do nothing but admire what has been done. He takes nothing of himself, but is jealous of his charge. He follows his heart's desire, but having found what he sought he wanders round to everyone's door with his song and his speech, so that all can admire the hero as he does, be proud of the hero as he is. That is his achievement, his humble task, this his faithful service in the hero's house. If he remains thus true to his love, if he struggles night and day against the wiles of oblivion, which would cheat him of his hero, then he has fulfilled his task, he is united with the hero who in his turn has loved him just as faithfully, for the poet is so to speak the hero's better nature, ineffectual certainly as a memory is, but also transfigured as a memory is. Therefore no one who was great will be forgotten: and however long it takes, even if a cloud of misunderstanding should take the hero away, his lover still comes, and the more time goes by the more faithfully he sticks by him.

No! No one shall be forgotten who was great in this world; but everyone was great in his own way, and everyone in proportion to the greatness of what he loved. For he who loved himself became great in himself, and he who loved others became great through his devotion, but he who loved God became greater than all. They shall all be remembered, but everyone became great in proportion to his expectancy. One became great through expecting the possible, another by expecting the eternal; but he who expected the impossible became greater than all. They shall all be remembered, but everyone was great in proportion to the magnitude of what he strove with. For he who strove with the world became great by conquering the world, and he who strove with himself became greater by conquering himself; but he who strove with God became greater than all. Thus there was strife in the world, man against man, one against thousands, but he who strove with God was greater than all. Thus there was strife upon earth: there was he who conquered everything by his own strength, and he who conquered God by his powerlessness, There was one relied upon himself and gained everything, and one who, secure in his own strength, sacrificed everything; but greater than all was the one who believed God. There was one who was great in his strength, and one who was great in his wisdom, and one who was great in hope, and one who was great in love; but greater than all was Abraham, great with that power whose strength is powerlessness, great in that wisdom whose secret is folly, great in that hope whose outward form is insanity, great in that love which is hatred of self.

It was by his faith that Abraham could leave the land of his fathers to become a stranger in the land of promise. He left one thing behind, took another with him. He left behind his worldly understanding and took with him his faith. Otherwise he would surely not have gone; certainly it would have been senseless to do so. It was by his faith that he could be a stranger in the promised land; there was nothing to remind him of what was dear, but the novelty of everything tempted his soul to sad longing. And yet he was God's chosen, in whom the Lord was well pleased! Yes, indeed! If only he had been disowned, cast out from God's grace, he would have understood it better. As it was it looked more like a mockery of himself and his faith. There was once another who lived in exile from the beloved land of his fathers. He is not forgotten, nor his songs of lament in which in sorrow he sought and found what he had lost. From Abraham we have no song of lament. It is human to complain, human to weep with one who weeps, but it is greater to have faith and more blessed to behold the believer.

It was faith that made Abraham accept the promise that all nations of the earth should be blessed in his seed. Time went by, the possibility was still there, and Abraham had faith; time went by, it became unlikely, and Abraham had faith. There was once another who held out an expectation. Time went by, the evening drew near, he was not so pitiful as to forget his expectation; therefore he too should not be forgotten. Then he sorrowed, and the sorrow did not deceive him as life had done; it did all it could for him and in the sweetness of sorrow he possessed his disappointed expectation. It is human to sorrow with the sorrower, but greater to have faith and more blessed to behold the believer. From Abraham we have no song of sorrow. As time went by he did not mournfully count the days, he did not cast suspicious glances at Sarah, fearing she was growing old; he did not stay the march of the sun, so that Sarah should not grow old and with her his expectation; he did not soothingly sing to Sarah his mournful lay. Abraham became old and Sarah was mocked in the land, and still he was God's chosen and heir to the promise that in his seed all nations of the earth would be blessed. Would it not be better, then, were he not God's chosen? What is it to be God's chosen? Is it to be denied in youth one's youthful desire in order to have it fulfilled in great travail in old age? But Abraham believed and held firm to the promise. Had Abraham wavered he would have renounced it. He would have said to God: 'So perhaps after all it is not your will that it should happen; then I will give up my desire, it was my only desire, my blessed joy. My soul is upright, I bear no secret grudge because you refused it.' He would not have been forgotten, he would have saved many by his example, yet he would not have become the father of faith; for it is great to give up one's desire, but greater to stick to it after having given it up; it is great to grasp hold of the eternal but greater to stick to the temporal after having given it up. But then came the fullness of time. Had Abraham not had faith, then Sarah would surely have died of sorrow, and Abraham, dull with grief, instead of understanding the fulfilment, would have smiled at it as at a youthful dream. But Abraham believed, and therefore he was young; for he who always hopes for the best becomes old, deceived by life, and he who is always prepared for the worst becomes old prematurely; but he who has faith, retains eternal youth. All praise then to that tale! For Sarah, though stricken in years, was young enough to covet the pleasure of motherhood; and Abraham, though grey of head, was young enough to want to be a father. Outwardly the wonder of faith is in Abraham and Sarah's being young enough for it to happen according to their expectations; in a deeper sense the wonder of faith lies in Abraham and Sarah's being young enough to wish, and in faith's having preserved their wish and through it their youthfulness. He accepted the fulfilment of the promise, he accepted it in faith, and it happened according to expectation and according to faith; for Moses struck the rock with his rod but he did not believe.

So there was rejoicing in Abraham's house when Sarah was bride on their golden-wedding day.

But it was not to remain so; Abraham was to be tried once more. He had fought with that subtle power that invents everything, with that watchful opponent that never takes a nap, with that old man who outlives everything — time itself. He had fought with it and kept his faith. Now all the horrors of the struggle were to be concentrated in one moment. 'And God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him ... Take now thy son, thine only son Isaac, whom thou lovest, and get thee into the land of Moriah; and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I will tell thee of.'

So all was lost, more terrible than if it had never been! So the Lord was only making sport of Abraham! Through a miracle he had made the preposterous come true, now he would see it again brought to nothing. Foolery indeed! But Abraham did not laugh at it, as Sarah had laughed when the promise had first been proclaimed. All was lost! Seventy years' faithful expectation, the brief joy at faith's fulfilment. Who is it then that snatches the staff from the old man, who is it that demands that the old man himself should break it? Who is it that makes a man's grey hairs forlorn, who is it that demands that he himself should make them so? Is there no compassion for this venerable greybeard, none for the innocent child? And yet Abraham was God's chosen, and it was the Lord who put him to this test. All was now surely lost! The glorious memory of the human race, the promise in Abraham's seed, it was only a whim, a fleeting thought of the Lord's, which Abraham himself must now eradicate. That glorious treasure, as old as the faith in Abraham's heart, many many years older than Isaac, the fruit of Abraham's life, hallowed with prayers, ripened in struggle — the blessing on Abraham's lips, this fruit was now to be plucked out of season and have no meaning; for what meaning could there be in it if Isaac was to be sacrificed! That sad yet still blessed hour when Abraham should take leave of everything he held dear, when he should raise his venerable head one time more, when his countenance should be radiant as the Lord's, when he should concentrate his whole soul in a blessing with the power to give Isaac joy all his days — that moment was not to come! For, yes, Abraham would indeed take leave of Isaac, but it was he that was to remain; death would divide them, but Isaac was to be its victim. The old man was not to lay his hand upon Isaac in blessing, but weary of life was to lay it upon him in violence. And it was God who tried him. Yes. Woe, woe to the messenger who came before Abraham with such tidings! Who would have dared be the emissary of such sorrow? Yet it was God who tried Abraham.

But Abraham had faith, and had faith for this life. Yes, had his faith only been for a future life it would indeed have been easier to cast everything aside in order to hasten out of this world to which he did not belong. But Abraham's faith was not of that kind, if there is such, for a faith like that is not really faith but only its remotest possibility, a faith that has some inkling of its object at the very edge of the field of vision but remains separated from it by a yawning abyss in which despair plays its pranks. But it was for this life that Abraham believed, he believed he would become old in his land, honoured among his people, blessed in his kin, eternally remembered in Isaac, the dearest in his life, whom he embraced with a love for which it was but a poor expression to say that he faithfully fulfilled the father's duty to love the son, as indeed the summons put it: 'the son whom thou lovest.' Jacob had twelve sons and he loved one; Abraham had just one, the son he loved.

But Abraham had faith and did not doubt. He believed the ridiculous. If Abraham had doubted — then he would have done something else, something great and glorious; for how could Abraham have done other than what is great and glorious? He would have marched out to the mountain in Moriah, chopped the firewood, set light to the fire, drawn the knife — he would have cried out to God: 'Do not scorn this sacrifice, it is not the best I possess, that I well know; for what is an old man compared with the child of promise, but it is the best I can give. Let Isaac never come to know, that he may comfort himself in his young years.' He would have thrust the knife into his own breast. He would have been admired in the world and his name never forgotten; but it is one thing to be admired, another to be a guiding star that saves the anguished.

But Abraham had faith. He did not beg for himself in hope of moving the Lord; it was only that time when the just punishment had been proclaimed upon Sodom and Gomorrah that Abraham came forward with his prayers.

We read in those Holy Scriptures: 'And God did tempt Abraham, and said unto him, Abraham: Abraham, where are you? but Abraham answered: here I am.' You, to whom my speech is addressed, was that the case with you? When you saw, far off, the heavy fate approaching, did you not say to the mountains, 'hide me', to the hills, fall on me'? Or if you were stronger, did your feet nevertheless not drag along the way? Did they not hanker, as it were, to get back into the old tracks? When you were called, did you answer, or did you not? Perhaps softly and in a whisper? Not so Abraham, gladly, boldly, trustingly he answered out loud 'here I am'. We read further: 'And Abraham rose up early in the morning.' He hurried as though to some celebration, and he was at the appointed place, the mountain in Moriah, early in the morning. He said nothing to Sarah, nothing to Eleazar. After all, who could have understood him? Hadn't the test by its very nature exacted an oath of silence from him? 'And [he] clave the wood, he bound Isaac, he kindled the fire, he drew the knife.' My hearer! Many a father has felt the loss of his child as the loss of the dearest thing he has in the world, to be bereft of every hope for the future; yet no son was the child of promise in the sense that Isaac was for Abraham. Many a father has lost his child, but then it was God, the unchangeable and inscrutable will of the Almighty, it was his hand that took it. Not so with Abraham. For him a harder trial was reserved; along with the knife the fate of Isaac was put into Abraham's own hand. And he stood there, the old man with his only hope! But he did not doubt, he did not look in anguish to left or right, he did not challenge heaven with his prayers. He knew it was God the Almighty that tried him, he knew it was the hardest sacrifice that could be demanded of him; but he also knew that no sacrifice was too hard when God demanded it — and he drew the knife.

Who gave strength to Abraham's arm, who kept his right arm raised so that it did not fall helplessly down! Anyone who saw this would be paralysed. Who gave strength to Abraham's soul, so that his eye did not become too clouded to see either Isaac or the ram! Anyone who saw this would become blind. And yet rare enough though they may be, those who are both paralysed and blind, still more rare is he who can tell the story and give it its due. We know it, all of us — it was only a trial.

Had Abraham doubted as he stood on the mountain in Moriah, had he looked about in indecision, if before drawing the knife he had accidentally caught sight of the ram and God had allowed him to offer it in place of Isaac — then he would have gone home, everything would have been as before, he would have had Sarah, he would have kept Isaac, and yet how changed! For his withdrawal would have been a flight, his deliverance an accident, his reward dishonour, his future perhaps damnation. Then he would have borne witness, not to his faith or to God's mercy, but to how dreadful was the journey to the mountain in Moriah. Abraham would not be forgotten, nor the mountain. Yet it would not be mentioned like Ararat, where the Ark came to land, but as a horror, for it was here that Abraham doubted.

Venerable Father Abraham! When you journeyed home from the mountain in Moriah you needed no speech of praise to console you for what was lost; for in fact you gained everything and kept Isaac. Was it not so? The Lord never again took him from you, you sat happily at table with him in your tent, as you do in the hereafter in all eternity. Venerable Father Abraham! Thousands of years have slipped by since those days, but you need no late-coming lover to snatch your memory from the power of oblivion; for every mothertongue commemorates you — and still you reward your lover more gloriously than anyone. You make him blessed hereafter in your bosom, you captivate his eye and his heart in the here and now with the marvel of your deed. Venerable Father Abraham! Second father to the human race! You who first saw and bore witness to that tremendous passion that scorns the fearful struggle with the raging elements and the forces of creation in order to struggle with God instead, you who first knew that supreme passion, the sacred, pure, and humble expression of the divine madness which the pagans admired — forgive him who would speak in your praise if he did not do it correctly. He spoke humbly, seeing it is his heart's desire; he spoke briefly, as is fitting; but he will never forget that you needed a hundred years to get the son of your old age, against every expectation, that you had to draw the knife before keeping Isaac; he will never forget that in one hundred and thirty years you got no further than faith.

Epilogue

Once when the spice market in Holland was a little slack, the merchants had some cargoes dumped at sea to force up the price. That was a pardonable, perhaps necessary, stratagem. Is it something similar we need in the world of spirit? Are we so convinced of having reached the heights that there is nothing left but piously to believe we still haven't come that far, so as at least to have something to fill the time with? Is it this kind of trick of self-deception the present generation needs, is it to a virtuosity in this it should be educated, or has it not already perfected itself sufficiently in the art of self-deception? Or is what it needs not rather an honest seriousness which fearlessly and incorruptibly calls attention to the tasks, an honest seriousness that lovingly fences the tasks about, which does not frighten people into wanting to dash precipitately to the heights, but keeps the tasks young and beautiful and charming to behold, and inviting to all, yet hard too and an inspiration to noble minds, since noble natures are only inspired by difficulty? However much one generation learns from another, it can never learn from its predecessor the genuinely human factor. In this respect every generation begins afresh, has no task other than that of any previous generation, and comes no further, provided the latter hasn't shirked its task and deceived itself. This authentically human factor is passion, in which the one generation also fully understands the other and understands itself. Thus no generation has learned from another how to love, no generation can begin other than at the beginning, the task of no later generation is shorter than its predecessor's, and if someone, unlike the previous generation, is unwilling to stay with love but wants to go further, then that is simply idle and foolish talk.

But the highest passion in a human being is faith, and here no generation begins other than where its predecessor did, every generation begins from the beginning, the succeeding generation comes no further than the previous one, provided the latter was true to its task and didn't betray it. That this sounds wearying is not of course for the generation to say, for it is indeed the generation that has the task and it has nothing to do with the fact that the previous generation had the same task, unless that particular generation or the individuals in it presumed to occupy the position to which only the spirit that governs the world, and which has the endurance not to grow weary, is entitled. If that is the kind of thing the generation begins to do, it is perverted, and what wonder then if the whole of existence should look perverted to it? For surely no one has found life more perverted than the tailor in the fairy-tale who got to heaven in his lifetime and from there looked down on the world. So long as the generation only worries about its task, which is the highest it can attain to, it cannot grow weary. That task is always enough for a human lifetime. When children on holiday get through all their games by noon and then ask impatiently, 'Can't anyone think of a new game?', does this show that they are more developed and advanced than children of the same or a previous generation who could make the games they already know last the whole day? Or does it not rather show that those children lack what I would call the good-natured seriousness that belongs to play?

Faith is the highest passion in a human being. Many in every generation may not come that far, but none comes further. Whether there are also many who do not discover it in our own age I leave open. I can only refer to my own experience, that of one who makes no secret of the fact that he has far to go, yet without therefore wishing to deceive either himself or what is great by reducing this latter to a triviality, to a children's disease which one must hope to get over as soon as possible. But life has tasks enough, even for one who fails to come as far as faith, and when he loves these honestly life won't be a waste either, even if it can never compare with that of those who had a sense of the highest and grasped it. But anyone who comes to faith (whether he be greatly talented or simple-minded makes no difference) won't remain at a standstill there. Indeed he would be shocked if anyone said this to him. Just as the lover would be indignant if someone said he had come to a standstill in his love, for he would reply, 'I'm by no means standing still in my love, for I have my life in it.' And yet he too doesn't come any further, not to anything else. For when he finds that out he has another explanation.

'One must go further, one must go further.' This need to go on is of ancient standing. Heraclitus the 'obscure' who reposited his thoughts in his writings and his writings in the Temple of Diana (for his thoughts had been his armour in life, which he therefore hung up in the temple of the goddess), the obscure Heraclitus has said, 'One can never walk through the same river twice.'[【1】] The obscure Heraclitus had a disciple who didn't remain standing there but went further and added, 'One cannot do it even once.'[【2】] Poor Heraclitus to have such a disciple! This improvement changed the Heraclitian principle into an Eleatic doctrine denying movement, and yet all that disciple wanted was to be a disciple of Heraclitus who went further, not back to what Heraclitus had abandoned.

注释

【1】 'Chai potamou roi apeikadzon ta onta legei hos dis es ton auton potamon ouk embaiis.' cf. Plato's Cratyllus §402, Ast. 3rd B. Pag. 158.

【2】 cf. Tennemann Gesch. d. Philos. Ister B. Pag. 220.

译者导读

西塞罗（全名马库斯·图留斯·西塞罗，Marcus Tullius Cicero，公元前106—前43），古罗马时期著名的演说家、政治家、教育家，古典共和思想最优秀的代表。曾先后在著名的修辞学家、法学家和斯多噶派哲学家所办的学校接受教育。起初，西塞罗从事律师工作，由于非常善于雄辩，所代理的案件几乎没有失败过。接着便步入政界，凭借自己善辩的口才而活跃于政界，并步步高升。公元前75年担任西西里行省的财政官，公元前57年担任市政官，次年为大法官，公元前63年担任执政官，成为图留斯家族中的第一个执政官。西塞罗在政治上拥护共和制，反对独裁统治。公元前44年恺撒被刺身亡，他极力拥护恺撒的继承人屋大维，并且连续发表了14篇著名的演说来抨击安东尼。公元前43年，安东尼、屋大维和雷必达结成“后三头同盟”，安东尼派人杀死了西塞罗。

西塞罗在政治和法律方面的代表作有《论国家》《论法律》；在哲学方面的著作有《论至善和至恶》《论神性》；在教育方面的著作有《论演说家》《论雄辩家》。不过，西塞罗最著名的是他众多的演说辞，如：《为马尔塞鲁辩护》《为普兰西乌辩护》《为米洛辩护》《为斯考鲁斯辩护》，以及本书中的两篇“反腓力辞”等。西塞罗的演说词汇丰富，句式考究，句中从属子句有一定的排列顺序，并且局部之间要求对称，句尾音调抑扬顿挫，以此来增强句子的说服力。除此之外，他在演说中采用对比、讽刺和夸张等修辞以激起听众的感情，并且善于利用直接向对手致辞、提问等方法，使其陷入被动之中。

西塞罗在恺撒死后，为批判安东尼连续发表的14篇演讲，统称为“反腓力辞”。“反腓力辞”是一个借用的名称。公元前4世纪雅典演说家德谟斯提尼曾发表一系列著名演说来反对马其顿国王腓力，这些演说辞被称为“反腓力辞”。本书中的这两篇演说辞是14篇“反腓力辞”中的前两篇。这两篇演说辞不仅反映了西塞罗的政治路线，比如：他极力拥护共和制，对刺杀恺撒的布鲁特斯大加赞扬；此外，西塞罗演说的技巧和特点在这两篇演说辞中都得到了淋漓尽致的体现，演说中运用了大量反问、对比、反讽以及夸张的修辞，例如，对自己和安东尼缺席元老院会议原由的对比、对安东尼演说技巧的反讽等。不管是对听众还是读者来讲，这两篇演说辞都有很大的冲击力和说服力，其威力丝毫不亚于军队，使其政敌安东尼在通往独裁之路上遇到众多困难，不过也为自己招来杀身之祸。由此可见西塞罗演说辞中技巧之高超、言辞之犀利、情感之深沉。即使在今天，西塞罗演说辞也以其独特的魅力为众人所推崇。

反腓力辞之一：驳马克·安东尼

众位元老院议员，我认为在这种情况下我有必要对当前政局中的一些情况作出评论。但在此之前，我要简单地解释一下我离开以及再次返回罗马的原因。

只要国家仍有望回到你们的掌控和权威之下，作为执政官和元老院议员，我决心坚守自己的岗位。因此，自从我们被召集到忒路斯神庙集会的那天起，我便从未离开，也从未将视线从公共事务上转移。在神庙中，我尽自己所能去为和平做准备。对于雅典人所创古老先例的成员们，我在演说中运用了当年希腊用来平息内乱的言辞提醒他们，并建议大家永远忘记所有的内部纷争。

马克·安东尼那天的演讲精彩绝伦，他的本意也是善良的。事实上，正是他和他的孩子们让我们伟大的同胞有了实现和平的可能。接下来的事情与开端的方向一致。他邀请政治首脑到自己的家中商讨国事，并向元老院提出优秀的建议。那个时候，除了众所周知的事情以外，并没有从盖厄斯·恺撒的记事本中发现其他事情。安东尼非常坦率地回答了所有问题。有流放者被召回吗？他说，有一个被召回了，除此之外再无其他人。有没有豁免税务？他回答，没有。他甚至希望我们接受杰出的赛维厄斯·苏佩修斯的提议：从三月中旬起，不再实施恺撒的任何法令或其施加的任何恩惠。不过，我想说说马克·安东尼那项特别的法令，其他众多优秀的法令就先略过。毫无疑问，在他的管理之下，篡夺君权的独裁政权被彻底废除了。他希望元老院能够通过自己提出的法令草案。在草案被宣读之后，我们以极大的热情接受了他的提议，并投票对他表示高度的赞扬。我们的前途看起来一片光明，因为我们不仅摆脱了曾经奴役我们的暴政，也从对暴政的恐惧中解脱出来。虽然过去常有受法律认可的独裁者，但近来的独裁专政给人们留下了无法磨灭的记忆。然而马克·安东尼废除了整个独裁政府，向全国人民有力地证明了他希望这是一个自由的国家。

此外，几天后，在盗用马里厄斯这个名字逃亡的奴隶被处死并拖走后，元老院也从杀戮的危险中解放出来。所有这些行动都是安东尼和他的同僚一起完成的，后来的一些事则是多拉贝拉独自实施的，但我确信，要不是他的同僚不在，这些事也会由两个人共同完成。那时，一个最危险的问题正潜入这座城市并逐渐扩散。那些曾为恺撒组织和举办葬礼的人正在广场上为其建造墓碑。每天都有越来越多的无赖和像他们一样的奴隶聚集在一起，威胁和破坏着城里的住宅和神庙。但是当多拉贝拉摧毁那可憎的石碑后，这些放肆无礼的戴罪奴隶以及与他们为伍的那些可恶的、臭名昭著的自由民便步入了穷途末路。他的行动如此坚决果断，我对这一行动和后续行动之间的差别感到震惊。

6月1日是我们集会的固定日期，你们在这里就能发现所有的事情是如何改变的。任何事都不再通过元老院就直接实施，许多重要措施直接由人民议会通过，而其他措施居然不咨询议会的意见甚至违背其意愿。当选的执政官称他们根本不敢踏入元老院半步。同样地，尽管执政官在公共集会以及私下交谈中对那些解放者们赞赏有加，但解放者们却恰恰被那些他们曾经解放的城市所驱逐。除此之外，退役军人们要求拥有老兵的权利。元老院对此非常担心，因为那些人不仅想要保留已有的利益，并且在受到怂恿之后又觊觎新的权益。

我发现，听说这些事情的发生远比亲眼目睹其发生要让我好过一些。再者，我被赋予特殊使命而出游。正是这样，我离开了罗马并且打算在接下来的1月1日返回，因为这似乎是元老院有可能举行集会的最早日子。

元老院的议员们，这些就是我离开的原因。现在我要简单说明一下我回来的理由，我的返回无疑更加使人意外。我避开了布林迪西和去往希腊的一般路线——这是唯一的明智之法，并在6月1日抵达了锡拉库扎，因为我听说从那里进入希腊的通道畅通无阻。虽然我与这座城市有着最紧密的联系，但是我却不愿意在那里多耽搁一晚，尽管它也希望我留下来。因为我担心如果我多逗留的话，我对那里朋友的突然造访会引起某些怀疑。因此，我继续前行到达利吉姆的一个海角地区留科佩拉，在那里乘船前往希腊。

但是没走多远一阵南风就把我的船吹回登船之处。那时候已是深更半夜，我待在朋友的家里，与帕布利厄斯·华勒流斯在一起。第二天，正当我在那里等待，希望会有利于出行的海风时，一些利吉姆人来探望我，他们中有些人刚刚从罗马回来。我从他们那里第一次得知了马克·安东尼的演说。读完这篇演说之后我非常高兴，第一次开始考虑要返回罗马。不久之后就传来了布鲁特斯和卡修斯的宣言，在我看来这是公平的典范，或许因为我尊重他们更多的是因为他们是国家领导而不仅仅是我的朋友。但是，传达好消息的信使们往往喜欢添油加醋，以便使他们的好消息更受欢迎。因此，那些人还告诉我有一项协议即将缔结；8月1日将会召开元老院全体会议；安东尼会抛弃他那些邪恶的顾问，并辞去他在高卢行省的职务，重新效忠于元老院。

听到这些消息，我是那么地渴望回国，任何船桨和大风都无法满足我急切的心情，并不是我觉得自己无法及时到达，而是迫不及待地想要向元老院表示祝贺。在尽快赶到韦利亚之后，我见到了布鲁特斯，但这次见面让我感到悲伤。因为对我来说，在布鲁特斯离开这个城市之际我却想要回去，我可以在那里安稳地生活而他却不能，这样的事实让我感到羞愧不已。然而，我发觉他并没有像我一样沮丧，因为他为自己崇高而伟大的行为感到骄傲，他也不抱怨自己的命运，更多的是为你们的命运感到担忧。

正是在他那里，我第一次听说了卢修斯·皮索8月1日在元老院的演讲。布鲁特斯说那些本该支持皮索的人大都没有支持他，不过他认为皮索所做的努力无疑是非常崇高的。这是最权威的观点，也是我根据后来与我交谈过的人所做的正面评价得出的结论。因此，我急忙赶回去对他施以援手。但我并不是要去成就些什么，因为我从没有这样的期望，事实上也没有做成过什么。但如今，很多违背自然规律和命运常理的事情似乎随时都有可能发生。因此，为了以防那注定的厄运降临在我身上，我现在就表达出自己对祖国的感情，并以此为证表明我将永远致力于为国家谋取福利。

好了，众位议员，这些就是我离开又回到罗马的原因，相信我的解释能让你们满意。不过现在，我觉得有必要在谈论政事之前就安东尼昨天对我的不公平待遇表示抗议。我是他的朋友，而且由于他曾经帮助过我，我一直在维护我们的友谊。但我不明白他强拉硬拽着让我参加昨天的元老院会议时，为什么表现得那么不满。难道只有我一个人缺席吗？还是出席人数比以往都少？又或者是会上讨论的事情已经严重到有必要像过去那样连病人也要抬去参加商议？难道说汉尼拔已经兵临城下了？还是说我们正在讨论的是与皮拉斯的和平问题？而根据历史记载，在这种情况之下，年迈失明的阿皮乌斯是自己去元老院参加会议的。但是，这次会议的目的是讨论公开谢恩仪式的相关事宜，这样的事情从来都不缺乏参会议员，也无需安保措施来确保议员们的出席，因为他们热切地想要对接受这份荣誉的人表达自己的善意。同样地，当胜利成为讨论的话题时，情况也是如此。在这种情形下，执政官对议员们根据自己的意愿决定是否参加会议漠不关心。

我知道这种惯例，况且当时我旅行疲惫，身体欠佳。因此，出于友谊，我差人通知了安东尼。结果正如你们所听到的那样，他竟然说要带人来把我的房子拆掉。他这样显然是脾气恶劣、口无遮拦的表现。到底是什么样的过错竟需如此苛刻的惩罚？他竟然在议员们面前说要动用政府的力量去拆掉一栋房子，并且这个房子是在元老院的支持下利用公款建造的。从未有人对一名元老院的议员实施如此严厉的处罚。事实上，曾有过的惩罚也只有没收财产或罚款而已。此外，如果他知道我在会议上将要发表的意见，相信他绝不会坚持如此强硬的态度。众位议员，你们可能没有料到我会支持你们昨天极不情愿通过的那项法令，因为它将谢恩仪式和祭奠死者的祭祀混淆在一起，在国家的宗教仪式中掺杂了亵渎神明的程序，因此变成了为纪念死者而颁布的谢恩法令。这个人是谁并不重要，就算是仅凭一己之力将国家从专制统治中拯救出来的著名之士——布鲁特斯本人，并且即使他的后代在近五百年里也传承了这一崇高的英雄主义，也没什么能使我将任何已故之人和不朽的神明相提并论，并为其举行公开的谢恩仪式，因为本应通过祭祀就可让其获得相应的荣耀。但是，如果这个国家发生了重大灾难，譬如战争、瘟疫或饥荒，那么罗马人民就会认为我的投票是正当的，因为虽然有些灾难已经发生了，而另一些也有可能即将降临。然而事实上，关于昨天的法令，我能做的也只有请求神明宽恕那些无论如何都不同意这一举措的罗马人民，同时也宽恕极不情愿通过这项法令的元老院。

接下来，我可以对我们国家政治上一些其他的弊端发表看法吗？我认为我有自由（并且始终应该有自由）捍卫我的观点，视死如归，永不改变。只要我能来到这个地方，就会不顾一切危险，畅所欲言。

元老院的议员们，我多么希望自己能参加8月1日的元老院会议啊！并不是说我参加这个会议有多大的用处，但至少也不会像当时那样——只有一个执政官在履行自己的职责，为国效力。最得罗马民心的执政官们竟然不支持卢修斯·皮索那着实优秀的提案，多么悲哀啊！难道罗马人民推选我们成为执政官就是为了这种悲哀的结果吗？难道我们享受着国家给予的高官厚禄却可以完全置国家的利益于不顾吗？没有任何一位前任执政官在言辞，甚至是神情上对卢修斯·皮索予以支持。

该死！你们一定要自愿为奴吗？我承认一定程度的奴性向来是无法避免的。我也承认，我的批判没必要不加区别地针对每一位执政官，因为我能分得清哪些人保持沉默可以被原谅，而哪些人有义务开口讲话。我很遗憾地告诉大家，后者已经遭到了罗马人民的怀疑，而这更多不是因为他们的恐惧——虽然恐惧本身是可耻的，而是因为不管出于什么原因——当然是出于各种原因，他们在其位却不谋其政。

因此，我首先要向皮索表达我最深的谢意。他没有因为为国家谋福利受到阻碍而气馁，而是想着自己有责任为国家做些什么。元老院的议员们，接下来我再谈谈我的另外一个观点。我觉得你们可能不太敢对我即将向你们提出的观点和做法予以支持，但我请你们继续仁慈地听下去，就像到现在为止你们一直在听的那样。

首先，我认为我们应当保留恺撒的法令。我这么说并不是因为我赞成这些法令。有谁会赞成呢？当然没有！我这样说是因为我认为和平安定非常重要。我希望马克·安东尼今天能够在场，但是他的顾问团最好别来！不过我想他有权身体不适，虽然他昨天不允许我身体不适。如果安东尼在这里，他会跟我说，确切地说，他会对你们这些元老院的议员说他采取了什么措施来捍卫恺撒的法令。而我想说的是：安东尼依仗自己的权威提出的那些恺撒草草记录在他杂乱的备忘录、随笔和记事本上的法令，甚至有些都不是恺撒本人撰写而是引用的法令我们就要通过，而那些恺撒刻在铜器上用以维护国家议会的法令和明确的法律却要完全被无视吗？我个人认为，没有什么可以成为恺撒法令中不可更改的成分，就像恺撒提案中被采纳成为法律的那些一样。但是，从另一方面来讲，如果他曾对某人作出承诺，但自己却没有能力兑现，那么这也得视为不可改变的事情吗？事实上，恺撒一生中作出的很多承诺都没有履行。人们在他死后发现，恺撒众多没有实现的诺言甚至超过了他有生之年所作的所有贡献。

但是，我绝不打算改变，甚至是触及这些承诺。相反地，我极力捍卫他那些优秀的法令。例如，我衷心希望那些在奥普斯神庙所筹集的钱还在那里。虽然这些钱沾满了鲜血，不过因为现在已经不能物归原主了，所以我们还可以好好利用这些钱。但是如果恺撒的法令对这些钱财作出相关规定，那只好忍受其被浪费掉。

毫无疑问，对于一个位高权重的官员来说，他所倡导的法令就会成为最重要的法律。比如，一提及盖厄斯·格拉古的法令，人们就会想起塞姆普罗尼阿斯法，一说起苏拉法令，人们就会想到高奈留法。或者想一下庞培第三次担任执政官——那时通过了什么法令？当然是庞培自己的法律了。如果让恺撒来谈谈他在罗马公民生活中的法令，他会回答说自己引进了许多一流的法律。但另一方面，他把自己的那些笔记要么当作是临时的、需要修改的，要么就根本不整理出来，就算是整理出来也不会将其当作自己的法令。不过，这一点正是我在某些情况下所认可和默认的。但是只要恺撒的那些法律涉及最重要的问题，我绝不容忍将其废除。

就拿这条法律来说，它规定前执法官在其执政行省出任总督的任期不得超过一年，而前任执政官任期则不超过两年。这条法律非常有用，意义重大，也正是罗马在其鼎盛之时所需要的东西。如果这项法律都被废除了，还何谈恺撒法令的保留？再者，那条有关第三种陪审员的法案否定了恺撒所有有关陪审员的司法法令。你既说要捍卫恺撒的法令，又为何要将他的法律废除？那些恺撒匆匆写在笔记本上帮助自己记忆的东西——不管它们多么不公平、无用——都必须被视为法令，而那些在百人会议上通过投票的提案却不包含在法令之中，这究竟是什么逻辑？

新的第三种审判员究竟是什么？“它是由百人队队长组成的”，安东尼说。朱利叶斯法案以及之前的庞培法案、奥勒留法案已经授予了他们担任陪审员的权利，难道不是吗？的确如此，但这不仅仅针对百夫长，也包括骑士。所以，昔日那些极其勇敢并且威望极高的军队指挥官们，他们至今一直都可以担任陪审员一职。“但是，这些人都不是我所说的。”他接着说道，“我想让每一位曾经担任过百人指挥官的人都能成为一名陪审员。”不过，就算是将这个原则应用于每一位骑士——毕竟骑士相比百夫长更为尊贵一些——也毫无说服力。因为当你任命一个陪审员的时候，最好的依据就是他的财产和地位。“但是，我对这些限制一点兴趣都没有。事实上，我希望能从另一些人中任命陪审员，比如‘云雀军团’中的士兵。否则的话，那些拥护我们的人会觉得我们在欺骗他们。”安东尼说。但是对于你想纳入审判席的那些对象来说，这是怎样的一种侮辱啊（虽然他们自己没有意识到这点）！因为这条法律意味着第三种陪审员中有人不敢作出公正判决。哦，天哪！制定这条法律的人犯下了多么严重的一个错误啊！事实上，那些出身平凡的陪审员会努力使自己摆脱低微的地位，他们认为只有作出最严格的审判才能使自己从原本普通的陪审员晋升为更高一级的陪审员。

另外一条已经公布的法律规定：那些实施暴力或犯下叛国罪的人有权向议会申请上诉。我想问你，这究竟是一条法律，还是废除其他所有法律的法律？不过，不管怎么样，当下还有谁在意这条法律的保留与否呢？事实上，现在根本没有一个人会因为触犯那些法律（暴乱罪或叛国罪）而受到审判。并且，我认为将来也不会有，因为很显然那些手持武器的罪犯根本不会被带上法庭。

但是，据我们所知，这项法案很受欢迎。如果你的想法真的很受欢迎，这的确是一件很美好的事情。但就我们的现状而言，罗马公民一致认为国家政治上的需要才是最重要的。因此，我很不理解为什么你对提出一项本质上不受大家欢迎，并且必定会败坏你声誉的法案如此热情。一个人因为对罗马人民犯下了暴乱罪和叛国罪被定罪后，随后却又让他可以再次犯下同样的罪行，还有比这样的法案更可耻的吗？但是，我们没有必要在这项法案上继续浪费口舌，因为很明显，它真正所担心的根本就不是能否上诉；它的目标，也就是你推出这项法案的目标是防止任何人受到法律的制裁。有谁见过一个原告会傻到将自己置身于被告花钱雇来为自己辩护的众敌之中，或者有谁见过一个法官会冒着被别人收买的一伙恶棍伤害的危险而判处一个人有罪。

不，这项法案的真正目的并不是赋予人们上诉的权利。相反地，这废除了两个非常有益的法律和法庭。换句话说，它能直接诱导年轻人发动暴乱、扰乱治安、危害社会。当审判暴乱罪和叛国罪的这两个法庭被废除后，我们根本不敢想象这会让那些激烈的护民官作出什么样的毁灭性举动。此外，这项法案也废除了恺撒所制定的法律，后者规定：禁止犯下了这两种罪行的罪犯在审讯期间进食。毫无疑问，如果这些罪犯可以申请上诉，那不就等于直接宣布废除恺撒的这些法令了吗？众位议员们，就我个人而言，我绝对不会支持恺撒的法令，但是为了国家的团结，我们应该好好地维持这些法令。因此，我不主张在这个时候废除恺撒的法律，这不仅包括他生前所提出的，也包括你们现在所看到的那些在他死后公布的。

诚然，是一位死者召回了那些流亡犯；也是一位死者授予了人民公民权，这不仅仅是针对个人，也面向整个民族和行省；同样地，也是一位死者通过无数的赦免取消了众多税收。虽然这些法案都是在恺撒一人的权威（无可否认，这权威举足轻重）之下保证实施并且出自他本人之手，可是即便如此，我还是愿意来捍卫这些法案。恺撒曾亲自当着我们的面宣读、公布并提出这些议案。他极力倡导这些有关行省和法庭的法律，因为他认为这与我们国家的利益息息相关。如果我们都同意这一点，那又怎么能同时要求废除这些法律呢？当法律被公布的时候（就像恺撒的那些一样），如果我们愿意，至少还有机会来抱怨一下。但是，对于那些只能根据传闻才知道已经被通过的法律，我们连抱怨的机会都没有。安东尼提出的那些法律没有任何事先的公示就得以通过，我们甚至连草案初稿都没见过。

的确，元老院的议员们，如果我们有好的保民官，那么我或者你们中的任何一个人根本没必要担心一些不好的法律会被采纳。事实上，我们的确拥有这样的保民官，他们随时准备否决那些不好的提议，履行他们的神圣职责来保卫国家。所以，我们也应该无所畏惧。安东尼问：“这个否决指什么？你们所说的神圣职责又是什么？”自然是否决权和那些对国家安全至关重要的职责。安东尼说：“我们觉得那些一点都不重要，那都是过时的、愚蠢的。我们应该在广场的讲坛设禁，封闭它的所有入口，并派军队在多处驻守。”

我猜想，以这种方式确定的结果将会成为法律。然后，你会命人在铜碑上刻上这些法律条文“根据法律，执政官有权向人民提出这个问题”。但是，这和我们从祖先那里继承的提出问题的权利一样吗？后面继续刻着“并且人民有权通过提案”。什么样的人民？那些被隔离在外的人民吗？凭借什么样的权利？是那些被武装暴力废除的权利吗？

这些评论都可以当成以后的指导，因为作为一个朋友就应该对那些可以避免的不幸事先提出警告。如果这些不幸一直没有发生，那么我的评论自会受到驳斥。但是，现在我所谈论是不久将正式公布的议案。你可以提出任何提案，没有人能够阻止你。但就我而言，我认为自己有责任指出那些可能存在的缺点，并要求你来废除它，也就是说，我会批判武装暴力并要求你来消灭它。

多拉贝拉，我提出这些建议完全是出于对国家的热爱，希望你们执政官不要对此感到生气。不过，我不认为你会生气，因为我知道你的脾气很好。但是，据说你的同僚——马克·安东尼生气了。因为他沉溺于当前的情境之中，认为自己很幸运（说的委婉一点吧！我觉得如果他能像他的祖父和舅舅那样担任执政官，那么他会更幸运）。我明白，当一个手持武器之人对你发起进攻，特别是他的武器可以使自己免于受罚之时，这确实让人感到很不快。但是，我要提出一个约定，虽然它看起来对我很公平，不过我相信安东尼不会反对。约定的内容是：如果我对他的私生活或道德品行作出了任何侮辱性的评论，我对他将我视为死敌没有任何异议。另一方面，如果我只是遵循自己处理政务之时的习惯，坦白地说出自己对一些国家事务的看法时，首先，我希望他不要因此迁怒于我；其次，如果他非要迁怒于我，我希望这种不满仅限于两个公民之间。正如他所声称的那样，如果有必要他一定会雇佣武装警卫来保护自己，但是千万不要让他们伤害那些正在对国家事务发表观点的人。还有比这更好的建议吗？不过，就像他的一些朋友对我所说的那样，任何违背了他意愿的言辞都会让他感到不快，即使对他没有任何侮辱。那么，我们对此也无可奈何，只能忍受我们朋友这样的性情了。但是，安东尼的这些亲信还告诉我：“作为恺撒的反对者，你不会得到像他的岳父庇索那么多的宽容。”同时他们也警告我，这个警告我永远不会忘记：“用生病作为缺席元老院会议的理由对你来说根本没用，除非是死亡这个更好的借口。”

多拉贝拉，我亲密的朋友。天知道，当我看到你坐在那里的时候，我根本无法对你们俩所犯的错误保持沉默。你们每个人都是心怀崇高理想的尊贵之士。我不会和那些极易受骗的人一样认为你所追求的是钱财，因为那向来都是拥有极高地位和声誉之人所藐视的东西。我更不相信你所追求的是通过暴力获得财富或者是不为罗马人民所容忍的权力。相反地，我深信你们所追求的是同胞的热爱和良好的声誉。这样的声誉是通过高尚的行为和为国家作出巨大贡献所赢得的，是被国家领导和普通民众所认可的。多拉贝拉，我想更加深入地讨论崇高行为回报这一主题，因为我看到近年来你对这个问题的理解与别人相比，并不是很深刻。

你还能想起此生中比那天更愉快的日子吗？在回家之前，你清理了广场的讲坛，驱散了那群亵渎神明的恶棍，惩罚了那些罪魁祸首，拯救这座城市于焚毁和屠杀的危难之中。所有人，不管他们是什么等级、什么家族都向你表示赞扬和祝贺。事实上，更有一些忠诚的公民以你的名义向我表示感谢和祝贺，因为他们相信你的行为受到了我的影响。多拉贝拉，请你回头想想！剧院里所有观众抛开以往对你的敌意，全都为你喝彩的时候，这是不是说明你那时的行为已经化解了他们以前对你的种种怨恨呢？

但是，在赢得如此美誉之后，你竟然冷漠地将其放置一边。多拉贝拉，这着实让我感到十分的悲痛！

至于你——马克·安东尼，虽然你现在不在这里，但我还是对你有一个请求。元老院在忒路斯神庙开会的那天应该是你最愉快的日子吧！虽然在随后的几个月里有很多人都（当然，这些人和我不同）认为你很愉快，不过再也没有什么比那天更能让你幸福吧！那天你发表的有关国家团结的演讲是多么精彩绝伦啊！当你抛开对另一位执政官的敌意，忘却你作为罗马的占卜官时所宣布的不利于他选举的征兆，也就是当你第一次接受他作为你的同僚时，你将自己襁褓中的儿子作为人质送到卡皮托利山，是你，让众多退伍军人不再为自己的处境担心。事实上，也是你，让整个国家从焦虑中解放出来。不管是元老院，还是罗马人民有谁不觉得那是最愉快的一天呢？那天所聚集的罗马人民比以往任何公共集会都要多。在那个时刻，我们似乎终于可以肯定那些最英勇的公民为我们带来了自由，他们的目标似乎也已实现，自由终会为大家带来和平。

在接下来的第一天、第二天、第三天以及随后的每一天，你一直在为国家作新的贡献，而其中最伟大的一项就是你对独裁者头衔的废除。你让恺撒这个名字成为恶贯满盈的代名词。在过去，根据曼利厄斯家族的规定，鉴于马库斯·曼利厄斯所犯的罪行，禁止任何曼利厄斯家族的人取名为马库斯。同样的道理，出于大家对这位独裁者的厌恶，你废除了独裁者这一头衔。

但是，在你为国家作出了这些杰出的贡献后，又发生了什么呢？你是不是对自己获得的这些好运、荣誉和声望感到后悔？为什么变化如此之快？我绝不相信金钱就是你堕落的缘由。别人想说什么就让他们说吧，我们可以选择不相信他们。况且，我从来没有发现你的品格有什么卑劣之处。的确，有时候一个人堕落是受到了周围人的影响，但我很清楚你意志坚强，不会受其影响。我只是遗憾，虽然你是无罪之身，但还是不免遭人怀疑。

但是比起这些莫须有的罪名，我更担心你可能会无视通往光荣的正确之路。你真的认为自己所拥有的权力高于其他任何人，别人都畏惧你而不是敬爱你，这就是荣誉吗？如果这是你的真实想法，那么在这个问题上你就大错特错了。因为真正的荣誉是别人对你爱国之情的赞赏，是别人对你的尊敬和热爱；相反地，让别人感到害怕和讨厌恰好是虚弱和危险的表现。这在那部戏里表现得淋漓尽致，戏中有人说“倘若他们害怕，那让他们憎恨也无妨”。正是这一想法使他走向了毁灭。马克·安东尼，如果你能时刻以你的祖父为榜样，结果将会大有不同。你曾多次听我详细地讲述他的事迹，你觉得他会通过武装力量来震慑人民从而使自己永垂不朽吗？当然不会！对他而言，自己的生命以及事业的飞黄腾达与其他人的自由同样重要，并且他让人更为敬重的一点是将别人的自由看得更为重要一些。现在我不想再谈论他那些辉煌的成就，我想说的是，虽然他的生命最终以悲剧收尾，被卢修斯·秦纳残忍地杀害，但是相比于残暴的秦纳，他的结局要更好一些。

不过，我觉得自己所说的话对你没有任何作用。如果连盖厄斯·恺撒的结局都不能对你有所启示，不能让你期待人民的热爱而不是恐惧，那么任何人的话都对你没有影响。那些羡慕恺撒的人都受到了极大的误导。因为，当一个人被残暴地杀害而凶手不仅没有受到惩罚反而获得了至高的荣誉时，那么任何人也就没有幸福可言了。所以我恳求你，不要再执迷不悟了。想想你的祖辈们，好好来治理我们的国家吧！让我们的同胞因为你的存在而感到愉快，因为没有人民的爱戴，幸福、声望和安全根本无从谈起。

罗马同胞已经对你们提出了很多警告，但我仍担心这不会引起你们足够的重视。想想无数市民们在观看角斗表演时的呐喊，想想那些广为流传的口号，想想庞培雕像前那些无尽的欢呼，想想反对你们的那两名保民官吧！这些都充分表明了罗马人民万众一心，众志成城。还有，想想那些阿波罗赛会上的掌声，或者我应该称之为全体罗马人民的证词和审判，这些难道都不能引起你们的重视吗？虽然有的人因为武装暴力的阻止不能到场，但事实上他们到了，因为他们活在罗马人民的心中，这是多么光荣的一件事啊！不过，你们真的以为那些掌声是献给戏剧家阿基厄斯的吗？是他那部悲剧在第一次表演后迟来了六十年的奖励吗？当然不是！人们的掌声和鼓励都是献给布鲁特斯的。虽然他不能出席这个展示着他名字的赛会，但是见证了那场华丽表演的罗马人民仍然在他不在场的情况下表达了对他深深的感谢，并且以热烈的掌声和不断欢呼来纪念这位不能与他们同在的解放者。

我自己一直都鄙视为那些沽名钓誉之人所响起的掌声。同样地，即使这些掌声来自全体人民，同时来自最高阶层、中间阶层和最低阶层；当那些过去常常随波逐流的政客忽然作出一反常态的事情之时，这时的掌声在我看来根本不是赞赏，而是一种裁定。

如果你觉得这无关紧要——虽然事实上很重要，那么你是不是也认为罗马人民迫切渴望奥鲁斯·希尔提厄斯恢复健康也是微不足道的？罗马人民如此敬爱他，他的朋友如此关心他，他的家人如此珍爱他，这是多么荣耀的事情啊！现今在他生病之际，历史上还有谁能像他一样让所有人为其担心，为之牵挂？从来没有人享受过这种待遇。难道你从没想过，那些深切地关心着自己心中执政官生命健康的人也会想到你吗？

元老院的议员们，我已经得到了我返回罗马想要的奖赏，因为我今天向你们所表达的观点保证了今后无论发生了什么，大家都会了解我的决心。并且，谢谢大家仔细、和善的聆听。在对我和你们都没有危险的情况下，如果我还可以进一步发表自己的看法，那么我将竭尽全力来利用这些机会。如果没有机会，我将尽自己最大的努力来为国家服务。此外，我认为我已经活得很久了，不管是从时间的流逝还是名誉的获得来说。如果我还可以活得更久一些，那么像之前一样，我不会为自己，相反地，会为了你们，为了罗马而活。

驳自由之敌（反腓力辞之二：驳马克·安东尼）

众位元老院议员，为什么我的命运会是这样？在过去的20年里，每一个国家的敌人同时也都视我为敌。不用我说出他们的名字，你们都知道我说的是谁，不过他们所受到的惩罚比我所希望的还要严厉。

安东尼，你正在步那些人的后尘。但让我吃惊的是那些人的遭遇竟然没有使你心生怯意。当那些人将我和罗马同时视为敌人的时候，我并没有太过惊讶，因为他们没有将我单独列出作为他们的敌人。或者说，出于爱国的原因，我主动将他们每一个人视为敌人。但我从来没有伤害过你，即使是在言语上也没有。然而，在毫无根据的情况下，你却狠狠地羞辱了我。就算是喀提林本人也没有这么可恶，即使是帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯也没有这么疯狂。很显然，你觉得只有与我断绝关系才可以结交那些声名狼藉的家伙。

你在采取这一行动时是不是非常蔑视我？然而就我现在的生活、名声和品格而言，我不认为其中有什么能被你所诟病。当然，安东尼也不相信自己能在元老院里成功地将我贬低，这是因为虽然元老院经常会赞扬那些为国家作出贡献的杰出人物，但事实上元老院真正赞美过的人只有一个。那人使元老院绝境逢生，而我恰好就是此人。也许，安东尼是想在演讲方面与我一争高低？但如果是这样的话，他是多么的慷慨啊！因为他为我提供了这样一个主题——既能为自己辩护，又可以将他批判，难道还能有比这更丰富、更具有吸引力的主题吗？当然不是！很明显事实是这样：只有与我为敌，他才有机会向那些和他一样的人证明自己是罗马的敌人。

在对安东尼的其他指控作出回应之前，我想在“是我破坏我们之间友谊”这个问题上谈谈自己的想法，因为我认为这是最严重的指责。他对我曾在诉讼中发表对他不利的讲话表示不满。但是，我当然得支持我熟悉的朋友，反驳那些和我没有关系的人。况且，我朋友诉讼对手的支持者只是贪图他的美色，并不是看重他的品行。由于那位支持者通过一些不齿的行为来操控投票，导致我的朋友没有得到公正的结果，所以我才不得不参与这场诉讼。但是，我知道你提起这件事的原因。你想提醒所有人你是前奴隶——昆塔斯·法迪厄斯的女婿，你的孩子是一个前奴隶的外孙，从而使你在底层社会左右逢源。

此外，你声称为了得到我的教诲常来我家拜访。如果你真的那么做了，你的名声和道德会比现在高很多，但是你没有。即使你自己想这么做，盖厄斯·斯克里波尼厄斯·库里奥也决不允许你这样做。接着，你又说为我着想，放弃担任占卜官候选人。这纯属胡扯八道，简直太厚颜无耻了。那时候，整个占卜团都希望我能担任占卜官一职，并且庞培和昆塔斯·霍腾西厄斯将我提名为候选人（只允许两个人来提名）。除非你发动革命，否则你根本不可能成为候选人。况且那个时候库里奥也不在意大利，你根本无法成为一名占卜官。就算你后来参加竞选，如果没有库里奥的帮助你连一个部落的选票都没有。事实上，他那些朋友还是疯狂地为你拉选票，最后竟因实施暴力而在法庭上被判罪。

虽然你不承认，但你确实帮了我。当然，我一直都承认你所说的那些事实。不过对我来说，承认自己蒙受你的恩情要比让那些不知原委的人把我当作一个忘恩负义的人要好得多。然而，你对我的帮助就是——你没有在布隆迪西杀我——不是吗？不过，我认为你根本就不敢杀我，因为我已经奉命要返回意大利。下达这道命令的正是那位征服者，而你恰好如自己所期望的那样成为了他的众匪之首，你敢违背他的命令吗？

不过，就算假设你可以杀我。众位元老院议员们，这就是那些帮匪之徒所谓的帮助。他们无权处决某人，因此便吹嘘放过他一马。如果这是一种真正的恩惠，那么那些在得到恺撒饶命之后却反过来将其杀掉的人就不该被视为伟大之人，但是你自己为什么要将他们视为崇高之士呢？事实上，虽然这种行为与恐怖犯罪仅一步之遥，但绝不能被当作是一种恩惠。当你对我施以此种“恩惠”的时候，我不会因为你没有杀我而感到喜悦，反而对你可以这样做却又能免于惩罚而感到悲伤。

不过，就让我们把这当成一种恩惠吧，就算是一个匪徒所能给予的最大恩惠。但是，你为什么将我称作忘恩负义之人？难道我对我们国家的衰落表示不满是错的吗？你把这当作忘恩负义的一种表现。我承认，我的抱怨里充满了悲伤与不幸。但是如果一个人和我一样位居于此，担任着元老院和罗马人民所授予的职位，都会有这样的反应。况且，我的言语向来都是有所节制、非常友好，决不会侮辱别人的。当然，我在对你抱怨的时候也是有所节制，没有半点侮辱的意思。

安东尼，罗马现在剩下的这些东西最终都会因为你而消失，因为所有事情在你的家里都会标上价码，多么肮脏的一系列交易啊！你自己也承认那些出于你自己的利益而通过的法律甚至都没有正式提出过。作为一名占卜官，你却从没有占卜过；作为一名执政官，你却废除了其他官员的否决权。你竟然用武装护卫队来保卫自己。你嗜酒如命，好色成性，没有一天不是在这种最放荡的生活中度过的。

尽管如此，我还是努力克制自己，只对我们国家的事务进行谨慎的抱怨，从没有谈论过你的私事。一直以来，我都把我们之间的冲突当成我和马库斯·李锡尼·克拉苏之间的冲突一样（常常是事关国家大事的冲突），而不是与一名穷凶极恶的角斗士两人之间的战斗。

因此，今天我要让他理解在那种情况下我给予了他多大的一个恩惠。这个家伙公开宣读了一封信，并且说是我寄给他的。很显然，他根本不知道怎么为人处世，不了解别人怎么接人待物。即使是那些对绅士行为一无所知的人，有谁会因为跟自己朋友意见不合，就利用朋友曾寄给他的信并且公开宣读这些信件呢？这种行为会对人际关系造成严重的破坏，它意味着将那位不在场的朋友逐出交际圈。因为那些信里会有一些轻率、无礼的言辞，而这些如果公之于众就会显得没有品位，并且信中所提到的一些重要问题根本不适合广泛流传。安东尼的这种行为证明了他是一个野蛮无礼之人。

不过，我们来看看，他是多么愚不可及啊！请回答我下面的问题吧，伟大的辩手！（至少在西厄斯·穆斯特拉和纳米修斯·提罗看来，他是一名伟大的辩手。他们俩现在正手持长剑出现在元老院里。如果你能告诉我在他们俩被指控犯下了杀人罪后你是怎么使他们无罪释放的，我也会承认你是一名伟大的辩手。）不过，如果我否认自己曾寄过那封信给你，你有什么证据来证明是我寄给你的？难道用笔迹吗？的确，你对笔迹的了解十分有用。然而，你所做的一切都将是枉然，因为这封信是由一个秘书代写的。你的辩论老师是多么幸运的一个人啊！你交给了他一大笔学费（我稍后会提醒你），但是在他离开以后，你还是一个彻头彻尾的傻子！因为不会有任何演说者，事实上，根本不会有任何人用那些毫无根据的理由来指控对手，并且不能对其作出更进一步的辩解。但是，我并不否认那封信里面的内容正是我的原意。不过我在承认这一点的时候，我也确信你不是一个没有教养的人，而是一个十足的疯子。因为我的信里充满了谦卑与和善，甚至可以被当作行为举止的楷模，而你对其内容的指责竟是：我没有说你的坏话；我把你当作一位罗马公民、一位正派人士，而不是一个恶棍和罪犯来与你交流。

虽然在这种挑衅之下我也有权念出你的信，但我不想这么做。在那封信里你请求我准予你召回某些流放者，并且保证没有我的允许你绝不会让他们回来。我的确同意了你的请求，因为我根本不能阻止你那狂妄无礼的行为。事实上，即使是元老院的命令、全体人民的意见和所有法律对你来说都没有约束力。但是，恺撒实际上已经通过了一条法律，允许你信中所提到的人重返祖国，你为什么还要征求我的同意？毫无疑问，虽然这个问题已经通过立法解决了，但安东尼认为我应该以我的名誉对此作保，毕竟他不能赢得人民的信任。

众位元老院议员们：我有很多事例可以用来为自己辩护，并且谴责安东尼。但关于前者，我希望在我为自己辩护的时候你们能够宽容一点。第二个问题是对我自己提出的，我保证在驳斥安东尼的时候，自己所讲的事情会让你们印象深刻。同时，我也请求你们注意这一点：我的职业。事实上我一生都是一个演说者，我相信这已经向你们证明了我是一个有节制之人，并非一个极端主义者。所以，当我回答他对我的谴责的时候，请不要相信我会忘了自己是谁。我不会把他当作一名执政官，因为他并没有把我当作一名执政官，一名执政官级别的人。此外，不管是从他的生活作风、工作方法还是选举方式来看，他根本就不是一名真正的执政官。相反地，毫无疑问我曾是一名执政官。

你们可以从他对我担任执政官时的批判看出他想成为什么样的执政官。但是众位议员们，我的执政官职位表面上是我自己的，事实上它是你们的。因为，我所作的每一个决定，实行的每一项政策，采取的每一个行动都是根据元老院的审议、权威和法则来实施的。安东尼，当你在这些人面前诋毁我的行为的时候，你所展示的是一种多么奇怪的智慧啊！——很显然与你的辩论才能一样奇怪。难道你不知道我的那些行为是经过这些人共同的判定才得以实施的吗？除了你和帕布利厄斯·克劳狄斯厄斯外，没有人污蔑过我的执政。并且克劳狄厄斯的命运——那同样降落在库里奥身上的命运，也将会降落在你的头上，因为让他们死去的原因现在正在你的家里。[1]

虽然安东尼对我的执政表示不满。但是，首先就拿最近刚过世的帕布利厄斯·赛维留斯·瓦提·伊索里库斯来说，他是那个时期的执政官，并且很欣赏我的执政。除此之外，永远在人民心中占有举足轻重地位的昆塔斯·卢泰修斯·卡图鲁斯也对我表示赞许。不仅如此，卢修斯·李锡尼·卢库勒斯和他的兄弟马库斯、马库斯·李锡尼·克拉苏、昆塔斯·霍腾西厄斯、老盖厄斯·斯克里伯尼厄斯·库里奥、盖厄斯·卡尔普米厄斯·庇索、曼尼厄斯·阿奇利厄斯·格拉布里奥、曼尼厄斯·阿米里厄斯·雷必达、卢修斯·沃尔卡奇厄斯·图路斯、盖厄斯·马西厄斯·菲古卢斯，以及那时的两位执政官德修斯·朱尼厄斯·西拉努斯、卢修斯·李锡尼·穆瑞纳也对此持肯定态度。马库斯·波西厄斯·加图也和这些执政官的观点一样，对我赞赏有加。然而，他在临死之前所担心的众多事情中，尤其不看好你担任执政官。我的另外一个强有力的支持者就是庞培。他从叙利亚回来后，第一次和我见面便与我相拥并对我表示祝贺，他说正是由于我担任执政官才能让他再次看到罗马这个国家。但是，我为什么要提到这些人呢？整个元老院都曾以热烈的掌声来庆祝我担任执政官，没有一个人不感谢我，就像我是他们的再生父母一样。他们都认为是我拯救了他们的财产和生命、他们的孩子和他们的国家。

然而，由于我刚才提到的那些伟人都已经不在了，所以我们还是谈谈依然健在的那个时期的两位执政官。其中一位是卓越的政治家卢修斯·奥里利厄斯·科塔，他对你所批判的那些行为大加赞扬，并提议大家应该对我致以最深的感谢。这项提议也得到了我刚才所提到的那些执政官们的认可，事实上得到了整个元老院的认可。自这个城市建立以来，除了我以外还没有其他人获得这样的荣誉。第二位就是你的舅舅卢修斯·朱利叶斯·恺撒。那时，他批判自己姐姐的丈夫也就是你的继父，他的演说是那么得有力、庄严和坚定！你应该把他当作导师和顾问，你一生中作的所有决定都应该向他请教。但是，你没选他，却事事以你的继父为榜样。虽然我和卢修斯·恺撒没有亲戚关系，但在我担任执政官的时候我还是会向他请教政务。你虽是他姐姐的儿子，可你什么时候向他请教过政事呢？

到底谁才是安东尼的顾问呢？很显然，是那些我们不知道他们生日的人。安东尼没有出席今天的元老院会议，这是为什么呢？因为他正在自己家里举行生日晚会，为谁而设的呢？不用我说出名字，肯定不是某个福米奥，就是哪个格纳所或者是巴里奥[2]。这是一个多么让人厌恶的好色之徒啊！一个多么令人讨厌的骗子啊！安东尼，你从不向你的那位近亲、那位让人尊敬的元老院议员卢修斯·恺撒请教政务，反而听取那些穷困潦倒的寄生虫们的意见，这是怎么回事呢？

我明白了，你担任执政官便对大家有益，而我担任则有害。如果你敢在神庙作出这样的论断，那简直就是无耻下流到了极点。作为执政官，我曾经在这里与元老院议员共商国是。在元老院最荣耀的时候，它拥有至高无上的权力；而现在，这座神庙里到处都是你派来的那些手持武器的恶棍、流氓。而你竟然如此的厚颜无耻（事实上没有什么事情是你干不出来的）地说在我担任执政官的时候，通往卡皮托利圣山的路上到处都是武装的奴隶！你是不是想说，我以武力来威胁元老院通过我那些不正当的法令？多么愚蠢的家伙啊！如果你知道真相，那你怎么还敢在这样的会议上说出如此鲁莽的话来？又或者，你根本就不知道，因为你心里就从来没有好事。

当元老院在神庙举行会议的时候，每一个罗马骑士，每一个出身高贵的青年（除了你外），每一个清楚自己罗马公民身份的人（不管是哪个等级的）都聚集在通往神庙的路上。他们每一位都报上自己的名字，但是由于人数太多，没有足够的记录人员或签名簿来登记所有人的名字。

那个时候，由于同谋的揭露和那些被当作证词公之于众的亲笔信，那些邪恶的叛国者不得不承认他们曾企图摧毁这个国家。从信中可以看出他们打算残害罗马人民、掠夺意大利、发动反动革命战争。在这个关键的时刻，所有人都会响应号召保卫祖国，尤其是在那个时候元老院和罗马人民拥有这样一位领袖。如果现在也有一位像那样的领袖，那些反动者的下场也将是你的下场。

安东尼对我拒绝交出他继父的尸体来下葬表示极大的不满，但是即使是帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯也没有因此指责我。毫无疑问，我是克劳狄厄斯的敌人。但我觉得很遗憾，你竟然比他错得更加离谱。你为什么要提醒我们你曾在继父家里成长？难道你担心我们会怀疑你本性难移？还是想以此为证说明你为什么会变得如此可恶？

事实上，你的演讲简直毫无逻辑可言，你所说的从头到尾不仅没有联系而且自相矛盾，你对自己的反驳比对我的还要多。你承认你的继父参与了那滔天大罪，但你又抱怨他因此受到惩罚。不过，这场辩论的结果就是对我予以表扬，而对整个元老院加以斥责。因为虽然是我逮捕了罪犯，但是惩罚他们的却是元老院。所以，我们这位“雄辩者”根本就不知道他正在表扬自己想要批判的对手，侮辱了在座的听众。

我不会把这称之为放肆无礼，那一直是他引以为豪的一种品质。不过安东尼并不想成为一个愚蠢之人，但是当武装人员将我们团团包围，并且手握长剑驻守在协和神庙的时候，他却谈起了卡皮托利山，真是愚不可及啊！苍天在上！就是在我担任执政官的时候，在这座协和神庙里作出了那些拯救我们国家、让我们能安全至今的决策。

接着，他又批判元老院，批判当时与元老院结盟的骑士阶层。当他的以提利亚士兵将正在开会的我们包围时，他谴责每一个阶层、每一位公民。你并不是因为肆无忌惮才说出了这些不知羞耻的论断，而是你根本不知道自己所说的话是自相矛盾的。说实话，你简直愚蠢到不能再愚蠢了，因为一个神志正常的人怎么会先手执武器摧毁自己的国家，而后又指责别人拿起武器来拯救国家呢？

曾经有一度你想让自己变得机智风趣，但是天知道，这根本与你不相适宜。你在这方面的失败尤其应该受到谴责，因为你本可以从那位专业的女戏子也就是你的妻子身上学到一些。你曾因我说过“让武器向托加袍投降”[3]而嘲笑我。但是，那个时候情况的确如此，难道不是吗？不过，因为你的武器取得了胜利，让我们来考虑一下到底哪个更好：是捍卫罗马自由之人战胜了那些匪盗之徒的武器更好，还是现在你用武器将自由摧毁更好？我的诗就是我的答案。不过我想说你既不懂我的诗，也不懂其他文学作品。相反地，我不但谨记着我对国家和人民的责任，也利用闲暇时间来进行各种文学创作。但是，我的作品都是为了让年轻人从中获益、为国家辉煌的前途所着想。不过，这是另外一个话题了。还是让我们回到那些更为重要的问题上吧！

你说，因为我的提议帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯被泰特斯·安尼厄斯·米洛处死了。但是，如果当你手持长剑在万众瞩目之下将他追赶到广场上，他才被杀死，人们会怎么想？如果他没有藏在书店的楼梯底下反抗你，你或许已经将他杀死了。就算你没有告诉大家是我煽动你这么做的，我也会承认我支持你当时的做法。但是至于米洛，我根本就没有机会对他的行动予以支持，因为他在任何人猜到他要做什么之前就已经付诸实践了。你说是我煽动他的，那也就是说要是没有一个敦促者他就不能实施一项爱国行动。你说当这一行动完成之时，我为此庆祝。但是在全国都为此感到高兴的时候，为什么我要成为这唯一的哀悼者。当然，对克劳狄厄斯之死的调查并不是一个非常明智而谨慎的计划。因为，如果之前有关谋杀所设立的司法程序是有效的，那么设立新的法律来处理这个案件就没有任何意义。无论如何，谋杀已经发生了，也对其进行了调查。不过，即使是在这件事情备受大家关注的时候也没有人因此指控我，你竟然在事隔多年之后以此来指责我。

接着，你又对我作出轻率而又冗长的指控。你说是我让恺撒疏远庞培，因此导致了内战。你所犯的错误不仅是对事实的扭曲，更重要的是连时间都搞错了。的确，在杰出的马库斯·卡尔普米厄斯·彼布卢斯担任执政官期间，我曾不遗余力地想让庞培离开恺撒。但是恺撒更为成功一些，因为他让庞培和我疏远起来。当庞培全心全意加入恺撒阵营的时候，我又怎么能使他们分开呢？如果这时我还对此抱有希望，那就愚蠢至极了；如果我还试图说服庞培，那就太不合时宜了。不过，我的确曾两次劝导庞培来反对恺撒。如果你一定要指责我，这倒可以成为你的理由。第一，我建议他不要让恺撒在高卢续任五年；第二，我建议他不要承认在自己缺席时恺撒所获得的执政官候选人资格。如果这两次中有一次成功，那我们也就不必承受现在的苦难了。

但是相反地，庞培带着自己和罗马的所有军队投奔了恺撒。只是在这发生以后，他才开始理解我在很久之前所做的预言，但是为时已晚。同样是在这个时候，我意识到我们国家马上就要遭受一场浩劫。这也就是为什么从那时起我一直呼吁和平、和谐与和解。很多人都知道我说过：“庞培，要是你没有与恺撒结盟，或者，要是你没有与恺撒闹翻，那该多好啊！但是你坚定的个性决定了前者，你的英明决定了后者。”安东尼，这是我一直给庞培和我们国家提出的建议，如果这个建议被采纳了，那么我们的国家现在依然会繁荣昌盛。但是你却不会，因为你会被你无耻、肮脏的行为所毁灭。

不过，这些都已经是陈年往事了。现在，你又指控恺撒之死是我造成的。众位元老院议员们：我担心此时看上去似乎我犯下一桩可叹的过错，即在一项针对我的事件中，导致一位虚假的控诉人的诞生——无论我是否当得起，他都对我充满赞扬。有谁听过我也是这项光荣行动的参与者呢？再说，有哪位参与者隐瞒了自己的名字呢？如果真是我所说的隐瞒，那为什么大家会立即知道他们每个人的名字呢？相信我，就算有些人没有参与这件事也会吹嘘自己参与过，而不是说，有人参与了却想要掩盖这个事实。参与这件事的人很多，有的人默默无闻，有的人很年轻，他们都不是那种能保守别人身份秘密之人。所以，如果我真的参与了，但是却没有人知道我参与过，这究竟是为什么呢？

此外，就算我们认为这个行动的发起者需要别人的激励才能解放自己的祖国，难道是我鼓励那两位布鲁特斯的吗？他们两个人每天都会在自己家里看到卢修斯·朱尼厄斯·布鲁特斯的雕像，而另外一个还能看到盖恩斯·瑟维菲厄斯·阿哈拉的塑像。有这样的祖先，这些活着的布鲁特斯家族人根本不需要外人的建议，因为他们自己家里一直都有为他们提供意见之人。同样，盖厄斯·卡修斯·郎吉努斯也属于这样的家族，他不能容忍一个贵族甚至任何人拥有过高的权力。很显然，他的确需要我这样的顾问！但是，在他还没有现在这些杰出的顾问之前，卡修斯就认为如果恺撒将船泊在河岸的这一边而非另一边，他便打算在居努斯河口西里西亚执行这个任务。同样地，当恢复自由这一任务受到威胁之时，格奈乌斯·多米提乌斯难道需要我来鼓励他吗？他尊贵的父亲之死、他母舅之死以及他自己怎么被剥夺了公民权利这些痛苦的记忆难道不足以激励着他来完成这项光荣的任务吗？至于盖厄斯·却波尼乌斯，难道也是我说服他的吗？他与恺撒那么亲近，我甚至根本不敢冒险去建议他。不过正是由于他们之间的亲密关系使我们国家和人民更加感激他。因为对他来讲，罗马人民的自由比他个人的友谊更重要。他本可以和恺撒一起实行独裁统治，而他却选择推翻独裁统治。又或者，是我建议卢修斯·提留斯·基伯尔这么做的？当然不是，在他完成了这一任务之后，我对他肃然起敬，因为在这之前我没有信心认为他会参与这一行动。我之所以敬仰他更多的是因为他不顾自身的利益，全心全意只为罗马着想。然后是两位赛维留斯，我不知道该叫他们卡斯卡[4]还是阿哈拉？你认为他们需要我的建议吗？难道他们不是因为热爱自己的祖国吗？列举出剩下的所有人会花费太多的时间，因为人数众多。这不仅仅是他们个人的荣誉，也是整个罗马的荣誉。

但是，请看看，这个狡猾的人是怎么证明我是他们的同谋的。他说：“在恺撒被杀之后，布鲁特斯立即挥舞着他那沾满鲜血的匕首，并喊着西塞罗的名字向他祝贺国家恢复了自由。”但是，就凭他选择喊我的名字而不是其他人名字这一点就能断定我是同谋吗？这根本不是他喊我名字的原因，他所做的事情和我所做的事情非常相似，所以他喊我的名字以表明他以我为榜样。

安东尼，你多么愚蠢啊！你难道不理解这一点吗？如果想要杀掉恺撒（就如你所指责的那样）就是犯罪，那么如果因为他的死而感到高兴便也是犯罪了，因为一种行为的倡导者和在这件事被实施后对其表示赞同之人没有任何差别。不管是我希望完成这件事还是在它实施后表现出很愉快都是一样的。但是，除了那些拥护他为独裁统治者的人，所有人都希望他被杀死，所有人也都会因他被杀死而感到高兴，所以每个人都有罪。每个人都在恺撒被杀这件事上有一定的作用，虽然有些人计划不周、勇气不足、缺少机会，但是每个人都想要杀掉恺撒。

就让我们听一下他，更确切地说，听一下这个胆小鬼的胡言乱语吧！他说：“每当我提到布鲁特斯的名字时，心中都充满了对他的尊敬之情。在布鲁特斯手持沾满鲜血的匕首时，他大喊西塞罗的名字，由此可知西塞罗是他的同谋。”所以，就因为你怀疑我可能做了某些事就认定我是一个罪犯，况且那个手持血淋淋匕首的人是你提到的自己“非常尊敬”之人。你说的这些话已经够愚蠢了，但是你的行为和想法更加愚蠢。执政官啊！你一定要考虑清楚，因为你必须对布鲁特斯家族之人，对盖厄斯·卡修斯、格奈乌斯·多米提乌斯、盖厄斯·却波尼乌斯以及其他剩下之人的行为作出最终的评判。好好休息吧！别再醉话连篇了。或许，必须得用一个火炬才能让你从昏睡中清醒。难道你真的不清楚参与这件事的那些人究竟是谋杀犯，还是让恢复国家自由的解放者吗？

请集中精力，哪怕只有一小会儿！让你的头脑好好运转一下，就像你清醒着一样。我承认我是他们的朋友，但你更愿意将我称为他们的同谋。但是，我还是不想看到任何折中的解决方法。如果这些人没有解放罗马人民、拯救国家，那么，我会认为他们比刺客、比杀人犯还要可恶。如果我们认为弑杀国父要比弑杀自己的父亲更加穷凶极恶，那他们连弑父者都不如。

所以，聪明而又周到的人啊！如果他们是弑父者，你为什么在元老院会议和罗马人民的集会上对他们尊敬有加？为什么在马库斯·布鲁特斯离开城市10多天后，提议让他得到豁免1？为什么在阿波罗赛会上人们会对他赞不绝口？为什么这么多行省赋予布鲁特斯和盖厄斯荣耀，要为他们指派额外的财务官和使者？这些事情都是你做的，很显然你并1.作为保民官不允许离开罗马10天以上。

没有将他们当作杀人犯。鉴于没有其他折中的可能，所以你无疑是将他们当作解放者来看待的。因此，这究竟是怎么回事？我并没有让你难堪，不是吗？我觉得你很擅长处理这种情况带给你的困境。不过，我最后的结论是：你并没有将布鲁特斯和其他相关人等当作罪犯，这也就是你在无意识地宣告他们应该得到最丰厚的奖赏。

因此，我必须重新组织我的演讲。我应该写信给这些人，告诉他们如果有任何人向他们问起你对我的指控是否属实，请他们不要否认这一点。因为如果我是他们的共谋，而他们又隐藏了这个事实，这恐怕会有损他们的声誉；但是，如果是他们想要邀请我，却遭到我的拒绝，这样也会使我的声誉大为受损。上天为证！除了罗马，世上还有哪个国家的人有过这样的壮举？再也没有比这更加光荣、更加伟大的行为了，他们会流芳百世！所以，如果你认为我是特洛伊木马，与这件事的主谋一起合谋，我没有任何异议。相反，不管你出于什么动机，我都要感谢你，因为事关这一伟大的行动，我认为你要强加给我的污点不是别的正是一种荣耀。

你吹嘘说你将这些人赶走并驱逐出去。但是，他们福泽无边。世上没有那么荒凉和野蛮的地方，人们定会欢迎他们的到来并为此感到愉快。世界上的人，不管他们的文明程度多低，都懂得这些人能够为他们带来幸福。他们的光荣事迹将被一代又一代的作家永远传颂。

我祈求你，把我也列入这些英雄的行列吧！但是，我担心有一件事你不会赞同。如果我是他们中的一员，我不仅让我们的国家摆脱了这一个独裁者，也摆脱了独裁统治。如果正如你所断定的那样，我是这部作品的作者，那么相信我，我绝不会满足于仅完成了这一项任务，我会完成整个剧本[5]。

如果想让恺撒死是一种罪，那么想想你自己的处境吧，安东尼！众所周知，你和盖厄斯·却波尼乌斯在那波制定了一个类似的计划，正是由于这个计划，却波尼乌斯才在恺撒被杀的时候让你置身事外。如此看来，我对你是友好的。我赞美你曾有过的善意，我感谢你没有将计划外泄，我原谅你没有参与实施。这项任务需要另外一个人来完成。

但是，如果有人用法官卢修斯·卡修斯·朗吉努斯的名言“那么谁会受益呢”来控告你，你就要小心一点，因为你可能会受到牵连。的确如此，之前你便注意到这会使那些不愿意成为奴隶的人受益。然而，这一行动对谁最有益呢？是你自己。你不仅摆脱了奴隶这一身份，甚至可以说成为了一个独裁统治者。你利用奥普斯神庙里的钱财还清了你的巨额债务；你篡改这些账本浪费了无数的钱财；你将恺撒家里无数的财产转移给自己。那些在你家里伪造的虚假票据和你所模仿的笔迹为你提供了多么大的一笔财富啊！你的家简直就是一个专门伪造文件的作坊，一个黑市，在那里进行与土地和城市有关的可耻交易，免除了大量的税务。

唯有恺撒之死才能将你从你债务人的毁灭之中解救出来。你看起来很紧张，是不是在暗自担心会受到牵连？不会的，我向你保证：你不必担心，没有人会相信你有这样的行为。我们国家有完成这一光荣任务的伟大之人。我并没有说你参与其中，只是说你对此感到高兴而已。

现在，我对你最严重的指控已经作出回答。接下来，我必须对其他指控也作出回应。你指责我曾出现在庞培的军营，指责我在那段时间的所做所为。的确，就像我之前所说的那样——如果那个时候大家接受了我的建议，现在的你就会是一个可怜之人，而我们大家都可以享受自由，我们国家也不会损失那么多的军队和指挥官。当我预见现在所要发生的事情之时，我和其他忠诚的公民一样感到十分悲伤，如果他们也有我那样的预见的话。众位元老院议员，我很悲伤，我为我们的共和国即将灭亡而感到悲伤，那可是你们众位议员以及我的顾问们曾竭力保护的共和国啊！在这种情况下，我还不至于因为无知而担心自己是否能继续存活下去。虽然我现在还活着，但是我的生活却充满了痛苦，失去生命对我来说也就意味着结束所有的麻烦。不过，我希望那些杰出之士能够继续活下去，他们是罗马的荣耀，是我们的执政官、执法官、优秀的元老院议员，是我们高贵之士的希望，是忠诚的罗马人民所组成的军队。对我来说，任何能够使我们人民团结的和平都比那些让他们自相残杀的战争要好得多。事实上，不管实现和平的环境有多么恶劣，如果这些人现在还活着，至少我们会觉得共和国仍与我们同在。

如果我的这一观点得到广泛的认可，如果我想要保住他们生命的那些人并没有在对他们的武装力量过分乐观的情况下与我为敌，一定会出现这样的结果：元老院不能容你，甚至整个罗马也不能容你。

你驳斥我，认为是我的演讲使庞培疏远了我，这简直太荒谬了！他对我的关心比其他任何人都多。庞培和我之间的交流，以及他对我的请教比世界上其他任何人都要频繁。对于两个在政务上观点如此不同的人来说，能成为这么亲密的朋友实非易事。我们两人都熟知彼此的想法和观点。我最关心的就是让我们的罗马同胞们活下去，只有这样我们随后才有机会来考虑他们的公民权利。相反地，庞培所关注的是他们当下的权利。但是不管怎样，我们之间的分歧在可容忍的范围之内。并且，因为我们双方都专注于自己的具体目标，所以分歧更是在可容忍的范围之内。

那些和庞培一起从法塞利亚撤退到帕福斯的人很了解这位杰出的人物对我的看法。当他提到我的名字时都是赞美的话语，并为我们没有在一起而感到十分遗憾。他自己也承认，他对未来抱有很高的希望，而我对未来拥有更准的预测。但是，你在承认我是庞培朋友的同时，又怎么能无耻地以他的名义指控我？别忘了，你甚至买下了他那些被充公的财物。

不过不管怎样，我们还是不要再讨论这场你在其中极为幸运的战争了。并且，我也不会回复你对我在军营时所讲的那些笑话的指控。那里生活的确不易，但是无论环境有多恶劣，人们——只要他们还是人——便会偶尔放松一下。安东尼不但批判我的悲伤，就连我讲的笑话也要批判！不过这也恰好证明了我在这两方面都很有节制。

你说没有人给我留下任何遗产[6]。我多么希望你的这个指控是对的啊！因为这意味着我的很多朋友和亲戚现在都还健在。但是，我想知道你怎么会有这个想法，事实上别人留给我的遗产加起来已经超过了两千万赛斯特斯[7]。我承认在这方面你一直都比我幸运，因为我所继承的东西都来自于我的朋友，他们认为留给我的这些财产可以抚慰我的悲伤，如果可以起到这种作用的话。但是，你竟然是卢修斯·鲁伯里厄斯·卡西纳斯的财产继承人，你跟他素未谋面，连他究竟是黑是白都不知道啊！他一定是非常喜欢你才会将你立为继承人吧。他甚至越过他朋友昆塔斯·富菲乌斯（一位非常值得尊敬的骑士）的儿子，直接将你立为他的财产继承人。鲁伯里厄斯一直对外宣称富菲乌斯的儿子将会是他的财产继承人，而他竟然没有出现在其遗嘱之中。相反地，你却成为他的财产继承人，可是他之前从来也没见过你，甚至没跟你说过一句话啊！如果方便的话，请你告诉我，你的另一位恩主卢修斯·忒赛留斯长什么样子，身高是多少，来自哪里，哪个部族？你会回答说“我什么都不知道，除了他所拥有的那些财产”。难道这一回答就足以让他剥夺自己兄弟的财产继承权而改立你为继承人吗？此外，还有很多人，他们几乎和安东尼没有任何关系，而安东尼却将他们真正的继承人加以驱逐，从他们手里攫取了大量的钱财，就像自己是他们的继承人一样。

让我觉得惊讶的还有另外一个原因，你连自己父亲的继承人都不是，就敢厚颜无耻地提到遗产继承这个问题。

愚蠢的家伙啊！难道这些就是你在另外一个人的别墅里一天又一天地练习辩论所找到的论证吗？不过，正如你最亲密的朋友所说的那样，你练习辩论只是为了清除宿醉而不是使你的思维更加机智。在那些酒徒朋友的支持下，你就像开玩笑一样为自己找了一位演说老师，并允许他以任何方式来反驳你。而他肯定也是一个十分搞笑的家伙，但是由于你和你的朋友是他反驳的对象，他也不能抱怨缺乏反驳你们的实例。

请看一下你和你祖父之间的区别吧！他在深思熟虑之后会提出与自己情况相关的论证，而你呢，只会说一些无关紧要的话语。就这样，你的辩论老师竟然还从你那里得到了丰厚的报酬。众位元老院议员们，请听听他给国家造成的损失吧！他给了这位辩论老师——赛克斯都·克劳狄厄斯1250英亩的土地，并且免除了税务。安东尼，你让罗马人民为你支付了这笔巨额学费，但是最后除了把自己学成一个傻瓜外，你还学到其他东西了吗？你这个毫无原则的家伙！难道这也是你在恺撒的记事本中找到的指令吗？不过关于列奥蒂尼这片土地和坎帕尼亚的那些土地，我稍后会提到。这些全是安东尼从罗马人民手中掠夺的，他将这些土地赠给那些品行低下之人，任由他们玷污。

对于他的指控我已经作出了充分的回答。现在，我必须来说一下我们这位道德家和改革家本人了。不过，我并不打算一次把所有故事都讲完。这样的话，如果我又回到某个争论之中就不必再重复自己说过的话了。由于他的罪行和错误简直罄竹难书，所以这对我来说没有任何困难。

安东尼，你想让我们从你童年时期的行为开始说起吗？我想是的，就让我们从头开始吧。你还记得你少年时期的破产吗？你肯定会说那是你父亲的错误。这的确是作为子女的自我辩护！你自年少时便鲁莽无知。当时洛斯基乌斯法案为破产者指定了特殊座位，不论其破产是因为运气不佳还是行为不端，但是你去剧院后却坐在了为骑士们预留的第十四排座位之中。接着，你穿上了成年男子的托袈，或者就你的所作所为而言，更确切地说应该是女人的托袈。起初，你只是一个普通的男妓，靠这个收取固定的费用，并且价格奇高。但是，没有多久库里奥出现了，他将你从这个行当中赎回。就像有人说的那样，让你拥有了妻子般的地位，使你俨然成为了一个拥有持久稳定婚姻的妇女。从来没有一个男子像你那样完全是因为主人库里奥的淫欲才被买来的。多少次，他的父亲将你扔出家门，甚至派人驻守在门外防止你进入。但是，在黑夜的帮助之下，淫欲的促使之下，钱财的驱使之下，你甚至会爬上房顶进去。

那个家庭根本不能容忍这样不耻的勾当。你知道吗？我对我现在所说的事情一清二楚。那个时候库里奥的父亲躺在床上老泪纵横，而他的儿子也泪眼婆娑地跪在我脚下，祈求我帮助你，并让我为他辩护，否则他就得给他父亲600万赛斯特斯保证金。那个年轻人深爱着你，他发誓要离开这个国家，因为他不能忍受与你分离。那时，我为那个显赫的家庭解决了无数的问题或者说为所有问题画上了句号。我说服这位父亲来偿还儿子的债务，并用自己的一部分财产来让这个年轻人重获社会地位，因为他的头脑和性格都是极好的。但是，我也劝导他行使自己作为父亲的合法权威来阻止库里奥与你亲近，甚至阻止他与你见面。当你回想起我所做的这些事之后，只有一样东西能给你挑战和侮辱我的勇气，那就是你所拥有的强有力的武器，就是我们今天在元老院看到的那些。

不过关于安东尼那堕落、淫逸的生活我就说到这里，因为有的事情我觉得说出来真是有失体面。就演说的自由而言，安东尼比我更有优势，因为他所做的那些事情对一位值得尊敬的对手来说是不屑于提起的。所以，我现在简单地谈一下他在这之后的生活。我们会很自然地想到他在国家遭受内战之苦时的所作所为以及他现在的行为举止。众位议员们，你们和我一样都知道这些事情，甚至比我了解得更清楚。不过，我还是恳请你们继续仔细地听下去，因为在这种情况下仅仅了解这些事情是不够的，它们必须被重新提起，这样才能使我们对其有深切的感受。

但是由于时间有限，我就长话短说。安东尼现在向我示好，然而在帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯担任保民官的时候，他与克劳狄厄斯是亲密的朋友，是克劳狄厄斯所有阴谋的煽动者。事实上，安东尼的一个阴谋就是在克劳狄厄斯家中计划的，他很清楚我说的是哪一个。接着，他不顾元老院的权威、不顾国家的利益、不顾上天的旨意去了亚历山大里亚。不过在伽比纽斯的领导之下，他的行为似乎没有任何不当之处。接下来，我们来想想安东尼返回的本质和情景吧。在他回家之前，他从埃及到了最远的高卢。回家？我说的是回家吗？那时，其他人还有家；但是你——安东尼——根本就没有家。家？除了塞米努，这世上根本没有你的容身之处。不过那个地方也是你和同伙所共有的，就像西萨波矿一样。

离开高卢后，你参加了财务官的竞选。我敢断定在那种情况下你在见我之前先去见拜见了你的父亲。因为在这之前我就已经收到恺撒的一封信，他在信中让我接受你所陈述的理由，所以我甚至不允许你对我表以谢意。在那之后，你对我尊敬有加，我也帮助你获得了财务官候选人的资格。也就是在那个时候，在罗马人民的赞成之下你想要杀掉帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯。这完全是你自己的想法，和我一点关系都没有，你认为只有杀掉他才能补偿我因你而遭受的苦难。不过，现在你为什么又说米洛是在我的怂恿之下杀死了克劳狄厄斯？即使是在你自告奋勇要去做这件事的时候，我也并没有给你任何鼓励。我认为，如果你真的做了这件事，也不过是因为自己想要获得荣誉而已，并不是受我的影响。

就这样，你成为了财务官。但是在没有元老院法令的允许下，在没有抽签也没有任何法律认可的情况下，你立即投向了恺撒的怀抱。那里是身陷绝境之人唯一的避难所，你觉得只有那个地方才能使你摆脱贫穷和债务，才能免于因罪受罚。恺撒慷慨的赏赐和你的掠夺让你补偿了自己的损失——如果你所贪污的那些公款被你立即挥霍后也能称为一种补偿的话。接着，你又百般祈求想要成为保民官。也许，你想成为保民官的目的只是为了模仿你的情人吧！

元老院的议员们，请你们了解这一点。我想说的并不是安东尼那些令人作呕的不当行为给他自己造成的各种丑闻，而是他以邪恶和无礼的手段对我们所有人、我们的财富以及我们整个国家所造成的伤害。我们所有灾难的根源都与他的罪行相关。当卢修斯·科尼利厄斯·伦图卢斯和盖厄斯·克劳狄厄斯·马凯鲁斯在1月1日担任执政官后，罗马共和政府就岌岌可危。众位元老院议员都想要保住这个国家，如果恺撒头脑正常的话，你们甚至愿意满足他的愿望。但是，安东尼却在这时将自己的保民官职位卖给别人并臣服于另外一人。此外，他利用职务之便处处对你们进行阻挠。也就是说，安东尼已经放肆到将自己的脖子置于刀斧之下，而这刀斧已经处置过众多比他所犯之罪还要轻的人。那时，元老院还可以自行做主，现在那些受人尊敬但已经去世的议员们还是其中的一员。元老院为了惩罚你，根据古老的传统颁布了这项法令，这是针对那些罗马公敌所设立的。你竟然如此鲁莽，在众位元老院议员面前批判我。要知道元老院曾宣布，我是国家的拯救者，而你是国家的敌人。

虽然我现在并没有提起你在那时所犯的罪行，但这并不表示它们被忘记了。只要这世界上还有人在，只要罗马这个名字还在（它会永存于世，除非被你摧毁），那么你那致命的否决[8]就会永远存在于人们的记忆之中。在元老院的会议记录中，没有一点儿偏见和夸张。你一个年轻人投了否决票，使得整个元老院不能通过一项关乎国家安全的法令。并且，这样的事情你做了不止一次，做过很多次。此外，你拒绝与元老院进行任何谈判。在这种关键的时刻，你的这一举动并不亚于你想让整个国家陷入混乱和废墟之中。不管是国家首领的请求、长者的警告还是整个元老院都不能阻止你提出这项法令，因为你早已被别人贿赂和收买。

所以，在多次劝导无果后，大家别无他法，只能对你进行严厉的打击。只有极少数人受到过这种打击，并且无一生还。于是，元老院命令执政官以及其他权力机构拿起武器来反抗你，而你只能躲在恺撒背后。

恺撒企图发动革命。但是，是你——安东尼——让恺撒有了向自己祖国开战的借口。恺撒在作出他那疯狂的决定和行为时唯一的借口就是：元老院无视保民官的否决权，这是对保民官应有权利的否定，安东尼的权利受到了侵犯。虽然任何一个拿起武器反抗自己国家的人都没有正当的理由，事实上我也并不是想说这些理由非常虚伪、无足轻重。因为我想说的并不是恺撒，而是你——安东尼。是你为这个最可怕的战争提供了理由，这一点不容否认。

如果你已经知道我接下来要说什么，那么你就明白你的命运将非常悲哀；如果你不知道，那就更加悲哀了。现有的书面记录证明了这些事情的发生，而且这些事情会永远留在我们子孙后代的记忆之中。那里面记录着执政官们被驱逐出意大利；同他们一起被驱逐的还有庞培，而他一人的荣光就足以照亮我们整个国家；只要身体还能忍受，所有的前执政官都纷纷撤退，所有的执法官、前执法官、保民官，大部分元老院议员、大批年轻人，总而言之，所有的罗马人都被驱逐出自己的家园。

正如种子是大树和植物的根源一样，你就是那场最可怕战争的种子。元老院的议员们，你们正在为在战争中惨遭覆灭的三个部队而悲伤，是安东尼杀了他们啊！你们正在为罗马的那些伟人感到哀痛，是安东尼夺走了他们的生命啊！元老院权威被摧毁，是安东尼毁了它啊！从那时开始，我们所看到的每一个不幸（还有什么是我们没见过的呢？）都是他造成的，再无其他任何可能。就如同特洛伊人眼中的海伦一样，他给我们国家带来了战争、伤害和毁灭。

他在保民官剩下的任期中的表现和刚开始没什么区别。当罗马共和国还存在的时候，在元老院认为那些不可能犯下的罪行中，他一样都没有落下。并且，请注意他所犯下的罪中之罪，虽然他让许多不幸的人恢复了荣誉，却唯独将他的叔叔排除在外。如果他是一个严厉之人，为什么不对每一个人都严厉？如果他是一个仁慈之人，为什么对自己的亲人不仁慈？

在他恢复公民权利的那些人中，我只想说一下他那位被判定犯有赌博罪的同伴利慈尼乌斯·丹提库卢。我只能这样想：安东尼认为虽然他的同伴聚在赌桌旁，但肯定没有犯罪。不过，他真正的目的是免除自己的赌债，赦免丹提库卢罪行的这一法令只是托词而已。安东尼，现在你能向罗马人民说出你恢复他公民权利的正当理由吗？一般人可能会这样反驳：丹提库卢是在没有出庭的情况下被起诉定罪的；这个案件根本没有论据来证实；法律没有就掷骰子作出司法审判的规定；或者说这是屈打成招的结果；又或者，就像你叔叔案例中最后的反驳一样，法庭作出这样的判决是因为收受贿赂。但是，根本不是这样，这些都不是你的理由。你声称丹提库卢是一个好人，对国家有用。虽然这与案情没有任何关系，不过如果你说的这一点是事实，我也不会反对你，毕竟赌博并不是多么严重的罪行。但是，你所说的话没有一个字是真的。丹提库卢被定罪不仅仅是因为赌博，他竟敢在讲坛上肆意赌博，简直是罪大恶极。如果一个人为这样的恶棍恢复权利，那这也证明了他自己的品格大有问题。

接着，我们看一下安东尼在担任保民官期间的其他行为。恺撒去西班牙后，将意大利托付给安东尼，安东尼对其任意践踏。他的那些旅程和他所到达的那些城镇很值得我们进行深入探讨。不过，我意识到我现在所讲的问题大家都很清楚并且经常议论。我也知道我对自己现在所说的和将要说的事情的了解甚至没有当时任何一个在意大利的人清楚，因为我那时候并不在意大利。虽然我要说的肯定没有你们所知道的多，但是请允许我讲一些特定的细节。

世界上怎么会有人作出这样卑鄙无耻的事情？身为人民的保民官，他竟然坐着一辆女式马车出行。在他前面，侍从们头戴月桂花环一路前行。队伍中，有一个坐着露天式轿子的女戏子。城中那些高贵之士被迫前来迎接他，并向女戏子问好。他们并没有用她那闻名遐迩的戏名来称呼她，而是称其为伏鲁尼娅。在这之后是一辆四轮马车，车上全是那些拉皮条的，是安东尼那些令人讨厌的朋友。接下来是被他忽略的母亲，她和她那堕落儿子的情人待在一起，就像婆婆一样。可恶的女人，她的生育给大家带来了多大的灾难啊！就这样，安东尼在很多城镇，事实上是在整个意大利都留下了他那无耻的印记。

众位元老院议员们，对他的其他行为进行谴责确实是一件困难而艰巨的事情。他参加过战争，身上沾满了敌人的鲜血，不过那些敌人是与他势不两立的罗马人。如果犯罪也能交上好运的话，他就是那个幸运的人。但是，我并不想冒犯那些老兵——因为这些士兵的情况和安东尼完全不一样（他们只是追随自己的领导，而你却是主动追随别人），所以对于这场战争的性质我不会说什么，不会让你有任何机会来煽动他们反抗我。

作为一个征服者，你带着你的军团从帖撒利回到布隆迪西。但是，你竟然在布隆迪西没有杀掉我，多么仁慈啊！我承认，你本可以杀了我的。不过，那时你身边的人全都认为必须宽恕我。甚至你自己的军团也对我尊敬有加，因为他们记得是我拯救了他们的国家。爱国之情是多么伟大啊！不过，就让我们假设：如果你没从我这里掠夺的东西就可以当作你给我的礼物；那么你没有剥夺我的生命其实也是对我的一种恩惠了。但是，在听了你对我的所有侮辱之后，我几乎忘记了你对我的恩惠，但是我并没有忘记。此外，你知道我会以什么方式来还击你，所以你才会肆无忌惮地侮辱我。

到达布隆迪西对你而言就意味着你可以与你的女戏子尽情地拥抱、热吻。什么？这是谎话吗？不能否认，那些有损自己名誉的事情的确很痛苦，难道不是吗？不过，如果在那些城镇居民面前你没有感到羞耻，难道在自己的老兵面前你也不觉得羞耻吗？哪一个在布隆迪西的士兵没有见过她？哪一个士兵不知道她远道而来向你祝贺？哪一个士兵不为太晚发现自己追随的领导是一个卑劣之人而感到悲伤？

此外，这个女戏子又陪着你去了意大利。你派重兵把守你所经过的那些镇子，到处都是残忍、不幸的景象。在罗马，你自己也从那个可悲之人沦落成黄金、白银还有美酒的掠夺者。最重要的是，恺撒的朋友对你青睐有加，在恺撒不知情的情况下（他当时在亚历山大里亚）便任命你为骑兵统领。那个时候，你觉得自己有权和西庇亚住在一起，并且把那些用于国家比赛的赛马交给了另外一个戏子瑟古厄斯。安东尼那时并没有选择住在他现在费尽周折才得到的房子里，而是住在马库斯·庇索的房子里。我对他的那些法令，那些掠夺物，那些因继承或霸占而得的遗产都不予置评，是需求迫使他这么做的。除此之外，他毫无选择。因为他还没有从卢修斯·鲁伯里厄斯和卢修斯·忒塞留斯那里得到丰厚的遗产，也没有成为庞培和其他人的财产继承人。他不得不过着强盗般的生活，因为他一无所有，除非他抢到东西。

不过，他的这一类恶行就先说到这里。我们还是来看看他那些更加卑鄙无耻的丑行吧。在西庇亚的婚礼上，安东尼——你用尽你角斗士般的力气胡吃海喝，结果因为喝了太多的酒，第二天在大庭广众之下呕吐不止。那场景简直太恶心了，即使是听到也会让人觉得恶心。如果在一个私人宴会上你还像在那场婚礼上一样，到处都是你那硕大的酒杯，所有人都会认为这是十分可耻的。但是，在罗马人民的集会上，一个担任公职之人，一个骑兵统领却吐得到处都是，可本来对他而言就算是打嗝也是不得体的。他也承认这是他非常失礼的一个行为。现在我们来看看他那些比这更加可恶的罪行吧！

恺撒从亚历山大里亚返回，他认为自己是个幸运之人，但我认为一个给自己国家带来不幸的人根本不能被称作是一个幸运之人。他在朱庇特神庙前竖起了长矛，而庞培的财产——一想到这里我就悲痛不已，即使是眼泪流尽了，悲伤还是深深地印在心底——哎！庞培的财产被那些拍卖者无情地拍卖了。

整个共和国都为此忧伤。虽然奴隶制已被忘却，但是恐惧让人们觉得自己仍然是一个奴隶，即使是这样，罗马人民还是深深地为此哀悼。所有人都在等着看会不会有一些疯狂的无耻之徒胆敢悖逆上天和人类的意愿来参加这个罪恶的拍卖。虽然也有一些人聚在长矛周围，但也仅此而已。只有安东尼一个人胆敢参加拍卖，只有他！只有他一个无耻到犯下这样的罪行，而其他人不管有多无耻也都因为心有所怯而没有参加拍卖。不过，安东尼你是不是太愚蠢了，或者说疯狂更合适一些，你竟然没有意识到购买这些被没收的财物，并且是购买庞培的财物会使你不仅现在而且永远成为罗马人民咒骂的对象，成为诸神和所有人憎恨的对象。这个房子的主人曾凭借他的勇猛让其他国家对罗马更加敬畏，凭借他的公正让其他国家对罗马更加热爱，而你这个贪婪的人竟然无耻地立即占有了他的房子。

安东尼在突然得到这个伟大之人的财物后便沉溺于快乐之中，就像戏剧中那些一夜暴富的穷人一样。但是，正如一些诗人写的那样“不义之财，来去匆匆”。不过让人难以相信的是：他不是在几个月内而是几天之内就挥霍掉了庞培的大笔财产，这简直是一个“奇迹”。那栋房子里有大量的美酒，众多精美无比的银器，价值不菲的长袍，大气而又优雅的家具——庞培虽然生活并不奢侈，却正当地拥有不少财产。但是，所有的这些东西在几天之内便一件都不剩了。就算卡里狄斯她真的存在，也只是一个动物而已。我敢发誓，即使是大海也很难将这些分散在各处的大量财物以那样的速度吞没。

所有东西都没有上锁、没有封印也没有登记。房子里所有的东西都被当作礼物送给那些无赖之徒。那些男戏子和女戏子也得到了他们想要的一切。房子里到处都是赌徒和醉汉。一连好几天，房子里很多地方肆无忌惮的喝酒狂欢在持续不断。安东尼的好运也只是暂时的，输的钱渐渐多了起来。而那些曾经属于庞培的精美床单，现在竟然在奴隶们的阁楼里，在他们的床上！

希望你们不会对这一大笔财产以这样的速度被花掉而感到惊讶。像安东尼这样肆意挥霍，不只是一个人的遗产——即使是像庞培那样充裕的遗产，就算是整个城市和整个国家的遗产也能很快被花光。不仅如此，他还占有了房子和花园！安东尼，你简直是厚颜无耻到了极点！你怎么敢踏进那个房子，跨过那道最为神圣的门槛？你怎么敢让住在那里的门神看到你那张无耻的嘴脸？长久以来，人们都会在看到或经过这栋房子时流下悲伤的眼泪。你竟然敢住在这里，难道不觉得羞耻吗？

虽然你十分愚蠢，但我敢肯定，这里没有什么东西能给你带来快乐。当你在走廊里看到这些船只[9]的时候，你根本不可能把这栋房子当成自己的。这点毫无疑问！虽然你麻木不仁，但你还知道自己是谁，知道自己的朋友和财产，所以，我相信不管你是醒着还是睡了都不会感到安心。虽然你会因为喝酒而神志不清，但是当他在你梦里出现的时候，你一定会被惊醒；同样地，当你清醒的时候，他那反复出现的身影定会让你思绪更加混乱。

我为那座房子的墙壁和屋顶感到悲哀，因为在这之前，它们所见证的都是严格的礼节——美好、高尚的传统与美德。众位议员，正如你们所了解的那样，庞培不管是在国内还是国际事务的处理上都是值得称颂的，不管是在私人生活还是公共事务方面都享有很高的声誉。但是，如今他家里的每个餐厅都变了酒馆，每个卧室都成了妓院。不过，安东尼现在可能会对这些都予以否认。他现在已经变聪明了，这点不需要证明，因为他已经变得节俭了。按照十二铜牌法令，他让他的女戏子收拾好她的东西，并且让她归还了自己的钥匙，然后把她赶了出去。多好的一个公民啊！多么值得人尊敬啊！他和女戏子分手了，这是他一生中做的最光荣的一件事。

他经常使用“我，执政官安东尼”这个短语。其实这就相当于在说“我，纵欲的执政官”或者“我，罪恶的执政官”，因为这就是“安东尼”的意义。如果这个名字还有一点尊严，我想是因为你的祖父也许有时会称自己“执政官，安东尼”。但事实上，他从来没有这么做过。你的叔叔也是如此，他是我的同僚。难道只有你一个人叫安东尼吗？

不过，我想略过这些过错，因为它们与你在摧毁我们国家时所扮演的角色没有直接关系。我们还是来谈谈后者——内战吧！内战的起因、发生和后果都是你造成的。但是你在战争中却无足轻重，因为你胆小如鼠，或者更恰当点说你只专注于自己的淫欲。但是，你也曾品尝甚至痛饮罗马人民的鲜血。你曾在法塞利亚的前线杀死了尊贵的卢修斯·多米提乌和众多从战场中逃亡的人。即使是恺撒也很有可能会饶恕他们，因为他的确曾经饶恕过其他一些人。但是，你却将他们赶尽杀绝。

然而，在取得了这些重要和辉煌的成就后，战争还在持续。为什么你不追随恺撒到阿非利加继续征战？我们来看看恺撒从阿非利加回来后赐给你的职位和头衔吧！当他是统帅的时候，你是他的财务官；他是独裁者的时候，你是他的骑兵统领。事实上，这场战争是你发起的，恺撒的每一个暴行都是你怂恿的，在一场场连续的抢劫中，你也一直都是他的同伙。你自己认为恺撒在遗嘱中会将你当作养子[10]，而他那个时候在做什么呢？他在采取措施对付你，你在拍卖中因为买房子、花园以及其他财物所欠的钱，恺撒都要求你如数返还。

你的回答在刚开始异常可恶，不过，我承认有些地方是公平合理的，我不想让人觉得我对你有偏见。“恺撒要钱是因为我吗？难道我不是因为他才要钱的？或者说没有我的帮助他能在这场战争中获胜吗？当然不是，没有我他不可能赢。是我！为他发动内战提供借口；是我！提出了那些邪恶的法令；是我！不但竭力反对罗马人民的执政官和将军，而且反对整个元老院和罗马人民，反对天上的诸神、祭坛和我们祖先的家园——实际上是反抗整个罗马。恺撒不是独自一人完成征服的，为什么共苦的人不能同甘呢？”的确很合理，但这个理由不能击中要害，因为恺撒是比较强的那一个。所以，为了平息你的不满，他派了士兵去见你和你的保证人。

接着，突然就出现了你那份惊人的财产清单。所有人都在嘲笑那份清单的长度，嘲笑那些各种不同的财物，因为那里面没有一个（除了密塞努的土地）可以称得上是他自己的。不过，这场拍卖本身的场景就十分惨淡。那里有庞培的一些长袍，有的上面甚至还有污点，一些磨损变形的银质杯盘，几个衣衫褴褛的奴隶。剩下的东西也寥寥无几。不过，如果没有任何东西留下来，我们的悲伤可能会少一些。

但是，卢修斯·鲁伯里厄斯·卡西纳斯的继承人以恺撒的一道法令来反对这场拍卖。安东尼这个挥霍者陷入了尴尬之中，无处可躲。就在这个特殊的时刻有消息传出：在恺撒家中逮捕了安东尼派去的一名手持匕首的杀手。恺撒以此为由在元老院公开指责你。但是因为你实在太穷了，他宽限你在几天之内还债，接着便去了西班牙。即使这样，你也没有和他一起出行。一个如此优秀的角斗士竟然这么早就退休了？一个人如果在支持自己这一方时（同样也意味着支持自己）都表现得如此恐惧，那么别人肯定不会对他有所畏惧了。

最终在过了一段时间后，安东尼的确去了西班牙。但正如他所想的那样，他没能安全抵达。那么，多拉贝拉是怎么到达那里的？安东尼，你要么就别使用这个借口，要是使用了，就应该坚持到底。恺撒曾三次与自己的同胞为敌，分别是在帖撒利、阿非利加和西班牙。多拉贝拉参加了这些所有的战斗，并且在西班牙负伤。如果你想知道我的看法，我希望他没有参加这些战斗。虽然他最初的决定应该受到谴责，不过他至少应该因为自己的坚持而受到表扬。但是，你呢？那个时候，庞培的儿子们正在杀出一条回家之路，这无疑让所有效忠于恺撒的人都焦虑不堪。换句话说，庞培的儿子们正在竭力恢复他们家神的神龛，他们神圣的炉灶、家园以及他们家族的守护神，这些都是被你夺走的东西。当他们不得不使用武力来夺回属于自己的合法财产时谁最应该成为他们的主要目标呢？（虽然在这种不当的行为中根本没有公正可言）这个人就是——你！他们财产的占有者。所以这是你与他们之间的战争，难道不是吗？但是多拉贝拉却不得不因此在西班牙作战，而你却在那波，在主人的餐桌前呕吐。

接着你从那波返回。事实上，你是想知道我为什么突然中断旅行返回罗马。对此我已经向元老院作出解释。如果可以的话，我想在新年到来之前就为国效力。你问我是怎么回来的。首先，我是在白天到达的，而不是黑夜。其次，我是穿着我自己的靴子和托迦袍回来的，而不是穿着高卢便鞋和斗篷。不过，我看到你似乎对我怒目相视。但是如果你知道我为你的无耻而感到羞愧——相反地，你自己却没有——你就应该对我友好一点。在我的所见所闻之中，没有任何一个人所犯的所有罪行比这更加无耻。你——曾经的骑兵统领，而今为了竞选下一届执政官竟然穿着高卢便鞋和斗篷访遍了高卢的所有城镇，这简直和乞丐没什么两样。当我们是执政官候选人的时候，也会在这些城镇拉选票，不过那时候要得到任命靠的是选票而不是个人的施舍。

看看这个人有多轻浮！那天在3点钟的时候，他到达罗马，来到了达萨科萨卢拉。然后便躲在一个破旧的小酒馆里喝酒，一直喝到晚上。接着一辆双轮马车快速将他带到市里，他蒙着脸到了自己的家里。守门人问他：“你是谁？”他答道：“我是安东尼的信使。”随即被带到一个女人面前，并且交给她一封信。这个女人便是他回来的原因。看了信后，她哭了起来，因为这是一封情书，主要内容是他不再跟那个女戏子有瓜葛，只爱她一个人。当她哭得越来越厉害的时候，这个软心肠的家伙再也忍不住了。他揭开自己的头巾，双手抱住了她的脖子。多么无耻的家伙啊！就算是再无耻的词也不足以形容他。仅仅为了让自己突然出现在这女人面前，他便让整个城市在晚上陷入恐惧之中，让意大利陷入长久的烦恼之中。在她看到一个男妓这样的行为后，定会觉得惊喜万分。

在家里你可以声称是为了爱情，但是在其他地方你却有一些更加邪恶的意图：为了阻止鲁西乌斯·普兰库斯出售你的抵押品。一位保民官曾在一个公共集会上买下了你，但是你却回答说：“我来这里是为了我的私人财产。”所有的人都把这当作一个天大的笑话。[11]

不过，这些小事就说到这里，我们还是回到那些更重要的问题上吧！当恺撒从西班牙回来后，你不远千里去见他，并且速去速回，因为这样会让恺撒觉得虽然你不勇敢但至少精力充沛。不知怎么地，你再次和他重归于好。不过，恺撒就是那样的人，对于那些因为濒临破产而陷于绝望之中的无耻之徒，他都愿意与其成为亲密的朋友。你在这些方面表现得非常出色，所以他任命你为执政官，作为他的同僚。人们只能向多拉贝拉表示同情，恺撒一直鼓励多拉贝拉参加竞选，但是最后却欺骗了他。大家都知道你和恺撒在这个问题上背叛了多拉贝拉。恺撒让他成为执政官的候选人，并允诺让他赢得选举，却背弃之前的承诺将职位收为己有，而你也在其中推波助澜。

1月1日，我们大家被迫来到元老院。多拉贝拉对安东尼进行了批判，比我现在的更加全面和强烈。天啊！安东尼在愤怒之中都说了什么啊！恺撒在他东去之前便表明要任命多拉贝拉为执政官。不过，他们竟然否认言行一向如此的人是一个独裁者。但是，在恺撒这样说过之后，这位杰出的占卜官安东尼宣布，他作为一名祭司可以利用占卜征兆阻止或废除选举。并且，他宣称自己将会这么做。大家看看，他真是蠢得让人难以置信啊！安东尼，占卜官的职位让你有权实施这些行为。但是就算不是占卜官，仅仅作为执政官，你也有权那么做。事实上，执政官的权力难道不是更大吗？我们占卜官只被授予报告预兆的权力，而执政官和其他行政官员实际上却有观察天象的权力。

很好，就算是因为你缺乏经验而搞砸了这件事吧。我们不能期待从一个永远糊里糊涂的人那里得到正确的判断。不过，请大家看看他有多无知。几个月之前，他曾在元老院宣布他要么利用占卜征兆阻止议会选举多拉贝拉，要么换种方式这么做。现在，除了那个已经正式开始观察天象的人，还有谁能够预言占卜中的不足？不过在选举中这样做是不合法的，如果有任何人事先观察了天象，那么他必须在选举开始之前进行报告而不是之后。安东尼既无知又无耻，他的行为所展现的无知已经达到了极点，就像他对一个占卜官职责的无知一样。所以，让我们回忆一下从他担任执政官的那天起，一直到3月15日所发生的事情。没有一个仆人能够如此谦虚，如此卑微。他自己什么事情都不会做，每件事都得求别人。你可以看到他将头缩回自己的轿子后面请求同僚[12]的帮助。

多拉贝拉选举的日子到了，最先投票的权利是由抽签决定的，安东尼对此没有任何异议。抽签结果出来后，安东尼保持沉默。于是，第一等级的人投票，公布投票结果；然后，第二等级的人投票——这一切很快就结束了，比我讲这个故事还要快。当前面这些程序结束后，再接着，就是我们这位杰出的占卜官——你们可能会认为他是盖厄斯·莱留斯本人——宣布：“会议推迟到另外一天。”多么荒谬啊！多么鲁莽啊！你没有看到，也没有领悟到，更没有听到任何预兆。你没有说你之前一直在观察天象，今天也没有。所以这个问题就在于这是你在很久之前也就是1月1日时所预言过的。换句话说，你肯定是在报告假的预兆。你利用宗教来约束罗马人民。作为占卜官你向占卜官报告假的预兆，作为执政官你向执政官报告假的预兆。希望那些可怕的恶果不要降临在罗马人民身上，只降临在你的身上。

这就是我要说的全部事情，否则再说下去就有可能看起来在否定多拉贝拉的行为，不过占卜团肯定在某个时间会得知此事。大家看看这个人有多么蛮横无理！只要你安东尼自己乐意，多拉贝拉的执政官选举就是不合法的。接着，你又改了主意，认为占卜征兆的程序在这次选举上根本没有任何问题！如果你所说的占卜官报告没有意义，那也就相当于承认，你在说延期的时候不是清醒的。但若这些话有某种意义，那么作为我的占卜官同僚，我想请问你这些话是什么意思。

不过，我绝对不会在这次演说中故意略去安东尼众多功绩中那极为优秀的一个行为。所以，我们来谈一下牧神节吧！众位元老院议员，大家请看。他无法隐藏内心的焦虑，你们看到他看起来有多烦恼了吗？他脸色惨白，汗流不止。不过没关系，只要他没有生病，他就会像在木诺西乌柱廊那里一样。他是怎么在牧神节为自己那可耻的行为辩护的？我很希望能听到这个辩护，顺便了解一下他在给自己辩论老师缴纳了那一大笔学费和列奥蒂尼的土地后，有什么样的成果。

你的同僚正身穿紫袍，头戴花环就座于讲坛的金色椅子之上。你爬上讲坛，走向恺撒的椅子——虽然你就像卢佩库斯牧神一样，不过你也应该记得你是一名执政官——然后拿出一顶王冠。整个讲坛此时都发出一阵叹息。这个王冠是从哪里得来的？肯定不是你在地上捡到的吧！当然不是，这是你从自己家里带来的。这是一项有预谋的犯罪。然后，你将王冠戴在他的头上，人们为之悲叹。然而，他又将王冠拿下，人们为之鼓掌。

所以，罪人，你独自一人已经准备好在集会上倡导在罗马建立独裁统治，希望你的同僚能成为你的君主，并且要将罗马人民置于独裁统治的水深火热之中。你甚至像一个乞丐一样趴在他的脚下试图让他对你有所怜悯。你在祈求什么呢？成为他的奴隶吗？不过就你自己而言，这个祈求倒是很合适，因为从童年开始你便屈服于所有发生在你身上的事情。对你一个人来说，要转变为奴隶制很简单，不过，我们自己、全体罗马人民都没有授予你这样的权利。

你赤身裸体时所发表的那个演讲是多么雄辩机智啊！不过，还有什么行为能比这更加可耻，更应受到最严厉的惩罚？你是一个在恐惧中等待主人鞭打的奴隶吗？如果你还有一点感觉，那你现在肯定能感到鞭打，因为我对这些事情的解释定会让你血流不止。虽然这并不是我的本意，但我这样解释也许会贬低那些伟大的解放者。不过，你的恶行着实让人心痛，我必须说出我的观点。当看到那个拒绝王冠的人被杀，并且是在众人的一致希望下被杀后，让人惊讶的是那个献给他王冠的人却还存活于世。更让人吃惊的是，他竟然让人在牧神节的公共记录中写下：“在人民的命令之下，执政官安东尼授予永久的独裁者——恺撒王权。恺撒予以拒绝。”

因此，在你仇恨罗马，仇恨光明，整日和那些鸡鸣狗盗之徒喝酒之时，我并没有对你破坏国家和平感到意外。因为对你来说，没有什么地方是安全的。你能在那些拥有法律和法庭的地方找到容身之处吗？不能，因为这些正是你竭尽全力想要通过暴政废除和替代的东西。这难道不是塔奎纽斯被驱逐，斯普利乌·卡修斯、斯普利乌·买利厄斯、马库斯·曼利厄斯被处死的原因吗？然而在几百年过去后，安东尼却犯下了在罗马拥立国王这一邪恶的罪行。

还是让我们回到占卜这个话题吧！恺撒打算在3月15日的元老院会议上处理这个问题。安东尼，我必须问你在当时想要说什么。我听说你那天去元老院主要是为了反驳我，因为我曾断言你的占卜预兆报告是虚假的——占卜预兆除非被宣布无效，否则就必须严格遵守。不过上天保佑才使得那天本来要进行的事情没有发生。恺撒之死打消了你关于预兆的念头了吗？

但是，在我讨论这个话题之前，我必须谈一下其他事情。在那个光荣的日子里，你惊慌逃窜，偷偷躲在家里，因为良心的不安让你感到死亡在向你靠近。那些关心你生命安全的人照看着你，因为他们希望你行为理智。我对未来的预言一向准确无误，但却总被大家忽略。在卡皮托利山上，当我们那些尊贵的解放者希望我去劝说你为共和政府效力时，我便告诉他们，在你害怕的时候，你会允诺所有事情，但是当你不再害怕的时候，你就会恢复本性。因此，当其他一些前任执政官频繁出入于你的家里时，我依然坚持自己的观点。并且，那天以及之后的第二天我都没有见你。因为我相信忠诚的罗马公民不会和一个没有原则的敌人达成任何协议，也不会和他结成同盟。

两天后，我十分不情愿地来到忒路斯神庙，因为士兵们封锁了所有的通道。这天对你来说多么重要啊！虽然你突然间与我为敌，不过我还是为你感到遗憾，因为你随后的行为有愧于你良好的声誉。天知道，只要你能坚持你那天所表现出的态度，你也会成为一个英雄。并且，在那种情况下我们可以通过那位出身高贵的人质——马库斯·班巴里奥的孙子——得到所期盼的和平。

在恐惧的指导下，你行为举止良好，俨然是一位好公民。但是，恐惧缺乏持久性。相反地，一直伴随你的是狂妄嚣张，用不了多久你便会再一次走向罪恶，因为只有在你害怕的时候它才会消失。事实上，那时人们（除我以外）都对你赞扬有加，而你却无耻地主持了那位暴君的葬礼——如果那个仪式可以被称作葬礼的话。你在葬礼上宣读了庄重的悼词，作出了悲怆的道德呼吁。你点燃火把，火化了恺撒的尸体，同样也是这把火烧毁了卢修斯·贝利努斯的房子。安东尼，你发动那些大多是奴隶的流氓破坏我们的家园，使得我们不得不亲自来对抗这些暴行。

不过，似乎是你清理了火葬堆的那些烟灰。随后，你在卡皮托利山上、在元老院面前提出了优秀的决议。我指的是那些宣布从3月15日起，不再张贴免税或者其他类似特权的公告。至于那些赦免，以及那些流放的人，你知道你自己说了什么。不过，在这之中最值得称赞的就是你为这个国家永远地废除了独裁者这个头衔。因为你感觉到人们近来对独裁者的恐惧，以及对其无比的仇视，所以决定将其永远废除。

至此，对于其他人来说，国家似乎稳稳地建立了起来，不过我并不这样想，因为我认为由你掌舵的船一定会出事故。难道我错了吗？一个人能长时间伪装自己吗？元老院的议员们，你们都亲自看到了接下来所发生的事情。卡皮托利山上到处都张贴着公告，出售免税权，不仅仅面向个人，而且面向整个国家；公民权不再授予个人而是授予整个行省。如果这些决议长期有效，我们的国家势必走向衰败。众位议员，你们已经失去了所有的行省，并且他在自己开设的市场内大幅度削减税收。他是在削弱整个罗马帝国啊！

奥浦斯神庙账本中所记载的那7亿塞特拉斯现在在哪里？虽然这笔钱财是不义之财，但是如果这些钱不能归还给它的主人，至少它还可以使我们免除财产税。不过，安东尼你能不能解释一下：为什么在3月15日的时候，你负债400万塞特拉斯，而在4月1日的时候便还清了所有债务？

此外，你很清楚自己的众多法令都是通过钱财收买别人才得到支持的。不过，那些张贴在卡皮托利山上的法令中的确有一条十分优秀。这与罗马人民的好朋友——戴奥塔鲁斯国王相关。尽管所有人都处于悲伤之中，但是在看到这条法令时都忍不住大笑。因为没有人像恺撒恨戴奥塔鲁斯那样恨过别人。他对戴奥塔鲁斯的恨就像他对元老院、罗马骑士、马西利亚人以及每一个他认为热爱罗马和罗马人民的人的恨一样。在恺撒的一生中，不管是当着戴奥塔鲁斯的面还是在他缺席的时候，他从没有公平、友好地对待戴奥塔鲁斯。但是，你却想让我们相信在恺撒死了之后，戴奥塔鲁斯得到了他的青睐。戴奥塔鲁斯作为主人招待恺撒，与他待在一起。但是恺撒召见他，让他上缴金钱，并安排一名希腊人在他的执政区任职。除此之外，恺撒还剥夺了元老院附赠给戴奥塔鲁斯的管辖之地——亚美尼亚。但是，你现在却想让我们相信恺撒活着时占有的东西在他死后却归还了出来。

请大家注意一下他是怎么表述的。很明显，他有时将这次归还描述成“公正”的，有时候是“并非不公正”。多么特殊的阐释啊！虽然我没有和戴奥塔鲁斯在一起，但我永远为他辩护。不过，我们为戴奥塔鲁斯作出的任何辩护在恺撒看来似乎都是不公正的。

安东尼那个女人的房间里曾进行过很多交易，现在也仍在继续。也正是在这个房间里，戴奥塔鲁斯派遣他的使者在谈判后签署了一千万赛斯特斯的付款保证书。这些使者都很善良，但是有点胆小、缺乏经验，也没有询问我和国王其他一些朋友的意见。关于这个付款保证书，我建议你仔细考虑一下该怎么处理。因为，当戴奥塔鲁斯听闻恺撒的死讯后，便主动出击，依靠自己的力量拿回了属于自己的东西，根本没有考虑恺撒有可能留下来的任何备忘录。戴奥塔鲁斯是明智的，因为他知道这样做永远是合法的，即当偷取他人财产的暴君被杀死后，那些受害者有权拿回自己被侵占的财产。所以，没有一个律师，就算是现在代表你的专属律师也不会说你是戴奥塔鲁斯的债权人，因为在这份合约执行前他已经拿回了属于自己的东西。他并没有从你的手里买到那些东西，因为在你能把他自己的那些财产卖给他之前，他已经拿回了那些东西。他确实是个不简单的人物！不过另一方面，我们的确有点可鄙，因为我们对自己憎恨之人的一些行为予以支持。

对于那些无数的备忘录以及众多所谓的恺撒亲笔签名，我不发表任何看法。不过，我们可以看看制造这些东西的伪造犯，他们公开出售这些备忘录、签名，就像这些东西是角斗士表演简介一样。因此，安东尼现在居住的地方堆积了大量的金钱，这些钱只能用秤来称，因为根本数不过来。但是，贪婪也让他犯下了很多无知的过错。例如，他最近张贴了一个免除克里特最富有群体的税务的告示。这个告示宣布：“当马库斯·布鲁特斯执政期结束的时候，”克里特将不再是一个行省。不过，安东尼你的理智呢？难道就真的没有什么可以约束你吗？恺撒怎么可能会颁布一条这样的法令——“在布鲁特斯任期结束的时候”豁免克里特的税务？因为在恺撒活着的时候，布鲁特斯和克里特根本就没有这样的关系。不过，众位元老院议员，不要认为因为这个原因这条法令就不会被出售，事实上，它已经让你们失去了克里特行省。只要一件东西有人买，安东尼随时都准备将其出售。

安东尼，至于你提出那条召回流亡犯的法律，是不是也是恺撒颁布的呢？我并不是想迫害任何身处困境之人，只是有以下几点抱怨。首先，这批新召回的流亡犯对于那些被恺撒单独列出、认为他们应该被召回的人来说是一种侮辱。其次，我不明白为什么你不能对所有人一视同仁，因为剩下的人最多三四个而已。我不明白为什么你没有给予身处同样困境的人以同样的怜悯，为什么不能对你的叔叔以及其他一些人一视同仁？当你为别人制定法律的时候，为什么要将自己的叔叔排除在外。而另一方面，你却敦促他去竞选监察官之位！事实上，正是这一点激起了人们的嘲讽和抗议。不过，你既然这么支持他，为什么不亲自主持那场竞选呢？难道是因为有位保民官在那之前宣布将会有不祥之兆？当占卜涉及你自身利益的时候，征兆便没有任何作用；但是，当涉及到朋友的利益的时候，你就变得小心翼翼了。接着，当你的叔叔在竞选“七人委员会”候选人的时候，你再一次背离了他。不要告诉我们这是因为你受到一些可怕敌人的威胁，你不敢违背他们的意愿，担心自己会有生命危险。如果你还忠于自己的家族，你就应该像尊敬父亲一样尊敬他，但是，你却多次对他进行侮辱。

更无耻的是，在你找到新欢之后，你便将他的女儿，也就是你的堂妹安东尼娅赶出家门。在此之前你曾四处张望，但作出了另一种安排。对此你还不满意，甚至控告她犯下通奸之罪，然而世界上再也没有哪个女人比她更清白了。你简直已经丧心病狂到了极点，就算是这样你还不满意。在1月1日元老院全体会议上，当然你的叔叔也出席了那次会议，你竟然厚颜无耻地宣布就是因为多拉贝拉与你的堂妹，也就是你的妻子通奸，所以你才将他视为敌人。要说出你的哪一个行为是最可恶的确实很难。是你厚颜无耻地在元老院里作出这样指控？是你不择手段地反对多拉贝拉？还是你无礼地在她父亲面前说出这些话语？又或者是你残忍地用这些肮脏的言语来污蔑这位不幸的女人？

但是，还是让我们回到那些被当成是恺撒亲笔签署的法令上吧。安东尼，你怎么证明这些是恺撒的法令？元老院为了和平已经批准了恺撒的一些法令，当然是那些真的，而不是你所声称的那些。不过，这些法令是从哪里来的？又是依仗谁的权威提出来的？如果它们是伪造的，为什么会被批准？如果是真的，为什么要花钱来通过这些法令？元老院已经作出了这样的决定，自6月1日起，元老院议员将会在一个顾问委员会的帮助之下对恺撒的法令进行调查。什么委员会？你曾经召集过这个委员会的成员吗？你所等待的那个6月1日，无疑是你从退伍士兵殖民城邦返回的日子，因为你会带着军队再次返回。

在你四五月的那次旅途中，你甚至想要在加普亚建立一个殖民城邦，多么辉煌的一件事情啊！但是，我们都知道你是怎么离开那里的，或者说你差点不能离开，不过，你还是口口声声地威胁加普亚。我希望你能把你所说的那些话付诸实践，这样“差点”这个词就可以删掉了。你的确取得了很大的进步！不过我不想谈论你那些丰盛的晚宴和疯狂的酗酒，这不仅仅是你的损失，也是我们的损失。即使是之前为了将土地分发给士兵，免除坎帕尼亚的税务，我们也认为这对国家的利益造成了很大的冲击。但是，事实上你却将那里的土地分给了和你一起吃喝玩乐、一起赌博的朋友。元老院的议员们啊！他甚至将那些男男女女的戏子们都安置在加普亚。让人同样厌恶的是他对列奥蒂尼土地的处理。那里曾经土壤肥沃，作物收成良好，就像坎帕尼亚一样，为罗马作出了很大的贡献，是罗马必不可少的一个地方。但是，你竟然将1875英亩的土地送给了你的医生。有些人可能会问道：如果他真的将你的脑子医治好了，你会给他多大一块土地啊？此外，你又将1250英亩的土地送给了你的辩论老师。如果他真的让你成为一个演说家，那你究竟会给他多少土地啊？

不过，我们还是回到你的旅行，以及它对意大利所造成的影响这个话题上吧！你在恺撒曾经建立了殖民城邦的地方——卡西努姆，重新建立了一个由退伍士兵组成的殖民城邦。你写信给我，询问我对在加普亚建立殖民城邦的意见，不过我给你的答复和有关卡西努姆问题的答复一样。你问我在一个已经建立了殖民城邦的地方再建一个殖民城邦是不是合法，我回复说，在遵循占卜预兆、已经正式建立了一个殖民城邦的地方再建立一个新的殖民城邦是不合法的，不过我也指出可以让新的殖民者居住在旧殖民城邦。尽管如此，你对占卜的所有规定置若罔闻，就算几年之前刚刚在卡西努姆建立了一个殖民城邦，你还是在这里重新建立了一个。你甚至提高了你的标准，用犁头划出了界线。但是你的犁头几乎划过加普亚的城门，严重地侵犯了那个最繁荣的殖民城邦的领地。

刚违反了宗教规定，你便又迫不及待地违反其他规定，因为你又觊觎马库斯·特伦替厄斯·瓦罗在卡西努姆的财产。不过，马库斯·瓦罗是一个非常虔诚、十分高尚之人，你这样做究竟是出于法律还是道德的制裁？你的回答肯定和你当初掠夺卢修斯·鲁伯里厄斯的继承人、卢修斯·忒塞留斯的继承人，以及其他众多继承人财产的理由一样。那么，既然现在你是在拍卖上得到这些财产的，我们承认拍卖有这样的权利，不过我们认为书面说明也有一定的权利。比如，这些证据能够证明财产是恺撒的，而不是你的；又如，它们能够证明你是一个债务人，而不是免除你的债务。

至于瓦罗在卡西努姆的农场，谁说它已经被卖了？有人看见拍卖时的长矛，还是听到了拍卖者的叫喊？你说你派了一个人去亚历山大里亚从恺撒那里购买这片土地。你迫不及待，根本无法等到恺撒归来。不过，没有一个人听说过瓦罗有任何财产被充公，也没有任何人的福利能比瓦罗的更引起大家的关注。如果事实是恺撒写信命你将这些土地还回去，那么我们简直找不到合适的词来形容你这些暴行。只要你把我们能看见的那些士兵都调走一会儿，只要你那样做了，你很快就会明白无论恺撒拍卖的理由是什么，你自己的无耻之举完全在另外一个水平上。因为只要这些士兵一撤走，你就将发现自己会被扔到瓦罗家门外。不仅房子的主人会驱逐你，他的每一个朋友、邻居、访客和仆人也肯定会驱赶你。

你日复一日地在瓦罗的别墅里放纵自己。从早上7点开始，就一直饮酒、赌博、呕吐。这个房子如此不幸，拥有这样一个“邪恶的主人”。

但是，安东尼怎么能被称作是它的主人呢？我们还是叫他占有者吧。就这样，这个房子有了一个邪恶的占有者，马库斯·瓦罗选择这个地方不是为了放纵而是为了退隐、学习。这些墙壁曾经见证了那些机智的讨论、高贵的思想、杰出的著作，罗马人民的法律、我们祖先的历史、智慧的真理以及所有的知识。但是，当你成为这里的房客后——我不会把你称作房主，房子里充满了酒徒的喧嚣，小路上洒满了酒，就连墙壁上也有酒滴下来。在那里总能看见出身自由的青年与男妓厮混不止，家庭妇女与妓女纠缠不休。

人们从卡西努姆、阿奎努姆、英特拉纳前来向他致敬，但是他不允许任何人进门拜访。不过这样做也十分合适，因为像他这么堕落的人根本配不上这一职位的徽章。当他经过阿奎努姆前往罗马的时候，因为这里人口众多，所以有很多人前来欢迎他。但是，他坐在一个封闭的轿子里穿过街道，就像那里面抬着死人一样。毫无疑问，阿奎努姆这些人的行为确实很愚蠢，但是他们就住在安东尼经过的路边。而阿纳尼亚的那些人呢？相反地，他们住的离他经过的地方很远，但他们以为安东尼是执政官因此前来欢迎他。不过，让人难以置信的是他竟然对这些问候没有任何回应。虽然我不在现场，但是我可以保证所有的人当时都注意到了这一点。更让人难以置信的是，他身边有两个阿纳尼亚人——穆斯特拉和拉珂。前者照看他的剑，后者管理他的酒杯。

根本不用我来提醒，你们都知道他曾经威胁和侮辱昔狄西尼人和普特利人，而这都是因为他们选择了卡修斯家族和布鲁特斯家族来做自己的保护人。不过，他们的选择完全是出于积极的肯定、正确的判断、友好的感觉以及自己的情感，而不是因为武力和暴力的威胁。而你和米纽修斯·巴西鲁斯，以及其他像你们这样的人都是用这种方式来强迫别人选你们，否则没人会自愿选择你们来做他的保护人，即使是依附者，你们也不在选择之内。

与此同时，当你不在的时候，你的同僚[13]推翻了讲坛上那座让你一直尊敬有加的墓碑，这一天对他来说意义非凡。当你得知这件事后，竟然晕厥过去。当时和你在一起的人都知道这件事。我并不清楚随后发生的事情，但我认为是恐惧和武装暴力让你晕厥的。因为，你让你的同僚从天堂坠落，使他不像原来的自己，不过要是说你让他成为第二个你却言之过甚。

你重返罗马使整个城市陷入骚动之中。因为我们都记得卢修斯·科尼厄斯·秦纳的大权在握、苏拉的高压统治，而之后恺撒的独裁统治也仍然记忆犹新。那时候，也可能有刀剑，但是它们仍在剑鞘之中，并且数量也不多。然而你的队伍却是十分野蛮的，你的追随者都处于战争的命令之下，手握出鞘刀剑，肩扛轻便盾牌。不过，众位熟悉这些场景的元老院议员也都对此习以为常。

尽管我们尽自己最大的努力去参加原定在6月1日的元老院会议，却因突然受到威胁，不得不缺席会议。不过，安东尼对此欣喜若狂，因为他认为元老院根本没有存在的必要，也不希望我们任何人出席会议，随即便开始实施那些滔天罪行。他曾因为自己的个人利益而为恺撒的法令辩护，也曾为了颠覆这个国家的体制而废除恺撒的法律，尽管那些法律是好的。例如，他延长了行省官员的任期。虽然他应该保护恺撒的法令，但是事实上却将那些有关国家事务和私人事务的法律通通予以废除。现今，在国家事务中最为重要的就是法律，在私人事务中最为有效的则是遗嘱。然而，他却将两者都废除了。他在有或者没有通告的情况之下便将法律废除；而他所废除的遗嘱就算是最低等的公民也应该遵守。他从庞培的花园和西皮奥的别墅里将恺撒留给继承人——罗马人民——的那些雕像、绘画通通都搬走了。

不过，安东尼你如此怀念恺撒，你热爱这个已经死去的人，对吗？然而，他所获得的最大荣耀也就是神榻、塑像、山形墙和他的祭司而已。正是因为这些荣耀，就像朱庇特、玛尔斯、奎利努斯有自己的祭司一样，安东尼就是朱利叶斯的祭司。不过，安东尼你并没有就职，没有承担起一个祭司的责任，这是为什么呢？你尽可以选择一个时间，选一个人来安排你就职。我们是你的同僚，没人会拒绝你。不过，无论是恺撒这个独裁者的祭司，还是一个死者的祭司都同样令人厌恶。

现在，我得问你一个问题：你难道不知道今天是什么日子吗？你难道不知道昨天是罗马广场赛会的第四天吗？你亲自向人民集会提议：为了表示对恺撒的尊敬，应该将赛会延长一天。但是，为什么我们现在没有身着节日盛装？为什么要忽略你的法律所授予恺撒的荣耀？很显然，你也打算作出让步，你认为这个神圣的日子应该被额外的感恩节日所玷污，而不是被神榻玷污。不过，你要么完全废除宗教仪式，要么就一成不变地保留下来。

你问我是不是喜欢这些神榻、山形墙和神圣的祭司，我一个都不喜欢。但是作为恺撒法令的维护者，你却没有理由来解释为什么你只维持了其中的一些而忽略了另一些，除非你打算承认你这样做是出于自己的利益而非恺撒的荣耀。请你回答这些问题，我很期待你的雄辩。我知道你的祖父是一个出色的雄辩家，不过，你肯定在演讲时拥有比他更多的自由，因为他从来不会将自己的想法完全赤裸裸地表达出来！但是，你这个头脑简单的家伙，竟然让我们都对你的想法一清二楚！对此你能让我作答吗？你敢开口吗？事实上，我怀疑在我这么长的演讲中，你是否有勇气来回答其中的任何一个指责。

不过，过去的就让它过去吧，我们来谈谈此时此刻我正在说话时你的那些行为吧！为自己辩护吧，如果你可以的话。请解释一下为什么元老院被这些士兵包围？为什么我的听众中有你那帮手握刀剑的匪徒？为什么要关上协和神庙的大门？为什么要让世上最野蛮的以提利亚人手持弓箭来到讲坛？安东尼说：“我这么做都是自我防卫。”不过，一千人的死亡难道要比一个人死亡更好吗？况且，那一个人要是没有武装护卫就不能在自己的团体中存活下去。但是，我可以告诉你武装护卫并不是真正的保护。你所需要的保护不是来自武器，而是出自同胞们对你的关爱和友善。因为罗马人民将会夺取你的武器并在你面前将其毁掉。我希望在那发生之前，我们仍然健在。不过，不管你怎么对我们，相信我，这些办法都不是长久之计。你的妻子并非吝啬之人，当然这句话并没有任何不敬的意思，不过她对罗马人民的第三次分期付款[14]已经拖了很久。

我们国家并不缺少管理政务之人。不管他们在哪里，他们都是保卫国家的中流砥柱，是我们罗马的中流砥柱。罗马虽然为自己复了仇，但是还没有完全恢复。不过，那些尊贵的青年们随时都准备好保卫我们的祖国。他们也许想要退隐一些时日，但是罗马最终会将他们召回。

和平之名美丽动人，和平本身幸福美好。但是和平与奴役这两者有很大的不同：和平是人们安享自由；而奴役是万恶之首，应当被废除，如果有必要，即使是以战争，甚至是以死亡为代价也在所不惜。虽然我们的解放者们已经退出了我们的视线，但是他们英勇的行为成了我们学习的榜样。他们的功绩前所未有。卢修斯·朱尼厄斯·布鲁特斯发动了反对塔奎因国王的战争，而那个时候王权在罗马是合法的；斯普利乌·卡修斯·维塞林厄斯、斯普利乌·买利厄斯、马库斯·曼利厄斯·卡庇托林努斯因为被怀疑谋夺王权而被处死。但是，这是人们第一次举起刀剑杀掉那个不仅仅觊觎王权，并且就像国王一样实行统治的人。他们的行为本身就极其高贵，并且为我们树立了榜样。很显然，即使是广阔无垠的天堂也无法容纳他们所取得的荣耀。况且，承认这是一次高贵的胜利本身就是非常丰厚的奖赏，但是我相信，没有人会反对他们已经赢得了更大的荣耀——永垂不朽！

安东尼，你应该记得你永远废除独裁的那一天！你回想一下，那个时候元老院和罗马人民是多么喜悦啊！可是将这与你和你的朋友们现在忙于的交易相比，你就会意识到收获和荣誉的不同。正如有些疾病或味觉上的迟钝会让人们无法品尝食物一样，同样的道理，荣耀对于放荡之人、守财奴和罪犯都没有吸引力。

不过，如果荣耀都不能激励你表现得体一点，那么恐惧是不是同样也不能让你停止那些令人讨厌的行为？我知道你不惧怕法庭。如果这是因为无辜，那么你应该被赞扬；但如果是因为你依靠武力，那你就会害怕另外一些人。难道你不知道因为武力而无视法律的人必定会畏惧另外一类人吗？如果你是因为自己有随从保护而不害怕罗马的勇士和忠诚的公民，那么相信我，你的拥护者不会长久地支持你。日夜担心自己的追随者会对自己不利，这还能被称为一种生活吗？并且就恩惠而言，恺撒曾经赐给那些杀手的恩惠比你赐给别人的更多。

不过，你和恺撒没有任何可比性。恺撒集天赋、手段、博闻强记、修养、执着、智慧和勤勉于一身。虽然他发动战争给我们国家带来了灾难，但他在战争中所取得的成就依然是伟大的。多年来他旨在谋取王位和王权，付出了无尽的努力、克服了无数的困难才实现了自己的目标。他利用娱乐演出、公共建设、分发食物和宴会来笼络那些无知的大众，他用丰厚的奖赏来保持朋友对自己的忠心，而对于自己的敌人，他会施以怜悯从而获得他们的支持。他恩威并施，让一个自由的国度变成了奴役之国。

安东尼，只有你的统治之欲可以和恺撒相比，在其他每个方面，你都无法与他相提并论。虽然恺撒给我们国家带来了伤害，但是至少也有一定好处。比如，罗马人民现在已经知道他们应该相信谁，应该将自己的命运托付给谁，而又该警惕谁。你没有想过这些事情吗？那些勇士已经明白杀死一个暴君是一个极为高尚的行为，将会得到丰厚的回报和无限的荣誉。你难道不懂这件事的重要性吗？在人们不能容忍恺撒的时候，他们还会容忍你吗？相信我吧，这次他们会迫不及待、争先恐后地来做这件事。缺乏耐心的他们甚至不会等到时机成熟便来实施这一行动。

最后，安东尼，请你想想自己的国家吧！想想生你养你的人，而不是现在和你一伙的那些人。你可以对我为所欲为，但我请求你不要再与国家为敌，不过，决定权都在你手里。至于我，我知道自己该怎么做。我年轻的时候在捍卫我们的国家，现在就算我老了，也不会抛弃她。我既然藐视喀提林的武士，自然也不会害怕你的。相反，如果我的死亡能换回我们国家的自由，能让长期遭受苦难的罗马人民得到最终的解脱，我很乐意献出自己的生命。大概在20年之前，如果我在这座神庙里说过死亡不能提前降临到一个执政官头上，那么在我年老的时候再说这话便包含更多的道理。各位元老院议员们，在我获得了众多荣誉之后，在我做了这些事情以后，我甚至有点向往死亡。现在我只有两个愿望：第一，如果我的死亡能够让罗马人民获得自由，那将是不朽的诸神对我最大的恩赐；第二，所有人的命运都应该与他对国家的贡献相一致。

[1]富尔维亚（Fulvia），曾先后是帕布利厄斯·克劳狄厄斯、库里奥和安东尼的妻子。

[2]福米奥和格纳所分别是特伦斯（公元前195—前159）所著的两部喜剧《福米奥》（Phorrnio）和《阉人》（Eunuch）中的食客。巴里奥是普劳图斯（公元前254—前184）所著的《撒谎者》（The Cheat）中的皮条客。

[3]出自西塞罗备受争议之诗《在他执政之期》（On his Consulate），后面一句是“让荣誉归属于诚实之士”（let laurel yield to honest worth）。

[4]帕布利厄斯·卡斯卡是第一个举起反抗恺撒大旗之人，他的弟弟是盖厄斯。

[5]即杀掉安东尼。

[6]如果一个朋友的遗嘱里没有提到某人，这被视为对其的一种轻蔑。那些不能收取费用的律师特别希望能得到这种回报。

[7]古罗马时候的货币。——译者注

[8]公元前49年1月2日，安东尼和另外一个保民官否决了元老院的一个提议，该提议认为除非恺撒在一个指定的时间之前交出他的军队领导权，否则将宣布他是一个公敌。8天后，恺撒越过卢比孔河。

[9]公元前67年，庞培在与海盗作战时捕获的。

[10]当安东尼知道在恺撒的公开遗嘱中将继承权留给屋大维，只任命安东尼为第二继承人后，很受打击。

[11]这个笑话就是大家都知道安东尼一贫如洗，这在罗马人看来是一种耻辱。

[12]恺撒。

[13]多拉贝拉，现任执政官。

[14]她的三次分期付款分别是她的三个丈夫（37页的脚注）。

The First Philippic against Mark Antony

Senators, before I offer the views on the political situation which the circumstances seem to me to demand, I will briefly indicate to you the reasons, first why I left Rome, and then why I turned back again.

As long as it still seemed possible to hope that you had resumed your control and authority over the government, I felt determined, as consul and Senator, to remain at my post. And so, from the day when we were summoned to meet in the Temple of Tellus, I made no journeys and never lifted my eyes from public affairs. In that temple I did all that was within my power to lay the foundations of peace. I reminded members of the ancient precedent created by the Athenians – making use in my oration of the Greek term which that state then employed to calm down civil strife – and I moved that every memory of our internal discords should be effaced in everlasting oblivion.

Mark Antony made a fine speech on that day, and his intentions were excellent. It was, indeed, he and his children who made it possible for peace to be established with the greatest of our fellow-citizens. What followed was in harmony with these beginnings. He held consultations on the national situation at his home, and invited the political leaders to attend. He offered admirable recommendations to the Senate. At that stage nothing was disinterred from Gaius Caesar's notebooks except matters that were generally known already. In his reply to every question Antony was completely direct. Were any exiles recalled? One, he said, and nobody else. Were any tax-exemptions granted? None, he replied. He even wanted us to accept the proposal of the illustrious Servius Sulpicius that no announcement should be posted of any decree or favour attributed to Caesar which had originated subsequently to the Ides of March. Of the many other excellent measures of Mark Antony I will say nothing, because I want to pass immediately to one particular admirable step that he took. The dictatorship, which had come to usurp virtually monarchical powers, was completely eliminated from the Roman constitution by his agency; we did not even debate the question. He brought us a draft of the decree he wanted the Senate to adopt, and when this was read out we accepted his proposal with the utmost enthusiasm, and passed a highly complimentary vote of thanks in his honour. The prospect ahead of us now seemed brilliant. For we had won liberation from the tyranny under which we had been labouring and, what is more, from all fears of similar tyranny in the future. Although there had often been legitimate dictators in the past, men could not forget the perpetual dictatorship of recent times, and by abolishing the entire office Mark Antony gave the state a mighty proof that he wanted our country to be free.

And then again, only a few days later, the Senate was delivered from the peril of a massacre when the runaway slave who had appropriated the name of Marius was executed and dragged away on a hook. All these deeds were performed jointly with his colleague; other things, later, were done by Dolabella alone, but I am sure that if his colleague had not been away these also would have been matters for collaboration. For during this period a most pernicious trouble was insinuating itself into the city and gaining strength day by day. The same men who had organized that travesty of a burial were now building a funeral monument in the Forum. Every day an increasing number of ruffians, together with their equally degraded slaves, menaced the dwellings and temples of the city with destruction. But these impudent criminal slaves, and their loathsome and infamous counterparts who were free, met their deserts from Dolabella when he pulled that accursed column down. So determined was his action that I am amazed by the contrast between that day and all the others which have followed.

For by the first of June, the date fixed for our meeting, you can see how everything had been transformed. Nothing was any longer done through the Senate, many significant measures were passed through the Assembly of the people – and others, what is more, without even consulting the Assembly, and against its wishes. The consuls elect declared they did not dare come into the Senate at all. The liberators of our country, too, were excluded from the very city which they had rescued from servitude – though the consuls simultaneously kept on praising them at public meetings and in private talk. Moreover, ex-soldiers claiming veteran rights, on whose behalf this Senate had shown great solicitude, were being egged on to cherish hopes of new plunder in addition to what they already possessed.

I came to the conclusion it was less disagreeable to hear of these things than to see them for myself; and, besides, I was entitled to go travelling on a special mission. This being so, I left Rome with the intention of being back by the first of the following January – which seemed the earliest likely date for a meeting of this body.

And so those, Senators, were the circumstances which prompted my departure. I will now indicate briefly the motives behind my return – which no doubt gives greater cause for surprise. After avoiding Brundisium and the usual route to Greece – as it was only sensible to do – I arrived on the first of August at Syracuse, since the crossing from there to Greece was well spoken of. But although I was associated with that city by the closest ties, I could not allow it to detain me for more than a single night, despite its desire to do so, because I was afraid that my sudden arrival among my friends there might arouse suspicion if I lingered. And so I proceeded with a fair wind to Leucopetra, which is a promontory in the district of Rhegium, and there I embarked to cross over to Greece.

But I had not gone very far when a southerly gale blew me back to my embarkation point. It was the middle of the night, and I stopped at the house of my friend and associate Publius Valerius. On the next day, while I was waiting there in the hope of a favourable wind, a number of citizens of Rhegium came to see me, including newcomers from Rome. They supplied my first news of Mark Antony's speech, which pleased me so much that after reading it I first began to consider the idea of returning to Rome. A little later the manifesto of Brutus and Cassius arrived, and it seemed to me – perhaps because I esteem them as national figures even more highly than as personal friends – a model of fair-mindedness. But bearers of good news have the habit of inventing additional points to give their message an even better welcome than it would otherwise receive, and so my informants added that an agreement was about to be reached, that there would be a well-attended meeting of the Senate on the first of August, and that Antony was going to drop his bad advisers, renounce his governorship of the Gallic provinces, and resume his allegiance to the authority of the Senate.

On hearing this I felt so enthusiastic to come back that no oars and no winds were speedy enough to satisfy my impatience – not that I imagined I would fail to return in time, but I was eager not to waste a moment in offering the government my congratulations. I made a quick passage to Velia, where I saw Brutus; though I found this a sorrowful meeting. I for my part was overcome by shame at the idea of returning to the city which Brutus had just left, and consenting to live there in security when he could not do the same. However, I did not find him as upset as I was myself. For he was exalted by the consciousness of his superb and magnificent deed. And he had no complaints to make about his own fate – but many about yours.

It was he who gave me my first information about Lucius Piso's speech in the Senate on August the first. Piso had received little support, Brutus said, from the people who ought to have backed him. And yet in Brutus’ opinion – which is the most authoritative view you could have – and according also to the complimentary comments of everyone I have spoken to since then, his effort was evidently a noble one. And so I hastened back to lend him my aid. My purpose was not so much to accomplish anything concrete, for such a thing I neither expected nor, in fact, achieved. But this is a time when many things contrary to the order of nature and even against the ordinary course of fate seem likely to happen at any moment, and, in case the doom that is common to all of us should come my way, I wanted to bequeath our country the sentiments I am now expressing, as a testimonial of my eternal devotion to its welfare.

Well, those, Senators, were the motives for my two successive courses of action, and I trust I have explained them to your satisfaction. And now, before I begin to speak about the political question, I feel obliged to enter a brief protest about the injustice Antony did me yesterday. I am his friend, and, because of a service he rendered me, I have always insisted on maintaining that this is so. Then why, I should like to know, did he show such unpleasantness in endeavouring to drag me to yesterday's Senate meeting? Was I the only absentee? Were the numbers of those present lower than on many previous occasions? Did the matter under discussion attain the degree of gravity which has some-times in the past meant that even sick men had to be carried to meetings? Are you telling me that Hannibal himself was at the gates? Or perhaps we were considering the question of peace with Pyrrhus – since that, tradition records, was the debate for which the great Appius, blind and old, had himself carried into the Senate. But no: the motion was about public thanks-givings, and that is a subject for which Senators are not usually in short supply. Securities need not be called for to guarantee their attendance, since this is ensured by their eagerness to show goodwill to the proposed recipients of the honour; and the same applies when a Triumph is being discussed. On such occasions the consuls can afford to be so indifferent that a Senator is virtually free to attend or not as he pleases.

I knew that this was the practice; and I was tired after my journey, and not very well. So for friendship's sake I sent a message to inform Antony. Whereupon he declared, in your hearing, that he would come to my house with a demolition squad. This was a remarkably ill-tempered and immoderate way to talk. Whatever sort of an offence did he suppose he was penalizing by this harsh declaration, in the presence of the Senators, of his intention to use state employees to demolish a residence that had been erected at state expense in accordance with a decision of the Senate? Never has compulsion been applied to a Senator by any sanction as severe as that. Indeed, the only known penalties are a security or a fine. Besides, had he known the opinion I should have expressed if I had in fact attended, I am sure he would have wanted to relax the rigour of his coercive attitude quite a bit!

For you cannot imagine, gentlemen, that the decree you yesterday passed so unwillingly would have had my support. For that decree involved the confusion of a thanksgiving with a sacrifice in honour of the dead, and the insertion of sacrilegious procedures into the state religion – for such was the effect of proclaiming a thanksgiving in honour of a man who was no longer alive. The question of his identity is neither here nor there. Even if he were that famous Brutus himself, the man who by his own hand liberated the country from the tyranny of royal rule, whose descendants have maintained the same tradition of active heroism for very nearly five hundred years, still nothing would induce me to equate a dead human being with the immortal gods by awarding him a public thanksgiving when he should instead have had honours rendered to him in his grave. No, the vote I should have cast would have been one capable of justification to the Roman people in case some outstanding catastrophe such as a war or a plague or a famine overtook the country. For some of these disasters have already actually come about; while the rest, I fear, are impending. But as it is, all I can do about yesterday's decree is entreat the gods to pardon the people of Rome, who in any case do not like the measure – and to pardon the Senate that only passed it with reluctance.

Well, as regards our other political ills, am I permitted to offer my observations? For I regard myself at liberty （and always shall） to fight in defence of my own position, and to think nothing of death; and that will always be my attitude. Only give me free access to this place, and I am prepared to express my thoughts whatever the risk.

Well, gentlemen, I wish after all it had been possible for me to attend on August the first! Not that it would have been any use, but then at least there would not have been, as there was, only one isolated consul whose behaviour lived up to his own high rank and his country's needs. How sad that the men who had received Rome's greatest favours failed to support Lucius Piso in his truly admirable motion! Was it for this meagre result that the people of Rome made us consuls? Were we supposed to enjoy the highest position that the state is able to confer, and yet remain entirely oblivious of the national interests? For not one single former consul supported Lucius Piso either by word of mouth or even by the expression on his face!

Curse it, do you have to be voluntary slaves? I grant you that a measure of servility may formerly have been unavoidable. And I am also prepared to concede that my criticism need not apply to every consular speaker indiscriminately. For I distinguish between certain people whose silence I excuse and others who I feel are under an obligation to speak out. The latter category, I regret to say, has incurred suspicion in the eyes of the Roman people. This is not so much because they are frightened, though such a thing would certainly be shameful, but because for whatever reasons – and these are various – they have fallen short of what their eminent status demands.

First of all, therefore, I want to express the warm gratitude I feel towards Piso, who was undeterred by the practical limitations of what he could achieve for his country, and thought only of what his duty demanded that he should attempt. And then, as to my next point, Senators, I realize you may not feel sufficiently intrepid to support the point of view and course of action which I am now going to urge upon you. Nevertheless, I ask you to continue to listen with the same goodwill that you have shown me up to this point.

To begin with, then, I hold that the acts of Caesar ought to be retained. I say this not because I approve of them: for who could do that? No, I say it because I attach supreme importance to peace and tranquillity. I wish Mark Antony were here today （though I should prefer his advisers to remain elsewhere!）. But I suppose he has the right to be unwell – even if yesterday he did not allow it to myself. If he were here, he would tell me, or rather he would tell you, Senators, what line he adopts as regards the justification of Caesar's acts. The point is this: are the acts we are being asked to ratify the ones that are jotted down in scrappy memoranda and handwritten scrawls and notebooks produced on the sole authority of Antony – or rather not even produced but merely quoted – whereas the acts that Caesar himself engraved on brass tablets, with the intention of preserving the national Assembly's directions and definitive laws, are to be totally disregarded? My own view is that nothing forms such an indissoluble part of Caesar's acts as the laws which were adopted on Caesar's proposal. But if, on the other hand, he once made some promise or other to some-body, does that also really have to be regarded as irrevocable, even though he was never able to give effect to it himself? It is true that in his lifetime he offered many promises which he did not, in fact, fulfil. But these promises of his which have been dug up after his death are so immensely numerous that they exceed the entire total of the favours he actually dispensed for services rendered, or as free gifts, during all the years of his life.

All the same, it is not by any means my intention to tamper with any of those items; I do not even propose to touch them. On the contrary, I am an enthusiastic defender of his excellent acts. For example, I sincerely wish that the funds he collected in the Temple of Ops were still there this day. Blood-stained that money certainly was, but since it cannot be restored to its owners we could make good use of it today. However, let us put up with its dissipation – if it is a fact that this is what his acts laid down.

But surely the most important of all the acts of a civil officer of state, conducting the government through the powers vested in his person, are the laws which were passed on his initiative. Look for the acts of Gaius Gracchus; you will find the Sempronian laws. Consider the acts of Sulla; the Cornelian laws are what you see. Or think of the third consulship of Pompeius – what acts did that produce? Surely his legislation again. If you asked Caesar himself to describe his acts at Rome and in civil life, he would answer that he had sponsored many first-rate laws. But his handwritten notes, on the other hand, he would either regard as provisional and liable to emendation, or he would omit to produce them at all, or even if he produced them he would not wish for their inclusion among his acts. However, that is a point on which I am prepared, in certain instances, to give way and turn a blind eye. But the most important aspect of the matter relates to his laws, and in so far as they are concerned I am by no means ready to tolerate the annulment of Caesar's acts.

Take, for example, that exceptionally salutary and valuable law, frequently longed for in the happy days of the Republic, which provides that former praetors should not govern provinces for longer than a year, and former consuls for not more than two. Suppress this law, and how can you still speak of preserving Caesar's acts? And then again this bill that has been published about a third panel of judges – surely it rescinds Caesar's entire legislation relating to those panels. If you are going to abolish Caesar's laws how on earth can you say you defend his acts? For it is totally illogical to suggest that everything he jotted down in a notebook to help his memory, however unjust and useless, must be regarded as part of his acts, whereas what he actually had passed by the people, voting in its Assembly of Centuries, is not going to be included among them at all.

But let us see what this new third panel is. It consists of centurions, Antony says. Well, they were authorized to serve as judges, were they not, by a Julian law, and before that by Pompeian and Aurelian laws. So they did serve: and not only in cases concerning a centurion but a Roman knight as well – and so it has come about that gentlemen of great valour and repute, former commanders of troops, have served as judges in the past and still do so to this day. ‘But those are not the men I am concerned with,’ he continues. ‘I want everyone who has ever commanded a unit of a hundred men to be a judge.’ Even if you applied this principle to everyone who had served as a knight, which is after all a more distinguished rank, the argument would still be totally unconvincing. For when you appoint a judge it is perfectly proper to be guided by considerations of property and rank. ‘But such qualifications do not interest me,’ answers Antony. ‘Indeed, I am proposing that judges should be taken from another category also: from private soldiers of the Legion of the Lark. For without such a measure our supporters are sure they will suffer victimization.’ But what an insult to these people whom （though nothing was further from their thoughts） you are proposing to mobilize as judges! For what your law implies is that the third panel is going to consist of members who will not dare to produce impartial verdicts. But, heavens, what a miscalculation on the part of the people who thought up the law! For what in fact will happen is that people of no standing who are now to be included among the judges will try to force themselves up out of their obscurity by producing the strictest possible decisions – calculating that these can get them promoted to grander panels instead of the undistinguished one to which, quite rightly, they had been allotted.

Another bill that has now been published rules that men convicted of violence and treason shall have the right to appeal to the Assembly. But, I ask you, is this a law at all – is it not rather a law to end all laws? And anyway, who cares nowadays whether this bill is persevered with or not? For there is not, in fact, one single person today awaiting trial under the laws concerned with those offences. And I do not suppose that there will be anyone in the future either – since acts perpetrated by people under arms will clearly never be brought into court!

But the measure, we are told, is a popular one. What a good thing it would be if you really had something popular in mind! For in our present circumstances, Roman citizens are unanimous in their estimate of the country's political needs. So I cannot understand your enthusiasm to propose a law which, far from being a source of popularity, is bound to earn you discredit. For it is in the highest degree discreditable that a man who has committed violence and treason against the Roman people, and suffered condemnation for those offences, should forthwith be allowed to relapse into precisely the same violent behaviour which was responsible for his conviction. However, it is a waste of time to go on arguing about the proposed law. For obviously its real concern is not with the question of appeal at all. Its object, and your object in bringing it forward, is to prevent any and every prosecution under the laws in question. For how could one ever find a prosecutor idiotic enough to secure a conviction and thus expose himself to hostile crowds on someone else's payroll, or a judge rash enough to pronounce a sentence which will get him dragged before a gang of bribed toughs?

No, the bill is not really designed to give a right of appeal. What it does instead is to hand over two particularly useful laws and courts to suppression. In other words it offers young men a clear invitation to become riotous, seditious, pernicious citizens. One hesitates to think of the ruinous excesses to which rabid tribunes will be encouraged to go when these two courts for violence and treason are no more. Besides, the measure will also have the effect of superseding the laws of Caesar which rule that men convicted of the two offences in question become outlaws banned from water and fire. Because, surely, to allow people condemned for these crimes to appeal is tantamount to declaring that these acts of Caesar are abolished. Although I personally was never in favour of his acts, gentlemen, I nevertheless maintained that for unity's sake they ought to be kept intact. That is why I maintain that nothing should be done at this juncture to annul the laws he sponsored in his lifetime – or even, for that matter, the ones you now see published and posted after his death.

It is true that exiles are recalled from banishment – by a man who is dead. A dead man, again, has conferred citizenship, not merely on individuals but on entire nations and provinces. A dead man has wiped out national revenues, by unlimited grants of ex-emption. And yet, even so, I assert my willingness to defend these measures, even when they are only guaranteed by a single individual's authority （a substantial authority, admittedly） and produced from his own house. But, if this is accepted, how on earth can we simultaneously urge the suppression of laws which Caesar himself read out in our presence and published and proposed, laws about provinces and about courts which he was well content to sponsor and considered indispensable to our national interests? When laws are publicly announced, as those were, at least we are afforded a chance to complain if we want to. But when we merely have to rely on hearsay to discover that a law has been passed at all, no such opportunity exists. And the laws produced by Antony were passed with-out any prior advertisement whatever: we were not even shown a preliminary draft.

There is no reason, it is true, Senators, why I myself, or any of you, need have the slightest fear of bad laws being adopted so long as good tribunes are available. And we do possess such tribunes, men ready to apply their veto, ready to use their sacred office in defence of the constitution. Obviously we ought, then, to lack the slightest grounds for apprehension. ‘But what is this veto,’ asks Antony, ‘what sacred office are you talking about?’ The answer is that the right of veto, and the office to which I refer, are institutions fundamental to the security of the state. ‘That does not impress us at all,’ Antony comments. ‘We regard it as old-fashioned and stupid. What we shall do is to barricade the Forum and close all its entrances; detachments of armed men will be posted at numerous points.’

And then, I suppose, what is transacted in that fashion will be law. And you will give orders to have bronze tablets engraved with the legal formula ‘the consuls by right of law put the question to the people’. But how can you call this the same right of putting the question which our forefathers handed down to us? The formula continues, ‘and the people by right of law passed the measure’. Which people? The ones who were shut out? And what right of law? The law which armed violence has obliterated out of existence?

These observations are intended as guidance for the future – since it is the duty of a friend to offer advance warning against things that can still be avoided. If these unfortunate occurrences never materialize, then my comments will automatically be refuted. The bills I am talking about are ones which are going to be published in due form, and there is nothing to stop you from proposing whatever you like. But as for myself, I consider it my duty to forecast possible flaws and ask you for their removal – to denounce, in other words, armed violence, and to demand its elimination!

When patriotic motives impel me, Dolabella, to offer such suggestions, I am justified in hoping that you consuls will not take it amiss. I do not imagine that you yourself will be angry, since I know what a good-tempered man you are. But people are commenting that your colleague Mark Antony, as he luxuriates in his present position which he regards as so fine （though I would hold him more fortunate, to put it mildly, if he modelled his consulship on those of his grandfathers and his maternal uncle）, has taken offence. Now it is far from agreeable, I can see, when a man who has something against you holds a weapon in his hand – especially now that swords can be used with such impunity. But I will propose a pact: it seems to me a fair arrangement and I do not believe Antony will turn it down. That is to say, if I utter one single insulting remark about his private life or his morals I shall not object to him treating me as a bitter enemy. But if, on the other hand, I merely adhere to the custom of my entire political career and pronounce my frank opinion about national issues, first of all I beg him not to be indignant with me, and next, if that plea fails, I at least urge that his indignation should only be that of one fellow-citizen against another. Let him by all means employ an armed guard if this is needed, as he claims, for self-defence; but do not let their weapons be used on people who are expressing their views on public affairs. Now, what could be a fairer request than that? However, if any and every speech which goes against his wishes causes him to take umbrage even though it may contain not a trace of an insult – and some of his friends have told me that this is what happens – then we shall just have to put up with our friend's disposition and leave it at that. But these same henchmen of Antony also advise me, ‘You as an opponent of Caesar will not be allowed the same indulgence as Piso, who was the father of his wife.’ And at the same time they give me a word of warning which I do not propose to neglect, and it is this: being ill has not served me as an excuse for absence from the Senate – but I shall have a better excuse if I am dead!

You are my intimate friend, Dolabella; and, when I see you sitting there, heaven knows I find it impossible to keep silent about the mistake that you are both making. Each of you is a nobleman with lofty aims, and I must part company with those who maintain, in their excessive credulity, that it is money you are after; for that is something which men of true greatness and renown have always despised. I refuse to believe that what you want is wealth acquired by violent means, or the sort of power that Romans would find intolerable. Yours, I am convinced, is the very different ambition of gaining the love of your fellow-citizens and winning a splendid reputation. Such a reputation means praise won by noble actions and by great services to one's country, and endorsed by the testimony of national leaders and the whole population. And I would be prepared to enlarge further, Dolabella, on this subject of the rewards won by splendid deeds, did I not see that in these recent times you yourself have shown that you appreciate this very matter even better than anyone else.

For you can surely remember no happier occasion in all your life than the day on which, before returning home, you cleaned up the Forum, dispersed that concourse of blasphemous scoundrels, punished the ringleaders for their loathsome designs, and rescued the city from incendiarism and the menace of massacre. All members of the community, whatever their rank or class or station, pressed forward to compliment and congratulate you. Indeed, loyal citizens were even thanking and congratulating me as your proxy; because they believed your deed had been instigated by myself. Cast your mind back, I urge you, Dolabella, to that unanimous demonstration in the theatre when the entire crowd of spectators, dismissing from their minds what they had held against you previously, revealed that your recent action on their behalf had made them put aside all recollection of their earlier grudges.

And so it distresses me deeply, Dolabella, that after winning such great respect you should now be prepared to cast this all aside with complete equanimity.

And as for you, Mark Antony, you are not with us now, but I have an appeal to address to you all the same. That one day, on which the Senate met in the temple of Tellus, must surely have happier memories for you than all the subsequent months in which so many people （greatly differing from me） have accounted you fortunate. For what a splendid speech you made about national unity! When you renounced your hostility towards your fellow-consul and forgot the unfavourable auspices which you yourself as an augur of Rome had declared to be an impediment to his election: when you accepted him for the first time as your colleague, and sent your infant son to the Capitol as a hostage, your words freed the ex-soldiers from all apprehensions about their position, and indeed delivered our entire nation from its anxieties. Never has there been more rejoicing than there was on that day, both in the Senate and among the whole people of Rome – which was gathered together in numbers such as had never been seen at any public meeting before. At that juncture it finally and definitely seemed true that the action of those most valiant citizens had brought us our liberty, because their wish had come true, and the outcome of liberation was peace.

And then again on the next day and the second and the third and those that followed, you daily continued to confer some fresh gift upon your country; and the greatest of all these benefits was your abolition of the title of dictator. For that was the time when you （of all people） branded the dead Caesar's memory with ineradicable infamy. In a bygone age the crime of a single Marcus Manlius caused the Manlian family to decree that no patrician Manlius should ever again bear the first name of Marcus. And now, by the same token, the detestation felt for a single dictator caused you to suppress the name of dictator altogether.

But then, after these outstanding services that you had contributed to the nation, whatever can have happened? Did you regret the good fortune and illustriousness and glory and renown you had won? I wonder how that sudden transformation came about. I cannot bring myself to suspect you were corrupted by financial considerations. Let people say what they like, one is not forced to believe them: and I have never found anything squalid or mean in your character. It is true that the people in a man's home some-times deprave him – but I know very well that you are a strong-minded person. I am only sorry that your freedom from guilt is not equalled by your freedom from suspicion.

But what frightens me more than such imputations is the possibility that you yourself may disregard the true path of glory, and instead consider it glorious to possess more power than all your fellow-citizens combined – preferring that they should fear you rather than like you. If that is what you think, your idea of where the road of glory lies is mistaken. For glory consists of being regarded with affection by one's country, winning praise and respect and love; whereas to be feared and disliked, on the other hand, is unpleasant and hateful and debilitating and precarious. This is clear enough from the play in which the man said, ‘Let them hate provided that they fear’. He found to his cost that such a policy was his ruin. It would have been so much better, Mark Antony, if you had kept the record of your grandfather before your eyes. You have heard me speak of him at length and on numerous occasions. Do you think he would have regarded his claim to immortality as being best served by terrorizing people with armed gangs? No, what life and good fortune meant to him was to be the equal of everybody else in freedom, but their superior in his honourable way of life. About his glorious successes I shall say nothing now; but I want to record my conviction that the last tragic day of his life was preferable to the tyranny of Lucius Cinna who brutally slew him.

However, I see no hope of influencing you by what I say. For if the end that befell Gaius Caesar does not persuade you that it is better to inspire affection than terror, no words that anyone could utter will have the slightest effect or success. People who say Caesar was enviable are profoundly misguided. For no one can be said to have a happy life when its violent termination brings his slayers not merely impunity but the height of glory. So change your ways, I entreat you. Remember your ancestors – and govern our country in such a way that your fellow-citizens will rejoice that you were born. For without that there is no such thing as happiness, or renown, or security.

Your fellow-Romans have furnished you both with ample warnings, and it worries me that they fail to impress you sufficiently. Think of the clamour raised by countless citizens at gladiatorial shows, think of all the versified popular slogans, think of those endless acclamations in front of the statue of Pompeius, think of the two tribunes who are against you! Surely these are sufficient indications that every Roman speaks with a single voice! And then again did you attach no importance to the applause at Apollo's Games? – or rather I should call it the testimony and judgement of the entire Roman people. What an honour for the men who were prevented by armed violence from being present in person – though they were present in the hearts and emotions of the people of Rome! Or did you really suppose that all that approval was meant for the playwright Accius – that his tragedy was winning a belated prize sixty years after its first performance? No, Brutus was the man for whom the cheering and the prize were intended. He could not himself attend the games that were displayed in his name, but the Romans who witnessed that sumptuous show paid their tribute to him in his absence, and sought to comfort the sadness which they felt because their liberator was not with them by incessant cheers and shouts of sympathy.

Personally I have always despised applause of this kind – when its recipients are the sort of men who will do anything to win popularity. All the same, when the cheering comes unanimously from the highest and middle and lowest classes of the community alike, and when the politicians who used to bow to the popular will are suddenly found going in the opposite direction, that seems to me to constitute not merely applause but a verdict!

Or if you regard that as a trivial matter – although it is actually most significant – do you also attach no importance to the proof you have seen of Rome's loving solicitude for the health of Aulus Hirtius? It was already a very notable fact that Roman people esteem him as they do, that unique affection is lavished on him by his friends, that his family hold him so exceptionally dear. But now, in his illness, is there anyone in the memory of mankind who has been the object of such profound anxiety among all good citizens, and of such universal alarm? Nobody has ever been favoured with such demonstrations before. And so does it not occur to you that the people who are so deeply concerned for the lives of those they hope will serve the state may start having thoughts about your own lives as well?

Senators, the rewards I hoped to gain from my return are now mine. For the views I have expressed to you today are a guarantee that, whatever may happen in the future, my determination shall be on record: Moreover, you have given me an attentive and sympathetic hearing. If, without peril to myself and you, I am allowed further opportunities to speak, I shall use them as often as I can. If not, I shall work to the best of my ability for the welfare not of my own self but of our country. Meanwhile, I can say that my life has now lasted long enough, by the measure of years and fame alike. If an additional span is now to be vouchsafed to me, I shall again not devote it to my own interests, but it will be placed, as before, at the disposal of yourselves and Rome.

An Attack on an Enemy of Freedom
（The Second Philippic against Mark Antony）

Members of the Senate: Why is this my fate? I am obliged to record that, for twenty years past, our country has never had an enemy who has not, simultaneously, made himself an enemy of mine as well. I need mention no names. You remember the men for yourselves. They have paid me graver penalties than I could have wished.

Antony, you are modelling your actions on theirs. So what happened to them ought to frighten you; I am amazed that it does not. When those others were against me as well as against Rome I was less surprised. For they did not seek me out as an enemy. No, it was I who, for patriotic reasons, took the initiative against every one of them. But you I have never injured, even in words. And yet, without provocation, you have assailed me with gross insults. Catiline himself could not have been so outrageous, nor Publius Clodius so hysterical. Evidently you felt that the way to make friends, in disreputable circles, was by breaking off relations with me.

Did you take this step in a spirit of contempt? I should not have thought that my life, and my reputation, and my qualities – such as they are – provide suitable material for Antony's contempt. Nor can he have believed, surely, that he could successfully disparage me before the Senate. Accustomed though it is to complimenting distinguished Romans for good service to the state, the Senate has praised only one man for actually rescuing it from annihilation: and that is myself. But perhaps Antony's ambition was to compete with me as a speaker? If so, how extremely generous of him to present me with such a subject – justification of myself, criticism of him: the richest and most promising theme imaginable! No, the truth is clearly this. He saw no chance of proving to people like himself that he was Rome's enemy, unless he became mine too.

Before I reply to his other accusations, I should like to say a few words in answer to one particular complaint, namely that it was I who broke our friend-ship. Because I regard this as a very serious charge. He has protested that I once spoke against him in a lawsuit. But surely I was obliged to support my close friend against someone with whom I had no connexion. Besides, the backer of my friend's opponent was only interested in him from a discreditable interest in his youthfulness, and not because the young man was really promising. Since his supporter had procured an unfair result through a scandalous exercise of the veto, I had no choice but to intervene. However, I think I know why you brought the matter up. You wanted to ingratiate yourself with the underworld, by reminding everybody that you are the son-in-law of an ex-slave, Quintus Fadius; in other words, a former slave is the grandfather of your children.

Yet you allege that you constantly visited my house, in order to receive my tuition. If you had, your reputation and your morals would have benefited. But you did not! Even if you had wanted to, Gains Scribonius Curio would never have let you. Then you claim that you retired from the election to the augurship in my favour. That is sheer effrontery: monstrous, shameless, and unbelievable. In those days, when the entire Board of Augurs was pressing me to become a member, and my nominators （only two being allowed） were Pompey and Quintus Hortensius, you were completely destitute. There was only one hope of safety which you could see, and that was revolution. At that juncture you stood no chance whatever of becoming an augur; for Curio was out of Italy. Later, when you came up for election, you could not have secured the votes of a single tribe without Curio. So energetic, indeed, was the canvassing of his friends on your behalf, that they were condemned in the courts for the use of violence!

You did me a favour, you object. Certainly; I have always admitted the instance that you quote. It seemed to me less undesirable to admit my obligation to you than to let ignorant people think me ungrateful. However, the favour was this, was it not? – that you did not kill me at Brundisium. But I do not see how you could have killed me. For I had been ordered to Italy by the conqueror himself – the very man whose chief gangster you were congratulating yourself on having become.

Nevertheless, let us imagine that you could have killed me. That, Senators, is what a favour from gangsters amounts to. They refrain from murdering someone; then they boast that they have spared him! If that is a true favour, then those who killed Caesar, after he had spared them, would never have been regarded as so glorious – and they are men whom you yourself habitually describe as noble. But the mere abstention from a dreadful crime is surely no sort of favour. In the situation in which this ‘favour’ placed me, my dominant feelings ought not to have been pleasure because you did not kill me, but sorrow because you could have done so with impunity.

However, let us even assume that it was a favour; at any rate the best favour that a gangster could confer. Still, in what respect can you call me ungrateful? Were my protests against the downfall of our country wrong, because you might think they showed ingratitude? I admit that there was no lack of grief and misery in my complaints. But a man in my position, the position conferred on me by the Senate and people of Rome, could not help that. And my words were restrained and friendly, never insulting. Surely that is real moderation – to protest about Antony and yet refrain from abuse!

For what was left of Rome, Antony, owed its final annihilation to yourself. In your home everything had a price: and a truly sordid series of deals it was. Laws you passed, laws you caused to be put through in your interests, had never even been formally proposed. You admitted this yourself. You were an augur, yet you never took the auspices. You were a consul, yet you blocked the legal right of other officials to exercise the veto. Your armed escort was shocking. You are a drink-sodden, sex-ridden wreck. Never a day passes in that ill-reputed house of yours without orgies of the most repulsive kind.

In spite of all that, I restricted myself in my speech to solemn complaints concerning the state of our nation. I said nothing personal about the man. I might have been conducting a case against Marcus Licinius Crassus （as I often have, on grave issues） instead of against this utterly loathsome gladiator.

Today, therefore, I am going to ensure that he under-stands what a favour I, on that occasion, conferred upon himself. He read out a letter, this creature, which he said I had sent him. But he has absolutely no idea how to behave – how other people behave. Who, with the slightest knowledge of decent people's habits, could conceivably produce letters sent him by a friend, and read them in public, merely because some quarrel has arisen between him and the other? Such conduct strikes at the roots of human relations; it means that absent friends are excluded from communicating with each other. For men fill their letters with flippancies which appear tasteless if they are published – and with serious matters which are quite unsuitable for wide circulation. Antony's action proves he is totally uncivilized.

But just see how unbelievably stupid he is as well. Try to answer my next point, you marvel of eloquence! （At least that is what you seem to Seius Mustela and Numisius Tiro, who stand here in full view of the Senate at this very moment, sword in hand: and even I shall admit that you are an eloquent orator after you explain to me how, when they were charged with assassination, you could get them acquitted.） However, to resume – what if I denied that I had ever sent you that letter? You would be left without an answer: you could not find a shred of evidence to convict me. By the handwriting? It is true that you have found your knowledge of handwriting very lucrative. All the same, your efforts would be pointless, because the letter was written by a secretary. What a lucky man your teacher of oratory was! You paid him very handsomely （as I shall remind you later）, and yet when you left his hands you were still a complete fool. To charge one's opponent with something which, in the face of a blank denial, he cannot press home to the slightest effect is of no service whatever to any speaker; indeed to anyone with any sense at all. Nevertheless I do not deny authorship. And when I say that, I am also saying that you are not ill-behaved but a lunatic. For my whole letter was replete with dutiful kindness – it was a veritable model of how to behave. Your criticism concerning its contents merely amounts to this: that I do not express a bad opinion of you; and that I address you as a Roman citizen and a decent man, instead of as a bandit and a criminal.

Now I do not propose to produce your letter, though under this provocation I should be entitled to: the letter in which you begged me to consent to someone's return from exile, and promised that you would not bring him back unless I agreed. And I did agree. For it was not for me to stand in the way of your outrageous behaviour, seeing that this is uncontrollable even by the authority of this Senatorial Order, and universal public opinion, and the whole body of the law. But what was the point of making me such a plea, when Caesar had actually passed a law authorizing the return of the very man with whom your letter was concerned? No doubt Antony was eager that I should get the credit! – seeing that even he was not going to win any credit, since the matter had already been settled by legislation.

Senators: in self-defence, and in denunciation of Antony, I have no lack of material. But as regards the former of those themes, I have an appeal to make: while I speak in my own defence I urge you to be indulgent. The second matter I shall look after on my own account – I shall ensure that what I am going to say against Antony impresses itself upon your attention. At the same time I beg this of you. My whole career as a speaker, indeed my whole life, has, I believe, demonstrated to you that I am a moderate man and not an extremist. So do not suppose that I have forgotten myself when I reply to this man in the spirit in which he has challenged me. I am not going to treat him as a consul, for he did not treat me as a former consul, as a man of consular rank. Besides, he is no true consul at all. He does not live like one; he does not work like one; and he was never elected to be one. Whereas a former consul I unquestionably am.

You can see what sort of a consul he claims to be by the way in which he criticizes my tenure of that office. Yet my consulship, Senators, though it can be called mine, was in plain fact yours. For everything I decided, every policy I carried out, every action I took, derived from this Senatorial Order – from its deliberations, its authority, and its rulings. What a strange kind of wisdom you show, Antony – eloquence is evidently not your only quality – when you abuse me before the very men whose corporate judgement inspired those actions of mine! The only people who have ever abused my consulship are Publius Clodius and yourself. And his fate – the fate which also overtook Curio – will be yours: for what brought death to both of them is now in your home!(1)

So Antony disapproves of my consulship. But – to name first the most recently deceased of the ex-consuls of that time – Publius Servilius Vatia Isauricus thought well of it. Quintus Lutatius Catulus, who will always carry weight among our countrymen, like-wise bestowed upon me his approval. So did Lucius Licinius Lucullus and his brother Marcus, and Marcus Licinius Crassus, Quintus Hortensius, Gaius Scribonius Curio the elder, Gaius Calpurnius Piso, Manius Acilius Glabrio, Manius Aemilius Lepidus, Lucius Volcacius Tullus, Gaius Marcius Figulus, and the two consuls designate at the time, Decimus Junius Silanus and Lucius Licinius Murena. And Marcus Porcius Cato felt the same as those of consular rank: he too praised my activities as consul. Your consulship, on the other hand, was the worst of the many things which death spared Cato. Another very strong supporter of mine was Pompey. When we first met after his return from Syria, he embraced me, offered his congratulations, and declared that it was through my services that there was still a Rome for him to see. But why do I mention individuals? A very full house of the Senate so warmly applauded my consulship that there was not a man there who did not thank me as if I had been his father. Their possessions, their lives, their children's lives, their country – they owed all these, said every one of them, to me.

However, since Rome has lost all the great men whom I have mentioned, let us pass to the two ex-consuls of that time who are still with us. For those very actions which you denounce, that brilliant statesman Lucius Aurelius Cotta proposed that I should be accorded a most generous vote of thanks. And this proposal was adopted – by those very ex-consuls whose names I have just recorded, and indeed by the whole Senate. This was an honour which, ever since the city's foundation, had been awarded to no civilian before me. On that occasion your uncle Lucius Julius Caesar attacked his sister's husband, your stepfather; and he spoke with great eloquence, solemnity, and firmness. In all your activities throughout your whole life, your inspiration, your teacher, ought to have been Lucius Caesar. But instead of your uncle, the man on whom you preferred to model yourself was your step-father. When I was consul I consulted Lucius Caesar, though we were not related. You are his sister's son: but when did you ever consult him on state affairs?

Who, indeed, are Antony's advisers? Evidently people whose birthdays have not come to our attention. Antony is not attending the Senate today. Why? He is giving a birthday-party on his estate. For whom? I shall name no names. No doubt it is some comic Phormio or other, some Gnatho or Ballio.(2) What a disgusting, intolerable sensualist the man is, as well as a vicious, unsavoury crook! How is it possible, Antony, that you should consistently fail to consult that admi-rable leading Senator Lucius Caesar, who is your close relation, while instead you prefer to rely on the advice of this collection of down-and-out spongers?

I see; your consulship is beneficent, mine was destructive. Your impudence must be equal to your debauchery if you dare make that assertion in the very place where, as consul, I consulted the Senate, which once, in its glory, presided over the whole world: namely, in this temple of Concord, now crammed – by your agency – with delinquents bristling with weapons. And yet you had the effrontery, the unlimited effrontery, to claim that, when I was consul, the road up the Capitoline Hillwas packed with armed slaves! Do you really mean to suggest that I was applying violent pres-sure upon the Senate in order to force through those decrees of mine – in other words, that they were discreditable? You poor fool, to utter such impertinences before men of this calibre! – if the facts are known to you: or perhaps they are not, since all that is good is completely foreign to your mind.

When the Senate met in this temple, every single Roman knight, every young man of aristocratic birth – except yourself – every man （of whatever class） who was conscious of his Roman citizenship, gathered together on the road to the Capitol; each of them gave in his name. So many were they that no number of secretaries or writing tablets could have been enough for the registration of the entire multitude of them.

For that was the very moment when evil men were confessing that they had planned to assassinate their country. The revelations of their own accomplices had forced them to this admission. So had their own hand-writing, and the almost audible testimony of their own letters. To murder the citizens of Rome – that was the intention which emerged; to ravage Italy; revolution! At such a time, no one could fail to hear the call to defend the common cause – especially as the Senate and Roman people, in those days, possessed a leader. If they had his like as a leader now, the fate that descended upon those anarchists would be yours also.

Antony protests that I refused to give up his stepfather's body for burial. But even Publius Clodius never brought that charge. I was the enemy of Clodius – justifiably: but your faults, I regret to see, are blacker even than his. Why did it occur to you, I wonder, to remind us of your upbringing in your stepfather's home? I suppose you were afraid that we should be sceptical of nature's unaided effects; that we should need this evidence of upbringing before we could understand why you had turned out so criminally.

Really, your speech was demented, it was so full of inconsistencies. From beginning to end, you were not merely incoherent but glaringly self-contradictory: indeed you contradicted yourself more often than you contradicted me. You admitted that your stepfather was involved in that terrible crime, and yet you complained because he had been punished for what he did. But the effect of that argument was to praise my part in the matter, and to blame what was wholly the Senate's part. For whereas it was I who arrested the guilty men, it was the Senate which punished them. So our masterly speaker here does not realize he is praising the man he is trying to attack, and is abusing those who sit here listening to him!

I will not call this effrontery – which is in any case a quality he proudly claims. But Antony has no desire to be stupid, and he must be the most stupid man alive to talk of the Capitoline road at this moment – when armed men are actually standing here among our benches, are stationed with their swords in that same temple of Concord, heaven bear me witness, where my consulship saw decisions which saved our nation and brought us in safety to this day.

Go on, criticize the Senate, criticize the knights who were at that time its partners. Assail every class and every citizen with your accusations, provided you admit that at the present moment this meeting of ours here is picketed by your Ituraean police. Unscrupulous-ness is not what prompts these shameless statements of yours; you make them because you entirely fail to grasp how you are contradicting yourself. In fact, you must be an imbecile. How could a sane person first take up arms to destroy his country, and then protest because someone else had armed himself to save it?

At one point you tried to be witty. Heaven knows this did not suit you. And your failure is particularly blameworthy, since you could have acquired some wit from that professional actress known as your wife. ‘Let gown be mightier than sword’(3) were the words of mine that you mocked. Well, that was so in those days, was it not? But since then your swords have won. Let us consider which was the better: the time when gangsters’ weapons were overcome by men defending Roman freedom, or now, when your weapons have struck that freedom down. As far as my poem is concerned that is the only answer I have to give. I will merely add briefly that you understand neither this poem nor any other literature. I, on the other hand, though I have not neglected my duty to our country or to my friends, have nevertheless employed my leisure hours in literary productions of many kinds. All that I have written, the whole of my effort, has been intended for the benefit of young people and for the greater glory of Rome. However, that is another matter. Let us turn to questions of more importance.

It was upon my initiative, you said, that Publius Clodius was killed by Titus Annius Milo. But what would people have thought if he had been killed when, sword in hand, you chased him into the Forum, with the whole of Rome looking on? If he had not stopped you by hiding under the stairs of a bookshop and barricading them, you would have finished him off. Now I admit that I viewed your attempt with favour; yet even you do not claim that I prompted you. But as for Milo, I did not have an opportunity even to favour his attempt, since he had completed the job before anyone suspected what he was going to do. You say I prompted him. So presumably Milo was not the sort of man who could perform a patriotic action without a prompter! I celebrated the deed when it was done, you point out. But when the whole nation was rejoicing, why should I be the only mourner? Certainly, the inquiry into Clodius's death was not very judiciously designed. For when an established legal procedure for murder was available, the creation of a new law to deal with the case was pointless. Anyway, that is what was done, and the inquiry took its course. At the time, when the matter was under active consideration, no one brought this charge against me. It remained for you to perpetrate the fabrication after all these years!

Your next impudent accusation – made at considerable length – is that I was responsible for alienating Pompey from Caesar, and that by so doing I caused the Civil War. Your mistake in saying this is not wholly factual, but chronological; and this is a significant point. It is true that, during the consul-ship of the admirable Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus, I made every possible attempt to separate Pompey from Caesar. But Caesar was more successful: for he alienated Pompey from me. And when Pompey had wholeheartedly joined Caesar, how could I endeavour to set them apart? I should have been foolish to hope for such a thing – and impertinent to attempt persuasion. Yet there were two occasions on which I advised Pompey against Caesar. Blame me for them, if you can. First, I advised him not to renew Caesar's five-year term in Gaul; secondly, I urged him not to allow Caesar's candidature for the consulship in absentia. If I had been successful on either occasion, our present miseries would never have befallen us.

But instead Pompey made a present to Caesar of all his own resources, and all the resources of Rome. Only then did he belatedly begin to understand what I had foreseen long before. But by that time I had also come to realize that a criminal attack on our country was imminent. That is why, from then onward, I never ceased to urge peace, harmony, and arrangement. Many people knew what I was saying: ‘If only, Pompey, you had either avoided joining Caesar or avoided breaking with him! Your strength of character demanded the former course, and your wisdom the latter!’ That, Antony, was the advice I consistently gave in regard to Pompey and the crisis of our Republic. If this advice had prevailed, the Republic would still be flourishing: but you would not be, for your scandalous, down-at-heels, infamous behaviour would have brought you down.

However, these are old stories. Your new story is this: I was responsible for the killing of Caesar. Now, Senators, I am afraid I may look guilty, at this point, of a deplorable offence: namely the production, in a case against myself, of a sham prosecutor – a man who will load me with compliments whether I am entitled to them or not. For among the company who did that most glorious of deeds, my name was never once heard. Yet not a name among them remained secret. Secret, do I say? Every one of them was instantly known far and wide! It was much more likely, believe me, that men should have boasted of complicity, though they had nothing to do with the deed, than that having been accomplices they should have desired to conceal the fact. There were quite a number of them; some obscure, some youthful – not the sort of people who would keep anyone's identity quiet. So, if I had been involved, how on earth could my participation have remained unknown?

Besides – if we really need to assume that the prime movers in that operation needed prompting to free their country! – was it for me to inspire the two Brutuses? Every day, in their own homes, each of them had the statue of Lucius Junius Brutus to gaze upon – and one of them had Gaius Servilius Ahala as well. These living Brutuses, with these ancestors, needed no outside advisers from other houses: they had advisers ready to hand within their own homes. Gaius Cassius Longinus, too, belongs to a clan incapable of tolerating not only autocracy but even excessive power in any single individual. Yet apparently he needed me as his instigator! On the contrary, even before his present distinguished associates were avail-able, Cassius had proposed to perform this same task in Cilicia at the mouth of the Cydnus, if only Caesar, after deciding to moor his ships on one bank of the river, had not moored them on the other instead. And then again, when the recovery of freedom was at stake, what need had Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus of me to inspire him? Inspiration enough for Domitius was the memory of how his noble father and his uncle had died – and how he himself had been deprived of his rights as a citizen. As for Gaius Trebonius, far from persuading him, I should not even have ventured to advise him – so close were his ties with Caesar. The existence of those ties increases the debt of gratitude which our country owes Trebonius: for one man's friendship seemed to him of less importance than the freedom of the Roman people – he could have shared autocracy, but he preferred to strike it down. Or was I Lucius Tillius Cimber's counsellor? No, my admiration for him after he had done the deed was a great deal stronger than my confidence, beforehand, that he would do it; I admired him all the more because he disregarded the personal favours he had received: he thought only of Rome. And then the two Serviliuses – whether to call them Cascas(4) or Ahalas I do not know. Do you suppose they needed my advice to urge them on? They had their love for their country. To enumerate all the rest would take too long; it reflects great credit on themselves, and great glory on Rome, that they were so many!

But remember, please, how this astute man demonstrated my complicity. ‘When Caesar had been killed,’ said he, ‘Brutus immediately brandished aloft his bloodstained dagger and called out Cicero's name, congratulating him on the recovery of national freedom.’ But this choice of myself, above all others – why must it indicate my foreknowledge? Consider instead whether the reason why Brutus called upon me was not this. The deed which he had done resembled the deeds which I had done myself: that is why he singled me out – to proclaim that he had modelled himself on me.

What a fool you are, Antony. Do you not under-stand this? If wanting Caesar to be killed （as you complain that I did） is a crime, then it is also criminal to have rejoiced when he was dead. For between the man who advises an action and the man who approves when it is done there is not the slightest difference. Whether I wished the deed to be performed or am glad after its performance, is wholly immaterial. Yet, with the exception of the men who wanted to make an autocratic monarch of him, all were willing for this to happen – or were glad when it had happened. So everyone is guilty! For every decent person, in so far as he had any say in the matter, killed Caesar! Plans, courage, opportunities were in some cases lacking; but the desire nobody lacked.

Just listen to the fatuity of this man – this sheep, rather. Here were his words: ‘Brutus, whose name I mention with all respect, called out Cicero's name while he was holding the bloodstained dagger: from which you must understand that Cicero was an accomplice.’ So, just because you suspect that I suspected something you call me a criminal, yet the man who brandished a dripping dagger is mentioned by you ‘with all respect’! Very well, use this imbecile language if you must; and your actions and opinions are even more brainless. In the end, Consul, you will have to make up your mind! You must pronounce your final judgement on the cause of the Brutuses, Cassius, Gnaeus Domitius Ahenobarbus, Gaius Trebonius, and the rest. Sleep off your hangover – breathe it out. Perhaps a torch might be administered, to sting you out of your snoring over this far from unimportant matter. Will you never understand that you must decide which description to apply to the men who did that deed: are they murderers or are they the restorers of national freedom?

Concentrate, please – just for a little. Try to make your brain work for a moment as if you were sober. I confess I am their friend – you prefer to call me their associate. And yet even I refuse to see any compromise solution. If these men are not liberators of the Roman people and saviours of the state, then even I assert that they are worse than assassins, worse than murderers. Indeed, on the assumption that even the murder of one's own father is less horrible than to kill the father of one's country, even parricides are better than they are.

Well, then, you wise and thoughtful man, what do you say to this: if they are parricides, why, in the Senate and Assembly, do you refer to them with respect? You will also have to explain why you yourself proposed Marcus Brutus's exemption from the laws(5) when he remained outside the city for more than ten days; why, at the Games of Apollo, he received such a complimentary reception; and why he and Cassius were given provincial commands, and supernumerary quaestors and legates were assigned to them for the purpose. This was all your doing! So evidently you do not regard them as murderers. It follows – since no compromise is possible – that you must regard them as liberators. What is the matter? I am not embarrassing you, am I? For I doubt if you are quite competent to grasp the sort of dilemma in which this places you. Anyway, what my conclusion amounts to is this: by not regarding Brutus and the rest as criminals, you have automatically proclaimed that they deserve the most glorious rewards.

So I must redesign my speech. I shall write to these men and say that, if anyone asks whether your charge against me is true, they must offer no denials. For, if I was their accomplice and they conceal the fact, I am afraid this may discredit them; whereas if I was invited to join them and refused, this will reflect the gravest discredit on me. For heaven will bear witness that Rome – that any nation throughout the whole world – has never seen a greater act than theirs! There has never been an achievement more glorious – more greatly deserving of renown for all eternity. So if you pen me in a Trojan horse of complicity with the chief partners in that deed, I do not protest. Thank you, I say – whatever your motives. For where so outstanding an action is concerned, I account the unpopularity, which you hope to unload upon me, as nothing beside the glory.

You have driven these men away and expelled them, you boast. Yet they are blessed beyond measure. There is no place in the world too deserted and too barbarous to welcome them and delight in their presence. All people on earth, however uncivilized, are capable of understanding that life could offer no more outstanding happiness than a sight of these men. Writers will continue, for generation after generation throughout time everlasting, to immortalize the glory of their achievement.

Enrol me among such heroes, I beg of you! Though I am afraid that one thing may not be to your liking. If I had been among their number I should have freed our country not only from the autocrat but from the autocracy. For if, as you assert, I had been the author of the work, believe me, I should not have been satisfied to finish only one act: I should have completed the play!(6)

If it is a crime to have wanted Caesar to be put to death, consider your own situation, Antony. Everyone knows that at Narbo you formed a similar plan with Gaius Trebonius: it was because of this plot, while Caesar was being killed, that we saw Trebonius taking you aside. You see – my intentions to you are friendly. I am praising you for the good intention you once had! For not having reported the plot, I thank you; for not having carried it out, I excuse you. That task needed a man.

But suppose that someone prosecutes you; that he applies the test of the jurist Lucius Cassius Longinus: ‘who benefited thereby?’. Then you will have to take care, for you might be implicated. True, you used to observe, once upon a time, that such an act would benefit all who were unwilling to be slaves. Nevertheless, whom did its performance benefit most of all? Yourself! You, who, far from being a slave, are an autocratic ruler: you, who employed the treasure in the Temple of Ops to wipe off your gigantic debts, who after manipulating these same account-books squandered countless sums, who transferred enormous possessions from Caesar's house to your own. What an immensely profitable output of fake memoranda and forged handwritings your home produces! The place is a forger's workshop, a black market: whole properties and cities, mass exemptions from tribute and taxation are the wares of its truly scandalous trade.

Nothing short of Caesar's death could have rescued you from your debtor's ruin. You look rather worried. Are you secretly nervous that you may be implicated? No, I can set your fears at rest: no one will ever believe such a thing of you. You are not the man to perform a patriotic act. Our country has great men, and they did that noble deed. I do not say you took part. I only say you were glad.

Now I have answered your most serious accusations. Well, I must reply to the others. You have complained about my presence in Pompey's camp, and about my conduct throughout that period. True, at that time – and I have said this before – if my advice and authority had prevailed, you would be a poor man today, and we should be free; and our country would not have lost so many armies and commanders. For when I foresaw what has now happened, I confess that I mourned as sadly as all other good citizens, if they had possessed my foresight, would likewise have mourned. I grieved, Senators, I grieved that our Republic, which your and my counsels had once preserved, was moving towards rapid annihilation. In such circumstances I was not uneducated and ignorant enough to be overcome by fears whether I personally should survive. For my life, while it was still mine, was full of anguish; whereas its loss would mean an end of all troubles. But I wanted life to remain for the magnificent men who were Rome's glory – all those who have served as consul and praetor, the fine Senators, the flower and promise of our nobility, the armies of good Romans. So for me any peace that could unite our citizens seemed preferable to a war that tore them apart. And indeed, however hard the circumstances of peace, if those men were only living today, at least the Republic would still be with us.

If this view of mine had prevailed, and if the very men whose lives I sought to preserve had not, in their military over-optimism, set themselves against me, one of many results would certainly be this: you would never still be in the Senate. You would not even be at Rome!

You object that my speech alienated Pompey from me. That is absurd. He had more affection for me than for anyone. There was no one in the world whom he talked to and consulted more often. Indeed it was a splendid thing that two men with so widely differing views on government policy should remain such close friends. Each of us knew, equally well, the thoughts and opinions of the other. My first concern was to keep our fellow-Romans alive: by so doing, we could give ourselves time to think later on about their civic rights. Pompey, on the other hand, was preoccupied with their rights in the immediate present. Nevertheless, our disagreement was tolerable – the more so because we both concentrated on our own specific objectives.

But what Pompey, with his outstanding and almost superhuman gifts, thought about myself is well known to those who accompanied him on his retreat from Pharsalus to Paphos. He never mentioned my name except in complimentary terms and with an abundance of friendly regrets that we were not together. He also admitted that, whereas his had been the higher hopes, the more accurate prophet had been myself. But how can you have the effrontery to taunt me with Pompey, when you have to admit that I was his friend: whereas you, on the other hand, were the purchaser of his confiscated property!

However, let us say no more about that war – in which you fared only too well. Nor have I any answer to give you about the jokes which you say I made while I was in camp. Life was certainly anxious there. Yet however grim circumstances are, human beings, if they really are human, occasionally relax. Antony criticizes my gloom, and he criticizes my jokes! Which proves that I showed moderation in both.

No one left me any legacies,(7) you said. I only wish that the charge were justified, for then more of my friends and relations would be alive today. But I wonder how that idea came into your mind. For men have made me bequests amounting to more than twenty million sesterces. True, I admit that in this respect you have been more fortunate than I have. For all who have made me their heirs have been my friends. That has been their way of soothing my grief with some mitigating benefit – if it could be regarded as such. But you inherited from Lucius Rubrius Casinas: whom you had never seen! He must indeed have loved you dearly, seeing that you do not even know whether he was black or white. He passed over in your favour the sons of that very worthy knight, his friend Quintus Fufius. Rubrius had constantly announced, in public, that Fufius's son was to be his heir. And yet he did not even mention him in his will! Instead, you were the man he made his heir – you whom he had never seen or, at any rate, had never spoken to. And tell me this, please, if it is not too much trouble: what did your other benefactor Lucius Turselius look like? How tall was he, where did he come from, what was his tribe? ‘I know nothing,’ you will answer, ‘except what properties he owned.’ Was that sufficient cause for him to disinherit his brother and make you his heir? But there were many others too, equally remote from any connexion with him, from whom Antony grabbed huge sums of money, ejecting the true heirs, and behaving as if he himself were the inheritor.

And there is another reason too why I am surprised, particularly surprised, that you should have had the impudence even to mention matters of inheritance. For you did not come into your own father's property!

Fool! Were these the arguments you were trying to hunt out when you spent day after day in another man's country house, practising oratory? Though your oratorical practice, as your closest friends point out, is intended to work off your hangovers rather than to sharpen your brain, you have facetiously appointed a teacher of oratory – the appointment carried by the supporting votes of your fellow-drinkers – and you have allowed the man to speak against you in any way he likes. He is certainly an amusing enough fellow. But, since you and your friends are his targets, he cannot complain of any lack of material!

Note the contrast between yourself and your grand-father. He, with deliberation, produced arguments relevant to his case; you just pour out irrelevancies. And yet what a salary your teacher of rhetoric has drawn from you. Listen to this, Senators: take note of the wounds inflicted upon our nation. To this elocution trainer – Sextus Clodius – he handed over 1,250 acres of land, taxfree. You made the people of Rome defray this enormous charge, Antony, with no other result than to make you learn to be the idiot that you are. You unprincipled rogue! Was this one of the directions you found in Caesar's notebooks? However, about this estate at Leontini I will say something later; also about other properties in Campania – all of them lands which Antony has wrenched from Rome, and polluted by the utterly degraded characters of the men to whom he has given them.

I have said enough in answer to his charges. Now some attention must be given to our moralist and reformer himself. However, I do not propose to tell the whole story at once: so that if I have to return to the fray, I shall not need to repeat myself. In view of the extraordinary quantity of his crimes and vices, that presents no difficulty.

Would you like us to consider your behaviour from boyhood onwards, Antony? I think so. Let us begin then at the beginning. Your bankruptcy, in early adolescence – do you remember that? Your father's fault, you will say. Certainly; and what a truly filial self-defence! But it was typical of your impudence to go to the theatre and sit in one of the fourteen rows reserved for knights, when the Roscian Law assigned special seats for bankrupts – and meant this to apply whether it was bad luck or bad conduct had caused the bankruptcy. Then you graduated to man's clothing – or rather it was woman's as far as you were concerned. At first you were just a public prostitute, with a fixed price: quite a high one, too. But very soon Curio intervened and took you off the streets, promoting you, one might say, to wifely status, and making a sound, steady, married woman of you. No boy bought for sensual purposes was ever so completely in his master's power as you were in Curio's. On countless occasions his father threw you out of the house. He even stationed guards to keep you out! Nevertheless, helped by nocturnal darkness, urged on by sensuality, compelled by the promised fee – in, through the roof, you climbed.

The household found these repulsive goings on completely unendurable. I wonder if you realize that I have a very thorough knowledge of what I am speaking about. Cast your mind back to the time when Curio's father lay weeping in his bed. The son, likewise in tears, threw himself at my feet and begged me to help you – and to defend himself against a demand, which he expected from his own father, for six million sesterces. The young man loved you so passionately that he swore he would leave the country because he could not bear to be kept apart from you. In those days, within that renowned family, there were troubles without number which I helped to mitigate – or rather, brought to an end altogether. I persuaded the father to pay his son's debts. I persuaded him to sacrifice part of his property to restore the position of this young man, whose promise of brain and character was so brilliant. But I also persuaded him to use all his legal authority as a father to prevent Curio from associating with you or even meeting you. When you remembered all these interventions of mine, only one thing can have given you the nerve to provoke and abuse me in the way you have, and that is your reliance on the brute force of arms: the weapons which we see in the Senate today.

But about Antony's degradations and sex-crimes that is as far as I will go. For there are some things which it would be indecent for me to describe. As far as free speaking goes you have the advantage of me! – since you have done things which a respectable opponent cannot even mention. So instead I will now turn briefly to the remaining portion of this man's life. For our thoughts will naturally run on to what he did during the national miseries of the Civil War – and what he is doing today. You know those things, Senators, as well as I do, and indeed much better. Yet continue, I beg of you, to listen to them carefully. For in such cases knowledge about events is not enough. There is also need to be reminded of them: only thus will they be fully felt.

However, since I must allow myself time to reach the end of these happenings, I must cut short the middle part of the story. Well, Antony now recounts his kindnesses towards me. All the same, when Publius Clodius was tribune, the two men were intimate friends. Antony was the firebrand who started all Clodius's fires. Indeed, one of his projects – he knows very well which one I mean – was actually located in Clodius's home. Then Antony went to Alexandria: in defiance of the Senate, and of patriotism, and of the will of heaven. But he was under a man with whom he could do no wrong – Aulus Gabinius. Then consider the nature and circumstances of Antony's return. Before he came home, he went from Egypt to farthest Gaul. Home, did I say? At that time, other men still possessed homes: but you, Antony, had none at all. Home? You had no piece of ground of your own in the whole world, except at Misenum; and that you only shared with partners, as though it were a company affair like the Sisapo mines.

From Gaul you came to stand for the quaestorship. On that occasion, I dare you to claim that you went to your father before you came to me! I had already received a letter from Caesar asking me to accept your excuses; so I did not even allow you to thank me. After that, you treated me with respect, and I helped you in your candidature for the quaestorship. That was the time when, with the approval of Rome, you tried to kill Publius Clodius. Now, though this was entirely your own idea, and owed nothing to my initiative, nevertheless you proclaimed the conviction that only his murder could ever repay me for the injuries I had suffered from you. This makes me wonder why you say Titus Annius Milo killed Clodius on my instigation. For, when you spontaneously proposed to me that you should perform the same action, I had given you no encouragement. If you went through with the deed, I wanted you yourself, and not my influence upon you, to have the glory.

Well, you became quaestor; and instantly – without benefit of Senate's decree, drawing of lots, or legal sanction – you ran off to Caesar. For that seemed to you the only place on earth where destitution, debt, and crime could find shelter: the only refuge for ruined men. There, through Caesar's generosity and your own looting, you reimbursed your losses – if you can call it reimbursement when you immediately squander what you have embezzled! So then, beggared again, you hastened to apply for a tribuneship. Your aim in acquiring it, presumably, was to model yourself on your lover.

Now listen, I beg you, Senators, I do not mean to the personal and domestic scandals created by Antony's disgusting improprieties, but to the evil, godless way in which he has undermined us all, and our fortunes, and our whole country. At the root of all our disasters you will find his wickedness. When Lucius Cornelius Lentulus Crus and Gaius Claudius Marcellus became consuls on the first of January, the Republican government was tottering and on the verge of collapse. You, members of the Senate, wanted to support the government; you also desired to meet the wishes of Caesar himself, if he was in his right mind. Yet Antony had sold and subjected his tribuneship to another man, and he exploited the office for your obstruction. That is to say, to the axe which had struck down many men for lesser crimes he had the audacity to expose his own neck. In those days the Senate was still its own master; those honourable members who are now dead were still among its number. That Senate, Antony, employed for your censure the decree reserved, by ancestral custom, for Roman citizens who are the enemies of Rome. And yet, as audience for your criticisms of me, you have the impertinence to select the Senate – that very body which pronounced me to be its saviour, and you the enemy of the state!

Your criminal action at that time has not been mentioned lately; but what you did has not been forgotten. So long as there are human beings in the world, so long as the name of Rome remains upon the earth – and that means everlastingly, barring destructive action by yourself – that pestilential veto(8) of yours will be remembered. In the Senate's proceedings there had not been the slightest sign of bias or impetuosity. Yet you, a single young man, imposed your veto, and thus prevented the entire Senatorial Order from passing a measure on which the safety of our nation depended. And this you did not once, but repeatedly. Furthermore, you rejected all efforts to open negotiations with you about upholding the authority of this House. Yet the matter at stake was nothing less than your itch to plunge the whole country into anarchy and desolation. The pleas of the nation's leaders, the warnings of your elders, a crowded Senate, none of them sufficed to deter you from this measure you had been bribed and bought into proposing.

Next, therefore, after many attempts to dissuade you, there was no alternative; you had to be dealt the blow which few had received before – and which none had survived. So this Senatorial Order directed the consuls, and other powers and authorities, to take up arms against you. You only escaped those arms by sheltering behind Caesar's.

Caesar's intentions were wholly revolutionary. But the man who gave him his principal excuse for attacking his country was yourself. For that was the only pretext he claimed, the only reason he put forward for his maniacal decision and action: he quoted the Senate's disregard of a veto, its abolition of a tribune's entitlement, its encroachment on Antony's rights. I say nothing of the falsity and frivolity of these charges – though no man can possibly be justified in taking up arms against his own nation. But I am not speaking of Caesar. You, Antony, were the man who provided the pretext for this most catastrophic of wars: you cannot deny it.

If what I am now going to say is known to you already, then your fate is sad indeed: and sadder still if it is not. Now, there exist written records, to be recollected without possibility of oblivion by remotest posterity until the end of time, proving that these things happened. That the consuls were expelled from Italy; that they were accompanied by the man whose glory illuminated our nation – Pompey; that all former consuls whose health enabled them to share in that disastrous retreat, all praetors and expraetors, tribunes of the people, a great part of the Senate, the flower of our young manhood, in a word all the components of the entire Roman state, were uprooted and driven from their homes.

Just as seeds are the origins of trees and plants, so, with equal certainty, you were the seed of that most grievous war. Senators, you are mourning three armies of Roman soldiers slain in battle: Antony killed them. You are sorrowing for great men of Rome: Antony robbed you of them. The authority of your Order has been destroyed: Antony destroyed it. For every evil which we have seen since that time – and what evils have we not seen? – he is responsible. There can be no other conclusion. He has been our Helen of Troy! He has brought upon our country war, and pestilence, and annihilation.

The rest of his tribuneship resembled the beginning. Of all the misdeeds which the Senate, while the Republic was still with us, had rendered impossible there was not one which he left undone. And note the crimes within his crime. Though he rehabilitated many who were in trouble, there was no mention of his uncle among them. But if he was severe, why was he not severe to everyone? and if merciful, why not merciful to his own kinsmen?

Among those whose civil rights he restored I will only mention Licinius Lenticula, his fellow-dicer – a man convicted for gambling. I can only suppose Antony protested that his partner at the tables must not be a convict! But his real aim was to utilize the law cancelling Lenticula's sentence as a cloak for the cancellation of his own gaming debts. Now, Antony, what reasons justifying his reinstatement did you quote to the people of Rome? The normal sort of argument would run like this: that Lenticula had been absent when the prosecution was instituted against him; that the case went undefended, that the law provided no judicial procedure to deal with dicing, that armed violence had been used to procure his downfall, or as a final objection what was said in your uncle's case – that the court's decision had been influenced by bribery. But not at all. Those were not your excuses. What you urged was that Lenticula was a good man, useful to his country. Well, that was irrelevant. All the same, I should excuse you on that count if your plea were only true, for the mere fact of having been convicted is of no great importance. But there is not a word of truth in it. Lenticula has been condemned under the law which relates to dicing: he is the sort of person who would not hesitate to throw dice in the Forum itself – a thoroughly criminal type. The man who can restore the rights of such a ruffian reveals a great deal about his own character.

Then consider another aspect of Antony's tribune-ship. When Caesar, on his way to Spain, had given him Italy to trample upon, the journeys Antony made and the towns he visited are well worth looking into. I realize I am speaking of matters which are thoroughly well known and widely talked about. I am also aware that the events of which I am, and shall be, speaking are better known to anyone who was in Italy at that time than to myself who was absent. Nevertheless, although what I tell you will undoubtedly fall short of what you know already, allow me to recall certain particulars.

For never, anywhere in the world, have there been stories of such depraved and discreditable misconduct. He travelled about in a lady's carriage, did this tribune of the people. In front of him marched attendants crowned with laurel-wreaths. Among them, carried in an open litter, went an actress. The respectable citizens of the country towns, compelled to come and meet him, greeted her, not by her well-known stage name, but as Volumnia. Next followed a repulsive collection of his friends: a four-wheeler full of procurers. Only then came his neglected mother, following, like a mother-in-law, her debauched son's mistress. Poor woman! Her capacity for child-bearing has indeed been catastrophic. In such fashion a wide variety of country towns, indeed the whole of Italy, was branded by Antony with the marks of his degraded behaviour.

To censure his other actions, Senators, is difficult and delicate. He fought in the war. He wallowed in the blood of Romans who were in every way his opposites. He was fortunate, if there can ever be good fortune in criminality. But since we do not want to offend the old soldiers – though the soldiers’ case and yours, Antony, are wholly unlike （they followed their leader, you went to seek him out） – nevertheless I shall give you no opportunity to incite them against me. For concerning the character of the war I shall say nothing.

From Thessaly to Brundisium you returned as conqueror with your legions. At Brundisium you refrained from killing me. How very kind of you! For you could have killed me, I admit. Though the men who were with you at that time unanimously maintained I must be spared. For even your own legionaries revered me: so great is man's love for their country, which they remembered that I had saved. However, let us concede that you gave me as a present what you did not take away from me; you did not deprive me of my life, which I therefore retain as a gift from your-self. After hearing all your insults I nearly forgot my gratitude, though not quite. And there was something particularly impudent about your abuse, because you knew how I would be able to retaliate!

Arrival at Brundisium for you meant envelopment in the embraces of your little actress. Well, is that a lie? It is distressing, is it not, to be unable to deny something that is disreputable to admit. But if the townsmen caused you to feel no shame, did not your own veteran army? For every single soldier who was at Brundisium saw her. Every one of them knew she had come all those days’ journey to congratulate you: every man grieved to have found out so late in the day the worthlessness of the leader he had followed.

Again you toured Italy, with this actress by your side. In the communities through which you passed, amid scenes of brutality and misery, you planted your soldiers as settlers. At Rome you cut a deplorable figure as a robber of gold and silver – and of wine. As a climax, unknown to Caesar （who was at Alexandria）, Caesar's friends were kind enough to make Antony his Master of Horse. At that juncture he felt entitled to live with Hippias; and to hand over race-horses, intended for the national games, to another actor Sergius. At that time Antony had chosen to live, not in the house which he so discreditably retains now, but in Marcus Pupius Piso's home. His decrees, his looting, his legacies inherited and grabbed I will pass over in silence. Need compelled him: he did not know which way to turn. Those substantial inheritances from Lucius Rubrius Casinas and Lucius Turselius had not yet come to him; not yet had he become the unexpected ‘heir’ to Pompey, and many more. He had nothing except what he could plunder; he was obliged to live like a bandit.

But about these examples of the tougher sorts of rascality, I shall speak no more. Let us turn instead to meaner kinds of misbehaviour. With those jaws of yours, and those lungs, and that gladiatorial strength, you drank so much wine at Hippias's wedding, Antony, that on the next day you had to be sick in full view of the people of Rome. It was a disgusting sight; even to hear what happened is disgusting. If you had behaved like that at a private dinner party, among those outsize drinking cups of yours, everyone would have regarded it as disgraceful enough. But here, in the Assembly of the Roman People, was a man holding public office, a Master of the Horse – from whom even a belch would have been unseemly – flooding his own lap and the whole platform with the gobbets of wine-reeking food he had vomited up. He admits that this was one of his filthier actions: let us now return to his grander misdeeds.

Well, Caesar returned from Alexandria, a fortunate man – as he seemed to himself at least: though in my view no one who brings misfortune upon his country can be called fortunate. The spear was set up before the temple of Jupiter Stator; and Pompey's property – the very thought brings unhappiness! for even when the tears no longer flow the sorrow remains deeply fixed in my heart – Pompey's property, I say, was subjected to the pitiless voice of the auctioneer.

On that single occasion the nation forgot its slavery, and mourned. Men felt slaves, because fear gripped them all, yet, even so, the people of Rome lamented freely enough. Every man waited to see if there would be some depraved madman, repulsive to heaven and humanity, who would dare to take part in that criminal auction. Though some of the men round that spear would have stopped at nothing else, no one had audacity enough for this – no one except Antony alone! One person, only one, was shameless enough to perpetrate the act which all others, however great their effrontery, had shunned in horror. But, Antony, were you too totally witless – or is not insanity the appropriate word? – to realize this: that in your station of life to become a purchaser of confiscated property, and of Pompey's property at that, would earn you the curses and loathing of the Roman people, the detestation of all gods and all human beings, now and for evermore? And then, think of the arrogance with which this debauchee took instant possession of the estate! The estate of a man who through his valour had made Rome more greatly feared, and by his justice had made her more greatly loved, by all the other nations upon earth.

So, abruptly seizing that great man's property, Antony wallowed in its midst. In his mighty satisfaction he gloated, like the character in a play who was poor and has suddenly become rich. But as some poet wrote, ‘ill-gotten gains will soon be squandered’. And the unbelievable – almost miraculous – fact is that he squandered Pompey's substantial fortune, not in a few months, but in a few days! In that house there were large quantities of wine, heavy pieces of the finest silver-ware, costly robes, ample and elegant furniture – all the splendid and abundant property of a man who, though not luxurious, had none the less been nobly endowed with possessions. Of these, within a few days, nothing was left! Charybdis, if she ever existed, was but a single animal. I swear that such a number of objects so widely scattered in so great a variety of places could hardly have been swallowed up, at such a speed, by the Ocean itself.

Nothing was locked up, nothing sealed, nothing listed. Whole store-rooms were disposed of as gifts, to unmitigated scoundrels. Actors and actresses grabbed everything they wanted. The place was packed with gamblers, crammed with inebriates. For days on end, in many parts of the house, the orgies of drinking went on and on. Gaming losses piled up; Antony's good luck did not always hold. On view were the richly worked counterpanes which had belonged to Pompey – now they were in the garrets of slaves, and on their beds!

So let it not surprise you that these riches were consumed with such speed. A profligacy so boundless as Antony's could have rapidly devoured not just a single man's patrimony, even one so abundant as Pompey's, but whole cities and whole kingdoms. And then the mansion and the parks that he took over! Your impudence, Antony, was preposterous. How could you have the effrontery to enter that house, to pass its most sacred threshold, to let the household gods of such an abode see you flaunting your degraded features? This was a home which no one, for many days and months, could gaze upon or pass by without weeping. As you linger on within its rooms, are you not overcome with shame?

You are brainless, I know: yet surely, even so, none of the things that are there can bring you enjoyment. When you look at those beaks of ships(9) in the hall, you cannot possibly imagine that the house you are entering is your own! That would be out of the question. For all your lack of sense and sensibility, still you are aware of what you yourself are, you know your own people and possessions. So I do not believe that, waking or sleeping, you can ever feel easy in your mind. Drink-sodden and demented though you are, the appearance in your dreams of that great man must surely rouse you in terror; and when you are awake, too, his recurring image must unhinge your mind still further.

I pity the very walls and roof of that house. For never before had the place witnessed anything but strict propriety – fine, high-minded tradition and virtue. As you know very well, Senators, Pompey was as praise-worthy in his domestic as in his international dealings; as admirable in his home life as in public affairs he was renowned. Yet nowadays, in his home, every dining-room is a taproom, every bedroom a brothel. Antony may deny this nowadays. Be tactful; do not investigate! For he has become economical. He has told that actress of his to gather up her own property and hand back his keys, as the Twelve Tables ordain – and he has driven her out. What a reputable citizen! What solid respectability! Here is the most honourable action of his whole life; he has divorced his actress.

How he harps on the phrase: ‘I, the consul Antony.’ That amounts to saying, ‘I, the consul, debauchee’, or ‘I, the consul, criminal’. For that is the significance of ‘Antony’. If there were any dignity in the name, I presume that your grandfather, too, would sometimes have called himself ‘the consul, Antony’. But he never did. So would your uncle, who was my colleague. Or has there been no Antony but yourself?

However, I pass over these offences, for they had no direct connexion with the part you played in ruining our country. I return to the latter – to the Civil War, which owed its birth, its rise, and its performance to yourself. True, your role in the war was insignificant. That was because you were frightened, or rather preoccupied with your sexual interests. But you had tasted Roman blood; indeed you had drunk deeply of it. At Pharsalus you were in the front rank. It was you who killed that fine nobleman, Lucius Domitius Ahenobarbus – as well as many others, fugitives from the battle-field. Caesar would perhaps have spared them, as he spared others. But you, on the other hand, hunted them down for your slaughter.

However, after these grand and glorious achievements, the war was still by no means ended. So why did you not follow Caesar to Africa? And then, when Caesar had returned from Africa, let us note the position and rank which he assigned to you. As general he had made you quaestor, when he was dictator you had become his Master of the Horse. You had begun the war. Every atrocity had been instigated by yourself; in each successive robbery you had been his associate. We have it on your own authority that his will adopted you as his son.(10) Yet what did he now do? He took action against you – the sums you owed for the house, and for its parks and the other property you acquired in the auction, were all demanded back from you by Caesar.

Your initial reply was vigorous enough: and, I admit – for I do not want to seem prejudiced against you – reasonably fair and just. ‘So Caesar claims money from me? Could I not just as reasonably claim money from him – or did he win the war without my help? No: nor could he have. It was I who provided him with the pretext for the Civil War, I who proposed those subversive laws, who forcibly resisted not merely the Roman people's consuls and generals, but the entire Senate and Roman people and the gods and altars and homes of our fathers – indeed Rome itself. Caesar did not conquer for himself alone; why should those who shared the work not share the plunder too?’ Reasonable enough. But reason was beside the point, for Caesar was the stronger. So he silenced you, and you and your guarantors received a visit from his soldiers.

And then, suddenly, out came that spectacular list of yours. Everyone laughed at the size of the list – at the varied and extensive catalogue of possessions, none of which （except a part of the Misenum property） the seller could call his own. But the auction itself was a melancholy sight. Few of Pompey's robes were now to be seen, and even they were covered with stains; a certain amount of his silver plate appeared in battered condition; and there were some Seedy-looking slaves. So the remains were meagre enough. If nothing at all had survived, our grief would have been less.

However, the heirs of Lucius Rubrius Casinas prevented the auction, and they were backed by a decree from Caesar. Antony, the wild spender, was embarrassed – he had nowhere to turn. And that was the precise moment of the arrest in Caesar's house （so the report went） of an assassin, dagger in hand – sent by you, Antony: and Caesar charged you openly with this in the Senate. Next, however, after allowing you a few days for payment – since you were so poor – he departed for Spain. Even then you did not follow him. So early a retirement, for so good a gladiator? A man who showed such timidity in standing up for his party （and that means standing up for himself） need surely inspire no fear in others!

In the end, some time afterwards, Antony did leave for Spain. But he proved unable to reach that country safely, he maintains. Then how did Publius Cornelius Dolabella get there? Either you ought not to have backed the cause you did, Antony, or, having done so, you ought to have stood up for your side to the end. Three times Caesar fought against his fellow-citizens: in Thessaly, in Africa, and in Spain. Dolabella took part in all these campaigns; in the Spanish war he was wounded. If you want to know my view, I wish he had not been there. Yet however blameworthy his initial decision, at least he deserves praise for consistent adherence thereafter. But what about yourself? That was the time when Pompey's sons were fighting to make their way home – a matter, surely, which concerned all Caesar's partisans. In other words, Pompey's sons were struggling to recover the shrines of their household gods, their sacred hearth and home, and the guardian spirits of their family – all of which you had seized. When, in order to recover what was theirs by law, they were obliged to use force, who would most justly （though indeed among such grievous wrongs to speak of justice is impossible） – who, I say, would be their principal target? The answer is, yourself, the taker of their property. So it was your battle, was it not, that Dolabella had to fight in Spain: while you stayed at Narbo, vomiting over your hosts’ tables.

And your return from Narbo! Antony actually wanted to know why I returned from my journey so suddenly. Now I have recently explained to the Senate the reasons for my return. I wanted, if I could, to be of service to the state even before the New Year. You ask how I returned. First, I arrived by daylight, not after dark. Secondly, I came in my boots and toga, not in Gallic sandals and a cloak. I see your eyes fixed upon me: in anger, it appears. But you ought, instead, to harbour friendly feelings if only you knew how ashamed I am – unlike yourself – of the depths to which you have fallen. Of all the offences that I have seen or heard of as committed by any single person this is the most deplorable. You, who claimed to have been Master of the Horse, who were standing for one of next year's consulships – or rather begging for one of them as a personal favour – off you went, in your Gallic sandals and mantle, speeding through the towns of Cisalpine Gaul: the towns in which, when we were candidates for consulships, we used to seek votes – in the days when these appointments went by votes and not by personal favour.

Note the frivolity of the man. When, at about three o'clock, he approached Rome and came to Red Rocks, he dived into a wretched little wine-shop, and, hiding there, drank and drank until evening. Then a two-wheeler took him rapidly into the city and he arrived at his house with his head veiled. ‘Who are you?’ said the porter. ‘A messenger from Antony,’ he replied. He was immediately taken to the lady for whose sake he had come, and he handed her a letter. As she read the contents, she wept; for it was amorously written – and the gist was that he had given up the actress and transferred all his love to this other lady. And as her weeping increased, this soft-hearted fellow could bear the sight no longer, but uncovered his head and threw his arms round her neck. Depraved character! No other epithet is adequate for this creature who plunged the city into terror by night, plunged Italy into a series of nerve-racking days, merely in order to make his sudden appearance before this woman. What a surprise this must have been to her: to see such behaviour from a male prostitute.

At home, then, you could lay claim to a love affair. But elsewhere there was an even nastier affair for you: to prevent Lucius Munatius Plancus from selling up your sureties. A tribune brought you before a public meeting, and you replied: ‘I have come here on a matter concerning my private property.’ This was regarded by everyone as an excellent joke.(11)

However, that is enough about trivialities; let us turn to more significant matters. When Caesar came back from Spain, you travelled a long way to meet him. You went quickly, and you returned quickly: Caesar could therefore note that, if not brave, you were at least energetic. Somehow or other you got on friendly terms with him again. Caesar was like that. He was extremely ready to offer his intimate friendship to anyone whom he knew to be corrupt and unbalanced, penniless, and hopelessly in debt. In these respects your credentials were excellent. So he gave orders that you should be made consul – with himself, moreover, as your colleague. One can only feel sympathy with Publius Cornelius Dolabella, who had been urged to stand, brought forward, and then fobbed off. Everyone knows how deceitfully both of you treated Dolabella in this matter. Caesar induced him to be a candidate for the consulship, and then, after promising and virtually granting him election, blocked the proceedings and transferred the post to himself. And you supported this treachery.

The first of January arrived. We were made to attend the Senate. Dolabella attacked Antony – with much greater fullness and preparation than I do now. And heavens, the things that Antony himself said in his rage! Caesar indicated his intention, before his forthcoming departure for the east, of ordering that Dolabella should become consul in his own place. And yet they deny that the man who was always acting and speaking like that was a totalitarian monarch! Well, after Caesar had said that, this splendid augur Antony announced that his priesthood empowered him to employ the auspices in order to obstruct or invalidate the proceedings of the Assembly. And he declared that this is what he would do. But first note the man's unbelievable stupidity. For your priestly office of augur, Antony, was what you relied upon for entitlement to perform those actions. Yet, as consul alone, without the added possession of your augurship, your entitlement would still have been just as good. Indeed, was your consulship not actually a better qualification? For we augurs are only empowered to report omens, whereas the consuls and other state officials have the right actually to watch the heavens.

Very well, you bungled the matter through inexperience. We cannot expect good judgement from someone who is never sober. But just observe the man's impudence. Many months earlier he had declared in the Senate that he would either use the auspices to prevent the Assembly from meeting to elect Dolabella, or alternatively would act as he finally did. Now, who on earth can divine what flaws there are going to be in the auspices, except the man who has already formally set about watching the heavens? Which cannot legally be done during an election – and if anyone has been watching the heavens previously, he is obliged to make his report not after but before the election has begun. But Antony is as ignorant as he is shameless: the insolence his actions display is as unbounded as his ignorance of what an augur ought to do. And yet cast your minds back to his consulship, from that day onwards until the fifteenth of March. No servant was ever so humble and abject. He could do nothing himself; everything had to be begged for. You could see him poking his head into the back of his litter asking his colleague(12) for the favours Antony wanted to market.

So the day of Dolabella's election arrived. The right of the first vote is settled by lot; Antony said nothing. The result of this ballot was announced. He remained silent. The first class was called to vote, its vote announced; then the six centuries which voted next, then the second class – all this in a shorter time than it takes to tell the story. Then, when the proceedings were over, came our brilliant augur's announcement – you would say he was Gaius Laelius himself: ‘the meeting is adjourned until another day’. What monstrous impudence! You had neither seen, nor understood, nor heard, any omen whatever. You did not even claim to have watched the heavens; you do not today. So the flaw in question was the one which you had foreseen and foretold as long ago as the first of January! In other words, you undoubtedly falsified the auspices. You employed religion to constrain an Assembly of the Roman People. You announced unfavourable omens, augur to augur, consul to consul: and you did so fraudulently. May the calamitous consequences fall not upon Rome, but upon your own head.

That is all I shall say, in case I should seem to be invalidating the actions of Dolabella – which must, at some time, be referred to our Board of Augurs. But mark the man's audacious arrogance. As long as it is your pleasure, Antony, the election of Dolabella as consul was irregular. Then you change your mind: the procedure in regard to the auspices had nothing wrong with it after all! If an augur's report in the terms you employed has no meaning, then admit that when you demanded an adjournment you were drunk. If, on the other hand, the words have any meaning at all, then I request you, as my fellow-augur, to tell me what their meaning is.

But I must make sure that this survey of Antony's numerous exploits does not by accident omit one outstandingly brilliant action. So let us turn to the festival of the Lupercalia. Look, Senators! He cannot hide his anxiety. Do you see how upset he looks – pale, and sweating? Never mind, so long as he is not sick, as he was in the Minucian Colonnade. How does he defend his scandalous behaviour at the Lupercalia? I should like to hear – and thereby learn the results of that generous fee and those lands at Leontini, which he gave his teacher of oratory.

Upon the dais on a golden chair, wearing a purple robe and a wreath, was seated your colleague. You mounted the dais. You went up to Caesar's chair – Lupercus though you were, you should have remembered you were consul too – and you displayed a diadem. From all over the Forum there were groans. Where did the diadem come from? You had not just found one on the ground and picked it up. No, you had brought it from your own house! This was crime, deliberate and premeditated. Then you placed the diadem on his head: the people groaned. He took it off – and they applauded.

So, criminal, you were ready, alone among all that gathering, to propose that there should be a king and autocrat at Rome; to transform your fellow-consul into your lord and master; and to inflict upon the Roman people this ultimate test of its capacity to suffer and endure. You even tried to move him to pity – when you hurled yourself at his feet as a suppliant. What were you begging for? To become his slave? For your-self alone that would be a fitting plea, seeing that from boyhood onwards there was nothing which you had not allowed to be done to you. For your own person, adjustment to slavery was easy. But from ourselves, and from the people of Rome, you had no such mandate.

What glorious eloquence that was – when you made that speech with no clothes on! Offensive misbehaviour could go no further. Nothing could have been more thoroughly deserying of the severest possible punishment. Are you a slave, cowering in expectation of the lash? If you have any feelings at all, you must be feeling the lash now: and my account of these events must surely be drawing blood. Far be it from me to detract from the glory of our noble liberators. Yet such is my grief that I must speak out. Seeing that the man who rejected the diadem was killed, and was, by general consent, killed justly, it is appalling that the man who made him the offer should still be alive. In the public records, what is more, under the heading of the Lupercalia, he even caused the following entry to be made: ‘At the bidding of the people, Antony, consul, offered Caesar, perpetual dictator, the kingship: Caesar refused.’

So I feel no surprise when you disturb the peace, when you shun Rome and the very daylight itself, when you drink with thieving riffraft from early in one day until dawn of the next. For you, no refuge can be safe. Where could you possibly find a place in any community owning laws and lawcourts – since these are precisely what you have done your utmost to abolish and to replace by tyranny? Was this why Tarquin was expelled, why Spurius Cassius Vecellinus and Spurius Maelius and Marcus Manlius Capitolinus were slain: to allow Antony, centuries after they were dead, to commit the forbidden evil of setting up a king at Rome?

Let us return to the auspices, the subject on which Caesar intended to address the Senate on the fifteenth of March. Antony, I must ask you this: what would you then have said? You came here today （or so I heard） primed to rebut my assertion that the auspices – which unless declared invalid require scrupulous obedience – were employed by you in a fraudulent manner. However, that day's business was eliminated – by our national destiny. Did Caesar's death also eliminate your opinion concerning the auspices?

But now I have come to that time which I must discuss before the subject upon which I had embarked. On that glorious day, you fled panic-stricken – your criminal conscience certain of impending death. You slunk surreptitiously home. Men interested in your survival looked after you; for they hoped you would behave sanely. My prophecies of the future have always fallen upon deaf ears. Yet how completely right they have proved! On the Capitol, when our noble liberators desired me to go to you and urge you to uphold the Republican government, I told them this: that as long as you were still frightened you would promise anything, but as soon as your fears ceased you would be yourself again. When, therefore, the other former consuls were continually in and out of your house, I held to my opinion. And I did not see you on that day or the next. For I believed that good Romans could come to no understanding, could have no association, with a totally unprincipled enemy.

After two days had passed, I came to the Temple of Tellus – reluctantly enough even then, since armed men locked all its approaches. What a day that was for you, Antony! Even though you have abruptly turned against me, yet I am sorry for you – because you have subsequently done so little justice to your own good fame. If only you had been able to maintain the attitude you showed on that day, heaven knows, you would have been a hero! And the peace, which was pledged on that occasion by the cession of an aristocratic hostage – the young grandson of Marcus Fulvius Bambalio – would be ours.

Fear made you a good citizen. However, as an instructor of good behaviour, fear lacks permanency; and your unscrupulousness – which never leaves you unless you are afraid – soon perverted you into evil ways again. And indeed even at that time, when people （other than myself） had an excellent opinion of you, your manner of presiding over the tyrant's funeral – if funeral that ceremony can be called – was outrageous. For you were the man who pronounced that grandiose eulogy, that lachrymose appeal to morality. You lit the torches which charred the very body of Caesar, which burnt down the house of Lucius Bellienus. You, Antony, unleashed against our homes those ruffians, slaves most of them, whose ferocity we had to repel with our own hands.

And yet you seemed to have wiped off the soot. For upon the Capitol, in the days that followed, the resolutions that you proposed before the Senate were excel-lent. I mean those declaring that, from the fifteenth of March onwards, there should be no publication of any announcement conferring exemptions from taxes, or similar favours. As regards these exemptions, and the men in exile, you yourself remember what you said. But the finest thing of all was that you abolished from the constitution, for ever, the title of dictator. On account of men's recent fears of dictators you decided to abolish, once and for all, the whole institution: so tremendous was the hatred of this tyranny which had apparently taken hold of you.

So to other men the government seemed securely established – though to me things looked differently, for with you at the helm I expected all manner of shipwreck. Was I wrong? Could a man, for very long, remain unlike himself? Members of the Senate, what happened next you saw for yourselves. Announcements were posted up all over the Capitol: tax exemptions were put on sale, not merely to individuals but to whole peoples. Citizenship was granted not to single persons only but to entire provinces. If these decisions are going to stand, it means the downfall of our state. Senators, you have lost complete provinces. In his own domestic market, this man has slashed the revenues of Rome. He has slashed the Roman empire itself.

Those seven hundred million sesterces, recorded in the account-books of the Temple of Ops – where are they now? The origins of that treasure store were tragic enough. Nevertheless, if the money was not going to be returned to its rightful owners, it could be used to save us from property-tax. But how do you account for the fact, Antony, that whereas on the fifteenth of March you owed four million sesterces, you had ceased to owe this sum by the first of April?

Your people sold countless concessions: and you were well aware of them. Nevertheless, the decrees posted up on the Capitol did include one excellent measure. This concerned a very good friend of Rome, King Deiotarus. Yet all who saw the document could not help laughing, in spite of their grief. For no man has ever hated another so much as Caesar hated Deiotarus. He felt quite as much hatred for Deiotarus as he felt for this Senate, and the Roman knights, and the citizens of Massilia, and every other person in whom he discerned a love for the Roman nation and its people. In his lifetime Caesar never treated Deiotarus fairly or kindly, either to his face or in his absence. Yet we are invited to believe that, when Caesar was dead, Deiotarus gained his favours! When they were together, and Deiotarus was his host, Caesar had summoned him, demanded an account of his resources, planted a Greek agent in his principality, and deprived him of Armenia, which the Roman Senate had added to his kingdom. And now we are asked to believe that what the living Caesar had confiscated, the dead Caesar gave back.

And the way in which he is stated to have expressed himself! At one point, apparently, he described this restoration as ‘fair’; at another as ‘not unfair’. A peculiar way of putting the matter! I was not with Deiotarus, but I always supported him; whereas Caesar never once said that anything we asked for on his behalf seemed to him fair.

A bond for ten million sesterces was negotiated at Antony's house in the women's suite – where a lot of selling went on, and goes on still. The negotiators were the envoys of Deiotarus. They were good men, but timid and inexperienced. I and the king's other friends were not asked for our views. About this bond, I suggest that you should consider carefully what you are to do. For, when he heard of Caesar's death, the king himself – with no thought for any memorandum Caesar might have left – recovered what belonged to him of his own accord, by the strength of his own hand. Deiotarus was wise. He knew that this had always been the law: that when tyrants who had stolen things were killed, the men whose property they had stolen take them back. So no jurist, not even the man whose only client is yourself and who is now representing you, will say that there is a debt on that bond for what Deiotarus had recovered before the bond was executed. For he did not buy these possessions from you: before you could sell him his own property, he took it himself. He was a man! How contemptible, on the other hand, are we, who uphold the actions of someone whose memory we hate.

Of the countless memoranda, the innumerable alleged examples of Caesar's handwriting which have been brought forward, I shall say nothing. We can view their forgers, selling their efforts as openly as though these were programmes of gladiatorial shows. Today, as a result, the house where Antony lives is piled high with such enormous heaps of money that they have to be weighed out instead of counted. But this greed has its blind spots. For example one of the recently displayed notices exempts from taxation the wealthiest communities of Crete. This notice decrees that Crete shall cease to be a province ‘when the governorship of Marcus Junius Brutus comes to an end’. But where is your sanity, Antony? Are you fit to be at large? How could there possibly be a decree by Caesar exempting Crete ‘when the tenure of Brutus comes to an end’, seeing that in Caesar's lifetime Brutus had not yet even formed this connexion with Crete at all? However, do not suppose, Senators, that this consideration prevented the decree from being put on sale – indeed it has resulted in your losing your Cretan province! There was never a thing, provided a buyer was available, that Antony was not ready to sell.

And this law, Antony, which you posted up about recalling exiles – I suppose Caesar composed that too? Far be it from me to persecute anyone who is in trouble. My only complaints are these. First, that the men recalled from exile because Caesar had singled them out as especially deserving have been discredited by this new batch. Secondly, I cannot see why you do not treat everyone alike. Not more than three or four are now left unrecalled, and I do not understand why men whose plight is the same do not qualify for the same degree of your indulgence: I refer to your uncle and those whom you have treated like him. When you legislated about the others, you refused to include him. Yet at the same time you encouraged him to stand for election as censor! Indeed, you even encouraged his election campaign – thus arousing universal ridicule and protest. But, having done so, why did you refrain from holding his election? Was it because a tribune had announced an ill-omened flash of lightning? When you personally are involved, the auspices are immaterial. Your scruples are reserved for when your friends are concerned. And then, while your uncle was standing for membership of the Board of Seven, you deserted him again. Do not tell us that this was because of objections by some formidable member to whom you could not say no, for fear of your life! If you had any family loyalty, you ought to have respected Gaius Antonius like a father. Instead, you loaded him with insults.

What is more, you threw his daughter out of the house – Antonia your cousin. You had looked around and made an alternative arrangement. And not content with that, though no woman could have been more blameless, you even charged her with adultery! You could hardly have sunk further. Yet you were still not satisfied. On January the first, at a full meeting of the Senate at which your uncle was present, you had the audacity to declare that this was why you regarded Publius Cornelius Dolabella as an enemy: because you had learnt of his adultery with your wife and cousin. It would be difficult to say which was the most outrageous – your audacity in making such allegations before the Senate; your unscrupulousness in directing them against Dolabella; your indecency in speaking in such terms before her father; or your brutality in employing against that poor woman such filthy, godforsaken language.

But let us return to the documents supposed to be in Caesar's handwriting. How did you verify them, Antony? To preserve the peace, the Senate had confirmed Caesar's acts – the acts which were truly his, not those which Antony alleged were his. Now, where do all these memoranda spring from? On whose authority are they produced? If they are forgeries, why are they approved? If genuine, why does money have to be paid for them? The decision had been taken that, from the first of June onwards, you should examine Caesar's acts, with the assistance of an advisory board. What was this board, and which of its members did you ever convene? And as for your awaiting the first of June, no doubt that was the day when you returned from your tour of the exsoldiers’ settlements: for you brought an armed guard to surround you.

That trip of yours in April and May, when you have even tried to found a settlement at Capua, what a splendid affair it was! We all know how you escaped from that town – or rather very nearly did not escape. And you are still uttering threats against Capua. I wish you would try to put them into practice: then that ‘very nearly’ could be struck out. Your progress was truly magnificent. Of your elaborate banquets and frantic drinking I say nothing; all that only damaged yourself. But we were damaged too. Even when, at an earlier date, the Campanian territory had been exempted from taxation, we regarded this as a grave blow to our national interests – although, on that occasion, soldiers were its recipients. But when you distributed land there, the beneficiaries were your fellow-diners and fellow-gamblers. Members of the Senate, these latest settlers in Campania were nothing but actors and actresses. Equally objectionable was the settlement at Leontini; seeing that at one time the crops in that area, like those of Campania, were renowned for their fertile and abundant contribution to the Roman domains of which they formed an integral part. You gave your doctor 1,875 acres. Whatever vast sum, one may ask, would you have given him if he had cured your mind? Your oratorical trainer received 1,250: what on earth would the total have been if he had succeeded in making a speaker of you?

But let us return to your journey, and to its effects on Italy. You founded a settlement of ex-soldiers at Casilinum, where Caesar had founded one before. About Capua, you had written asking for my advice; but I should have sent the same reply about Casilinum. You inquired whether it was legal to plant a new settlement where there was one already. I replied that the establishment of a new settlement, where there existed an earlier one duly founded in accordance with the auspices, was not legitimate – though I also pointed out that new settlers could be added to the old foundation. In spite of this, you had the arrogance to upset all the provisions of the auspices and plant a settlement at Casilinum, even though another settlement had been established there only a few years previously. You raised your standard; you marked out the boundaries with a plough. Indeed, your ploughshare nearly grazed the very gate of Capua, and the territory of that most flourishing settlement suffered grievous encroachment at your hands.

Fresh from this violation of religious observance, you rushed elsewhere: for you had designs on the property of the devout and high-principled Marcus Terentius Varro at Casinum. But what was the legal or moral sanction for this project? The same, you will say, as had enabled you to displace from their estates the heirs of Lucius Rubrius Casinas and Lucius Turselius – and countless others too. Now, if you had occupied these properties as a result of an auction, we may allow auctions their proper rights. We may concede rights also to written instructions, provided that they were Caesar's and not yours – and provided that they recorded you as a debtor, instead of releasing you from your debts!

As for Varro's farm at Casinum, who claims that this was ever sold at all? Did anyone ever see the auctioneer's spear or hear his voice? You sent someone to Alexandria, you say, to buy the place from Caesar. It was too much to expect that you should await his return! But no one ever heard that any part of Varro's property had been confiscated; and yet there was no man whose welfare was of more general concern. Now, if the truth is that Caesar wrote ordering you to hand the estate back, no words are fit to describe the outrage that you perpetrated. Just call off, for a spell, those armed men whom we see all round us. Do that, and you will very soon learn this lesson: whatever the justification for Caesar's auctions, your own deplorable conduct is on quite another level – for, once the armed men are gone, you will find yourself thrown outside Varro's gates. And it will not be the owner alone who expels you. Not one of his friends, his neighbours, his visitors, or his agents will fail to take a hand.

Day after day, at Varro's mansion, you continued your disgusting orgies. From seven in the morning onwards, there was incessant drinking, gambling, and vomiting. What a tragic fate for that house; and ‘what an ill-matched master’!

Though how could Antony be described as its master? Let us call him occupant. Well then, he was an occupant who matched it ill. For Marcus Varro had chosen this place not for indulgence, but for retirement and study. Those walls had witnessed noble discussions, noble thoughts, noble writings; laws for the Roman people, the history of our ancestors, the principles of all wisdom and all learning. When you, on the other hand, became the lodger – for house-holder I will not call you – the house rang with the din of drunkards, the pavements swam with wine, the walls dripped with it. On view were young free-born Roman youths consorting with paid boys; Roman matrons with prostitutes.

From Casinum, from Aquinum, from Interamna, came men to greet Antony. But no one was allowed in. And that was entirely proper, for in his degradation the emblems of office were a complete anomaly. When he left for Rome and approached Aquinum, quite a large crowd came to meet him, since the town has a considerable population. But he was carried through the streets in a covered litter, like a dead man. The people of Aquinum had no doubt been foolish to come; yet they did live beside the road on which he was passing by. What about the men of Anagnia? They, on the other hand, lived away from his path. But they too came down to greet him, on the supposition that he was consul. The incredible fact is – though I as a neighbour can vouch that everyone noticed it at the time – he did not return a single greeting. This was especially remarkable since he had with him two men of Anagnia, Mustela to look after his swords and Laco in charge of his drinking cups.

There is no need to recall to you the threats and insults with which he assailed the population of Teanum Sidicinum and harassed the inhabitants of Puteoli. This was because they had adopted Cassius and the Brutuses as their patrons. Their choice had been dictated by enthusiastic approval, sound judgement, friendly feelings, and personal, affection – not by force and violence, which compelled others to choose you and Minucius Basilus, and others like you, whom no one could voluntartly choose as their patrons. Even as dependants you would be undesirable.

Meantime, while you were away, your colleague(13) had a great day when he overturned, in the Forum, the funeral monument which you had persistently treated with reverence. When you were told of this, you fainted: everyone who was with you agrees that this is so. What happened afterwards I do not know. I suppose terror and armed violence had the final word. For you pulled your colleague down from heaven; you made him quite unlike himself – to say you made him your own replica would be going too far.

And that return of yours to Rome! The whole city was in an uproar. Lucius Cornelius Cinna's excess of power, Sulla's domination we remembered; Caesar's autocratic monarchy was fresh in our memories. In those days there had been swords perhaps, but they had stayed in their sheaths, and there were not many of them. Your procession, on the other hand, was totally barbaric. Your followers were in battle order, with drawn swords, and whole litter-loads of shields. And yet, Senators, familiarity with such spectacles has inured us to the shock.

The decision had been taken that the Senate should meet on the first of June, and we did our best to attend. But we encountered intimidation and were abruptly forced to retire. Antony, however, feeling no need of a Senate, missed none of us; on the contrary, our departure pleased him. Without delay he embarked on his extraordinary exploits. He, who had defended Caesar's memoranda for his own personal profit, suppressed Caesar's laws – good laws, too – in order to upset the constitution. He lengthened the tenures of provincial governorships. Instead of protecting Caesar's acts, as he should have, he annulled them: those relating to national and private affairs alike. Now in the national sphere nothing has greater weight than a law; while in private affairs the most valid of all things is a will. Antony abolished both – laws, with or without notice; wills, although even the humblest citizens have always respected them. The statues, the pictures, which Caesar, along with his gardens, had bequeathed to the people of Rome as his heirs – now they all went to Pompey's gardens, or Scipio's mansion: removed by Antony.

And yet, Antony, you are so attentive to Caesar's memory; you love the dead man, do you not? Now, the greatest honours he ever received were the sacred couch, the image, the gable, the priest for his worship. Because of these honours, on the analogy of the priesthoods of Jupiter, Mars, and Quirinus, Antony is the priest of the divine Julius. Yet you delay, Antony, to assume these duties: you have not been inducted. Why? Choose a day, choose someone to induct you. We are colleagues; no one will refuse. Loathsome man! – equally loathsome as priest of a tyrant, or priest of a dead human being!

And now I have to ask you a question: Do you not know what day this is? Yesterday, in case it escaped your notice, was the fourth day of the Roman Games in the Circus. Now you yourself moved in the Assembly a proposal that a fifth day also should be added to these Games in Caesar's honour. Why, then, are we not in our official robes? Why do we allow the honour which your law conferred on Caesar to be neglected? You were prepared to concede, apparently, that this holy day should be polluted by the addition of a thanks-giving, but not by a sacred couch ceremony. But you should either disregard religious observances altogether, or maintain them invariably.

You ask whether I like this couch, gable, priest of the divinity. I like none of them. But you, who defend the acts of Caesar, cannot possibly justify the maintenance of some of them and the neglect of others. Unless, that is, you are prepared to admit that your own profit, rather than Caesar's honour, is your guide. Come, answer these arguments! I look forward to your eloquence. I knew your grandfather; he was a very fine orator. And you certainly speak with even greater freedom than he did. For he never made a public speech naked! – whereas you, straightforward fellow that you are, have let us all have a look at your torso. Are you going to let me have a reply? Are you even going to venture to open your mouth? Indeed, I wonder whether in the whole of my long speech you will find anything at all which you can pluck up the courage to answer.

But let us leave the past. Your behaviour today, at the present day and moment at which I am speaking – defend that if you can! Explain why the Senate is surrounded by a ring of men with arms; why my listeners include gangsters of yours, sword in hand; why the doors of the temple of Concord are closed; why you bring into the Forum the world's most savage people, Ituraeans, with their bows and arrows. I do these things in self-defence, says Antony. But surely a thousand deaths are better than the inability to live in one's own community without an armed guard. A guard is no protection, I can tell you! The protection you need is not weapons, but the affection and good-will of your fellow-citizens. The people of Rome will seize your weapons and wrench them from you. I pray that we shall not perish before that is done! But however you behave towards ourselves, believe me, these are methods which cannot preserve you for long. Your wife – she is no miser, and this reference implies no disrespect – is already taking too long to pay the Roman people her third instalment.(14)

Our country does not lack men to place in charge of its affairs. Wherever they are, they are our national defence, indeed our very nation. Rome has avenged itself: but it has not yet recovered. However, that there are young noblemen ready to leap to its defence is beyond doubt. They may choose to retire for a spell, seeking quiet, but Rome will call them back.

The name of peace is beautiful – and peace itself is a blessing. Yet peace and slavery are very different things. Peace is freedom tranquilly enjoyed, slavery is the worst of all evils, to be repelled, if need be, at the cost of war and even of death. Even if those liberators of ours have withdrawn from our sight, they have left behind them the example of their deeds. They achieved what no one had ever achieved before. Lucius Junius Brutus made war against Tarquin, who was king at a time when kingship was lawful at Rome. Spurius Cassius Vecellinus, Spurius Maelius, and Marcus Manlius Capitolinus were killed because of the suspicion that they aimed at autocratic monarchy. But here, for the first time, are men raising their swords to kill one who was not merely aiming at monarchy, but actually reigning as monarch. Their action was super-humanly noble in itself, and it is set before us for our imitation: all the more conspicuously, because heaven itself is scarcely immense enough to hold the glory which this deed has made theirs. The consciousness of a noble achievement was reward enough; yet no one, I believe, should spurn that further reward which they have also won – immortality.

The day you ought to remember, Antony, is that day on which you abolished the dictatorship for ever. Let your memory dwell on the rejoicing of the Senate and people of Rome on that occasion. Contrast it with the haggling with which you and your friends busy your-selves now. Then you will realize that gain is a different thing from glory. Just as there are diseases, or dull-nesses of the senses, which prevent certain people from being able to taste food: so, by the same token, debauchees, misers, and criminals are unattracted by glory.

However, if the hope of being praised cannot entice you to behave decently, is fear equally incapable of scaring you out of your repulsive behaviour? I know the lawcourts cause you no alarm. If that is due to innocence, you are to be commended. But if the reason is your reliance upon force, do you not understand this: that the man whose imperviousness to judicial processes is due to such a cause has pressing reason to feel terrors of quite another kind? For if you are not afraid of brave men and good Romans – seeing that armed satellites keep them away from your person – believe me, your own supporters will not stand you for very much longer. To be afraid of danger from one's own people night and day is no sort of a life; and you can hardly have men who owe you more, in terms of benefactions, than some of Caesar's killers owed to him.

However, you and he are not in any way comparable! His character was an amalgamation of genius, method, memory, culture, thoroughness, intellect, and industry. His achievements in war, though disastrous for our country, were none the less mighty. After working for many years to become king and autocrat, he surmounted tremendous efforts and perils and achieved his purpose. By entertainments, public works, food-distributions, and banquets, he seduced the ignorant populace; his friends he bound to his allegiance by rewarding them, his enemies by what looked like mercy. By a mixture of intimidation and indulgence, he inculcated in a free community the habit of servitude.

Your ambition to reign, Antony, certainly deserves to be compared with Caesar's. But in not a single other respect are you entitled to the same comparison. For the many evils which Caesar inflicted upon our country have at least yielded certain benefits. To take a single example, the people of Rome have now discovered what degrees of confidence they can repose in this or that person. They have discovered who are fit to be entrusted with their fortunes, and who, on the other hand, need to be shunned. Do these facts never occur to you? Do you never understand the significance of this: that brave men have now learnt to appreciate the noble achievement, the wonderful benefaction, the glorious renown, of killing a tyrant? When men could not endure Caesar, will they endure you? Mark my words, this time there will be crowds competing to do the deed. They will not wait for a suitable opportunity – they will be too impatient.

Antony: some time, at long last, think of your country. Think of the people from whom you come – not the people with whom you associate. Let your relationship with myself be as you please: but your country I pray you to make your friend once again. However, your behaviour is a matter for yourself to decide. As for mine, I will declare how I shall conduct myself. When I was a young man I defended our state: in my old age I shall not abandon it. Having scorned the swords of Catiline, I shall not be intimidated by yours. On the contrary, I would gladly offer my own body, if my death could redeem the freedom of our nation – if it could cause the long-suffering people of Rome to find final relief from its labours. For if, nearly twenty years ago, I declared in this very temple that death could not come prematurely to a man who had been consul, how much greater will be my reason to say this again now that I am old. After the honours that I have been awarded, Senators, after the deeds that I have done, death actually seems to me desirable. Two things only I pray for. One, that in dying I may leave the Roman people free – the immortal gods could grant me no greater gift. My other prayer is this: that no man's fortunes may fail to correspond with his services to our country!

————————————————————

(1) Fulvia, successively the wife of Publius Clodius, Curio, and Antony.

(2) Phormio and Gnatho were parasites in the Phormio and Eunuch respectively, comedies by Terence （c．195-159 BC）. Ballio was the pimp in The Cheat by Plautus （c. 254-184 BC）.

(3) A quotation from Cicero's much maligned poem On his Consulate. The verse went on: ‘let laurel yield to honest worth.’

(4) Publius Servilius Casca, who struck the 昀 rst blow against Caesar, and his brother Gaius.

(5)  As city-praetor he was not allowed to be away from Rome for more than ten nights.

(6)  i. e. killed Antony too.

(7) It was regarded as a slight not to be mentioned in a friend's will. Lawyers, who were not allowed to accept fees, particularly expected this sort of reward.

(8)  On 2 January 49 bc, Antony and another tribune had vetoed a proposal in the Senate that unless Caesar disbanded his army before a named date he should be declared a public enemy. Caesar crossed the Rubicon eight days later.

(9)  Captured by Pompey in his campaign against the pirates in 67 BC.

(10)  It had been a blow for Antony when Caesar's published will reserved this distinction for Octavian, appointing Antony as one of the secondary heirs only.

(11)  The joke was that Antony was notoriously impoverished, a disgrace according to Roman ideas.

(12)  Caesar, his fellow-consul.

(13)  Dolabella, now consul.

(14)  Her three instalments were her three husbands （参见此处）.